<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1850" author="browningeb" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Poems</title>
   <year>1850</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<section>
<head>
    <title>Sonnets from the Portuguese</title>
</head>
<content>

<text id="browningeb2021102401">
<head>
    <title><num>I.</num>I thought once how Theocritus had sung</title>
    <firstline>I thought once how Theocritus had sung</firstline>
    <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I thought once how Theocritus had sung
Of the sweet years, the dear and wished for years,
Who each one in a gracious hand appears
To bear a gift for mortals, old or young:
And, as I mused it in his antique tongue,
I saw, in gradual vision through my tears,
The sweet, sad years, the melancholy years,
Those of my own life, who by turns had flung
A shadow across me. Straightway I was 'ware,
So weeping, how a mystic Shape did move
Behind me, and drew me backward by the hair,
And a voice said in mastery, while I strove, ...
Guess now who holds thee?'—Death,' I said. But there,
The silver answer rang ... Not Death, but Love.'
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningeb2021102403">
<head>
    <title><num>VI.</num>Go from me.  Yet I feel that I shall stand</title>
    <firstline>Go from me.  Yet I feel that I shall stand</firstline>
    <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Go from me.  Yet I feel that I shall stand
Henceforward in thy shadow.  Nevermore
Alone upon the threshold of my door
Of individual life, I shall command
The uses of my soul, nor lift my hand
Serenely in the sunshine as before,
Without the sense of that which I forbore—
Thy touch upon the palm.  The widest land
Doom takes to part us, leaves thy heart in mine
With pulses that beat double.  What I do
And what I dream include thee, as the wine
Must taste of its own grapes.  And when I sue
God for myself, He hears that name of thine,
And sees within my eyes the tears of two.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningeb2021102402">
<head>
    <title><num>XIV.</num>If thou must love me, let it be for nought</title>
    <firstline>If thou must love me, let it be for nought</firstline>
    <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
If thou must love me, let it be for nought
Except for love’s sake only.  Do not say
“I love her for her smile—her look—her way
Of speaking gently,—for a trick of thought
That falls in well with mine, and certes brought
A sense of pleasant ease on such a day”—
For these things in themselves, Belovëd, may
Be changed, or change for thee,—and love, so wrought,
May be unwrought so.  Neither love me for
Thine own dear pity’s wiping my cheeks dry,—
A creature might forget to weep, who bore
Thy comfort long, and lose thy love thereby!
But love me for love’s sake, that evermore
Thou may’st love on, through love’s eternity.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningeb2021102404">
<head>
    <title><num>XVIII.</num>I never gave a lock of hair away</title>
    <firstline>I never gave a lock of hair away</firstline>
    <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I never gave a lock of hair away
To a man, Dearest, except this to thee,
Which now upon my fingers thoughtfully
I ring out to the full brown length and say
“Take it.”  My day of youth went yesterday;
My hair no longer bounds to my foot’s glee,
Nor plant I it from rose- or myrtle-tree,
As girls do, any more: it only may
Now shade on two pale cheeks the mark of tears,
Taught drooping from the head that hangs aside
Through sorrow’s trick.  I thought the funeral-shears
Would take this first, but Love is justified,—
Take it thou,—finding pure, from all those years,
The kiss my mother left here when she died.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</content>
</section>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
