<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="post" author="keats" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="keats2001070401">
<head>
   <title>Fill for me a brimming bowl</title>
   <subtitle>"What wondrous beauty! From this moment I efface from my mind all women." Terence's <i>Eunuch</i>. Act 2. Sc. 4</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Fill for me a brimming bowl</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Fill for me a brimming bowl</indextitle>
   <firstline>Fill for me a brimming bowl</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten følger John Keats: <i>Complete Poems</i>, ed. Jack Stillinger, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1982</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
Fill for me a brimming bowl,
And let me in it drown my soul:
But put therein some drug design'd
To banish Woman from my mind.
For I want not the stream inspiring,
That heats the sense with lewd desiring;
But I want as deep a draught
As e'er from Lethe's waves was quaft,
From my despairing breast to charm
The image of the fairest form
That e'er my rev'ling eyes beheld,
That e'er my wand'ring fancy spell'd!

'Tis vain - away I cannot chace
The melting softness of that face -
The beaminess of those bright eyes -
That breast, earth's only paradise!

My sight will never more be blest,
For all I see has lost its zest;
Nor with delight can I explore
The classic page - the muse's lore.

Had she but known how beat my heart
And with one smile reliev'd its smart,
I should have felt a sweet relief,
I should have felt "the joy of grief"!
Yet as a Tuscan 'mid the snow
Of Lapland thinks on sweet Arno;
So for ever shall she be
The halo of my memory.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070701">
<head>
   <title>On Seeing the Elgin Marbles</title>
   <toctitle>On Seeing the Elgin Marbles</toctitle>
   <indextitle>On Seeing the Elgin Marbles</indextitle>
   <firstline>My spirit is too weak - mortality</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
My spirit is too weak - mortality
    Weighs heavily on me like unwilling sleep,
    And each imagined pinnacle and steep
Of godlike hardship tells me I must die
Like a sick eagle looking at the sky.
    Yet 'tis a gentle luxury to weep
    That I have not the cloudy winds to keep
Fresh for the opening of the morning's eye.
Such dim-conceived glories of the brain
    Bring round the heart an undescribable feud;
So do these wonders a most dizzy pain,
    That mingles Grecian grandeur with the rude
Wasting of old time - with a billowy main -
    A sun - a shadow of a magnitude.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001071119">
<head>
   <title>In drear nighted December</title>
   <toctitle>In drear nighted December</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In drear nighted December</indextitle>
   <firstline>In drear nighted December</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
In drear nighted December,
    Too happy, happy tree,
Thy branches ne'er remember
    Their green felicity -
The north cannot undo them
With a sleety whistle through them,
Nor frozen thawings glue them
    From budding at the prime.

In drear nighted December,
    Too happy, happy brook,
Thy bubblings ne'er remember
    Apollo's summer look;
But with a sweet forgetting,
They stay their crystal fretting,
Never, never petting
    About the frozen time.

Ah! would 'twere so with many
    A gentle girl and boy -
But were there ever any
    Writh'd not of passed joy?
The feel of not to feel it,
When there is none to heal it,
Nor numbed sense to steel it,
    Was never said in rhyme.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070702">
<head>
   <title>On Sitting Down to Read <I>King Lear</I> Once Again</title>
   <toctitle>On Sitting Down to Read <I>King Lear</I> Once Again</toctitle>
   <indextitle>On Sitting Down to Read <I>King Lear</I> Once Again</indextitle>
   <firstline>O golden-tongued Romance, with serene lute!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O golden-tongued Romance, with serene lute!
    Fair plumed syren, queen of far-away!
    Leave melodizing on this wintry day,
Shut up thine olden pages, and be mute.
Adieu! for, once again, the fierce dispute
    Betwixt damnation and impassion'd clay
    Must I burn through; once more humbly assay
The bitter-sweet of this Shakespearean fruit.
Chief Poet! and ye clouds of Albion,
    Begetters of our deep eternal theme!
When through the old oak forest I am gone,
    Let me not wander in a barren dream:
But, when I am consumed in the fire,
Give me new phoenix wings to fly at my desire.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070703">
<head>
   <title>When I have fears that I may cease to be</title>
   <toctitle>When I have fears that I may cease to be</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When I have fears that I may cease to be</indextitle>
   <firstline>When I have fears that I may cease to be</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten følger John Keats: <i>Complete Poems</i>, ed. Jack Stillinger, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1982</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When I have fears that I may cease to be
    Before my pen has glean'd my teeming brain,
Before high piled books, in charactry,
    Hold like rich garners the full ripen'd grain;
When I behold, upon the night's starr'd face,
    Huge cloudy symbols of a high romance,
And think that I may never live to trace
    Their shadows, with the magic hand of chance;
And when I feel, fair creature of an hour,
    That I shall never look upon thee more,
Never have relish in the fairy power
    Of unreflecting love; - then on the shore
Of the wide world I stand alone, and think
Till love and fame to nothingness do sink.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070704">
<head>
   <title>Time's sea hath been five years at its slow ebb</title>
   <toctitle>Time's sea hath been five years at its slow ebb</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Time's sea hath been five years at its slow ebb</indextitle>
   <firstline>Time's sea hath been five years at its slow ebb</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Time's sea hath been five years at its slow ebb;
    Long hours have to and fro let creep the sand,
Since I was tangled in thy beauty's web,
    And snared by the ungloving of thy hand:
And yet I never look on midnight sky,
    But I behold thine eyes' well-memoried light;
I cannot look upon the rose's dye,
    But to thy cheek my soul doth take its flight:
I cannot look on any budding flower,
    But my fond ear, in fancy at thy lips,
And hearkening for a love-sound, doth devour
    Its sweets in the wrong sense. - Thou dost eclipse
Every delight with sweet remembering,
And grief unto my darling joys dost bring.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001071120">
<head>
   <title>Asleep! O sleep a little while, white pearl</title>
   <toctitle>Asleep! O sleep a little while, white pearl</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Asleep! O sleep a little while, white pearl</indextitle>
   <firstline>Asleep! O sleep a little while, white pearl</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Asleep! O sleep a little while, white pearl,
And let me kneel, and let me pray to thee,
And let me call heaven's blessing on thine eyes,
And let me breathe into the happy air,
That doth enfold and touch thee all about,
Vows of my slavery, my giving up,
My sudden adoration, my great love!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001071121">
<head>
   <title>Four seasons fill the measure of the year</title>
   <toctitle>Four seasons fill the measure of the year</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Four seasons fill the measure of the year</indextitle>
   <firstline>Four seasons fill the measure of the year</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Four seasons fill the measure of the year;
    Four seasons are there in the mind of man.
He hath his lusty spring, when fancy clear
    Takes in all beauty with an easy span:
He hath his summer, when luxuriously
    He chews the honied cud of fair spring thoughts,
Till, in his soul dissolv'd, they come to be
    Part of himself. He hath his autumn ports
And havens of repose, when his tired wings
    Are folded up, and he content look
On mists in idleness: to let fair things
    Pass by unheeded as a threshold brook.
He hath his winter too of pale misfeature,
Or else he would forget his mortal nature.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070705">
<head>
   <title>To Homer</title>
   <toctitle>To Homer</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To Homer</indextitle>
   <firstline>Standing aloof in giant ignorance</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Standing aloof in giant ignorance,
    Of thee I hear and of the Cyclades,
As one who sits ashore and longs perchance
    To visit dolphin-coral in deep seas.
So wast thou blind; - but then the veil was rent,
    For Jove uncurtain'd heaven to let thee live,
And Neptune made for thee a spumy tent,
    And Pan made sing for thee his forest-hive;
Aye on the shores of darkness there is light,
    And precipices show untrodden green,
There is a budding morrow in midnight,
    There is a triple sight in blindness keen;
Such seeing hadst thou, as it once befel
To Dian, Queen of Earth, and Heaven, and Hell.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070706">
<head>
   <title>Why did I laugh tonight? No voice will tell</title>
   <toctitle>Why did I laugh tonight? No voice will tell</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Why did I laugh tonight? No voice will tell</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why did I laugh tonight? No voice will tell</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Why did I laugh tonight? No voice will tell:
    No god, no demon of severe response,
Deigns to reply from heaven or from hell.
    Then to my human heart I turn at once -
Heart! thou and I are here sad and alone;
    Say, wherefore did I laugh! O mortal pain!
O darkness! darkness! ever must I moan,
    To question heaven and hell and heart in vain!
Why did I laugh? I know this being's lease -
    My fancy to its utmost blisses spreads:
Yet could I on this very midnight cease,
    And the world's gaudy ensigns see in shreds.
Verse, fame, and beauty are intense indeed,
But death intenser - death is life's high meed.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2000012802">
<head>
   <title>Bright star, would I were stedfast as thou art</title>
   <toctitle>Bright star, would I were stedfast as thou art</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Bright star, would I were stedfast as thou art</indextitle>
   <firstline>Bright star, would I were stedfast as thou art</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Bright star, would I were stedfast as thou art -
    Not in lone splendor hung aloft the night,
And watching, with eternal lids apart,
    Like nature's patient, sleepless eremite,
The moving waters at their priestlike task
    Of pure ablution round earth's human shores,
Or gazing on the new soft-fallen mask
    Of snow upon the mountains and the moors;
No - yet still stedfast, still unchangeable,
    Pillow'd upon my fair love's ripening breast,
To feel for ever its soft swell and fall,
    Awake for ever in a sweet unrest,
Still, still to hear her tender-taken breath,
And so live ever - or else swoon to death.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2000012803">
<head>
   <title>La Belle Dame sans Merci: A Ballad</title>
   <toctitle>La Belle Dame sans Merci: A Ballad</toctitle>
   <indextitle>La Belle Dame sans Merci: A Ballad</indextitle>
   <firstline>O what can ail thee, knight at arms</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten følger John Keats: <i>Complete Poems</i>, ed. Jack Stillinger, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1982</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="keats2000012803-p1.jpg">John William Waterhouse (<year>1849</year>-<year>1917</year>): »La Belle Dame Sans Merci« (<year>1893</year>), oliemaleri, 112x81 cm, Hessisches Landesmuseum, Darmstadt.</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
1
O what can ail thee, knight at arms,
    Alone and palely loitering?
The sedge has wither'd from the lake,
       And no birds sing.

2
O what can ail thee, knight at arms,
    So haggard and so woe-begone?
The squirrel's granary is full,
       And the harvest's done.

3
I see a lily on thy brow
    With anguish moist and fever dew,
And on thy cheeks a fading rose
       Fast withereth too.

4
I met a lady in the meads,
    Full beautiful, a fairy's child;
Her hair was long, her foot was light,
       And her eyes were wild.

5
I made a garland for her head,
    And bracelets too, and fragrant zone;
She look'd at me as she did love,
       And made sweet moan.

6
I set her on my pacing steed,
    And nothing else saw all day long,
For sidelong would she bend, and sing
       A fairy's song.

7
She found me roots of relish sweet,
    And honey wild, and manna dew,
And sure in language strange she said -
       I love thee true.

8
She took me to her elfin grot,
    And there she wept, and sigh'd full sore,
And there I shut her wild wild eyes
       With kisses four.

9
And there she lulled me asleep,
    And there I dream'd - Ah! woe betide!
The latest dream I ever dream'd
       On the cold hill's side.

10
I saw pale kings, and princes too,
    Pale warriors, death pale were they all;
They cried - "La belle dame sans merci
       Hath thee in thrall!"

11
I saw their starv'd lips in the gloam
    With horrid warning gaped wide,
And I awoke and found me here
       On the cold hill's side.

12
And this is why I sojourn here,
    Alone and palely loitering,
Though the sedge is wither'd from the lake,
       And no birds sing.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070707">
<head>
   <title>Sonnet to Sleep</title>
   <toctitle>Sonnet to Sleep</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sonnet to Sleep</indextitle>
   <firstline>O soft embalmer of the still midnight</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O soft embalmer of the still midnight,
    Shutting with careful fingers and benign
Our gloom-pleas'd eyes, embower'd from the light,
    Enshaded in forgetfulness divine:
O soothest Sleep! if so it please thee, close,
    In midst of this thine hymn, my willing eyes,
Or wait the Amen ere thy poppy throws
    Around my bed its lulling charities.
Save me from curious conscience, that still hoards
    Its strength for darkness, burrowing like the mole;
Turn the key deftly in the oiled wards,
    And seal the hushed casket of my soul.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="keats2001070708">
<head>
   <title>Ode on Indolence</title>
   <subtitle>"They toil not, neither do they spin."</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Ode on Indolence</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Ode on Indolence</indextitle>
   <firstline>One morn before me were three figures seen</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>ode</keywords>
</head>
<body>
1
One morn before me were three figures seen,
    With bowed necks, and joined hands, side-faced;
And one behind the other stepp'd serene,
    In placid sandals, and in white robes graced:
They pass'd, like figures on a marble urn,
    When shifted round to see the other side;
        They came again; as when the urn once more
Is shifted round, the first seen shades return;
    And they were strange to me, as may betide
        With vases, to one deep in Phidian lore.

2
How is it, shadows! that I knew ye not?
    How came ye muffled in so hush a masque?
Was it a silent deep-disguised plot
    To steal away, and leave without a task
My idle days? Ripe was the drowsy hour;
    The blissful cloud of summer-indolence
        Benumb'd my eyes; my pulse grew less and less;
Pain had no sting, and pleasure's wreath no flower.
    O, why did ye not melt, and leave my sense
        Unhaunted quite of all but - nothingness?

3
A third time pass'd they by, and, passing, turn'd
    Each one the face a moment whiles to me;
Then faded, and to follow them I burn'd
    And ached for wings, because I knew the three:
The first was a fair maid, and Love her name;
    The second was Ambition, pale of cheek,
        And ever watchful with fatigued eye;
The last, whom I love more, the more of blame
    Is heap'd upon her, maiden most unmeek, -
        I knew to be my demon Poesy.

4
They faded, and, forsooth! I wanted wings:
    O folly! What is Love! and where is it?
And for that poor Ambition - it springs
    From a man's little heart's short fever-fit;
For Poesy! - no, - she has not a joy, -
    At least for me, - so sweet as drowsy noons,
        And evenings steep'd in honied indolence;
O, for an age so shelter'd from annoy,
    That I may never know how change the moons,
        Or hear the voice of busy common-sense!

5
A third time came they by; - alas! wherefore?
    My sleep had been embroider'd with dim dreams;
My soul had been a lawn besprinkled o'er
    With flowers, and stirring shades, and baffled beams:
The morn was clouded, but no shower fell,
    Though in her lids hung the sweet tears of May;
        The open casement press'd a new-leaved vine,
    Let in the budding warmth and throstle's lay;
O shadows! 'twas a time to bid farewell!
        Upon your skirts had fallen no tears of mine.

6
So, ye three ghosts, adieu! Ye cannot raise
    My head cool-bedded in the flowery grass;
For I would not be dieted with praise,
    A pet-lamb in a sentimental farce!
Fade softly from my eyes, and be once more
    In masque-like figures on the dreamy urn;
        Farewell! I yet have visions for the night,
And for the day faint visions there is store;
        Vanish, ye phantoms, from my idle spright,
    Into the clouds, and never more return!
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
