<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="arnold" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="arnold2019091201">
<head>
   <title>Quiet Work</title>
   <firstline>One lesson, Nature, let me learn of thee</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>One</sc> lesson, Nature, let me learn of thee,
One lesson which in every wind is blown,
One lesson of two duties kept at one
Though the loud world proclaim their enmity—

Of toil unsever'd from tranquillity!
Of labour, that in lasting fruit outgrows
Far noisier schemes, accomplish'd in repose,
Too great for haste, too high for rivalry!

Yes, while on earth a thousand discords ring,
Man's fitful uproar mingling with his toil,
Still do thy sleepless ministers move on,

Their glorious tasks in silence perfecting;
Still working, blaming still our vain turmoil,
Labourers that shall not fail, when man is gone.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="arnold2019091202">
<head>
    <title></title>
    <firstline>So far as I conceive the world's rebuke</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>So</sc> far as I conceive the world's rebuke
To him address'd who would recast her new,
Not from herself her fame of strength she took,
But from their weakness who would work her rue.

“Behold,” she cries, “so many rages lull'd,
So many fiery spirits quite cool'd down;
Look how so many valours, long undull'd,
After short commerce with me, fear my frown!

“Thou too, when thou against my crimes wouldst cry,
Let thy foreboded homage check thy tongue!”—
The world speaks well; yet might her foe reply:
“Are wills so weak?—then let not mine wait long!

“Hast thou so rare a poison?—let me be
Keener to slay thee, lest thou poison me!“

    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="arnold2019091203">
<head>
    <title>The Divinity</title>
    <firstline>Yes, write it in the rock, Saint Bernard said</firstline>
</head>
<body>
“<sc>Yes</sc>, write it in the rock,” Saint Bernard said,
“Grave it on brass with adamantine pen!
'Tis God himself becomes apparent, when
God's wisdom and God's goodness are display'd,

“For God of these his attributes is made.”—
Well spake the impetuous Saint, and bore of men
The suffrage captive; now, not one in ten
Recalls the obscure opposer he outweigh'd.

<i>God's wisdom and God's goodness!</i>—Ay, but fools
Mis-define these till God knows them no more.
<i>Wisdom and goodness, they are God!</i>—what schools

Have yet so much as heard this simpler lore?
This no Saint preaches, and this no Church rules;
'Tis in the desert, now and heretofore.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="arnold2019091204">
<head>
    <title>Self-Deception</title>
    <firstline>Say, what blinds us, that we claim the glory</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>Say</sc>, what blinds us, that we claim the glory
Of possessing powers not our share?
—Since man woke on earth, he knows his story,
But, before we woke on earth, we were.

Long, long since, undower'd yet, our spirit
Roam'd, ere birth, the treasuries of God;
Saw the gifts, the powers it might inherit,
Ask'd an outfit for its earthly road.

Then, as now, this tremulous, eager being
Strain'd and long'd and grasp'd each gift it saw;
Then, as now, a Power beyond our seeing
Staved us back, and gave our choice the law.

Ah, whose hand that day through Heaven guided
Man's new spirit, since it was not we?
Ah, who sway'd our choice, and who decided
What our gifts, and what our wants should be?

For, alas! he left us each retaining
Shreds of gifts which he refused in full.
Still these waste us with their hopeless straining,
Still the attempt to use them proves them null.

And on earth we wander, groping, reeling;
Powers stir in us, stir and disappear.
Ah! and he, who placed our master-feeling,
Fail'd to place that master-feeling clear.

We but dream we have our wish'd-for powers,
Ends we seek we never shall attain.
Ah! <i>some</i> power exists there, which is ours?
<i>Some</i> end is there, we indeed may gain?    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="arnold2019091205">
<head>
    <title>Self-Dependence</title>
    <firstline>Weary of myself, and sick of asking</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>Weary</sc> of myself, and sick of asking
What I am, and what I ought to be,
At this vessel's prow I stand, which bears me
Forwards, forwards, o'er the starlit sea.

And a look of passionate desire
O'er the sea and to the stars I send:
“Ye who from my childhood up have calm'd me,
Calm me, ah, compose me to the end!

“Ah, once more,” I cried, “ye stars, ye waters,
On my heart your mighty charm renew;
Still, still let me, as I gaze upon you,
Feel my soul becoming vast like you!”

From the intense, clear, star-sown vault of heaven,
Over the lit sea's unquiet way,
In the rustling night-air came the answer:
“Wouldst thou <i>be</i> as these are? <i>Live</i> as they.

“Unaffrighted by the silence round them,
Undistracted by the sights they see,
These demand not that the things without them
Yield them love, amusement, sympathy.

“And with joy the stars perform their shining,
And the sea its long moon-silver'd roll;
For self-poised they live, nor pine with noting
All the fever of some differing soul.

“Bounded by themselves, and unregardful
In what state God's other works may be,
In their own tasks all their powers pouring,
These attain the mighty life you see.”

O air-born voice! long since, severely clear,
A cry like thine in mine own heart I hear:
“Resolve to be thyself; and know that he,
Who finds himself, loses his misery!”
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
