<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="bayly" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="bayly201908251">
<head>
   <title>I'd be a butterfly born in a bower</title>
   <firstline>I'd be a butterfly born in a bower</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I'd be a butterfly born in a bower,
Where roses and lilies and violets meet;
Roving for ever from flower to flower,
Kissing all buds that are pretty and sweet.
I'd never languish for wealth or for power,
I'd never sigh to see slaves at my feet;
I'd be a butterfly born in a bower,
Kissing all buds that are pretty and sweet.

Oh! could I pilfer the wand of a fairy,
I'd have a pair of those beautiful wings.
Their summer day's ramble is sportive and airy,
They sleep in a rose when the nightingale sings.
Those who have wealth must be watchful and wary,
Power, alas! naught but misery brings;
I'd be a butterfly, sportive and airy,
Rock'd in a rose when the nightingale sings.

What though you tell me each gay little rover
Shrinks from the breath of the first autumn day;
Surely 't is better, when summer is over,
To die, when all fair things are fading away.
Some in life's winter may toil to discover
Means of procuring a weary delay:
I'd be a butterfly, living a rover,
Dying when fair things are fading away    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly201908252">
<head>
    <title>She Wore a Wreath of Roses</title>
    <firstline>She wore a wreath of roses</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
She wore a wreath of roses	
  The night that first we met;	
Her lovely face was smiling	
  Beneath her curls of jet.	
Her footstep had the lightness,	
  Her voice the joyous tone,—	
The tokens of a youthful heart,	
  Where sorrow is unknown.	
I saw her but a moment,	
  Yet methinks I see her now,	
With the wreath of summer flowers	
  Upon her snowy brow.	

A wreath of orange-blossoms,	
  When next we met, she wore;	
The expression of her features	
  Was more thoughtful than before;	
And standing by her side was one	
  Who strove, and not in vain,	
To soothe her, leaving that dear home	
  She ne’er might view again.	
I saw her but a moment,	
  Yet methinks I see her now,	
With the wreath of orange-blossoms	
  Upon her snowy brow.	

And once again I see that brow;	
  No bridal-wreath is there,	
The widow’s sombre cap conceals	
  Her once luxuriant hair.	
She weeps in silent solitude,	
  And there is no one near	
To press her hand within his own,	
  And wipe away the tear.	
I see her broken-hearted;	
  Yet methinks I see her now,	
In the pride of youth and beauty,	
  With a garland on her brow.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly201908253">
<head>
    <title>The Soldier's Tear</title>
    <firstline>Upon the hill he turn'd</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Upon the hill he turn'd
To take a last fond look
Of the valley and the village church
And the cottage by the brook;
He listen'd to the sounds,
So familiar to his ear,
And the soldier leant upon his sword,
And wiped away a tear.

Beside that cottage porch
A girl was on her knees,
She held aloft a snowy scarf,
Which flutter'd in the breeze;
She breath'd a prayer for him,
A prayer he could not hear,
But he paused to bless her, as she knelt,
And wiped away a tear.

He turn'd and left the spot,
Oh, do not deem him weak;
For dauntless was the soldier's heart,
Though tears were on his cheek;
Go watch the foremost rank
In danger's dark career,
Be sure the hand most daring there
Has wiped away a tear.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly201908254">
<head>
    <title>Oh, No! We Never Mention Her</title>
    <firstline>Oh, no! we never mention her, her name is never heard</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Oh, no! we never mention her, her name is never heard;
My lips are now forbid to speak that once familiar word:
From sport to sport they hurry me, to banish my regret;
And when they win a smile from me, they think that I forget.

They bid me seek in change of scene the charms that others see;
But were I in a foreign land, they'd find no change in me.
'Tis true that I behold no more the valley where we met,
I do not see the hawthorn-tree; but how can I forget?

For oh! there are so many things recall the past to me,—
The breeze upon the sunny hills, the billows of the sea;
The rosy tint that decks the sky before the sun is set;—
Ay, every leaf I look upon forbids me to forget.

They tell me she is happy now, the gayest of the gay;
They hint that she forgets me too,—I heed not what they say:
Perhaps like me she struggles with each feeling of regret;
But if she loves as I have loved, she never can forget.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly201908255">
<head>
    <title>Think Not of the Future</title>
    <firstline>Think not of the future, the prospect is uncertain</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Think not of the future, the prospect is uncertain; 
Laugh away the present, while laughing hours remain: 
Those who gaze too boldly through Time's mystic curtain 
Soon will wish to close it, and dream of joy again. 

I, like thee, was happy, and, on hope relying, 
Thought the present pleasure might revive again; 
But receive my counsel! time is always flying, 
Then laugh away the present, while laughing hours remain 

I have felt unkindness, keen as that which hurts thee; 
I have met with friendship fickle as the wind; 
Take what friendship offers ere its warmth deserts thee; 
Well I know the kindest may not long be kind. 

Would you waste the pleasure of the summer season, 
Thinking that the winter must return again? 
If our summer's fleeting, surely that's a reason 
For laughing off the present, while laughing hours remain.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly2019091101">
<head>
    <title>I'm Saddest When I Sing</title>
    <firstline>You think I have a merry heart</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
You think I have a merry heart,
  Because my songs are gay,
But oh! they all were taught to me
  By Friends now far away:
The Bird retains his silver note,
  Though bondage chains his wing;
His song is not a happy one—
  I'm saddest when I sing!

I heard them first in that sweet home
  I never more shall see,
And now each song of joy, has got
  A plaintive turn for me!
Alas 'tis vain in winter time
  To mock the songs of spring,
Each note recalls some withered leaf—
  I'm saddest when I sing!

Of all the Friends I used to love
  My harp remains alone,
Its faithful voice still seems to be
  An echo of my own:
My tears when I bend over it
  Will fall upon its string,
Yet those who hear me, little think
  I'm saddest when I sing!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="bayly2019091102">
<head>
    <title>Upon Thy Truth Relying</title>
    <firstline>They say we are too young to love</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
They say we are too young to love,
  Too wild to be united;
In scorn, they bid us both renounce
  The fond vows we have plighted.
They send thee forth to see the world,
  Thy love by absence trying;
Then go! for I can smile farewell—
  Upon thy truth relying.

I know that pleasure’s hand will throw
  Her silken nets about thee:
I know how lonesome I shall find
  The long—long days without thee.
But in thy letters there'll be joy:
  The reading—the replying;
I'll kiss each word that's traced by thee—
  Upon thy truth relying.

When friends applaud thee, I’ll sit by,
  In silent rapture gazing;
And oh! how proud of being loved,
  By her they have been praising!
But should detraction breathe thy name,
  The world's reproofs defying:
I’d love thee—laud thee—trust thee still—
  Upon thy truth relying.

E’en those who smile to see us part
  Shall see us meet with wonder:
Such trials only make the heart
  That truly loves grow fonder.
Our sorrows past shall be our pride,
  When with each other vying:
Thou wilt confide in him who lives
  Upon thy truth relying.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
