<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="smith" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="smith2019072101">
<head>
   <title>Barbara</title>
   <firstline>On the Sabbath-day</firstline>
</head>
<body>
   On the Sabbath-day, 
   Through the churchyard old and gray, 
Over the crisp and yellow leaves I held my rustling way; 
And amid the words of mercy, falling on my soul like balms, 
'Mid the gorgeous storms of music--in the mellow organ-calms, 
'Mid the upward-streaming prayers, and the rich and solemn psalms, 
   I stood careless, Barbara. 

   My heart was otherwhere, 
   While the organ shook the air, 
And the priest, with outspread hands, bless'd the people with a prayer; 
But when rising to go homeward, with a mild and saintlike shine 
Gleam'd a face of airy beauty with its heavenly eyes on mine-- 
Gleam'd and vanish'd in a moment--O that face was surely thine 
   Out of heaven, Barbara! 

   O pallid, pallid face! 
   O earnest eyes of grace! 
When last I saw thee, dearest, it was in another place. 
You came running forth to meet me with my love-gift on your wrist: 
The flutter of a long white dress, then all was lost in mist-- 
A purple stain of agony was on the mouth I kiss'd, 
   That wild morning, Barbara. 

   I search'd, in my despair, 
   Sunny noon and midnight air; 
I could not drive away the thought that you were lingering there. 
O many and many a winter night I sat when you were gone, 
My worn face buried in my hands, beside the fire alone-- 
Within the dripping churchyard, the rain plashing on your stone, 
   You were sleeping, Barbara. 

   'Mong angels, do you think 
   Of the precious golden link 
I clasp'd around your happy arm while sitting by yon brink? 
Or when that night of gliding dance, of laughter and guitars, 
Was emptied of its music, and we watch'd, through lattice-bars, 
The silent midnight heaven creeping o'er us with its stars, 
   Till the day broke, Barbara? 

   In the years I've changed; 
   Wild and far my heart has ranged, 
And many sins and errors now have been on me avenged; 
But to you I have been faithful whatsoever good I lack'd: 
I loved you, and above my life still hangs that love intact-- 
Your love the trembling rainbow, I the reckless cataract. 
   Still I love you. Barbara. 

   Yet, Love, I am unblest; 
   With many doubts opprest, 
I wander like the desert wind without a place of rest. 
Could I but win you for an hour from off that starry shore, 
The hunger of my soul were still'd; for Death hath told you more 
Than the melancholy world doth know--things deeper than all lore 
   You could teach me, Barbara. 

   In vain, in vain, in vain! 
   You will never come again. 
There droops upon the dreary hills a mournful fringe of rain; 
The gloaming closes slowly round, loud winds are in the tree, 
Round selfish shores for ever moans the hurt and wounded sea; 
There is no rest upon the earth, peace is with Death and thee-- 
   Barbara!     
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
