<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="scott" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="scott2001081501">
<head>
   <title>County Guy</title>
   <toctitle>County Guy</toctitle>
   <indextitle>County Guy</indextitle>
   <firstline>Ah! County Guy, the hour is nigh</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Ah! County Guy, the hour is nigh,
    The sun has left the lea,
The orange flower perfumes the bower,
    The breeze is on the sea.
The lark his lay who thrill'd all day
    Sits hush'd his partner nigh:
Breeze, bird, and flower confess the hour,
    But where is County Guy?

The village maid steals through the shade,
    Her shepherd's suit to hear;
To beauty shy, by lattice high,
    Sings high-born Cavalier.
The star of Love, all stars above
    Now reigns o'er earth and sky;
And high and low the influence know--
    But where is County Guy?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="scott2001081502">
<head>
   <title>Jock of Hazeldean</title>
   <toctitle>Jock of Hazeldean</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Jock of Hazeldean</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why weep ye by the tide, ladie</firstline>
</head>
<body>
"Why weep ye by the tide, ladie?
    Why weep ye by the tide?
I'll wed ye to my youngest son,
    And ye sall be his bride:
And ye sall be his bride, ladie,
    Sae comely to be seen"--
But aye she loot the tears down fa'
    For Jock of Hazeldean.

"Now let this wilful grief be done,
    And dry that cheek so pale;
Young Frank is chief of Errington,
    And lord of Langley-dale;
His step is first in peaceful ha',
    His sword in battle keen"--
But aye she loot the tears down fa'
    For Jock of Hazeldean.

"A chain of gold ye sall not lack,
    Nor braid to bind your hair;
Nor mettled hound, nor managed hawk,
    Nor palfrey fresh and fair;
And you, the foremost o' them a',
    Shall ride our forest queen"--
But aye she loot the tears down fa'
    For Jock of Hazeldean.

The kirk was deck'd at morning-tide,
    The tapers glimmer'd fair;
The priest and bridegroom wait the bride,
    And dame and knight are there.
They sought her baith by bower and ha';
    The ladie was not seen!
She's o'er the Border and awa'
    Wi' Jock of Hazeldean.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="scott2001081503">
<head>
   <title>Lullaby of an Infant Chief</title>
   <toctitle>Lullaby of an Infant Chief</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Lullaby of an Infant Chief</indextitle>
   <firstline>O hush thee, my babie, thy sire was a knight</firstline>
</head>
<body>
  O hush thee, my babie, thy sire was a knight,
Thy mother a lady, both lovely and bright;
The woods and the glens, from the towers which we see,
They all are belonging, dear babie, to thee.
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo,
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo.

  O fear not the bugle, though loudly it blows,
It calls but the warders that guard thy repose;
Their bows would be bended, their blades would be red,
Ere the step of a foeman drew near to thy bed.
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo,
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo.

  O hush thee, my babie, the time soon will come
When thy sleep shall be broken by trumpet and drum;
Then hush thee, my darling, take rest while you may,
For strife comes with manhood, and waking with day.
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo,
       O ho ro, i ri ri, cadul gu lo.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="scott2019021301">
<head>
   <title>The dying Bard</title>
   <firstline>Dinas Emlinn, lament; for the moment is nigh</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<num>I.</num>Dinas Emlinn, lament; for the moment is nigh,
When mute in the woodlands thine echoes shall die:
No more by sweet Teivi Cadwallon shall rave,
And mix his wild notes with the wild dashing wave.

<num>II.</num>In spring and in autumn thy glories of shade
Unhonour'd shall flourish, unhonour'd shall fade;
For soon shall be lifeless the eye and the tongue,
That view'd them with rapture, with rapture that sung.

<num>III.</num>Thy sons, Dinas Emlinn, may march in their pride,
And chase the proud Saxon from Prestatyn's side;
But where is the harp shall give life to their name?
And where is the bard shall give heroes their fame?

<num>IV.</num>And oh, Dinas Emlinn! thy daughters so fair,
Who heave the white bosom, and wave the dark hair;
What tuneful enthusiast shall worship their eye,
When half of their charms with Cadwallon shall die?

<num>V.</num>Then adieu, silver Teivi! I quit thy loved scene,
To join the dim choir of the bards who have been;
With Lewarch, and Meilor, and Merlin the Old,
And sage Taliessin, high harping to hold.

<num>VI.</num>And Adieu, Dinas Emlinn! still green be thy shades,
Unconquer'd thy warriors, and matchless thy maids!
And thou, whose faint warblings my weakness can tell,
Farewell, my loved Harp! my last treasure, farewell!     
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="scott2019021302">
<head>
   <title>The Palmer</title>
   <firstline>O, open the door, some pity to show</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
'O, open the door, some pity to show,
Keen blows the northern wind!
The glen is white with the drifted snow,
And the path is hard to find.

'No outlaw seeks your castle gate,
From chasing the King's deer,
Though even an outlaw's wretched state
Might claim compassion here.

'A weary Palmer, worn and weak,
I wander for my sin;
O, open, for our Lady's sake!
A pilgrim's blessing win!

'I'll give you pardons from the Pope, 
And reliques from o'er the sea,-
Or if for these you will not ope,
Yet open for charity.

'The hare is crouching in her form,
The hard beside the hind;
An aged man, amid the storm,
No shelter can I find.

'You hear the Ettrick's sullen roar,
Dark, deep, and strong is he,
And I must ford the Ettrick o'er, 
Unless you pity me.

'The iron gate is bolted hard,
At which I knock in vain;
The owner's heart is closer barr'd,
Who hears me thus complain.

'Farewell, farewell! and Mary grant,
When old and frail you be,
You never may the shelter want,
That's now denied to me.'

The Ranger on his couch lay warm,
And heard him plead in vain;
But oft amid December's storm,
He'll hear that voice again:

For lo, when through the vapours dank,
Morn shone on Ettrick fair,
A corpse amid the alders rank,
The Palmer welter'd there.     
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
