<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="hoffman" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="hoffman2019090801">
<head>
   <title>We Parted in Kindness</title>
   <firstline>We parted in kindness, but spoke not of parting</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>We</sc> parted in kindness, but spoke not of parting; 
  We talk’d not of hopes that we both must resign; 
I saw not her eyes, and but one teardrop starting 
  Fell down on her hand as it trembled in mine: 

Each felt that the past we could never recover, 
  Each felt that the future no hope could restore, 
<i>She</i> shudder'd at wringing the heart of her lover, 
  <i>I</i> dared not to say I must meet her no more. 

Long years have gone ny, and the springtime smiles ever
  As o'er our young loves it first smiled in their birth;
Long years have gone by, yet that parting, oh! never
  Can it be forgotten by either on earth.

The note of each wild bird that carols toward heaven 
  Must tell her of swift-winged hopes that were mine,
While the dew that steals over each blossom at even 
  Tells me of the teardrop that wept their decline.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="hoffman2019090802">
<head>
    <title>The Blighted Heart</title>
    <firstline>When the flowers of Friendship or Love have decayed</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>When</sc> the flowers of Friendship or Love have decayed 
In the heart that has trusted and once been betray'd, 
No sunshine of kindness their bloom can restore. 
For the verdure of feeling will quicken no more! 

Hope, cheated too often when life's in its spring, 
From the bosom that nursed it for ever takes wing; 
And memory comes, as its promises fade, 
To brood o'er the havoc that passion has made,—

As 'tis said that the swallow the tenement leaves 
Where ruin endangers her nest in the eaves. 
While the desolate owl takes her place on the wall, 
And builds in the mansion that nods to its fall.     
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="hoffman2019090803">
<head>
    <title>The Mint Julep</title>
    <firstline>Tis said that the gods on Olympus of old</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>'tis</sc> said that the gods on Olympus of old 
(And who the bright legend profanes with a doubt?) 
One night, 'mid their revels, by Bacchus were told 
That his last butt of nectar had somehow run out! 

But determined to send round the goblet once more, 
They sued to the fairer immortals for aid 
In composing a draught which, till drinking were o'er, 
Should cast every wine ever drank in the shade. 

Grave Ceres herself blithely yielded her corn, 
And the spirit that lives in each amber-hued grain, 
And which first had its birth from the dew of the morn, 
Was taught to steal out in bright dew-drops again. 

Pomona, whose choicest of fruits on the board 
Were scattered profusely in every one's reach, 
When called on a tribute to cull from the hoard, 
Expressed the mild juice of the delicate peach. 

The liquids were mingled while Venus looked on 
With glances so fraught with sweet magical power, 
That the honey of Hybla, e'en when they were gone, 
Has never been missed in the draught from that hour. 

Flora, then, from her bosom of fragrancy, shook, 
And with roseate fingers pressed down in the bowl, 
All dripping and fresh as it came from the brook, 
The herb whose aroma should flavor the whole. 

The draught was delicious, and loud the acclaim, 
Though something seemed wanting for all to bewail, 
But Juleps the drink of immortals became, 
When Jove himself added a handful of hail.     
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
