<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1816a" author="byron" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>The Prisoner of Chillon and other poems</title>
   <year>1816</year>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="byron2002021401">
<head>
   <title>Stanzas to [Augusta]</title>
   <toctitle>Stanzas to [Augusta]</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Stanzas to [Augusta]</indextitle>
   <firstline>Though the day of my destiny's over</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten følger: Lord Byron, <i>The Complete Poetical Works</i>, red. Jerome J. McGann, 7 bind, Clarendon Press 1980-93, bind 4, s. 33-35.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
Though the day of my destiny's over,
    And the star of my fate hath declined,
Thy soft heart refused to discover
    The faults which so many could find;
Though thy soul with my grief was acquainted,
    It shrunk not to share it with me,
And the love which my spirit hath painted
    It never hath found but in <i>thee</i>.

Then when nature around me is smiling
    The last smile which answers to mine,
I do not believe it beguiling
    Because it reminds me of thine;
And when winds are at war with the ocean,
    As the breasts I believed in with me,
If their billows excite an emotion,
    It is that they bear me from <i>thee</i>.

Though the rock of my last hope is shiver'd,
    And its fragments are sunk in the wave,
Though I feel that my soul is deliver'd
    To pain - it shall not be its slave.
There is many a pang to pursue me:
    They may crush, but they shall not contemn -
They may torture, but shall not subdue me -
    'Tis of <i>thee</i> that I think - not of them.

Though human, thou didst not deceive me,
    Though woman, thou didst not forsake,
Though loved, thou forborest to grieve me,
    Though slander'd, thou never could'st shake, -
Though trusted, thou didst not betray me,
    Though parted, it was not to fly,
Though watchful, 'twas not to defame me,
    Nor, mute, that the world might belie.

Yet I blame not the world, nor despise it,
    Nor the war of the many with one -
If my soul was not fitted to prize it
    'Twas folly not sooner to shun:
And if dearly that error hath cost me,
    And more than I once could foresee,
I have found that, whatever it lost me,
    It could not deprive me of <i>thee</i>.

From the wreck of the past, which hath perish'd,
    Thus much I at least may recall,
It hath taught me that which I most cherish'd
    Deserved to be dearest of all:
In the desert a fountain is springing,
    In the wide waste there still is a tree,
And a bird in the solitude singing,
    Which speaks to my spirit of <i>thee</i>.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
