<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1817a" author="byron" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Manfred</title>
   <year>1817</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="byron2001091801">
<head>
   <title>Act I</title>
   <toctitle>Act I</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Act I</indextitle>
   <firstline>The lamp must be replenish'd, but even then</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
DRAMATIS PERSONAE

MANFRED
CHAMOIS HUNTER
ABBOT OF ST. MAURICE
MANUEL
HERMAN
WITCH OF THE ALPS
ARIMANES
NEMESIS
THE DESTINIES
SPIRITS, etc

SCENE I

<i>MANFRED alone. - Scene, a Gothic Gallery. - Time, Midnight.</i>

MANFRED. The lamp must be replenish'd, but even then
It will not burn so long as I must watch.
My slumbers- if I slumber- are not sleep,
But a continuance of enduring thought,
Which then I can resist not: in my heart
There is a vigil, and these eyes but close
To look within; and yet I live, and bear
The aspect and the form of breathing men.
But grief should be the instructor of the wise;
Sorrow is knowledge: they who know the most
Must mourn the deepest o'er the fatal truth,
The Tree of Knowledge is not that of Life.
Philosophy and science, and the springs
Of wonder, and the wisdom of the world,
I have essay'd, and in my mind there is
A power to make these subject to itself-
But they avail not: I have done men good,
And I have met with good even among men-
But this avail'd not: I have had my foes,
And none have baffled, many fallen before me-
But this avail'd not: Good, or evil, life,
Powers, passions, all I see in other beings,
Have been to me as rain unto the sands,
Since that all-nameless hour. I have no dread,
And feel the curse to have no natural fear
Nor fluttering throb, that beats with hopes or wishes
Or lurking love of something on the earth.
Now to my task.-
                     Mysterious Agency!
Ye spirits of the unbounded Universe,
Whom I have sought in darkness and in light!
Ye, who do compass earth about, and dwell
In subtler essence!  ye, to whom the tops
Of mountains inaccessible are haunts,
And earth's and ocean's caves familiar things-
I call upon ye by the written charm
Which gives me power upon you- Rise! appear!   [A pause.]
They come not yet.- Now by the voice of him
Who is the first among you; by this sign,
Which makes you tremble; by the claims of him
Who is undying,- Rise! appear!- Appear!       [A pause.]
If it be so.- Spirits of earth and air,
Ye shall not thus elude me: by a power,
Deeper than all yet urged, a tyrant-spell,
Which had its birthplace in a star condemn'd,
The burning wreck of a demolish'd world,
A wandering hell in the eternal space;
By the strong curse which is upon my soul,
The thought which is within me and around me,
I do compel ye to my will.  Appear!

[A star is seen at the darker end of the gallery: it is stationary; and a voice is heard singing.]

               FIRST SPIRIT.

     Mortal! to thy bidding bow'd,
     From my mansion in the cloud,
     Which the breath of twilight builds,
     And the summer's sunset gilds
     With the azure and vermilion
     Which is mix'd for my pavilion;
     Though thy quest may be forbidden,
     On a star-beam I have ridden,
     To thine adjuration bow'd;
     Mortal- be thy wish avow'd!


          Voice of the SECOND SPIRIT.

     Mont Blanc is the monarch of mountains;
       They crown'd him long ago
     On a throne of rocks, in a robe of clouds,
       With a diadem of snow.
     Around his waist are forests braced,
       The Avalanche in his hand;
     But ere it fall, that thundering ball
       Must pause for my command.
     The Glacier's cold and restless mass
       Moves onward day by day;
     But I am he who bids it pass,
       Or with its ice delay.
     I am the spirit of the place,
       Could make the mountain bow
     And quiver to his cavern'd base-
     And what with me wouldst Thou?


          Voice of the THIRD SPIRIT.

     In the blue depth of the waters,
       Where the wave hath no strife,
     Where the wind is a stranger
       And the sea-snake hath life,
     Where the Mermaid is decking
       Her green hair with shells;
     Like the storm on the surface
       Came the sound of thy spells;
     O'er my calm Hall of Coral
       The deep echo roll'd-
     To the Spirit of Ocean
       Thy wishes unfold!


               FOURTH SPIRIT.

     Where the slumbering earthquake
         Lies pillow'd on fire,
     And the lakes of bitumen
         Rise boilingly higher;
     Where the roots of the Andes
         Strike deep in the earth,
     As their summits to heaven
       Shoot soaringly forth;
     I have quitted my birthplace,
       Thy bidding to bide-
     Thy spell hath subdued me,
       Thy will be my guide!


               FIFTH SPIRIT.

     I am the Rider of the wind,
       The Stirrer of the storm;
     The hurricane I left behind
       Is yet with lightning warm;
     To speed to thee, o'er shore and sea
       I swept upon the blast:
     The fleet I met sail'd well, and yet
       'T will sink ere night be past.


               SIXTH SPIRIT.

     My dwelling is the shadow of the night,
     Why doth thy magic torture me with light?


               SEVENTH SPIRIT

     The star which rules thy destiny
     Was ruled, ere earth began, by me:
     It was a world as fresh and fair
     As e'er revolved round sun in air;
     Its course was free and regular,
     Space bosom'd not a lovelier star.
     The hour arrived- and it became
     A wandering mass of shapeless flame,
     A pathless comet, and a curse,
     The menace of the universe;
     Still rolling on with innate force,
     Without a sphere, without a course,
     A bright deformity on high,
     The monster of the upper sky!
     And thou! beneath its influence born-
     Thou worm! whom I obey and scorn-
     Forced by a power (which is not thine,
     And lent thee but to make thee mine)
     For this brief moment to descend,
     Where these weak spirits round thee bend
     And parley with a thing like thee-
     What wouldst thou, Child of Clay! with me?


               The SEVEN SPIRITS

     Earth, ocean, air, night, mountains, winds, thy star,
     Are at thy beck and bidding, Child of Clay!
     Before thee at thy quest their spirits are-
     What wouldst thou with us, son of mortals- say?

MANFRED. Forgetfulness-

FIRST SPIRIT.    Of what- of whom- and why?

MANFRED. Of that which is within me; read it there-
Ye know it, and I cannot utter it.

SPIRIT. We can but give thee that which we possess:
Ask of us subjects, sovereignty, the power
O'er earth, the whole, or portion, or a sign
Which shall control the elements, whereof
We are the dominators,- each and all,
These shall be thine.

MANFRED.          Oblivion, self-oblivion-
Can ye not wring from out the hidden realms
Ye offer so profusely what I ask?

SPIRIT. It is not in our essence, in our skill;
But- thou mayst die.

MANFRED.       Will death bestow it on me?

SPIRIT. We are immortal, and do not forget;
We are eternal; and to us the past
Is, as the future, present. Art thou answered?

MANFRED. Ye mock me- but the power which brought ye here
Hath made you mine. Slaves, scoff not at my will!
The mind, the spirit, the Promethean spark,
The lightning of my being, is as bright,
Pervading, and far-darting as your own,
And shall not yield to yours, though coop'd in clay!
Answer, or I will teach you what I am.

SPIRIT. We answer as we answer'd; our reply
Is even in thine own words.

MANFRED.                   Why say ye so?

SPIRIT. If, as thou say'st, thine essence be as ours,
We have replied in telling thee, the thing
Mortals call death hath nought to do with us.

MANFRED. I then have call'd ye from your realms in vain;
Ye cannot, or ye will not, aid me.

SPIRIT.                           Say;
What we possess we offer; it is thine:
Bethink ere thou dismiss us, ask again-
Kingdom, and sway, and strength, and length of days-

MANFRED. Accursèd! what have I to do with days?
They are too long already.- Hence- begone!

SPIRIT. Yet pause: being here, our will would do thee service;
Bethink thee, is there then no other gift
Which we can make not worthless in thine eyes?

MANFRED. No, none: yet stay- one moment, ere we part-
I would behold ye face to face. I hear
Your voices, sweet and melancholy sounds,
As music on the waters; and I see
The steady aspect of a clear large star;
But nothing more. Approach me as ye are,
Or one, or all, in your accustom'd forms.

SPIRIT. We have no forms, beyond the elements
Of which we are the mind and principle:
But choose a form- in that we will appear.

MANFRED. I have no choice, there is no form on earth
Hideous or beautiful to me. Let him,
Who is most powerful of ye, take such aspect
As unto him may seem most fitting.- Come!

Seventh spirit (appearing in the shape of a beautiful female
figure).  Behold!

MANFRED. Oh God! if it be thus, and thou
Art not a madness and a mockery
I yet might be most happy-I will clasp thee,
And we again will be-                   [The figure vanishes.]
                      My heart is crushed!
                                        [MANFRED falls senseless.]

 (A voice is heard in the Incantation which follows.)

When the moon is on the wave,
  And the glow-worm in the grass,
And the meteor on the grave,
  And the wisp on the morass;
When the falling stars are shooting,
And the answer'd owls are hooting,
And the silent leaves are still
In the shadow of the hill,
Shall my soul be upon thine,
With a power and with a sign.

Though thy slumber may be deep,
Yet thy spirit shall not sleep;
There are shades which will not vanish,
There are thoughts thou canst not banish;
By a power to thee unknown,
Thou canst never be alone;
Thou art wrapt as with a shroud,
Thou art gather'd in a cloud;
And forever shalt thou dwell
In the spirit of this spell.

Though thou seest me not pass by,
Thou shalt feel me with thine eye
As a thing that, though unseen,
Must be near thee, and hath been;
And when in that secret dread
Thou hast turn'd around thy head,
Thou shalt marvel I am not
As thy shadow on the spot,
And the power which thou dost feel
Shall be what thou must conceal.

And a magic voice and verse
Hath baptized thee with a curse;
And a spirit of the air
Hath begirt thee with a snare;
In the wind there is a voice
Shall forbid thee to rejoice;
And to thee shall Night deny
All the quiet of her sky;
And the day shall have a sun,
Which shall make thee wish it done.

From thy false tears I did distil
An essence which hath strength to kill;
From thy own heart I then did wring
The black blood in its blackest spring;
From thy own smile I snatch'd the snake,
For there it coil'd as in a brake;
From thy own lip I drew the charm
Which gave all these their chiefest harm;
In proving every poison known,
I found the strongest was thine own.
By thy cold breast and serpent smile,
By thy unfathom'd gulfs of guile,
By that most seeming virtuous eye,
By thy shut soul's hypocrisy;
By the perfection of thine art
Which pass'd for human thine own heart;
By thy delight in others' pain,
And by thy brotherhood of Cain,
I call upon thee! and compel
Thyself to be thy proper Hell!

And on thy head I pour the vial
Which doth devote thee to this trial;
Nor to slumber, nor to die,
Shall be in thy destiny;
Though thy death shall still seem near
To thy wish, but as a fear;
Lo! the spell now works around thee,
And the clankless chain hath bound thee;
O'er thy heart and brain together
Hath the word been pass'd - now wither!

SCENE II

<i>The Mountain of the Jungfrau. - Time, Morning.- MANFRED alone upon the Cliffs.</i>

MANFRED. The spirits I have raised abandon me,
The spells which I have studied baffled me,
The remedy I reck'd of tortured me;
I lean no more on super-human aid,
It hath no power upon the past, and for
The future, till the past be gulf'd in darkness,
It is not of my search. - My mother Earth!
And thou fresh breaking Day, and you, ye Mountains,
Why are ye beautiful?  I cannot love ye.
And thou, the bright eye of the universe
That openest over all, and unto all
Art a delight - thou shin'st not on my heart.
And you, ye crags, upon whose extreme edge
I stand, and on the torrent's brink beneath
Behold the tall pines dwindled as to shrubs
In dizziness of distance; when a leap,
A stir, a motion, even a breath, would bring
My breast upon its rocky bosom's bed
To rest forever - wherefore do I pause?
I feel the impulse-yet I do not plunge;
I see the peril - yet do not recede;
And my brain reels - and yet my foot is firm.
There is a power upon me which withholds,
And makes it my fatality to live;
If it be life to wear within myself
This barrenness of spirit, and to be
My own soul's sepulchre, for I have ceased
To justify my deeds unto myself -
The last infirmity of evil.  Ay,
Thou winged and cloud-cleaving minister,     [An eagle passes.]
Whose happy flight is highest into heaven,
Well may'st thou swoop so near me - I should be
Thy prey, and gorge thine eaglets; thou art gone
Where the eye cannot follow thee; but thine
Yet pierces downward, onward, or above,
With a pervading vision. - Beautiful!
How beautiful is all this visible world!
How glorious in its action and itself!
But we, who name ourselves its sovereigns, we,
Half dust, half deity, alike unfit
To sink or soar, with our mix'd essence make
A conflict of its elements, and breathe
The breath of degradation and of pride,
Contending with low wants and lofty will,
Till our mortality predominates,
And men are what they name not to themselves,
And trust not to each other.  Hark! the note,
                  [The Shepherd's pipe in the distance is heard.]
The natural music of the mountain reed
(For here the patriarchal days are not
A pastoral fable) pipes in the liberal air,
Mix'd with the sweet bells of the sauntering herd;
My soul would drink those echoes. - Oh, that I were
The viewless spirit of a lovely sound,
A living voice, a breathing harmony,
A bodiless enjoyment - born and dying
With the blessed tone which made me!

       Enter from below a CHAMOIS HUNTER.

CHAMOIS HUNTER.               Even so
This way the chamois leapt: her nimble feet
Have baffled me; my gains to-day will scarce
Repay my break-neck travail. - What is here?
Who seems not of my trade, and yet hath reach'd
A height which none even of our mountaineers
Save our best hunters, may attain: his garb
Is goodly, his mien manly, and his air
Proud as a freeborn peasant's, at this distance -
I will approach him nearer.

MANFRED (not perceiving the other).  To be thus-
Gray-hair'd with anguish, like these blasted pines,
Wrecks of a single winter, barkless, branchless,
A blighted trunk upon a cursèd root
Which but supplies a feeling to decay -
And to be thus, eternally but thus,
Having been otherwise! Now furrowed o'er
With wrinkles, plough'd by moments, not by years
And hours - all tortured into ages - hours
Which I outlive! - Ye toppling crags of ice!
Ye avalanches, whom a breath draws down
In mountainous o'erwhelming, come and crush me!
I hear ye momently above, beneath,
Crash with a frequent conflict, but ye pass,
And only fall on things that still would live;
On the young flourishing forest, or the hut
And hamlet of the harmless villager.

CHAMOIS HUNTER. The mists begin to rise from up the valley;
I'll warn him to descend, or he may chance
To lose at once his way and life together.

MANFRED. The mists boil up around the glaciers; clouds
Rise curling fast beneath me, white and sulphury,
Like foam from the roused ocean of deep Hell,
Whose every wave breaks on a living shore
Heap'd with the damn'd like pebbles.- I am giddy.

CHAMOIS HUNTER. I must approach him cautiously; if near
A sudden step will startle him, and he
Seems tottering already.

MANFRED.             Mountains have fallen,
Leaving a gap in the clouds, and with the shock
Rocking their Alpine brethren; filling up
The ripe green valleys with destruction's splinters;
Damming the rivers with a sudden dash,
Which crush'd the waters into mist, and made
Their fountains find another channel- thus,
Thus, in its old age, did Mount Rosenberg-
Why stood I not beneath it?

CHAMOIS HUNTER.              Friend! have a care,
Your next step may be fatal!- for the love
Of him who made you, stand not on that brink!

MANFRED. (not hearing him).  Such would have been for me a
            fitting tomb;
My bones had then been quiet in their depth;
They had not then been strewn upon the rocks
For the wind's pastime- as thus- thus they shall be-
In this one plunge.- Farewell, ye opening heavens!
Look not upon me thus reproachfully-
Ye were not meant for me- Earth! take these atoms!

[As MANFRED is in act to spring from the cliff, the CHAMOIS HUNTER seizes and retains him with a sudden grasp.]

CHAMOIS HUNTER.  Hold, madman!- though aweary of thy life,
Stain not our pure vales with thy guilty blood!
Away with me- I will not quit my hold.

MANFRED. I am most sick at heart- nay, grasp me not-
I am all feebleness- the mountains whirl
Spinning around me- I grow blind- What art thou?

CHAMOIS HUNTER. I'll answer that anon.- Away with me!
The clouds grow thicker- there- now lean on me-
Place your foot here- here, take this staff, and cling
A moment to that shrub- now give me your hand,
And hold fast by my girdle- softly- well-
The Chalet will be gain'd within an hour.
Come on, we'll quickly find a surer footing,
And something like a pathway, which the torrent
Hath wash'd since winter.- Come, 'tis bravely done;
You should have been a hunter.-  Follow me.

[As they descend the rocks with difficulty, the scene closes.]
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="byron2001091802">
<head>
   <title>Act III</title>
   <toctitle>Act III</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Act III</indextitle>
   <firstline>What is the hour?</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
SCENE I

<i>A Hall in the Castle of Manfred. MANFRED and HERMAN.</i>

MANFRED. What is the hour?

HERMAN.             It wants but one till sunset,
And promises a lovely twilight.

MANFRED.                      Say,
Are all things so disposed of in the tower
As I directed?

HERMAN.    All, my lord, are ready;
Here is the key and casket.

MANFRED.                    It is well:
Thou mayst retire.                                [Exit HERMAN.]

MANFRED (alone).       There is a calm upon me-
Inexplicable stillness! which till now
Did not belong to what I knew of life.
If that I did not know philosophy
To be of all our vanities the motliest,
The merest word that ever fool'd the ear
From out the schoolman's jargon, I should deem
The golden secret, the sought 'Kalon,' found,
And seated in my soul. It will not last,
But it is well to have known it, though but once:
It hath enlarged my thoughts with a new sense,
And I within my tablets would note down
That there is such a feeling.  Who is there?


           Re-enter HERMAN.

HERMAN. My lord, the abbot of St. Maurice craves
To greet your presence.

            Enter the ABBOT OF ST. MAURICE.

ABBOT.          Peace be with Count Manfred!

MANFRED. Thanks, holy father! welcome to these walls;
Thy presence honours them, and blesseth those
Who dwell within them.

ABBOT.           Would it were so, Count!-
But I would fain confer with thee alone.

MANFRED. Herman, retire.- What would my reverend guest?

ABBOT. Thus, without prelude:- Age and zeal, my office,
And good intent, must plead my privilege;
Our near, though not acquainted neighbourhood,
May also be my herald. Rumours strange,
And of unholy nature, are abroad,
And busy with thy name; a noble name
For centuries: may he who bears it now
Transmit it unimpair'd!

MANFRED.         Proceed,- I listen.

ABBOT 'T is said thou holdest converse with the things
Which are forbidden to the search of man;
That with the dwellers of the dark abodes,
The many evil and unheavenly spirits
Which walk the valley of the shade of death,
Thou communest. I know that with mankind,
Thy fellows in creation, thou dost rarely
Exchange thy thoughts, and that thy solitude
Is as an anchorite's, were it but holy.

MANFRED. And what are they who do avouch these things?

ABBOT. My pious brethren, the scared peasantry,
Even thy own vassals, who do look on thee
With most unquiet eyes. Thy life's in peril.

MANFRED. Take it.

ABBOT.         I come to save, and not destroy.
I would not pry into thy secret soul;
But if these things be sooth, there still is time
For penitence and pity: reconcile thee
With the true church, and through the church to heaven.

MANFRED. I hear thee. This is my reply, whate'er
I may have been, or am, doth rest between
Heaven and myself; I shall not choose a mortal
To be my mediator. Have I sinn'd
Against your ordinances? prove and punish!

ABBOT. My son! I did not speak of punishment,
But penitence and pardon; with thyself
The choice of such remains- and for the last,
Our institutions and our strong belief
Have given me power to smooth the path from sin
To higher hope and better thoughts, the first
I leave to heaven- 'Vengeance is mine alone!'
So saith the Lord, and with all humbleness
His servant echoes back the awful word.

MANFRED. Old man! there is no power in holy men,
Nor charm in prayer, nor purifying form
Of penitence, nor outward look, nor fast,
Nor agony, nor, greater than all these,
The innate tortures of that deep despair
Which is remorse without the fear of hell
But all in all sufficient to itself
Would make a hell of heaven,- can exorcise
From out the unbounded spirit, the quick sense
Of its own sins, wrongs, sufferance, and revenge
Upon itself; there is no future pang
Can deal that justice on the self-condemn'd
He deals on his own soul.

ABBOT.                 All this is well;
For this will pass away, and be succeeded
By an auspicious hope, which shall look up
With calm assurance to that blessed place
Which all who seek may win, whatever be
Their earthly errors, so they be atoned:
And the commencement of atonement is
The sense of its necessity.- Say on-
And all our church can teach thee shall be taught;
And all we can absolve thee, shall be pardon'd.

MANFRED. When Rome's sixth Emperor was near his last,
The victim of a self-inflicted wound,
To shun the torments of a public death
From senates once his slaves, a certain soldier,
With show of loyal pity, would have staunch'd
The gushing throat with his officious robe;
The dying Roman thrust him back and said-
Some empire still in his expiring glance-
'It is too late- is this fidelity?'

ABBOT. And what of this?

MANFRED.          I answer with the Roman-
'It is too late!'

ABBOT.             It never can be so,
To reconcile thyself with thy own soul,
And thy own soul with heaven. Hast thou no hope?
'Tis strange- even those who do despair above,
Yet shape themselves some phantasy on earth,
To which frail twig they cling, like drowning men.

MANFRED.  Ay- father! I have had those earthly visions
And noble aspirations in my youth,
To make my own the mind of other men,
The enlightener of nations; and to rise
I knew not whither- it might be to fall;
But fall, even as the mountain-cataract,
Which having leapt from its more dazzling height,
Even in the foaming strength of its abyss
(Which casts up misty columns that become
Clouds raining from the re-ascended skies)
Lies low but mighty still.- But this is past,
My thoughts mistook themselves.

ABBOT.                And wherefore so?

MANFRED. I could not tame my nature down; for he
Must serve who fain would sway- and soothe, and sue,
And watch all time, and pry into all place,
And be a living lie, who would become
A mighty thing amongst the mean, and such
The mass are; I disdain'd to mingle with
A herd, though to be leader- and of wolves.
The lion is alone, and so am I.

ABBOT. And why not live and act with other men?

MANFRED. Because my nature was averse from life;
And yet not cruel; for I would not make,
But find a desolation.  Like the wind,
The red-hot breath of the most lone Simoom,
Which dwells but in the desert, and sweeps o'er
The barren sands which bear no shrubs to blast
And revels o'er their wild and arid waves,
And seeketh not, so that it is not sought,
But being met is deadly,- such hath been
The course of my existence; but there came
Things in my path which are no more.

ABBOT.                             Alas!
I 'gin to fear that thou art past all aid
From me and from my calling; yet so young,
I still would-

MANFRED. Look on me! there is an order
Of mortals on the earth, who do become
Old in their youth, and die ere middle age,
Without the violence of warlike death;
Some perishing of pleasure, some of study,
Some worn with toil, some of mere weariness,
Some of disease, and some insanity,
And some of wither'd or of broken hearts;
For this last is a malady which slays
More than are number'd in the lists of Fate,
Taking all shapes, and bearing many names.
Look upon me! for even of all these things
Have I partaken; and of all these things,
One were enough; then wonder not that I
Am what I am, but that I ever was,
Or, having been, that I am still on earth.

ABBOT. Yet, hear me still-

MANFRED.           Old man! I do respect
Thine order, and revere thine years; I deem
Thy purpose pious, but it is in vain.
Think me not churlish; I would spare thyself,
Far more than me, in shunning at this time
All further colloquy; and so- farewell.    [Exit MANFRED.]

ABBOT. This should have been a noble creature: he
Hath all the energy which would have made
A goodly frame of glorious elements,
Had they been wisely mingled; as it is,
It is an awful chaos- light and darkness,
And mind and dust- and passions and pure thoughts,
Mix'd, and contending without end or order,
All dormant or destructive. He will perish,
And yet he must not; I will try once more,
For such are worth redemption; and my duty
Is to dare all things for a righteous end.
I'll follow him- but cautiously, though surely.   [Exit ABBOT.]

SCENE II

<i>Another Chamber. MANFRED and HERMAN.</i>

HERMAN. My Lord, you bade me wait on you at sunset:
He sinks beyond the mountain.

MANFRED.                     Doth he so?
I will look on him.

     [MANFRED advances to the Window of the Hall.]

                   Glorious Orb! the idol
Of early nature, and the vigorous race
Of undiseased mankind the giant sons
Of the embrace of angels, with a sex
More beautiful than they, which did draw down
The erring spirits who can ne'er return;
Most glorious orb! that wert a worship, ere
The mystery of thy making was reveal'd!
Thou earliest minister of the Almighty,
Which gladden'd, on their mountain tops, the hearts
Of the Chaldean shepherds, till they pour'd
Themselves in orisons! Thou material God!
And representative of the Unknown,
Who chose thee for his shadow! Thou chief star!
Centre of many stars! which mak'st our earth
Endurable, and temperest the hues
And hearts of all who walk within thy rays!
Sire of the seasons! Monarch of the climes
And those who dwell in them! for near or far
Our inborn spirits have a tint of thee,
Even as our outward aspects;- thou dost rise,
And shine, and set in glory. Fare thee well!
I ne'er shall see thee more. As my first glance
Of love and wonder was for thee, then take
My latest look: thou wilt not beam on one
To whom the gifts of life and warmth have been
Of a more fatal nature. He is gone;
I follow.                            [Exit MANFRED.]

SCENE III

<i>The Mountains.- The Castle of MANFRED at some distance.- A Terrace before a Tower.- Time, Twilight. HERMAN, MANUEL, and other Dependants of MANFRED.</i>

HERMAN. 'T is strange enough; night after night, for years,
He hath pursued long vigils in this tower,
Without a witness. I have been within it,-
So have we all been oft-times; but from it
Or its contents, it were impossible
To draw conclusions absolute of aught
His studies tend to. To be sure, there is
One chamber where none enter: I would give
The fee of what I have to come these three years
To pore upon its mysteries.

MANUEL.                 'T were dangerous;
Content thyself with what thou know'st already.

HERMAN. Ah! Manuel! thou art elderly and wise,
And could'st say much; thou hast dwelt within the castle-
How many years is't?

MANUEL.        Ere Count Manfred's birth,
I served his father, whom he nought resembles.

HERMAN. There be more sons in like predicament.
But wherein do they differ?

MANUEL.                       I speak not
Of features or of form, but mind and habits;
Count Sigismund was proud, but gay and free-
A warrior and a reveller; he dwelt not
With books and solitude, nor made the night
A gloomy vigil, but a festal time,
Merrier than day; he did not walk the rocks
And forests like a wolf, nor turn aside
From men and their delights.

HERMAN.                 Beshrew the hour,
But those were jocund times! I would that such
Would visit the old walls again; they look
As if they had forgotten them.

MANUEL.                        These walls
Must change their chieftain first. Oh! I have seen
Some strange things in them, Herman.

HERMAN.                  Come, be friendly;
Relate me some to while away our watch:
I've heard thee darkly speak of an event
Which happen'd hereabouts, by this same tower.

MANUEL. That was a night indeed! I do remember
'T was twilight, as it may be now, and such
Another evening; yon red cloud, which rests
On Eigher's pinnacle, so rested then,-
So like that it might be the same; the wind
Was faint and gusty, and the mountain snows
Began to glitter with the climbing moon.
Count Manfred was, as now, within his tower,-
How occupied, we knew not, but with him
The sole companion of his wanderings
And watchings- her, whom of all earthly things
That lived, the only thing he seem'd to love,-
As he, indeed, by blood was bound to do,
The Lady Astarte, his-
                    Hush! who comes here?

          Enter the ABBOT.

ABBOT. Where is your master?

HERMAN.            Yonder in the tower.

ABBOT. I must speak with him.

MANUEL.             'T is impossible;
He is most private, and must not be thus
Intruded on.

ABBOT.        Upon myself I take
The forfeit of my fault, if fault there be-
But I must see him.

HERMAN.           Thou hast seen him once
This eve already.

ABBOT.         Herman! I command thee,
Knock, and apprize the Count of my approach.

HERMAN. We dare not.

ABBOT.        Then it seems I must be herald
Of my own purpose.

MANUEL.        Reverend father, stop-
I pray you pause.

ABBOT.            Why so?

MANUEL.                  But step this way,
And I will tell you further.          [Exeunt.]

SCENE IV

<i>Interior of the Tower. MANFRED alone.</i>

MANFRED. The stars are forth, the moon above the tops
Of the snow-shining mountains.- Beautiful!
I linger yet with Nature, for the night
Hath been to me a more familiar face
Than that of man; and in her starry shade
Of dim, and solitary loveliness,
I learn'd the language of another world.
I do remember me, that in my youth,
When I was wandering,- upon such a night
I stood within the Coloseum's wall,
Midst the chief relics of almighty Rome.
The trees which grew along the broken arches
Waved dark in the blue midnight, and the stars
Shone through the rents of ruin; from afar
The watchdog bay'd beyond the Tiber; and
More near from out the Caesars' palace came
The owl's long cry, and, interruptedly,
Of distant sentinels the fitful song
Begun and died upon the gentle wind.
Some cypresses beyond the time-worn breach
Appear'd to skirt the horizon, yet they stood
Within a bowshot. Where the Caesars dwelt,
And dwell the tuneless birds of night, amidst
A grove which springs through levell'd battlements,
And twines its roots with the imperial hearths,
Ivy usurps the laurel's place of growth;-
But the gladiators' bloody Circus stands,
A noble wreck in ruinous perfection!
While Caesar's chambers, and the Augustan halls
Grovel on earth in indistinct decay.-
And thou didst shine, thou rolling moon, upon
All this, and cast a wide and tender light,
Which soften'd down the hoar austerity
Of rugged desolation, and fill'd up,
As 'twere anew, the gaps of centuries;
Leaving that beautiful which still was so,
And making that which was not, till the place
Became religion, and the heart ran o'er
With silent worship of the great of old,-
The dead, but sceptred sovereigns, who still rule
Our spirits from their urns.-
                      'T was such a night!
'T is strange that I recall it at this time;
But I have found our thoughts take wildest flight
Even at the moment when they should array
Themselves in pensive order.

             Enter the ABBOT.

ABBOT.                     My good Lord!
I crave a second grace for this approach;
But yet let not my humble zeal offend
By its abruptness- all it hath of ill
Recoils on me; its good in the effect
May light upon your head- could I say heart-
Could I touch that, with words or prayers, I should
Recall a noble spirit which hath wander'd
But is not yet all lost.

MANFRED.               Thou know'st me not;
My days are number'd, and my deeds recorded:
Retire, or 't will be dangerous- Away!

ABBOT. Thou dost not mean to menace me?

MANFRED.                 Not I;
I simply tell thee peril is at hand,
And would preserve thee.

ABBOT.         What dost thou mean?

MANFRED.                  Look there!
What dost thou see?

ABBOT.             Nothing.

MANFRED.                 Look there, I say,
And steadfastly;- now tell me what thou seest?

ABBOT. That which should shake me- but I fear it not;
I see a dusk and awful figure rise,
Like an infernal god from out the earth;
His face wrapt in a mantle, and his form
Robed as with angry clouds: he stands between
Thyself and me- but I do fear him not.

MANFRED. Thou hast no cause; he shall not harm thee, but
His sight may shock thine old limbs into palsy.
I say to thee- Retire!

ABBOT.                   And, I reply,
Never- till I have battled with this fiend:-
What doth he here?

MANFRED.       Why- ay- what doth he here?
I did not send for him,- he is unbidden.

ABBOT. Alas! lost mortal! what with guests like these
Hast thou to do? I tremble for thy sake:
Why doth he gaze on thee, and thou on him?
Ah! he unveils his aspect; on his brow
The thunder-scars are graven; from his eye
Glares forth the immortality of hell-
Avaunt!-

MANFRED.    Pronounce- what is thy mission?

SPIRIT. Come!

ABBOT. What art thou, unknown being? answer!- speak!

SPIRIT. The genius of this mortal.- Come! 't is time.

MANFRED. I am prepared for all things, but deny
The power which summons me. Who sent thee here?

SPIRIT. Thou'lt know anon- Come! Come!

MANFRED.                  I have commanded
Things of an essence greater far than thine,
And striven with thy masters. Get thee hence!

SPIRIT. Mortal! thine hour is come- Away! I say.

MANFRED. I knew, and know my hour is come, but not
To render up my soul to such as thee:
Away! I'll die as I have lived- alone.

SPIRIT. Then I must summon up my brethren.- Rise!
                                   [Other spirits rise up.]

ABBOT. Avaunt! ye evil ones!- Avaunt! I say,-
Ye have no power where piety hath power,
And I do charge ye in the name-

SPIRIT.                            Old man!
We know ourselves, our mission, and thine order;
Waste not thy holy words on idle uses,
It were in vain; this man is forfeited.
Once more I summon him- Away! away!

MANFRED. I do defy ye,- though I feel my soul
Is ebbing from me, yet I do defy ye;
Nor will I hence, while I have earthly breath
To breathe my scorn upon ye- earthly strength
To wrestle, though with spirits; what ye take
Shall be ta'en limb by limb.

SPIRIT.                       Reluctant mortal!
Is this the Magian who would so pervade
The world invisible, and make himself
Almost our equal?- Can it be that thou
Art thus in love with life? the very life
Which made thee wretched!

MANFRED.       Thou false fiend, thou liest!
My life is in its last hour,- that I know,
Nor would redeem a moment of that hour.
I do not combat against death, but thee
And thy surrounding angels; my past power
Was purchased by no compact with thy crew,
But by superior science- penance- daring,
And length of watching- strength of mind- and skill
In knowledge of our fathers when the earth
Saw men and spirits walking side by side
And gave ye no supremacy: I stand
Upon my strength- I do defy- deny-
Spurn back, and scorn ye!-

SPIRIT.               But thy many crimes
Have made thee-

MANFRED.      What are they to such as thee?
Must crimes be punish'd but by other crimes,
And greater criminals?- Back to thy hell!
Thou hast no power upon me, that I feel;
Thou never shalt possess me, that I know:
What I have done is done; I bear within
A torture which could nothing gain from thine.
The mind which is immortal makes itself
Requital for its good or evil thoughts,
Is its own origin of ill and end,
And its own place and time; its innate sense,
When stripp'd of this mortality, derives
No colour from the fleeting things without,
But is absorb'd in sufferance or in joy,
Born from the knowledge of its own desert.
Thou didst not tempt me, and thou couldst not tempt me;
I have not been thy dupe nor am thy prey,
But was my own destroyer, and will be
My own hereafter.- Back, ye baffled fiends!
The hand of death is on me- but not yours!
                                   [The Demons disappear.]

ABBOT. Alas! how pale thou art- thy lips are white-
And thy breast heaves- and in thy gasping throat
The accents rattle. Give thy prayers to Heaven-
Pray- albeit but in thought,- but die not thus.

MANFRED. 'T is over- my dull eyes can fix thee not;
But all things swim around me, and the earth
Heaves as it were beneath me. Fare thee well-
Give me thy hand.

ABBOT.        Cold- cold- even to the heart-
But yet one prayer- Alas! how fares it with thee?

MANFRED.  Old man! 't is not so difficult to die.       [MANFRED expires.]

ABBOT. He's gone, his soul hath ta'en its earthless flight;
Whither? I dread to think; but he is gone.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
