<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="byron" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="byron2002022501">
<head>
   <title>To my son</title>
   <toctitle>To my son</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To my son</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those flaxen locks, those eyes of blue</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Skrevet 1807, først trykt i 1830.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Those flaxen locks, those eyes of blue
Bright as thy mother's in their hue;
Those rosy lips, whose dimples play
And smile to steal the heart away,
Recall a scene of former joy,
And touch thy fathers heart, my Boy!

And thou canst lisp a father's name -
Ah, William, were thine own the same,­
No self'reproach - but, let me cease -
My care for thee shall purchase peace;
Thy mother's shade shall smile in joy,
And pardon all the past, my Boy!

Her lowly grave the turf has prest,
And thou hast known a stranger's breast;
Derision sneers upon thy birth,
And yields thee scarce a name on earth;
Yet shall not these one hops destroy,-
A Father's heart is throe, my Boy!

Why, let the world unfeeling frown,
Must I fond Nature's claim disown?
Ah, no - though moralists reprove,
I hail thee, dearest child of love,
Fair cherub, pledge of youth and joy­
A Father guards thy birth, my Boy!

Oh, 'twill be sweet in thee to trace,
Ere age has wrinkled o'er my face,
Ere half my glass of life is run,
At once a brother and a son;
And all my wane of years employ
In justice done to thee, my Boy!

Although so young thy heedless sire,
Youth will not damp parental fire;
And, wert thou still less dear to me,
While Helen's form revives in thee,
The breast which beat to former joy,
Will ne'er desert its pledge, my Boy!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2002022502">
<head>
   <title>The isles of Greece</title>
   <toctitle>The isles of Greece</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The isles of Greece</indextitle>
   <firstline>The isles of Greece!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
The isles of Greece! the isles of Greece
  Where burning Sappho loved and sung,
Where grew the arts of war and peace,
  Where Delos rose, and Phoebus sprung!
Eternal summer gilds them yet,
But all, except their sun, is set.

The Scian and the Teian muse,
  The hero's harp, the lover's lute,
Have found the fame your shores refuse:
  Their place of birth alone is mute
To sounds which echo further west
Than your sires' 'Islands of the Blest.

The mountains look on Marathon?
  And Marathon looks on the sea;
And musing there an hour alone,
  I dream'd that Greece might still be free;
For standing on the Persians' grave,
I could not deem myself a slave.

A king sate on the rocky brow
  Which looks o'er sea-born Salamis;
And ships, by thousands, lay below,
  And men in nations;?all were his!
He counted them at break of day?
And when the sun set, where were they?

And where are they? and where art thou,
  My country? On thy voiceless shore
The heroic lay is tuneless now?
  The heroic bosom beats no more!
And must thy lyre, so long divine,
Degenerate into hands like mine?

'Tis something in the dearth of fame,
  Though link'd among a fetter'd race,
To feel at least a patriot's shame,
  Even as I sing, suffuse my face;
For what is left the poet here?
For Greeks a blush?for Greece a tear.

Must we but weep o'er days more blest?
  Must we but blush??Our fathers bled.
Earth! render back from out thy breast
  A remnant of our Spartan dead!
Of the three hundred grant but three,
To make a new Thermopyl?!

What, silent still? and silent all?
  Ah! no;?the voices of the dead
Sound like a distant torrent's fall,
  And answer, 'Let one living head,
But one, arise,?we come, we come!'
'Tis but the living who are dumb.

In vain?in vain: strike other chords;
  Fill high the cup with Samian wine!
Leave battles to the Turkish hordes,
  And shed the blood of Scio's vine:
Hark! rising to the ignoble call?
How answers each bold Bacchanal!

You have the Pyrrhic dance as yet;
  Where is the Pyrrhic phalanx gone?
Of two such lessons, why forget
  The nobler and the manlier one?
You have the letters Cadmus gave?
Think ye he meant them for a slave?

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!
  We will not think of themes like these!
It made Anacreon's song divine:
  He served?but served Polycrates?
A tyrant; but our masters then
Were still, at least, our countrymen.

The tyrant of the Chersonese
  Was freedom's best and bravest friend;
That tyrant was Miltiades!
  O that the present hour would lend
Another despot of the kind!
Such chains as his were sure to bind.

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!
  On Suli's rock, and Parga's shore,
Exists the remnant of a line
  Such as the Doric mothers bore;
And there, perhaps, some seed is sown,
The Heracleidan blood might own.

Trust not for freedom to the Franks?
  They have a king who buys and sells;
In native swords and native ranks
  The only hope of courage dwells:
But Turkish force and Latin fraud
Would break your shield, however broad.

Fill high the bowl with Samian wine!
  Our virgins dance beneath the shade?
I see their glorious black eyes shine;
  But gazing on each glowing maid,
My own the burning tear-drop laves,
To think such breasts must suckle slaves.

Place me on Sunium's marbled steep,
  Where nothing, save the waves and I,
May hear our mutual murmurs sweep;
  There, swan-like, let me sing and die:
A land of slaves shall ne'er be mine?
Dash down yon cup of Samian wine!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2005050701">
<head>
   <title>The Girl of Cadiz</title>
   <firstline>Oh never talk again to me</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Skrevet 1809.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Oh never talk again to me
Of northern climes and British ladies;
It has not been your lot to see,
Like me, the lovely girl of Cadiz
Although her eye be not of blue,
Nor fair her locks, like English lasses,
How far its own expressive hue
The languid azure eye surpasses!

Prometheus-like, from heaven she stole
The fire, that through those silken lashes
In darkest glances seem to roll,
From eyes that cannot hide their flashes:
And as along her bosom steal
In lengthen'd flow her raven tresses,
You'd swear each clustering lock could feel,
And curl'd to give her neck caresses.

Our English maids are long to woo,
And frigid even in possession;
And if their charms be fair to view,
Their lips are slow at Loves confession:
But, born beneath a brighter sun,
For love ordain'd the Spanish maid is,
And who,—when fondly, fairly won,—
Enchants you like the Girl of Cadiz?

The Spanish maid is no coquette,
Nor joys to see a lover tremble,
And if she love, or if she hate,
Alike she knows not to dissemble.
Her heart can ne'er be bought or sold—
Howe'er it beats, it beats sincerely;
And, though it will not bend to gold,
'T will love you long and love you dearly.

The Spanish girl that meets your love
Ne'er taunts you with a mock denial,
For every thought is bent to prove
Her passion in the hour of trial.
When thronging foemen menace Spain,
She dares the deed and shares the danger;
And should her lover press the plain,
She hurls the spear, her love's avenger.

And when, beneath the evening star,
She mingles in the gay Bolero,
Or sings to her attuned guitar
Of Christian knight or Moorish hero,
Or counts her beads with fairy hand
Beneath the twinkling rays of Hesper,
Or joins Devotion's choral band,
To chaunt the sweet and hallow'd vesper;—

In each her charms the heart must move
Of all who venture to behold her;
Then let not maids less fair reprove
Because her bosom is not colder:
Through many a clime 't is mine to roam
Where many a soft and melting maid is,
But none abroad, and few at home,
May match the dark-eyed Girl of Cadiz.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2018043001">
<head>
   <title>Farewell! If ever fondest prayer</title>
   <firstline>Farewell! If ever fondest prayer</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Farewell! If ever fondest prayer
For another’s weal avail’d on high,
Mine will not alle be lost in air,
But waft thy name beyond the sky.
‘Twere vain to speak, to weep, to sigh:
Oh! more than tears of blood can tell,
When wrung from guilt’s expiring eye,
Are in that word – Farewell! – Farewell!

These lips are mute, these eyes are dry;
But in my breast and in my brain,
Awake the pangs that pass not by,
The thought that ne’er shall sleep again.
My soul nor deigns nor dares complain,
Though grief and passion there rebel;
I only know we loved in vain —
I only feel – Farewell! – Farewell!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2018120801">
<head>
   <title>Parisina</title>
   <firstline>It is the hour when from the boughs</firstline>
   <notes>
       <note>Fra <i>The works of Lord Byron</i>, Ernest Hartley Coleridge (ed.), volume 3. John Murray, 1898.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<nonum><center><sc>i.</sc></center></nonum>

It is the hour when from the boughs
The nightingale’s high note is heard;
It is the hour when lovers’ vows
Seem sweet in every whispered word;
And gentle winds, and waters near,
Make music to the lonely ear.
Each flower the dews have lightly wet,
And in the sky the stars are met,
And on the wave is deeper blue,
And on the leaf a browner hue,
And in the heaven that clear obscure,
So softly dark, and darkly pure,
Which follows the decline of day,
As twilight melts beneath the moon away.

<nonum><center><sc>ii.</sc></center></nonum>

But it is not to list to the waterfall
That Parisina leaves her hall,
And it is not to gaze on the heavenly light
That the Lady walks in the shadow of night;
And if she sits in Este’s bower,
’Tis not for the sake of its full-blown flower;
She listens—but not for the nightingale—
Though her ear expects as soft a tale.
There glides a step through the foliage thick,
And her cheek grows pale, and her heart beats quick.
There whispers a voice through the rustling leaves,
And her blush returns, and her bosom heaves:
A moment more—and they shall meet—
’Tis past—her Lover’s at her feet.

<nonum><center><sc>iii.</sc></center></nonum>

And what unto them is the world beside,
With all its change of time and tide?
Its living things—its earth and sky—
Are nothing to their mind and eye.
And heedless as the dead are they
Of aught around, above, beneath;
As if all else had passed away,
They only for each other breathe;
Their very sighs are full of joy
So deep, that did it not decay,
That happy madness would destroy
The hearts which feel its fiery sway:
Of guilt, of peril, do they deem
In that tumultuous tender dream?
Who that have felt that passion’s power,
Or paused, or feared in such an hour?
Or thought how brief such moments last?
But yet—they are already past!
Alas! we must awake before
We know such vision comes no more.

<nonum><center><sc>iv.</sc></center></nonum>

With many a lingering look they leave
The spot of guilty gladness past:
And though they hope, and vow, they grieve,
As if that parting were the last.
The frequent sigh—the long embrace—
The lip that there would cling for ever,
While gleams on Parisina’s face
The Heaven she fears will not forgive her,
As if each calmly conscious star
Beheld her frailty from afar—
The frequent sigh, the long embrace,
Yet binds them to their trysting-place.
But it must come, and they must part
In fearful heaviness of heart,
With all the deep and shuddering chill
Which follows fast the deeds of ill.


<nonum><center><sc>v.</sc></center></nonum>

And Hugo is gone to his lonely bed,
To covet there another’s bride;
But she must lay her conscious head
A husband’s trusting heart beside.
But fevered in her sleep she seems,
And red her cheek with troubled dreams,
And mutters she in her unrest
A name she dare not breathe by day,
And clasps her Lord unto the breast
Which pants for one away:
And he to that embrace awakes,
And, happy in the thought, mistakes
That dreaming sigh, and warm caress,
For such as he was wont to bless;
And could in very fondness weep
O’er her who loves him even in sleep.

<nonum><center><sc>vi.</sc></center></nonum>

He clasped her sleeping to his heart,
And listened to each broken word:
He hears—Why doth Prince Azo start,
As if the Archangel’s voice he heard?
And well he may—a deeper doom
Could scarcely thunder o’er his tomb,
When he shall wake to sleep no more,
And stand the eternal throne before.
And well he may—his earthly peace
Upon that sound is doomed to cease.
That sleeping whisper of a name
Bespeaks her guilt and Azo’s shame.
And whose that name? that o’er his pillow
Sounds fearful as the breaking billow,
Which rolls the plank upon the shore,
And dashes on the pointed rock
The wretch who sinks to rise no more,—
So came upon his soul the shock.
And whose that name?—’tis Hugo’s,—his—
In sooth he had not deemed of this!—
’Tis Hugo’s,—he, the child of one
He loved—his own all-evil son—
The offspring of his wayward youth,
When he betrayed Bianca’s truth,
The maid whose folly could confide
In him who made her not his bride.

<nonum><center><sc>vii.</sc></center></nonum>

He plucked his poniard in its sheath,
But sheathed it ere the point was bare;
Howe’er unworthy now to breathe,
He could not slay a thing so fair—
At least, not smiling—sleeping—there—
Nay, more:—he did not wake her then,
But gazed upon her with a glance
Which, had she roused her from her trance,
Had frozen her sense to sleep again;
And o’er his brow the burning lamp
Gleamed on the dew-drops big and damp.
She spake no more—but still she slumbered—
While, in his thought, her days are numbered.

<nonum><center><sc>viii.</sc></center></nonum>

And with the morn he sought and found,
In many a tale from those around,
The proof of all he feared to know,
Their present guilt—his future woe;
The long-conniving damsels seek
To save themselves, and would transfer
The guilt—the shame—the doom—to her:
Concealment is no more—they speak
All circumstance which may compel
Full credence to the tale they tell:
And Azo’s tortured heart and ear
Have nothing more to feel or hear.

<nonum><center><sc>ix.</sc></center></nonum>

He was not one who brooked delay:
Within the chamber of his state,
The Chief of Este’s ancient sway
Upon his throne of judgement sate;
His nobles and his guards are there,—
Before him is the sinful pair;
Both young,—and one how passing fair!
With swordless belt, and fettered hand,
Oh, Christ! that thus a son should stand
Before a father’s face!
Yet thus must Hugo meet his sire,
And hear the sentence of his ire,
The tale of his disgrace!
And yet he seems not overcome,
Although, as yet, his voice be dumb.

<nonum><center><sc>x.</sc></center></nonum>

And still,—and pale—and silently
Did Parisina wait her doom;
How changed since last her speaking eye
Glanced gladness round the glittering room,
Where high-born men were proud to wait—
Where Beauty watched to imitate
Her gentle voice—her lovely mien—
And gather from her air and gait
The graces of its Queen:
Then,—had her eye in sorrow wept,
A thousand warriors forth had leapt,
A thousand swords had sheathless shone,
And made her quarrel all their own.
Now,—what is she? and what are they?
Can she command, or these obey?
All silent and unheeding now,
With downcast eyes and knitting brow,
And folded arms, and freezing air,
And lips that scarce their scorn forbear,
Her knights, her dames, her court—is there:
And he—the chosen one, whose lance
Had yet been couched before her glance,
Who—were his arm a moment free—
Had died or gained her liberty;
The minion of his father’s bride,—
He, too, is fettered by her side;
Nor sees her swoln and full eye swim
Less for her own despair than him:
Those lids—o’er which the violet vein
Wandering, leaves a tender stain,
Shining through the smoothest white
That e’er did softest kiss invite—
Now seemed with hot and livid glow
To press, not shade, the orbs below;
Which glance so heavily, and fill,
As tear on tear grows gathering still

<nonum><center><sc>xi.</sc></center></nonum>

And he for her had also wept,
But for the eyes that on him gazed:
His sorrow, if he felt it, slept;
Stern and erect his brow was raised.
Whate’er the grief his soul avowed,
He would not shrink before the crowd;
But yet he dared not look on her;
Remembrance of the hours that were—
His guilt—his love—his present state—
His father’s wrath, all good men’s hate—
His earthly, his eternal fate—
And hers,—oh, hers! he dared not throw
One look upon that death-like brow!
Else had his rising heart betrayed
Remorse for all the wreck it made.

<nonum><center><sc>xii.</sc></center></nonum>

And Azo spake:—“But yesterday
I gloried in a wife and son;
That dream this morning passed away;
Ere day declines, I shall have none.
My life must linger on alone;
Well,—let that pass,—there breathes not one
Who would not do as I have done:
Those ties are broken—not by me;
Let that too pass;—the doom’s prepared!
Hugo, the priest awaits on thee,
And then—thy crime’s reward!
Away! address thy prayers to Heaven.
Before its evening stars are met,
Learn if thou there canst be forgiven:
Its mercy may absolve thee yet.
But here, upon the earth beneath,
There is no spot where thou and I
Together for an hour could breathe:
Farewell! I will not see thee die—
But thou, frail thing! shall view his head—
Away! I cannot speak the rest:
Go! woman of the wanton breast;
Not I, but thou his blood dost shed:
Go! if that sight thou canst outlive,
And joy thee in the life I give.”

<nonum><center><sc>xiii.</sc></center></nonum>

And here stern Azo hid his face—
For on his brow the swelling vein
Throbbed as if back upon his brain
The hot blood ebbed and flowed again;
And therefore bowed he for a space,
And passed his shaking hand along
His eye, to veil it from the throng;
While Hugo raised his chainéd hands,
And for a brief delay demands
His father’s ear: the silent sire
Forbids not what his words require.
“It is not that I dread the death—
For thou hast seen me by thy side
All redly through the battle ride,
And that—not once a useless brand—
Thy slaves have wrested from my hand
Hath shed more blood in cause of thine,
Than e’er can stain the axe of mine:
Thou gav’st, and may’st resume my breath,
A gift for which I thank thee not;
Nor are my mother’s wrongs forgot,
Her slighted love and ruined name,
Her offspring’s heritage of shame;
But she is in the grave, where he,
Her son—thy rival—soon shall be.
Her broken heart—my severed head—
Shall witness for thee from the dead
How trusty and how tender were
Thy youthful love—paternal care.
’Tis true that I have done thee wrong—
But wrong for wrong:—this,—deemed thy bride,
The other victim of thy pride,—
Thou know’st for me was destined long;
Thou saw’st, and coveted’st her charms;
And with thy very crime—my birth,—
Thou taunted’st me—as little worth;
A match ignoble for her arms;
Because, forsooth, I could not claim
The lawful heirship of thy name,
Nor sit on Este’s lineal throne;
Yet, were a few short summers mine,
My name should more than Este’s shine
With honours all my own.
I had a sword—and have a breast
That should have won as haughta crest
As ever waved along the line
Of all these sovereign sires of thine.
Not always knightly spurs are worn
The brightest by the better born;
And mine have lanced my courser’s flank
Before proud chiefs of princely rank,
When charging to the cheering cry
Of ‘Este and of Victory!’
I will not plead the cause of crime,
Nor sue thee to redeem from time
A few brief hours or days that must
At length roll o’er my reckless dust;—
Such maddening moments as my past,
They could not, and they did not, last;—
Albeit my birth and name be base,
And thy nobility of race
Disdained to deck a thing like me—
Yet in my lineaments they trace
Some features of my father’s face,
And in my spirit—all of thee.
From thee this tamelessness of heart—
From thee—nay, wherefore dost thou start?——
From thee in all their vigour came
My arm of strength, my soul of flame—
Thou didst not give me life alone,
But all that made me more thine own.
See what thy guilty love hath done!
Repaid thee with too like a son!
I am no bastard in my soul,
For that, like thine, abhorred control;
And for my breath, that hasty boon
Thou gav’st and wilt resume so soon,
I valued it no more than thou,
When rose thy casque above thy brow,
And we, all side by side, have striven,
And o’er the dead our coursers driven:
The past is nothing—and at last
The future can but be the past;
Yet would I that I then had died:
For though thou work’dst my mother’s ill,
And made thy own my destined bride,
I feel thou art my father still:
And harsh as sounds thy hard decree,
’Tis not unjust, although from thee.
Begot in sin, to die in shame,
My life begun and ends the same:
As erred the sire, so erred the son,
And thou must punish both in one.
My crime seems worst to human view,
But God must judge between us too!”

<nonum><center><sc>xiv.</sc></center></nonum>

He ceased—and stood with folded arms,
On which the circling fetters sounded;
And not an ear but felt as wounded,
Of all the chiefs that there were ranked,
When those dull chains in meeting clanked:
Till Parisina’s fatal charms
Again attracted every eye—
Would she thus hear him doomed to die!
She stood, I said, all pale and still,
The living cause of Hugo’s ill:
Her eyes unmoved, but full and wide,
Not once had turned to either side—
Nor once did those sweet eyelids close,
Or shade the glance o’er which they rose,
But round their orbs of deepest blue
The circling white dilated grew—
And there with glassy gaze she stood
As ice were in her curdled blood;
But every now and then a tear
So large and slowly gathered slid
From the long dark fringe of that fair lid,
It was a thing to see, not hear!
And those who saw, it did surprise,
Such drops could fall from human eyes.
To speak she thought—the imperfect note
Was choked within her swelling throat,
Yet seemed in that low hollow groan
Her whole heart gushing in the tone.
It ceased—again she thought to speak,
Then burst her voice in one long shriek,
And to the earth she fell like stone
Or statue from its base o’erthrown,
More like a thing that ne’er had life,—
A monument of Azo’s wife,—
Than her, that living guilty thing,
Whose every passion was a sting,
Which urged to guilt, but could not bear
That guilt’s detection and despair.
But yet she lived—and all too soon
Recovered from that death-like swoon—
But scarce to reason—every sense
Had been o’erstrung by pangs intense;
And each frail fibre of her brain
(As bowstrings, when relaxed by rain,
The erring arrow launch aside)
Sent forth her thoughts all wild and wide—
The past a blank, the future black,
With glimpses of a dreary track,
Like lightning on the desert path,
When midnight storms are mustering wrath.
She feared—she felt that something ill
Lay on her soul, so deep and chill;
That there was sin and shame she knew,
That some one was to die—but who?
She had forgotten:—did she breathe?
Could this be still the earth beneath,
The sky above, and men around;
Or were they fiends who now so frowned
On one, before whose eyes each eye
Till then had smiled in sympathy?
All was confused and undefined
To her all-jarred and wandering mind;
A chaos of wild hopes and fears:
And now in laughter, now in tears,
But madly still in each extreme,
She strove with that convulsive dream;
For so it seemed on her to break:
Oh! vainly must she strive to wake!

<nonum><center><sc>xv.</sc></center></nonum>

The Convent bells are ringing,
But mournfully and slow;
In the grey square turret swinging,
With a deep sound, to and fro.
Heavily to the heart they go!
Hark! the hymn is singing—
The song for the dead below,
Or the living who shortly shall be so!
For a departed being’s soul
The death-hymn peals and the hollow bells knoll:
He is near his mortal goal;
Kneeling at the Friar’s knee,
Sad to hear, and piteous to see—
Kneeling on the bare cold ground.
With the block before and the guards around;
And the headsman with his bare arm ready,
That the blow may be both swift and steady,
Feels if the axe be sharp and true
Since he set its edge anew:
While the crowd in a speechless circle gather
To see the Son fall by the doom of the Father!

<nonum><center><sc>xvi.</sc></center></nonum>

It is a lovely hour as yet
Before the summer sun shall set,
Which rose upon that heavy day,
And mock’d it with his steadiest ray;
And his evening beams are shed
Full on Hugo’s fated head,
As his last confession pouring
To the monk, his doom deploring
In penitential holiness,
He bends to hear his accents bless
With absolution such as may
Wipe our mortal stains away.
That high sun on his head did glisten
As he there did bow and listen,
And the rings of chestnut hair
Curled half down his neck so bare;
But brighter still the beam was thrown
Upon the axe which near him shone
With a clear and ghastly glitter——
Oh! that parting hour was bitter!
Even the stern stood chilled with awe:
Dark the crime, and just the law—
Yet they shuddered as they saw.

<nonum><center><sc>xvii.</sc></center></nonum>

The parting prayers are said and over
Of that false son, and daring lover!
His beads and sins are all recounted,
His hours to their last minute mounted;
His mantling cloak before was stripped,
His bright brown locks must now be clipped;
’Tis done—all closely are they shorn;
The vest which till this moment worn—
The scarf which Parisina gave—
Must not adorn him to the grave.
Even that must now be thrown aside,
And o’er his eyes the kerchief tied;
But no—that last indignity
Shall ne’er approach his haughty eye.
All feelings seemingly subdued,
In deep disdain were half renewed,
When headsman’s hands prepared to bind
Those eyes which would not brook such blind,
As if they dared not look on death.
“No—yours my forfeit blood and breath;
These hands are chained, but let me die
At least with an unshackled eye—
Strike:"—and as the word he said,
Upon the block he bowed his head;
These the last accents Hugo spoke:
“Strike”—and flashing fell the stroke—
Rolled the head—and, gushing, sunk
Back the stained and heaving trunk,
In the dust, which each deep vein
Slaked with its ensanguined rain;
His eyes and lips a moment quiver,
Convulsed and quick—then fix for ever.
He died, as erring man should die,
Without display, without parade;
Meekly had he bowed and prayed,
As not disdaining priestly aid,
Nor desperate of all hope on high.
And while before the Prior kneeling,
His heart was weaned from earthly feeling;
His wrathful Sire—his Paramour—
What were they in such an hour?
No more reproach,—no more despair,—
No thought but Heaven,—no word but prayer—
Save the few which from him broke,
When, bared to meet the headsman’s stroke,
He claimed to die with eyes unbound,
His sole adieu to those around.

<nonum><center><sc>xviii.</sc></center></nonum>

Still as the lips that closed in death,
Each gazer’s bosom held his breath:
But yet, afar, from man to man,
A cold electricshiver ran,
As down the deadly blow descended
On him whose life and love thus ended;
And, with a hushing sound compressed,
A sigh shrunk back on every breast;
But no more thrilling noise rose there,
Beyond the blow that to the block
Pierced through with forced and sullen shock,
Save one:—what cleaves the silent air
So madly shrill, so passing wild?
That, as a mother’s o’er her child,
Done to death by sudden blow,
To the sky these accents go,
Like a soul’s in endless woe.
Through Azo’s palace-lattice driven,
That horrid voice ascends to heaven,
And every eye is turned thereon;
But sound and sight alike are gone!
It was a woman’s shriek—and ne’er
In madlier accents rose despair;
And those who heard it, as it past,
In mercy wished it were the last.

<nonum><center><sc>xix.</sc></center></nonum>

Hugo is fallen; and, from that hour,
No more in palace, hall, or bower,
Was Parisina heard or seen:
Her name—as if she ne’er had been—
Was banished from each lip and ear,
Like words of wantonness or fear;
And from Prince Azo’s voice, by none
Was mention heard of wife or son;
No tomb—no memory had they;
Theirs was unconsecrated clay—
At least the Knight’s who died that day.
But Parisina’s fate lies hid
Like dust beneath the coffin lid:
Whether in convent she abode,
And won to heaven her dreary road,
By blighted and remorseful years
Of scourge, and fast, and sleepless tears;
Or if she fell by bowl or steel,
For that dark love she dared to feel:
Or if, upon the moment smote,
She died by tortures less remote,
Like him she saw upon the block
With heart that shared the headsman’s shock,
In quickened brokenness that came,
In pity o’er her shattered frame,
None knew—and none can ever know:
But whatsoe’er its end below,
Her life began and closed in woe!

<nonum><center><sc>xx.</sc></center></nonum>

And Azo found another bride,
And goodly sons grew by his side;
But none so lovely and so brave
As him who withered in the grave;
Or if they were—on his cold eye
Their growth but glanced unheeded by,
Or noticed with a smothered sigh.
But never tear his cheek descended,
And never smile his brow unbended;
And o’er that fair broad brow were wrought
The intersected lines of thought;
Those furrows which the burning share
Of Sorrow ploughs untimely there;
Scars of the lacerating mind
Which the Soul’s war doth leave behind.
He was past all mirth or woe:
Nothing more remained below
But sleepless nights and heavy days,
A mind all dead to scorn or praise,
A heart which shunned itself—and yet
That would not yield, nor could forget,
Which, when it least appeared to melt,
Intensely thought—intensely felt:
The deepest ice which ever froze
Can only o’er the surface close;
The living stream lies quick below,
And flows, and cannot cease to flow.
Still was his sealed-up bosom haunted
By thoughts which Nature hath implanted;
Too deeply rooted thence to vanish,
Howe’er our stifled tears we banish;
When struggling as they rise to start,
We check those waters of the heart,
They are not dried—those tears unshed
But flow back to the fountain head,
And resting in their spring more pure,
For ever in its depth endure,
Unseen—unwept—but uncongealed,
And cherished most where least revealed.
With inward starts of feeling left,
To throb o’er those of life bereft,
Without the power to fill again
The desert gap which made his pain;
Without the hope to meet them where
United souls shall gladness share;
With all the consciousness that he
Had only passed a just decree;
That they had wrought their doom of ill;
Yet Azo’s age was wretched still.
The tainted branches of the tree,
If lopped with care, a strength may give,
By which the rest shall bloom and live
All greenly fresh and wildly free:
But if the lightning, in its wrath,
The waving boughs with fury scathe,
The massy trunk the ruin feels,
And never more a leaf reveals.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2018120802">
<head>
   <title>Stanzas Composed During A Thunderstorm</title>
   <firstline>Chill and mirk is the nightly blast</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Chill and mirk is the nightly blast,
Where Pindus' mountains rise,
And angry clouds are pouring fast
The vengeance of the skies.

Our guides are gone, our hope is lost,
And lightnings, as they play,
But show where rocks our path have crost,
Or gild the torrent's spray.

Is yon a cot I saw, though low?
When lightning broke the gloom—
How welcome were its shade!—ah, no!
'Tis but a Turkish tomb.

Through sounds of foaming waterfalls,
I hear a voice exclaim—
My way-worn countryman, who calls
On distant England's name.

A shot is fired—by foe or friend?
Another—'tis to tell
The mountain-peasants to descend,
And lead us where they dwell.

Oh! who in such a night will dare
To tempt the wilderness?
And who 'mid thunder-peals can hear
Our signal of distress?

And who that heard our shouts would rise
To try the dubious road?
Nor rather deem from nightly cries
That outlaws were abroad.

Clouds burst, skies flash, oh, dreadful hour!
More fiercely pours the storm!
Yet here one thought has still the power
To keep my bosom warm.

While wandering through each broken path,
O'er brake and craggy brow;
While elements exhaust their wrath,
Sweet Florence, where art thou?

Not on the sea, not on the sea—
Thy bark hath long been gone:
Oh, may the storm that pours on me,
Bow down my head alone!

Full swiftly blew the swift Siroc,
When last I pressed thy lip;
And long ere now, with foaming shock,
Impelled thy gallant ship.

Now thou art safe; nay, long ere now
Hast trod the shore of Spain;
'Twere hard if aught so fair as thou
Should linger on the main.

And since I now remember thee
In darkness and in dread,
As in those hours of revelry
Which Mirth and Music sped;

Do thou, amid the fair white walls,
If Cadiz yet be free,
At times from out her latticed halls
Look o'er the dark blue sea;

Then think upon Calypso's isles,
Endeared by days gone by;
To others give a thousand smiles,
To me a single sigh.

And when the admiring circle mark
The paleness of thy face,
A half-formed tear, a transient spark
Of melancholy grace,

Again thou'lt smile, and blushing shun
Some coxcomb's raillery;
Nor own for once thou thought'st on one,
Who ever thinks on thee.

Though smile and sigh alike are vain,
When severed hearts repine
My spirit flies o'er Mount and Main
And mourns in search of thine.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019021201">
<head>
   <title>Away, away, ye notes of woe!</title>
   <firstline>Away, away, ye notes of woe!</firstline>
   <notes>
       <note>December 6, 1811.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Away, away, ye notes of woe!
Be silent, thou once soothing strain,
Or I must flee from hence—for, oh!
I dare not trust those sounds again.
To me they speak of brighter days
But lull the chords, for now, alas!
I must not think, I may not gaze,
On what I am—on what I was.

The voice that made those sounds more sweet
Is hush'd, and all their charms are fled
And now their softest notes repeat
A dirge, an anthem o'er the dead!
Yes, Thyrza! yes, they breathe of thee,
Beloved dust! since dust thou art;
And all that once was harmony
Is worse than discord to my heart!

'Tis silent all!—but on my ear
The well remember'd echoes thrill;
I hear a voice I would not hear,
A voice that now might well be still:
Yet oft my doubting soul 'twill shake;
Even slumber owns its gentle tone,
Till consciousness will vainly wake
To listen, though the dream be flown.

Sweet Thyrza! waking as in sleep,
Thou art but now a lovely dream;
A star that trembled o'er the deep,
Then turn'd from earth its tender beam.
But he who through life's dreary way
Must pass, when heaven is veil'd in wrath,
Will long lament the vanish'd ray
That scatter'd gladness o'er his path.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>


<text id="byron201908241">
<head>
    <title>Stanzas To Augusta</title>
    <firstline>When all around grew drear and dark</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
When all around grew drear and dark,
And reason half withheld her ray—
And hope but shed a dying spark
Which more misled my lonely way;

In that deep midnight of the mind,
And that internal strife of heart,
When dreading to be deemed too kind,
The weak despair—the cold depart;

When fortune changed—and love fled far,
And hatred’s shafts flew thick and fast,
Thou wert the solitary star
Which rose, and set not to the last.

Oh, blest be thine unbroken light!
That watched me as a seraph’s eye,
And stood between me and the night,
For ever shining sweetly nigh.

And when the cloud upon us came,
Which strove to blacken o’er thy ray—
Then purer spread its gentle flame,
And dashed the darkness all away.

Still may thy spirit dwell on mine,
And teach it what to brave or brook—
There’s more in one soft word of thine
Than in the world’s defied rebuke.

Thou stood’st as stands a lovely tree
That, still unbroke though gently bent,
Still waves with fond fidelity
Its boughs above a monument.

The winds might rend, the skies might pour,
But there thou wert—and still wouldst be
Devoted in the stormiest hour
To shed thy weeping leaves o’er me.

But thou and thine shall know no blight,
Whatever fate on me may fall;
For heaven in sunshine will requite
The kind—and thee the most of all.

Then let the ties of baffled love
Be broken—thine will never break;
Thy heart can feel—but will not move;
Thy soul, though soft, will never shake.

And these, when all was lost beside,
Were found, and still are fixed in thee;—
And bearing still a breast so tried,
Earth is no desert—e’en to me.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090701">
<head>
    <title>Answer To A Beautiful Poem, Written By Montgomery, Author Of “The Wanderer Of Switzerland,” Etc., Entitled “The Common Lot.”</title>
    <linktitle>Answer To A Beautiful Poem, Entitled “The Common Lot.”</linktitle>
    <firstline>Montgomery! true, the common lot</firstline>
    <notes>
        <note>Cf. James Montgomery: <xref poem="montgomery2019090701"/>.</note>
    </notes>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Montgomery! true, the common lot
  Of mortals lies in Lethe’s wave;
Yet some shall never be forgot,
  Some shall exist beyond the grave.

“Unknown the region of his birth,”
  The hero rolls the tide of war;
Yet not unknown his martial worth,
  Which glares a meteor from afar.

His joy or grief, his weal or woe,
  Perchance may ’scape the page of fame;
Yet nations, now unborn, will know
  The record of his deathless name.

The Patriot’s and the Poet’s frame
  Must share the common tomb of all:
Their glory will not sleep the same;
  ‘That’ will arise, though Empires fall.

The lustre of a Beauty’s eye
  Assumes the ghastly stare of death;
The fair, the brave, the good must die,
  And sink the yawning grave beneath.

Once more, the speaking eye revives,
  Still beaming through the lover’s strain;
For Petrarch’s Laura still survives:
  She died, but ne’er will die again.

The rolling seasons pass away,
  And Time, untiring, waves his wing;
Whilst honour’s laurels ne’er decay,
  But bloom in fresh, unfading spring.

All, all must sleep in grim repose,
  Collected in the silent tomb;
The old, the young, with friends and foes,
  Fest’ring alike in shrouds, consume.

The mouldering marble lasts its day,
  Yet falls at length an useless fane;
To Ruin’s ruthless fangs a prey,
  The wrecks of pillar’d Pride remain.

What, though the sculpture be destroy’d,
  From dark Oblivion meant to guard;
A bright renown shall be enjoy’d,
  By those, whose virtues claim reward.

Then do not say the common lot
  Of all lies deep in Lethe’s wave;
Some few who ne’er will be forgot
  Shall burst the bondage of the grave.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090801">
<head>
    <title>When I Roved a Young Highlander</title>
    <firstline>When I rov'd a young Highlander o'er the dark heath</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>When</sc> I rov'd a young Highlander o'er the dark heath,
⁠ And climb'd thy steep summit, oh Morven of snow!
To gaze on the torrent that thunder'd beneath,
  Or the mist of the tempest that gather'd below;
Untutor'd by science, a stranger to fear,
  And rude as the rocks, where my infancy grew,
No feeling, save one, to my bosom was dear;
⁠ Need I say, my sweet Mary, 'twas centred in you?

Yet it could not be Love, for I knew not the name,—
⁠ What passion can dwell in the heart of a child?
But, still, I perceive an emotion the same
⁠ As I felt, when a boy, on the crag-cover'd wild:
One image, alone, on my bosom impress'd,
⁠ I lov'd my bleak regions, nor panted for new;
And few were my wants, for my wishes were bless'd,
⁠ And pure were my thoughts, for my soul was with you.

I arose with the dawn, with my dog as my guide,
⁠ From mountain to mountain I bounded along;
I breasted the billows of Dee's rushing tide,
⁠ And heard at a distance the Highlander's song:
At eve, on my heath-cover'd couch of repose,
⁠ No dreams, save of Mary, were spread to my view;
And warm to the skies my devotions arose,
⁠ For the first of my prayers was a blessing on you.

I left my bleak home, and my visions are gone;
⁠ The mountains are vanish'd, my youth is no more;
As the last of my race, I must wither alone,
⁠ And delight but in days, I have witness'd before:
Ah! splendour has rais'd, but embitter'd my lot;
⁠ More dear were the scenes which my infancy knew:
Though my hopes may have fail'd, yet they are not forgot,
⁠ Though cold is my heart, still it lingers with you.

When I see some dark hill point its crest to the sky,
⁠ I think of the rocks that o'ershadow Colbleen;
When I see the soft blue of a love-speaking eye,
⁠ I think of those eyes that endear'd the rude scene;
When, haply, some light-waving locks I behold,
⁠ That faintly resemble my Mary's in hue,
I think on the long flowing ringlets of gold,
⁠ The locks that were sacred to beauty, and you.

Yet the day may arrive, when the mountains once more
⁠ Shall rise to my sight, in their mantles of snow;
But while these soar above me, unchang'd as before,
⁠ Will Mary be there to receive me?—ah, no!
Adieu, then, ye hills, where my childhood was bred!
⁠ Thou sweet flowing Dee, to thy waters adieu!
No home in the forest shall shelter my head,—
⁠ Ah! Mary, what home could be mine, but with you?
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090802">
<head>
    <title>I would I were a Careless Child</title>
    <firstline>I would I were a careless child</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>I would</sc> I were a careless child,
⁠ Still dwelling in my Highland cave,
Or roaming through the dusky wild,
⁠ Or bounding o'er the dark blue wave;
The cumbrous pomp of Saxon pride,
⁠ Accords not with the freeborn soul,
Which loves the mountain's craggy side,
⁠ And seeks the rocks where billows roll.

Fortune! take back these cultur'd lands,
⁠ Take back this name of splendid sound!
I hate the touch of servile hands,
⁠ I hate the slaves that cringe around:
Place me among the rocks I love,
⁠ Which sound to Ocean's wildest roar;
I ask but this—again to rove
⁠ Through scenes my youth hath known before.

Few are my years, and yet I feel
⁠ The World was ne'er design'd for me:
Ah! why do dark'ning shades conceal
⁠ The hour when man must cease to be?
Once I beheld a splendid dream,
⁠ A visionary scene of bliss;
Truth!—wherefore did thy hated beam
⁠ Awake me to a world like this?

I lov'd—but those I lov'd are gone;
⁠ Had friends—my early friends are fled:
How cheerless feels the heart alone,
⁠ When all its former hopes are dead!
Though gay companions, o'er the bowl
⁠ Dispel awhile the sense of ill;
Though Pleasure stirs the maddening soul,
⁠ The heart—the heart—is lonely still.

How dull! to hear the voice of those
⁠ Whom Rank or Chance, whom Wealth or Power,
Have made, though neither friends nor foes,
⁠ Associates of the festive hour.
Give me again a faithful few,
⁠ In years and feelings still the same,
And I will fly the midnight crew,
⁠ Where boist'rous Joy is but a name.

And Woman, lovely Woman! thou,
⁠ My hope, my comforter, my all!
How cold must be my bosom now,
⁠ When e'en thy smiles begin to pall!
Without a sigh would I resign,
⁠ This busy scene of splendid Woe,
To make that calm contentment mine,
⁠ Which Virtue knows, or seems to know.

Fain would I fly the haunts of men—
⁠ I seek to shun, not hate mankind;
My breast requires the sullen glen,
⁠ Whose gloom may suit a darken'd mind.
Oh! that to me the wings were given,
⁠ Which bear the turtle to her nest!
Then would I cleave the vault of Heaven,
⁠ To flee away, and be at rest.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090803">
<head>
    <title>On Parting</title>
    <firstline>The kiss, dear maid! thy lip has left</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>The kiss</sc>, dear maid! thy lip has left
⁠ Shall never part from mine,
Till happier hours restore the gift
⁠ Untainted back to thine.

Thy parting glance, which fondly beams,
⁠ An equal love may see:
The tear that from thine eyelid streams
⁠ Can weep no change in me.

I ask no pledge to make me blest
⁠ In gazing when alone;
Nor one memorial for a breast,
⁠ Whose thoughts are all thine own.

Nor need I write—to tell the tale
⁠ My pen were doubly weak:
Oh! what can idle words avail,
⁠ Unless the heart could speak?

By day or night, in weal or woe,
⁠ That heart, no longer free,
Must bear the love it cannot show,
⁠ And silent ache for thee.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090804">
<head>
    <title>Stanzas written in passing the Ambracian Gulf</title>
    <firstline>Through cloudless skies, in silvery sheen</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Through cloudless skies, in silvery sheen,
⁠ Full beams the moon on Actium's coast:
And on these waves, for Egypt's queen,
⁠ The ancient world was won and lost.

And now upon the scene I look,
⁠ The azure grave of many a Roman;
Where stern Ambition once forsook
⁠ His wavering crown to followa <i>Woman</i>.

Florence! whom I will love as well
⁠ (As ever yet was said or sung.
Since Orpheus sang his spouse from Hell)
⁠ Whilst <i>thou</i> art <i>fair</i> and <i>I</i> am <i>young;</i>

Sweet Florence! those were pleasant times,
⁠ When worlds were staked for Ladies' eyes:
Had bards as many realms as rhymes,
⁠ Thy charms might raise new Antonies.

Though Fate forbids such things to be,
⁠ Yet, by thine eyes and ringlets curled!
I cannot lose a <i>world</i> for thee,
⁠ But would not lose thee for a World.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090805">
<head>
    <title>Stanzas for Music</title>
    <firstline>There's not a joy the world can give like that it takes away</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<nonum><right><small>"O Lachrymarum fons, tenero sacros</small></right></nonum>
<nonum><right><small>Ducentium ortus ex animo: quater</small></right></nonum>
<nonum><right><small>⁠Felix! in imo qui scatentem</small></right></nonum>
<nonum><right><small>⁠⁠Pectore te, pia Nympha, sensit."</small></right></nonum>
<nonum><right><small>Gray's <i>Poemata</i>.</small></right></nonum>

There's not a joy the world can give like that it takes away,
When the glow of early thought declines in Feeling's dull decay;
'Tis not on Youth's smooth cheek the blush alone, which fades so fast,
But the tender bloom of heart is gone, ere Youth itself be past.

Then the few whose spirits float above the wreck of happiness
Are driven o'er the shoals of guilt or ocean of excess:
The magnet of their course is gone, or only points in vain
The shore to which their shivered sail shall never stretch again.

Then the mortal coldness of the soul like Death itself comes down;
It cannot feel for others' woes, it dare not dream its own;
That heavy chill has frozen o'er the fountain of our tears,
And though the eye may sparkle still, 'tis where the ice appears.

Though wit may flash from fluent lips, and mirth distract the breast,
Through midnight hours that yield no more their former hope of rest;
'Tis but as ivy-leaves around the ruined turret wreath,
All green and wildly fresh without, but worn and grey beneath.

Oh, could I feel as I have felt,—or be what I have been,
Or weep as I could once have wept, o'er many a vanished scene;
As springs in deserts found seem sweet, all brackish though they be,
So, midst the withered waste of life, those tears would flow to me.

<nonum><right>March, 1815.</right></nonum>

</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090806">
<head>
    <title>Childe Harold's Good Night </title>
    <firstline>Adieu, adieu! my native shore</firstline>
    <notes>
        <note>Fra <i>Childe Harold's Pilgrimage</i>, Canto I.</note>
    </notes>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
"<sc>Adieu</sc>, adieu! my native shore
  Fades o'er the waters blue;
The night-winds sigh, the breakers roar,
⁠ And shrieks the wild sea-mew.
Yon Sun that sets upon the sea
⁠ We follow in his flight;
Farewell awhile to him and thee,
⁠ My native Land—Good Night!

"A few short hours and He will rise
⁠ To give the Morrow birth;
And I shall hail the main and skies,
⁠ But not my mother Earth.
Deserted is my own good Hall,
⁠ Its hearth is desolate;
Wild weeds are gathering on the wall;
⁠ My Dog howls at the gate.

"Come hither, hither, my little page!
⁠ Why dost thou weep and wail?
Or dost thou dread the billows' rage,
⁠ Or tremble at the gale?
But dash the tear-drop from thine eye;
⁠ Our ship is swift and strong:
Our fleetest falcon scarce can fly
⁠ More merrily along."

"Let winds be shrill, let waves roll high,
⁠ I fear not wave nor wind:
Yet marvel not, Sir Childe, that I
⁠ Am sorrowful in mind;
For I have from my father gone,
⁠ A mother whom I love,
And have no friend, save these alone,
⁠ But thee—and One above.

'My father blessed me fervently,
⁠ Yet did not much complain;
But sorely will my mother sigh
⁠ Till I come back again.'—
"Enough, enough, my little lad!
⁠ Such tears become thine eye;
If I thy guileless bosom had,
⁠ Mine own would not be dry.

"Come hither, hither, my staunch yeoman,
⁠ Why dost thou look so pale?
Or dost thou dread a French foeman?
⁠ Or shiver at the gale?"—
'Deem'st thou I tremble for my life?
⁠ Sir Childe, I'm not so weak;
But thinking on an absent wife
⁠ Will blanch a faithful cheek.

'My spouse and boys dwell near thy hall,
⁠ Along the bordering Lake,
And when they on their father call,
⁠ What answer shall she make?'—
"Enough, enough, my yeoman good,
⁠ Thy grief let none gainsay;
But I, who am of lighter mood,
⁠ Will laugh to flee away.

"For who would trust the seeming sighs
⁠ Of wife or paramour?
Fresh feeres will dry the bright blue eyes
⁠ We late saw streaming o'er.
For pleasures past I do not grieve,
⁠ Nor perils gathering near;
My greatest grief is that I leave
⁠ No thing that claims a tear.

"And now I'm in the world alone,
⁠ Upon the wide, wide sea:
But why should I for others groan,
⁠ When none will sigh for me?
Perchance my Dog will whine in vain,
⁠ Till fed by stranger hands;
But long ere I come back again,
⁠ He'd tear me where he stands.

"With thee, my bark, I'll swiftly go
⁠ Athwart the foaming brine;
Nor care what land thou bear'st me to,
⁠ So not again to mine.
Welcome, welcome, ye dark-blue waves!
⁠ And when you fail my sight,
Welcome, ye deserts, and ye caves!
⁠ My native Land—Good Night!"
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019090807">
<head>
    <title>Lines written in an Album, at Malta</title>
    <firstline>As o'er the cold sepulchral stone</firstline>
    <dates>
        <written>1809-09-14</written>
    </dates>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
As o'er the cold sepulchral stone
⁠ Some name arrests the passer-by;
Thus, when thou view'st this page alone,
⁠ May mine attract thy pensive eye!

And when by thee that name is read,
⁠ Perchance in some succeeding year,
Reflect on me as on the dead,
⁠ And think my Heart is buried here.

<nonum><right><small>Malta, <i>September</i>, 1809.</small></right></nonum>
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2019101701">
<head>
    <title>The Vision of Judgment</title>
    <firstline>Saint Peter sat by the celestial gate</firstline>
    <!-- http://www.jacklynch.net/Texts/vision.html -->
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<nonum><center>I</center></nonum>
Saint Peter sat by the celestial gate:
   His keys were rusty, and the lock was dull,
So little trouble had been given of late;
   Not that the place by any means was full,
But since the Gallic era "eighty-eight"
   The Devils had ta'en a longer, stronger pull,
And "a pull altogether," as they say
At sea — which drew most souls another way.

<nonum><center>II</center></nonum>
The Angels all were singing out of tune,
   And hoarse with having little else to do,
Excepting to wind up the sun and moon,
   Or curb a runaway young star or two,
Or wild colt of a comet, which too soon
   Broke out of bounds o'er the ethereal blue,
Splitting some planet with its playful tail,
As boats are sometimes by a wanton whale.

<nonum><center>III</center></nonum>
The Guardian Seraphs   had retired on high,
   Finding their charges past all care below;
Terrestrial business filled nought in the sky
   Save the Recording Angel's black bureau;
Who found, indeed, the facts to multiply
   With such rapidity of vice and woe,
That he had stripped off both his wings in quills,
And yet was in arrear of human ills.

<nonum><center>IV</center></nonum>
His business so augmented of late years,
   That he was forced, against his will, no doubt,
(Just like those cherubs, earthly ministers,)
   For some resource to turn himself about,
And claim the help of his celestial peers,
   To aid him ere he should be quite worn out
By the increased demand for his remarks:
Six Angels and twelve Saints were named his clerks.

<nonum><center>V</center></nonum>
This was a handsome board — at least for Heaven;
   And yet they had even then enough to do,
So many Conquerors' cars were daily driven,
   So many kingdoms fitted up anew;
Each day, too, slew its thousands six or seven,
   Till at the crowning carnage, Waterloo,
They threw their pens down in divine disgust—
The page was so besmeared with blood and dust.

<nonum><center>VI</center></nonum>
This by the way; 'tis not mine to record
   What Angels shrink from: even the very Devil
On this occasion his own work abhorred,
   So surfeited   with the infernal revel:
Though he himself had sharpened every sword,
   It almost quenched his innate thirst of evil.
(Here Satan's sole good work deserves insertion—
'Tis, that he has both Generals in reversion.  )

<nonum><center>VII</center></nonum>
Let's skip a few short years of hollow peace,
   Which peopled earth no better, Hell as wont,
And Heaven none — they form the tyrant's lease,
   With nothing but new names subscribed upon't;
'Twill one day finish: meantime they increase,
   "With seven heads and ten horns," and all in front,
Like Saint John's foretold beast;   but ours are born [55]
Less formidable in the head than horn.

<nonum><center>VIII</center></nonum>
In the first year of Freedom's second dawn
   Died George the Third; although no tyrant, one
Who shielded tyrants, till each sense withdrawn
   Left him nor mental nor external sun:   [60]
A better farmer   ne'er brushed dew from lawn,
   A worse king never left a realm undone!
He died — but left his subjects still behind,
One half as mad — and t'other no less blind.

<nonum><center>IX</center></nonum>
He died! his death made no great stir on earth:
   His burial made some pomp; there was profusion
Of velvet — gilding — brass — and no great dearth
   Of aught but tears — save those shed by collusion:
For these things may be bought at their true worth;
   Of elegy there was the due infusion—
Bought also; and the torches, cloaks and banners,
Heralds, and relics of old Gothic manners,

<nonum><center>X</center></nonum>
Formed a sepulchral melodrame. Of all
   The fools who flocked to swell or see the show,
Who cared about the corpse? The funeral
   Made the attraction, and the black the woe,
There throbbed not there a thought which pierced the pall;
   And when the gorgeous coffin was laid low,
It seemed the mockery of hell to fold
The rottenness of eighty years in gold.

<nonum><center>XI</center></nonum>
So mix his body with the dust! It might
   Return to what it must far sooner, were
The natural compound left alone to fight
   Its way back into earth, and fire, and air;
But the unnatural balsams merely blight
   What Nature made him at his birth, as bare
As the mere million's base unmummied clay—
Yet all his spices but prolong decay.

<nonum><center>XII</center></nonum>
He's dead — and upper earth with him has done;
   He's buried; save the undertaker's bill,
Or lapidary scrawl,   the world is gone
   For him, unless he left a German will:
But where's the proctor who will ask his son?
   In whom his qualities are reigning still,
Except that household virtue, most uncommon,
Of constancy to a bad, ugly woman.

<nonum><center>XIII</center></nonum>
"God save the king!" It is a large economy
   In God to save the like; but if he will
Be saving, all the better; for not one am I
   Of those who think damnation better still:
I hardly know too if not quite alone am I
   In this small hope of bettering future ill
By circumscribing, with some slight restriction,
The eternity of Hell's hot jurisdiction.

<nonum><center>XIV</center></nonum>
I know this is unpopular; I know
   'Tis blasphemous; I know one may be damned
For hoping no one else may e'er be so;
   I know my catechism; I know we're crammed
With the best doctrines till we quite o'erflow;
   I know that all save England's Church have shammed,
And that the other twice two hundred churches
And synagogues have made a damned bad purchase.

<nonum><center>XV</center></nonum>
God help us all! God help me too! I am,
   God knows, as helpless as the Devil can wish,
And not a whit more difficult to damn,
   Than is to bring to land a late-hooked fish,
Or to the butcher to purvey the lamb;
   Not that I'm fit for such a noble dish,
As one day will be that immortal fry
Of almost every body born to die.

<nonum><center>XVI</center></nonum>
Saint Peter sat by the celestial gate,
   And nodded o'er his keys: when, lo! there came
A wondrous noise he had not heard of late—
   A rushing sound of wind, and stream, and flame;
In short, a roar of things extremely great,
   Which would have made aught save a Saint exclaim;
But he, with first a start and then a wink,
Said, "There's another star gone out, I think!"

<nonum><center>XVII</center></nonum>
But ere he could return to his repose,
   A Cherub flapped his right wing o'er his eyes—
At which Saint Peter yawned, and rubbed his nose:
   "Saint porter," said the angel, "prithee rise!"
Waving a goodly wing, which glowed, as glows
   An earthly peacock's tail, with heavenly dyes:
To which the saint replied, "Well, what's the matter?
"Is Lucifer come back with all this clatter?"

<nonum><center>XVIII</center></nonum>
"No," quoth the Cherub: "George the Third is dead."
   "And who is George the Third?" replied the apostle:
"What George? what Third?" "The King of England," said
   The angel. "Well! he won't find kings to jostle
Him on his way; but does he wear his head?
   Because the last we saw here had a tustle,
And ne'er would have got into Heaven's good graces,
Had he not flung his head in all our faces.

<nonum><center>XIX</center></nonum>
"He was — if I remember — King of France;
   That head of his, which could not keep a crown
On earth, yet ventured in my face to advance
   A claim to those of martyrs — like my own:
If I had had my sword, as I had once
   When I cut ears off, I had cut him down;
But having but my keys, and not my brand,
I only knocked his head from out his hand.

<nonum><center>XX</center></nonum>
"And then he set up such a headless howl,
   That all the Saints came out and took him in;
And there he sits by Saint Paul, cheek by jowl;
   That fellow Paul — the parvenâ€”!   The skin
Of Saint Bartholomew, which makes his cowl
   In heaven, and upon earth redeemed his sin,
So as to make a martyr, never sped
Better than did this weak and wooden head.

<nonum><center>XXI</center></nonum>
"But had it come up here upon its shoulders,
   There would have been a different tale to tell:
The fellow-feeling in the Saint's beholders
   Seems to have acted on them like a spell;
And so this very foolish head Heaven solders
   Back on its trunk: it may be very well,
And seems the custom here to overthrow
Whatever has been wisely done below."

<nonum><center>XXII</center></nonum>
The Angel answered, "Peter! do not pout:
   The King who comes has head and all entire,
And never knew much what it was about—
   He did as doth the puppet — by its wire,
And will be judged like all the rest, no doubt:
   My business and your own is not to inquire
Into such matters, but to mind our cue—
Which is to act as we are bid to do."

<nonum><center>XXIII</center></nonum>
While thus they spake, the angelic caravan,
   Arriving like a rush of mighty wind,
Cleaving the fields of space, as doth the swan
   Some silver stream (say Ganges, Nile, or Inde,
Or Thames, or Tweed), and midst them an old man
   With an old soul, and both extremely blind,
Halted before the gate, and, in his shroud,
Seated their fellow-traveller on a cloud.

<nonum><center>XXIV</center></nonum>
But bringing up the rear of this bright host
   A Spirit of a different aspect waved
His wings, like thunder-clouds above some coast
   Whose barren beach with frequent wrecks is paved;
His brow was like the deep when tempest-tossed;
   Fierce and unfathomable thoughts engraved
Eternal wrath on his immortal face,
And where he gazed a gloom pervaded space.

<nonum><center>XXV</center></nonum>
As he drew near, he gazed upon the gate
   Ne'er to be entered more by him or Sin,
With such a glance of supernatural hate,
   As made Saint Peter wish himself within;
He pottered with his keys at a great rate,
   And sweated through his Apostolic skin:
Of course his perspiration was but ichor,
Or some such other spiritual liquor.

<nonum><center>XXVI</center></nonum>
The very Cherubs huddled all together,
   Like birds when soars the falcon; and they felt
A tingling to the tip of every feather,
   And formed a circle like Orion's belt
Around their poor old charge; who scarce knew whither
   His guards had led him, though they gently dealt
With royal Manes (for by many stories,
And true, we learn the Angels all are Tories).

<nonum><center>XXVII</center></nonum>
As things were in this posture, the gate flew
   Asunder, and the flashing of its hinges
Flung over space an universal hue
   Of many-coloured flame, until its tinges
Reached even our speck of earth, and made a new
   Aurora borealis spread its fringes
O'er the North Pole; the same seen, when ice-bound,
By Captain Parry's crew, in "Melville's Sound."

<nonum><center>XXVIII</center></nonum>
And from the gate thrown open issued beaming
   A beautiful and mighty Thing of Light,
Radiant with glory, like a banner streaming
   Victorious from some world-o'erthrowing fight:
My poor comparisons must needs be teeming
   With earthly likenesses, for here the night
Of clay obscures our best conceptions, saving
Johanna Southcote, or Bob Southey raving.

<nonum><center>XXIX</center></nonum>
'Twas the Archangel Michael: all men know
   The make of Angels and Archangels, since
There's scarce a scribbler has not one to show,
   From the fiends' leader to the Angels' Prince.
There also are some altar-pieces, though
   I really can't say that they much evince
One's inner notions of immortal spirits;
But let the connoisseurs explain their merits.

<nonum><center>XXX</center></nonum>
Michael flew forth in glory and in good;
   A goodly work of him from whom all Glory
And Good arise; the portal past — he stood;
   Before him the young Cherubs and Saints hoary—
(I say young, begging to be understood
   By looks, not years; and should be very sorry
To state, they were not older than St. Peter,
But merely that they seemed a little sweeter).

<nonum><center>XXXI</center></nonum>
The Cherubs and the Saints bowed down before
   That arch-angelic Hierarch, the first
Of Essences angelical who wore
   The aspect of a god; but this ne'er nursed
Pride in his heavenly bosom, in whose core
   No thought, save for his Maker's service, durst
Intrude, however glorified and high;
He knew him but the Viceroy of the sky.

<nonum><center>XXXII</center></nonum>
He and the sombre, silent Spirit met—
   They knew each other both for good and ill;
Such was their power, that neither could forget
   His former friend and future foe; but still
There was a high, immortal, proud regret
   In either's eye, as if 'twere less their will
Than destiny to make the eternal years
Their date of war, and their "Champ Clos" the spheres.

<nonum><center>XXXIII</center></nonum>
But here they were in neutral space: we know
   From Job, that Satan hath the power to pay
A heavenly visit thrice a-year or so;
   And that the "Sons of God," like those of clay,
Must keep him company; and we might show
   From the same book, in how polite a way
The dialogue is held between the Powers
Of Good and Evil — but 'twould take up hours.

<nonum><center>XXXIV</center></nonum>
And this is not a theologic tract,
   To prove with Hebrew and with Arabic,
If Job be allegory or a fact,
   But a true narrative; and thus I pick
From out the whole but such and such an act
   As sets aside the slightest thought of trick.
'Tis every tittle true, beyond suspicion,
And accurate as any other vision.

<nonum><center>XXXV</center></nonum>
The spirits were in neutral space, before
   The gate of Heaven; like eastern thresholds is
The place where Death's grand cause is argued o'er,
   And souls despatched to that world or to this;
And therefore Michael and the other wore
   A civil aspect: though they did not kiss,
Yet still between his Darkness and his Brightness
There passed a mutual glance of great politeness.

<nonum><center>XXXVI</center></nonum>
The Archangel bowed, not like a modern beau,
   But with a graceful oriental bend,
Pressing one radiant arm just where below
   The heart in good men is supposed to tend;
He turned as to an equal, not too low,
   But kindly; Satan met his ancient friend
With more hauteur, as might an old Castilian
Poor Noble meet a mushroom rich civilian.

<nonum><center>XXXVII</center></nonum>
He merely bent his diabolic brow
   An instant; and then raising it, he stood
In act to assert his right or wrong, and show
   Cause why King George by no means could or should
Make out a case to be exempt from woe
   Eternal, more than other kings, endued
With better sense and hearts, whom History mentions,
Who long have "paved Hell with their good intentions."

<nonum><center>XXXVIII</center></nonum>
Michael began: "What wouldst thou with this man,
   Now dead, and brought before the Lord? What ill
Hath he wrought since his mortal race began,
   That thou canst claim him? Speak! and do thy will,
If it be just: if in this earthly span
   He hath been greatly failing to fulfil
His duties as a king and mortal, say,
And he is thine; if not — let him have way."

<nonum><center>XXXIX</center></nonum>
"Michael!" replied the Prince of Air, "even here
   Before the gate of Him thou servest, must
I claim my subject: and will make appear
   That as he was my worshipper in dust,
So shall he be in spirit, although dear
   To thee and thine, because nor wine nor lust
Were of his weaknesses; yet on the throne
He reigned o'er millions to serve me alone.

<nonum><center>XL</center></nonum>
"Look to our earth, or rather mine; it was,
   Once, more thy master's: but I triumph not
In this poor planet's conquest; nor, alas!
   Need he thou servest envy me my lot:
With all the myriads of bright worlds which pass
   In worship round him, he may have forgot
Yon weak creation of such paltry things:
I think few worth damnation save their kings,

<nonum><center>XLI</center></nonum>
"And these but as a kind of quit-rent, to
   Assert my right as Lord: and even had
I such an inclination, 'twere (as you
   Well know) superfluous; they are grown so bad,
That Hell has nothing better left to do
   Than leave them to themselves: so much more mad
And evil by their own internal curse,
Heaven cannot make them better, nor I worse.

<nonum><center>XLII</center></nonum>
"Look to the earth, I said, and say again:
   When this old, blind, mad, helpless, weak, poor worm   [330]
Began in youth's first bloom and flush to reign,
   The world and he both wore a different form,
And much of earth and all the watery plain
   Of Ocean called him king: through many a storm
His isles had floated on the abyss of Time;
For the rough virtues chose them for their clime.

<nonum><center>XLIII</center></nonum>
"He came to his sceptre young; he leaves it old:
   Look to the state in which he found his realm,
And left it; and his annals too behold,
   How to a minion first he gave the helm;
How grew upon his heart a thirst for gold,
   The beggar's vice, which can but overwhelm
The meanest hearts; and for the rest, but glance
Thine eye along America and France.

<nonum><center>XLIV</center></nonum>
"'Tis true, he was a tool from first to last
   (I have the workmen safe); but as a tool
So let him be consumed. From out the past
   Of ages, since mankind have known the rule
Of monarchs — from the bloody rolls amassed
   Of Sin and Slaughter — from the Câ€˜sars' school,
Take the worst pupil; and produce a reign
More drenched with gore, more cumbered with the slain.

<nonum><center>XLV</center></nonum>
"He ever warred with freedom and the free:
   Nations as men, home subjects, foreign foes,
So that they uttered the word 'Liberty!'
   Found George the Third their first opponent. Whose
History was ever stained as his will be
   With national and individual woes?
I grant his household abstinence; I grant
His neutral virtues, which most monarchs want;

<nonum><center>XLVI</center></nonum>
"I know he was a constant consort; own
   He was a decent sire, and middling lord.
All this is much, and most upon a throne;
   As temperance, if at Apicius' board,
Is more than at an anchorite's supper shown.
   I grant him all the kindest can accord;
And this was well for him, but not for those
Millions who found him what Oppression chose.

<nonum><center>XLVII</center></nonum>
"The New World shook him off; the Old yet groans
   Beneath what he and his prepared, if not
Completed: he leaves heirs on many thrones
   To all his vices, without what begot
Compassion for him — his tame virtues; drones
   Who sleep, or despots who have now forgot
A lesson which shall be re-taught them, wake
Upon the thrones of earth; but let them quake!

<nonum><center>XLVIII</center></nonum>
"Five millions of the primitive, who hold
   The faith which makes ye great on earth, implored
A part of that vast all they held of old,—
   Freedom to worship — not alone your Lord,
Michael, but you, and you, Saint Peter! Cold
   Must be your souls, if you have not abhorred
The foe to Catholic participation
In all the license of a Christian nation.

<nonum><center>XLIX</center></nonum>
"True! he allowed them to pray God; but as
   A consequence of prayer, refused the law
Which would have placed them upon the same base
   With those who did not hold the Saints in awe."
But here Saint Peter started from his place
   And cried, "You may the prisoner withdraw:
Ere Heaven shall ope her portals to this Guelph,
While I am guard, may I be damned myself!

<nonum><center>L</center></nonum>
"Sooner will I with Cerberus exchange
   My office (and his is no sinecure)
Than see this royal Bedlam-bigot range
   The azure fields of Heaven, of that be sure!"
"Saint!" replied Satan, "you do well to avenge
   The wrongs he made your satellites endure;
And if to this exchange you should be given,
I'll try to coax our Cerberus up to Heaven!"

<nonum><center>LI</center></nonum>
Here Michael interposed: "Good Saint! and Devil!
   Pray, not so fast; you both outrun discretion.
Saint Peter! you were wont to be more civil:
   Satan! excuse this warmth of his expression,
And condescension to the vulgar's level:
   Even Saints sometimes forget themselves in session.
Have you got more to say?" — "No." — "If you please,
I'll trouble you to call your witnesses."

<nonum><center>LII</center></nonum>
Then Satan turned and waved his swarthy hand,
   Which stirred with its electric qualities
Clouds farther off than we can understand,
   Although we find him sometimes in our skies;
Infernal thunder shook both sea and land
   In all the planets — and Hell's batteries
Let off the artillery, which Milton mentions
As one of Satan's most sublime inventions.

<nonum><center>LIII</center></nonum>
This was a signal unto such damned souls
   As have the privilege of their damnation
Extended far beyond the mere controls
   Of worlds past, present, or to come; no station
Is theirs particularly in the rolls
   Of Hell assigned; but where their inclination
Or business carries them in search of game,
They may range freely — being damned the same.

<nonum><center>LIV</center></nonum>
They are proud of this — as very well they may,
   It being a sort of knighthood, or gilt key
Stuck in their loins; or like to an "entrâ€š"
   Up the back stairs, or such free-masonry.
I borrow my comparisons from clay,
   Being clay myself. Let not those spirits be
Offended with such base low likenesses;
We know their posts are nobler far than these.

<nonum><center>LV</center></nonum>
When the great signal ran from Heaven to Hell—
   About ten million times the distance reckoned
From our sun to its earth, as we can tell
   How much time it takes up, even to a second,
For every ray that travels to dispel
   The fogs of London, through which, dimly beaconed,
The weathercocks are gilt some thrice a year,
If that the summer is not too severe:

<nonum><center>LVI</center></nonum>
I say that I can tell — 'twas half a minute;
   I know the solar beams take up more time
Ere, packed up for their journey, they begin it;
   But then their Telegraph   is less sublime,
And if they ran a race, they would not win it
   'Gainst Satan's couriers bound for their own clime.
The sun takes up some years for every ray
To reach its goal — the Devil not half a day.

<nonum><center>LVII</center></nonum>
Upon the verge of space, about the size
   Of half-a-crown, a little speck appeared
(I've seen a something like it in the skies
   In the â€™gean, ere a squall); it neared,
And, growing bigger, took another guise;
   Like an aâ€°rial ship it tacked, and steered,
Or was steered (I am doubtful of the grammar
Of the last phrase, which makes the stanza stammer;

<nonum><center>LVIII</center></nonum>
But take your choice): and then it grew a cloud;
   And so it was — a cloud of witnesses.
But such a cloud! No land ere saw a crowd
   Of locusts numerous as the heavens saw these;
They shadowed with their myriads Space; their loud
   And varied cries were like those of wild geese,
(If nations may be likened to a goose),
And realised the phrase of "Hell broke loose,"

<nonum><center>LIX</center></nonum>
Here crashed a sturdy oath of stout John Bull,
   Who damned away his eyes as heretofore:
There Paddy brogued "By Jasus!" — "What's your wull?"
   The temperate Scot exclaimed: the French ghost swore
In certain terms I shan't translate in full,
   As the first coachman will; and 'midst the war,
The voice of Jonathan   was heard to express,
"Our President is going to war, I guess."

<nonum><center>LX</center></nonum>
Besides there were the Spaniard, Dutch, and Dane;
   In short, an universal shoal of shades
From Otaheite's isle   to Salisbury Plain, [475]
   Of all climes and professions, years and trades,
Ready to swear against the good king's reign,
   Bitter as clubs in cards are against spades:
All summoned by this grand "subpoena," to
Try if kings mayn't be damned like me or you.

<nonum><center>LXI</center></nonum>
When Michael saw this host, he first grew pale,
   As Angels can; next, like Italian twilight,
He turned all colours — as a peacock's tail,
   Or sunset streaming through a Gothic skylight
In some old abbey, or a trout not stale,
   Or distant lightning on the horizon by night,
Or a fresh rainbow, or a grand review
Of thirty regiments in red, green, and blue.

<nonum><center>LXII</center></nonum>
Then he addressed himself to Satan: "Why—
   My good old friend, for such I deem you, though
Our different parties make us fight so shy,
   I ne'er mistake you for a personal foe;
Our difference is political, and I
   Trust that, whatever may occur below,
You know my great respect for you: and this
Makes me regret whate'er you do amiss—

<nonum><center>LXIII</center></nonum>
"Why, my dear Lucifer, would you abuse
   My call for witnesses? I did not mean
That you should half of Earth and Hell produce;
   'Tis even superfluous, since two honest, clean,
True testimonies are enough: we lose
   Our Time, nay, our Eternity, between
The accusation and defence: if we
Hear both, 'twill stretch our immortality."

<nonum><center>LXIV</center></nonum>
Satan replied, "To me the matter is
   Indifferent, in a personal point of view:
I can have fifty better souls than this
   With far less trouble than we have gone through
Already; and I merely argued his
   Late Majesty of Britain's case with you
Upon a point of form: you may dispose
Of him; I've kings enough below, God knows!"

<nonum><center>LXV</center></nonum>
Thus spoke the Demon (late called "multifaced"
   By multo-scribbling Southey). "Then we'll call
One or two persons of the myriads placed
   Around our congress, and dispense with all
The rest," quoth Michael: "Who may be so graced
   As to speak first? there's choice enough — who shall
It be?" Then Satan answered, "There are many;
But you may choose Jack Wilkes as well as any."

<nonum><center>LXVI</center></nonum>
A merry, cock-eyed, curious-looking Sprite
   Upon the instant started from the throng,
Dressed in a fashion now forgotten quite;
   For all the fashions of the flesh stick long
By people in the next world; where unite
   All the costumes since Adam's, right or wrong,
From Eve's fig-leaf down to the petticoat,
Almost as scanty, of days less remote.

<nonum><center>LXVII</center></nonum>
The Spirit looked around upon the crowds
   Assembled, and exclaimed, "My friends of all
The spheres, we shall catch cold amongst these clouds;
   So let's to business: why this general call?
If those are freeholders I see in shrouds,
   And 'tis for an election that they bawl,
Behold a candidate with unturned coat!
Saint Peter, may I count upon your vote?"

<nonum><center>LXVIII</center></nonum>
"Sir," replied Michael, "you mistake; these things
   Are of a former life, and what we do
Above is more august; to judge of kings
   Is the tribunal met: so now you know."
"Then I presume those gentlemen with wings,"
   Said Wilkes, "are Cherubs; and that soul below
Looks much like George the Third, but to my mind
A good deal older — bless me! is he blind?"

<nonum><center>LXIX</center></nonum>
"He is what you behold him, and his doom
   Depends upon his deeds," the Angel said;
"If you have aught to arraign in him, the tomb
   Gives license to the humblest beggar's head
To lift itself against the loftiest." — "Some,"
   Said Wilkes, "don't wait to see them laid in lead,
For such a liberty — and I, for one,
Have told them what I thought beneath the sun."

<nonum><center>LXX</center></nonum>
"Above the sun repeat, then, what thou hast
   To urge against him," said the Archangel. "Why,"
Replied the spirit, "since old scores are past,
   Must I turn evidence? In faith, not I.
Besides, I beat him hollow at the last,
   With all his Lords and Commons: in the sky
I don't like ripping up old stories, since
His conduct was but natural in a prince.

<nonum><center>LXXI</center></nonum>
"Foolish, no doubt, and wicked, to oppress
   A poor unlucky devil without a shilling;
But then I blame the man himself much less
   Than Bute and Grafton, and shall be unwilling
To see him punished here for their excess,
   Since they were both damned long ago, and still in
Their place below: for me, I have forgiven,
And vote his habeas corpus into Heaven."

<nonum><center>LXXII</center></nonum>
"Wilkes," said the Devil, "I understand all this;
   You turned to half a courtier ere you died,
And seem to think it would not be amiss
   To grow a whole one on the other side
Of Charon's ferry; you forget that his
   Reign is concluded; whatsoe'er betide,
He won't be sovereign more: you've lost your labour,
For at the best he will but be your neighbour.

<nonum><center>LXXIII</center></nonum>
"However, I knew what to think of it,
   When I beheld you in your jesting way,
Flitting and whispering round about the spit
   Where Belial, upon duty for the day,
With Fox's lard was basting William Pitt,
   His pupil; I knew what to think, I say:
That fellow even in Hell breeds farther ills;
I'll have him gagged — 'twas one of his own Bills.

<nonum><center>LXXIV</center></nonum>
"Call Junius!"   From the crowd a shadow stalked, [585]
   And at the name there was a general squeeze,
So that the very ghosts no longer walked
   In comfort, at their own aâ€°rial ease,
But were all rammed, and jammed (but to be balked,
   As we shall see), and jostled hands and knees,
Like wind compressed and pent within a bladder,
Or like a human colic, which is sadder.

<nonum><center>LXXV</center></nonum>
The shadow came — a tall, thin, grey-haired figure,
   That looked as it had been a shade on earth;
Quick in its motions, with an air of vigour,
   But nought to mark its breeding or its birth;
Now it waxed little, then again grew bigger,
   With now an air of gloom, or savage mirth;
But as you gazed upon its features, they
Changed every instant — to what, none could say.

<nonum><center>LXXVI</center></nonum>
The more intently the ghosts gazed, the less
   Could they distinguish whose the features were;
The Devil himself seemed puzzled even to guess;
   They varied like a dream — now here, now there;
And several people swore from out the press,
   They knew him perfectly; and one could swear
He was his father; upon which another
Was sure he was his mother's cousin's brother:

<nonum><center>LXXVII</center></nonum>
Another, that he was a duke, or knight,
   An orator, a lawyer, or a priest,
A nabob, a man-midwife; but the wight
   Mysterious changed his countenance at least
As oft as they their minds: though in full sight
   He stood, the puzzle only was increased;
The man was a phantasmagoria in
Himself — he was so volatile and thin.

<nonum><center>LXXVIII</center></nonum>
The moment that you had pronounced him one,
   Presto! his face changed, and he was another;
And when that change was hardly well put on,
   It varied, till I don't think his own mother
(If that he had a mother) would her son
   Have known, he shifted so from one to t'other;
Till guessing from a pleasure grew a task,
At this epistolary "Iron Mask."

<nonum><center>LXXIX</center></nonum>
For sometimes he like Cerberus would seem—
   "Three gentlemen at once" (as sagely says
Good Mrs. Malaprop  ); then you might deem
   That he was not even one; now many rays
Were flashing round him; and now a thick steam
   Hid him from sight — like fogs on London days:
Now Burke, now Tooke, he grew to people's fancies
And certes often like Sir Philip Francis.

<nonum><center>LXXX</center></nonum>
I've an hypothesis — 'tis quite my own;
   I never let it out till now, for fear
Of doing people harm about the throne,
   And injuring some minister or peer,
On whom the stigma might perhaps be blown;
   It is — my gentle public, lend thine ear!
'Tis, that what Junius we are wont to call,
Was really — truly — nobody at all.

<nonum><center>LXXXI</center></nonum>
I don't see wherefore letters should not be
   Written without hands, since we daily view
Them written without heads; and books, we see,
   Are filled as well without the latter too:
And really till we fix on somebody
   For certain sure to claim them as his due,
Their author, like the Niger's mouth, will bother
The world to say if there be mouth or author.

<nonum><center>LXXXII</center></nonum>
"And who and what art thou?" the Archangel said.
   "For that you may consult my title-page,"
Replied this mighty shadow of a shade:
   "If I have kept my secret half an age,
I scarce shall tell it now." — "Canst thou upbraid,"
   Continued Michael, "George Rex, or allege
Aught further?" Junius answered, "You had better
First ask him for his answer to my letter:

<nonum><center>LXXXIII</center></nonum>
"My charges upon record will outlast
   The brass of both his epitaph and tomb."
"Repent'st thou not," said Michael, "of some past
   Exaggeration? something which may doom
Thyself if false, as him if true? Thou wast
   Too bitter — is it not so? — in thy gloom
Of passion?" — "Passion!" cried the phantom dim,
"I loved my country, and I hated him.

<nonum><center>LXXXIV</center></nonum>
"What I have written, I have written:   let
   The rest be on his head or mine!" So spoke
Old "Nominis Umbra"; and while speaking yet,
   Away he melted in celestial smoke.
Then Satan said to Michael, "Don't forget
   To call George Washington, and John Horne Tooke,
And Franklin"; — but at this time there was heard
A cry for room, though not a phantom stirred.

<nonum><center>LXXXV</center></nonum>
At length with jostling, elbowing, and the aid
   Of Cherubim appointed to that post,
The devil Asmodeus to the circle made
   His way, and looked as if his journey cost
Some trouble. When his burden down he laid,
   "What's this?" cried Michael; "why, 'tis not a ghost?"
"I know it," quoth the Incubus; "but he
Shall be one, if you leave the affair to me.

<nonum><center>LXXXVI</center></nonum>
"Confound the renegado! I have sprained
   My left wing, he's so heavy; one would think
Some of his works about his neck were chained.
   But to the point; while hovering o'er the brink
Of Skiddaw (where as usual it still rained),
   I saw a taper, far below me, wink,
And stooping, caught this fellow at a libel—
No less on History — than the Holy Bible.

<nonum><center>LXXXVII</center></nonum>
"The former is the Devil's scripture, and
   The latter yours, good Michael: so the affair
Belongs to all of us, you understand.
   I snatched him up just as you see him there,
And brought him off for sentence out of hand:
   I've scarcely been ten minutes in the air—
At least a quarter it can hardly be:
I dare say that his wife is still at tea."

<nonum><center>LXXXVIII</center></nonum>
Here Satan said, "I know this man of old,
   And have expected him for some time here;
A sillier fellow you will scarce behold,
   Or more conceited in his petty sphere:
But surely it was not worth while to fold
   Such trash below your wing, Asmodeus dear:
We had the poor wretch safe (without being bored
With carriage) coming of his own accord.

<nonum><center>LXXXIX</center></nonum>
"But since he's here, let's see what he has done."
   "Done!" cried Asmodeus, "he anticipates
The very business you are now upon,
   And scribbles as if head clerk to the Fates.
Who knows to what his ribaldry may run,
   When such an ass as this, like Balaam's, prates?"   [710]
"Let's hear," quoth Michael, "what he has to say:
You know we're bound to that in every way."

<nonum><center>XC</center></nonum>
Now the bard, glad to get an audience, which
   By no means often was his case below,
Began to cough, and hawk, and hem, and pitch
   His voice into that awful note of woe
To all unhappy hearers within reach
   Of poets when the tide of rhyme's in flow;
But stuck fast with his first hexameter,
Not one of all whose gouty feet would stir.

<nonum><center>XCI</center></nonum>
But ere the spavined dactyls could be spurred
   Into recitative, in great dismay
Both Cherubim and Seraphim were heard
   To murmur loudly through their long array;
And Michael rose ere he could get a word
   Of all his foundered verses under way,
And cried, "For God's sake stop, my friend! 'twere best—
'Non Di, non homines'   — you know the rest."

<nonum><center>XCII</center></nonum>
A general bustle spread throughout the throng,
   Which seemed to hold all verse in detestation;
The Angels had of course enough of song
   When upon service; and the generation
Of ghosts had heard too much in life, not long
   Before, to profit by a new occasion:
The Monarch, mute till then, exclaimed, "What! what!   [735]
Pye   come again? No more — no more of that!"

<nonum><center>XCIII</center></nonum>
The tumult grew; an universal cough
   Convulsed the skies, as during a debate,
When Castlereagh has been up long enough
   (Before he was first minister of state,
I mean — the slaves hear now); some cried "Off, off!"
   As at a farce; till, grown quite desperate,
The Bard Saint Peter prayed to interpose
(Himself an author) only for his prose.

<nonum><center>XCIV</center></nonum>
The varlet was not an ill-favoured knave;
   A good deal like a vulture in the face,
With a hook nose and a hawk's eye, which gave
   A smart and sharper-looking sort of grace
To his whole aspect, which, though rather grave,
   Was by no means so ugly as his case;
But that, indeed, was hopeless as can be,
Quite a poetic felony "de se."

<nonum><center>XCV</center></nonum>
Then Michael blew his trump, and stilled the noise
   With one still greater, as is yet the mode
On earth besides; except some grumbling voice,
   Which now and then will make a slight inroad
Upon decorous silence, few will twice
   Lift up their lungs when fairly overcrowed;
And now the Bard could plead his own bad cause,
With all the attitudes of self-applause.

<nonum><center>XCVI</center></nonum>
He said — (I only give the heads) — he said,
   He meant no harm in scribbling; 'twas his way
Upon all topics; 'twas, besides, his bread,
   Of which he buttered both sides; 'twould delay
Too long the assembly (he was pleased to dread),
   And take up rather more time than a day,
To name his works — he would but cite a few—
"Wat Tyler" — "Rhymes on Blenheim" — "Waterloo."

<nonum><center>XCVII</center></nonum>
He had written praises of a Regicide;
   He had written praises of all kings whatever;
He had written for republics far and wide,
   And then against them bitterer than ever;
For pantisocracy he once had cried
   Aloud, a scheme less moral than 'twas clever;
Then grew a hearty anti-jacobin—
Had turned his coat — and would have turned his skin.

<nonum><center>XCVIII</center></nonum>
He had sung against all battles, and again
   In their high praise and glory; he had called
Reviewing "the ungentle craft," and then
   Became as base a critic as e'er crawled—
Fed, paid, and pampered by the very men
   By whom his muse and morals had been mauled:
He had written much blank verse, and blanker prose,
And more of both than any body knows.

<nonum><center>XCIX</center></nonum>
He had written Wesley's life: — here turning round
   To Satan, "Sir, I'm ready to write yours,
In two octavo volumes, nicely bound,
   With notes and preface, all that most allures
The pious purchaser; and there's no ground
   For fear, for I can choose my own reviewers:
So let me have the proper documents,
That I may add you to my other saints."

<nonum><center>C</center></nonum>
Satan bowed, and was silent. "Well, if you,
   With amiable modesty, decline
My offer, what says Michael? There are few
   Whose memoirs could be rendered more divine.
Mine is a pen of all work; not so new
   As it was once, but I would make you shine
Like your own trumpet. By the way, my own
Has more of brass in it, and is as well blown.

<nonum><center>CI</center></nonum>
"But talking about trumpets, here's my 'Vision!'
   Now you shall judge, all people — yes — you shall
Judge with my judgment! and by my decision
   Be guided who shall enter heaven or fall.
I settle all these things by intuition,
   Times present, past, to come — Heaven — Hell — and all,
Like King Alfonso.   When I thus see double,
I save the Deity some worlds of trouble."

<nonum><center>CII</center></nonum>
He ceased, and drew forth an MS.; and no
   Persuasion on the part of Devils, Saints,
Or Angels, now could stop the torrent; so
   He read the first three lines of the contents;
But at the fourth, the whole spiritual show
   Had vanished, with variety of scents,
Ambrosial and sulphureous, as they sprang,
Like lightning, off from his "melodious twang."

<nonum><center>CIII</center></nonum>
Those grand heroics acted as a spell;
   The Angels stopped their ears and plied their pinions;
The Devils ran howling, deafened, down to Hell;
   The ghosts fled, gibbering, for their own dominions—
(For 'tis not yet decided where they dwell,
   And I leave every man to his opinions);
Michael took refuge in his trump — but, lo!
His teeth were set on edge, he could not blow!

<nonum><center>CIV</center></nonum>
Saint Peter, who has hitherto been known
   For an impetuous saint, upraised his keys,
And at the fifth line knocked the poet down;
   Who fell like Phaeton, but more at ease,
Into his lake, for there he did not drown;
   A different web being by the Destinies
Woven for the Laureate's final wreath, whene'er
Reform shall happen either here or there.

<nonum><center>CV</center></nonum>
He first sank to the bottom — like his works,
   But soon rose to the surface — like himself;
For all corrupted things are buoyed like corks,
   By their own rottenness, light as an elf,
Or wisp that flits o'er a morass: he lurks,
   It may be, still, like dull books on a shelf,
In his own den, to scrawl some "Life" or "Vision,"
As Welborn says — "the Devil turned precisian."

<nonum><center>CVI</center></nonum>
As for the rest, to come to the conclusion
   Of this true dream, the telescope is gone
Which kept my optics free from all delusion,
   And showed me what I in my turn have shown;
All I saw farther, in the last confusion,
   Was, that King George slipped into Heaven for one;
And when the tumult dwindled to a calm,
I left him practising the hundredth psalm.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="byron2020012601">
<head>
    <title>Ode to Napoleon Buonaparte</title>
    <firstline>Tis done—but yesterday a King!</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>’Tis</sc> done—but yesterday a King!
  And arm’d with Kings to strive—
And now thou art a nameless thing:
  So abject—yet alive!
Is this the man of thousand thrones,
Who strew’d our earth with hostile bones,
  And can he thus survive?
Since he, miscalled the Morning Star,
Nor man nor fiend hath fallen so far.

Ill-minded man! why scourge thy kind
  Who bow’d so low the knee?
By gazing on thyself grown blind,
  Thou taught’st the rest to see.
With might unquestion’d,—power to save,—
Thine only gift hath been the grave,
  To those that worshipp’d thee;
Nor till thy fall could mortals guess
Ambition’s less than littleness!

Thanks for that lesson—it will teach
  To after-warriors more
Than high Philosophy can preach,
  And vainly preach’d before.
That spell upon the minds of men
Breaks never to unite again,
  That led them to adore
Those Pagod things of sabre sway
With fronts of brass, and feet of clay.

The triumph and the vanity,
  The rapture of the strife—
The earthquake voice of Victory,
  To thee the breath of life;
The sword, the sceptre, and that sway
Which man seem’d made but to obey,
  Wherewith renown was rife—
All quell’d—Dark spirit! what must be
The madness of thy memory!

The Desolator desolate!
  The Victor overthrown!
The Arbiter of others’ fate
  A Suppliant for his own!
Is it some yet imperial hope
That with such change can calmly cope?
  Or dread of death alone?
To die a prince—or live a slave—
Thy choice is most ignobly brave!

He who of old would rend the oak,
  Dream’d not of the rebound:
Chain’d by the trunk he vainly broke—
  Alone—how look’d he round?
Thou, in the sternness of thy strength,
An equal deed hast done at length,
  And darker fate hast found:
He fell, the forest prowlers’ prey;
But thou must eat thy heart away!

The Roman, 1 when his burning heart
  Was slaked with blood of Rome,
Threw down the dagger—dared depart,
  In savage grandeur, home—
He dared depart in utter scorn
Of men that such a yoke had borne,
  Yet left him such a doom!
His only glory was that hour
Of self-upheld abandon’d power.

The Spaniard, 2 when the lust of sway
  Had lost its quickening spell,
Cast crowns for rosaries away,
  An empire for a cell;
A strict accountant of his beads,
A subtle disputant on creeds,
  His dotage trifled well:
Yet better had he neither known
A bigot’s shrine, nor despot’s throne.

But thou—from thy reluctant hand
  The thunderbolt is wrung—
Too late thou leav’st the high command
  To which thy weakness clung;
All Evil Spirit as thou art,
It is enough to grieve the heart
  To see thine own unstrung;
To think that God’s fair world hath been
The footstool of a thing so mean;

And Earth hath spilt her blood for him,
  Who thus can hoard his own!
And Monarchs bow’d the trembling limb,
  And thank’d him for a throne!
Fair Freedom! we may hold thee dear,
When thus thy mightiest foes their fear
  In humblest guise have shown.
Oh, ne’er may tyrant leave behind
A brighter name to lure mankind!

Thine evil deeds are writ in gore,
  Nor written thus in vain—
Thy triumphs tell of fame no more,
  Or deepen every stain:
If thou hadst died as honour dies,
Some new Napoleon might arise,
  To shame the world again—
But who would soar the solar height,
To set in such a starless night?

Weigh’d in the balance, hero dust
  Is vile as vulgar clay;
Thy scales, Mortality! are just
  To all that pass away;
But yet methought the living great
Some higher sparks should animate,
  To dazzle and dismay:
Nor deem’d Contempt could thus make mirth
Of these, the Conquerors of the earth.

And she, proud Austria’s mournful flower,
  Thy still imperial bride;
How bears her breast the torturing hour?
  Still clings she to thy side?
Must she too bend, must she too share
Thy late repentance, long despair,
  Thou throneless Homicide?
If still she loves thee, hoard that gem,—
’Tis worth thy vanish’d diadem!

Then haste thee to thy sullen Isle,
  And gaze upon the sea;
That element may meet thy smile—
  It ne’er was ruled by thee!
Or trace with thine all idle hand
In loitering mood upon the sand,
  That Earth is now as free!
That Corinth’s pedagogue hath now
Transferr’d his by-word to thy brow.

Thou Timour! in his captive’s cage 3
What thoughts will there be thine,
While brooding in thy prison’d rage?
  But one—‘The world was mine!’
Unless, like he of Babylon,
All sense is with thy sceptre gone, 4
  Life will not long confine
That spirit pour’d so widely forth—
So long obey’d—so little worth!

Or, like the thief of fire from heaven,
  Wilt thou withstand the shock?
And share with him, the unforgiven,
  His vulture and his rock!
Foredoom’d by God—by man accurst,
And that last act, though not thy worst,
  The very Fiend’s arch mock;
He in his fall preserved his pride
And, if a mortal, had as proudly died!

There was a day—there was an hour,
  While earth was Gaul’s—Gaul thine—
When that immeasurable power
  Unsated to resign,
Had been an act of purer fame
Than gathers round Marengo’s name,
  And gilded thy decline
Through the long twilight of all time,
Despite some passing clouds of crime.

But thou forsooth must be a king,
  And don the purple vest,
As if that foolish robe could wring
  Rememberance from thy breast.
Where is that faded garment? where
The gewgaws thou wert fond to wear,
  The star—the string—the crest?
Vain froward child of empire! say,
Are all thy playthings snatched away?

Where may the wearied eye repose
  When gazing on the Great;
Where neither guilty glory glows,
  Nor despicable state?
Yes—one—the first—the last—the best—
The Cincinnatus of the West,
  Whom envy dared not hate,
Bequeath’d the name of Washington,
To make man blush there was but one!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
