<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1827" author="poe" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Tamerlane and Other Poems</title>
   <year>1827</year>
   <notes>
      <note>Tilføjet af Henrik Nielsen.</note>
      <note>Denne digtsamling, som lang tid efter <i>Al Aaraaf, Tamerlane and Minor Poems</i> (1829), der betragtes som Poes egentlige debut, var slet ikke bekendt, og først efter 1876, hvor der blev fundet et eksemplar på British Museums bibliotek, anerkendte man eksistensen af denne tidlige digtsamling. I 1890 fandt man et andet eksemplar, og efter det hævdes der, at der har været op til 200 kopier. I dag kendes kun 12 eksemplarer, hvoraf flere er i dårlig stand. Udgaven her stammer fra faksimiler. Dette er altså førsteudgaven.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture type="titlepage" src="1827-p1.jpg">Titelblad (forside).</picture>
      <picture src="1827-p2.jpg">Titelblad (bagside).</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="poe2002011903">
<head>
   <title>Motto</title>
   <toctitle>Motto</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Motto</indextitle>
   <firstline>Young heads are giddy, and young hearts are warm</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
Young heads are giddy, and young hearts are warm,
And made mistakes for manhood to reform. <sc>Cowper</sc>.
</body>
</poem>

<prose id="poe2002011904">
<head>
   <title>Preface</title>
   <toctitle>Preface</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Preface</indextitle>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. iii-iv</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
THE greater part of the Poems which compose this little volume, were written in the year 1821-2, when the author had not completed his fourteenth year. They were of course not intended for publication ; why they are now published concerns no one but himself. Of the smaller pieces very little need be said ; they perhaps savour too much of Egotism ; but they were written by one too young to have any knowledge of the world but from his own breast.

In Tamerlane, he has endeavoured to expose the folly of even <i>risking</i> the best feelings of the heart at the shrine of Ambition. He is conscious that in this there are many faults, (besides that of the general character of the poem) which he flatters himself he could, with little trouble, have corrected, but unlike many of his predecessors, has been too fond of his early productions to amend them in his <i>old age</i>.

He will not say that he is indifferent as to the success of these Poems - it might stimulate him to other attempts - but he can safely assert that failure will not at all influence him in a resolution already adopted. This is challenging criticism - let it be so.  <i>Nos hæc novimus esse nihil</i><footnote>Den sidste linie er fra Martials 13. bog, 2. epigram, vers 2. Frit oversat: Jeg kender selv uvigtigheden af dette.</footnote>.

<center>___________</center>
</body>
</prose>

<poem id="poe2002012301">
<head>
   <title>Tamerlane</title>
   <toctitle>Tamerlane</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Tamerlane</indextitle>
   <firstline>I have sent for thee, holy friar</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. 5-21</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
I.

    I have sent for thee, holy friar;
But 'twas not with the drunken hope,
Which is but agony of desire
To shun the fate, with which to cope
Is more than crime may dare to dream,
That I have call'd thee at this hour:
Such father is not my theme -
Nor am I mad, to deem that power
Of earth may shrive me of the sin
Unearthly pride hath revell'd in -
I would not call thee fool, old man,
But hope is not a gift of thine;
If I can hope (O God! I can)
It falls from an eternal shrine.

II.

    The gay wall of this gaudy tower
Grows dim around me - death is near.
I had not thought, until this hour
When passing from the earth, that ear
Of any, were it not the shade
Of one whom in life I made
All mystery but a simple name,
Might know the secret of a spirit
Bow'd down in sorrow, and in shame. -
Shame said'st thou?

                         Aye I did inherit
That hatred portion, with the fame,
The worldly glory, which has shown
A demon-light around my throne,
Scorching my sear'd heart with a pain
Not Hell shall make me fear again.

III.

    I have not always been as now -
The fever'd diadem on my brow
I claim'd and won usurpingly -
Aye - the same heritage hath giv'n
Rome to the Cæsar - this to me;
The heirdom of a kingly mind -
And a proud spirit, which hath striv'n
Triumphantly with human kind.

    In mountain air I first drew life;
The mists of the Taglay have shed
Nightly their dews on my young head;
And my brain drank their venom then,
When after day of perilous strife
With chamois, I would seize his den
And slumber, in my pride of power,
The infant monarch of the hour -
For, with the mountain dew by night,
My soul imbib'd unhallow'd feeling;
And I would feel its essence stealing
In dreams upon me - while the light
Flashing from cloud that hover'd o'er,
Would seem to my half closing eye
The pageantry of monarchy!
And the deep thunder's echoing roar
Came hurriedly upon me, telling
Of war, and tumult, where my voice
My <i>own</i> voice, silly child! was swelling
(O how would my wild heart rejoice
And leap within me at the cry)
The battle-cry of victory!

   *      *      *      *      *

IV.

    The rain came down upon my head
But barely shelter'd - and the wind
Pass'd quickly o'er me - but my mind
Was mad'ning - for 'twas man that shed
Laurels upon me - and the rush,
The torrent of the chilly air
Gurgled in my pleas'd ear the crash
Of empires, with the captive's prayer,
The hum of suitors, the mix'd tone
Of flatt'ry round a sov'reign's throne.

    The storm had ceas'd - and I awoke -
Its spirit cradled me to sleep,
And as it pass'd me by, there broke
Strange light upon me, tho' it were
My soul in mystery to sleep:
For I was not as I had been;
The child of Nature, without care,
Or thought, save of the passing scene. -

V.

    My passions, from that hapless hour,
Usurp'd a tyranny, which men
Have deem'd, since I have reach'd to power
My innate nature - be it so:
But, father, there liv'd one who, then -
Then, in my boyhood, when their fire
Burn'd with a still intenser glow;
(For passion must with youth expire)
Ev'n <i>then</i>, who deem'd this iron heart
In woman's weakness had a part.

    I have no words, alas! to tell
The lovliness of loving well!
Nor would I dare attempt to trace
The breathing beauty of a face,
Which ev'n to <i>my</i> impassion'd mind,
Leaves not its memory behind.
In spring of life have ye ne'er dwelt
Some object of delight upon,
With steadfast eye, till ye have felt
The earth reel - and the vision gone?
And I have held to mem'ry's eye
One object - and but one - until
Its very form hath pass'd me by,
But left its influence with me still.

VI.

    'Tis not to thee that I should name -
Thou can'st not -would'st not dare to think
The magic empire of a flame
Which ev'n upon this perilous brink
Hath fix'd my soul, tho' unforgiv'n
By what it lost for passion - Heav'n.
I lov'd - and O, how tenderly!
Yes! she was worthy of all love!
Such as in infancy was mine
Tho' then its <i>passion</i> could not be:
'Twas such as angel minds above
Might envy - her young heart the shrine
On which my ev'ry hope and thought
Were incense - then a goodly gift -
For they were childish, without sin,
Pure as her young examples taught;
Why did I leave it and adrift,
Trust to the fickle star within

VII.

    We grew in age, and love together,
Roaming the forest and the wild;
My breast her shield in wintry weather,
And when the friendly sunshine smil'd
And she would mark the op'ning skies,
I saw no Heav'n, but in her eyes -
Ev'n childhood knows the human heart;
For when, in sunshine and in smiles,
From all our little cares apart,
Laughing at her half silly wiles,
I'd throw me on her throbbing breast,
And pour my spirit out in tears,
She'd look up in my wilder'd eye -
There was no need to speak the rest -
No need to quiet her kind fears -
She did not ask the reason why.

    The hallow'd mem'ry of those years
Comes o'er me in these lonely hours,
And, with sweet lovliness, appears
As perfume of strange summer flow'rs;
Of flow'rs which we have known before
In infancy, which seen, recall
To mind - not flow'rs alone - but more
Our earthly life, and love - and all.

VIII.

    Yes! she was worthy of all love!
Ev'n such as from th' accursed time
My spirit with the tempest strove,
When on the mountain peak alone,
Ambition lent it a new tone,
And bade it first to dream of crime,
My phrenzy to her bosom taught:
We still were young: no purer thought
Dwell in a seraph's breast than thine;
For passionate love is still divine:
<i>I</i> lov'd her as an angel might
With ray of the all living light
Which blazes upon Edis' shrine.
It is not surely sin to name,
With such as mine - that mystic flame,
I had no being but in thee!
The world with all its train of bright
And happy beauty (for to me
All was an undefin'd delight)
The world - its joy - its share of pain
Which I felt not - its bodied forms
Of varied being, which contain
The bodiless spirits of the storms,
The sunshine, and the calm - the ideal
And fleeting vanities of dreams,
Fearfully beautiful! the real
Nothings of mid-day waking life -
Of an enchanted life, which seems,
Now as I look back, the strife
Of some ill demon, with a power
Which left me in an evil hour,
All that I felt, or saw, or thought,
Crowding, confused became
(With thine unearthly beauty fraught)
Thou - and the nothing of a name.

IX.

    The passionate spirit which hath known,
And deeply felt the silent tone
Of its own self supremacy, -
(I speak thus openly to thee,
'Twere folly <i>now</i> to veil a thought
With which this aching, breast is fraught)
The soul which feels its innate right -
The mystic empire and high power
Giv'n by the energetic might
Of Genius, at its natal hour;
Which knows (believe me at this time,
When falsehood were a ten-fold crime,
There is a power in the high spirit
To <i>know</i> the fate it will inherit)
The soul, which knows such power, will still
Find <i>Pride</i> the ruler of its will.

    Yes! I was proud - and ye who know
The magic of that meaning word,
So oft perverted, will bestow
Your scorn, perhaps, when ye have heard
That the proud spirit had been broken,
The proud heart burst in agony
At one upbraiding word or token
Of her that heart's idolatry -
I was ambitious - have ye known
Its fiery passion? - ye have not -
A cottager, I mark'd a throne
Of half the world, as all my own,
And murmur'd at such lowly lot!
But it had pass'd me as a dream
Which, of light step, flies with the dew,
That kindling thought - did not the beam
Of Beauty, which did guide it through
The livelong summer day, oppress
My mind with double loveliness -
     *       *       *       *       *

X.

    We walk'd together on the crown
Of a high mountain, which look'd down
Afar from its proud natural towers
Of rock and forest, on the hills -
The dwindled hills, whence amid bowers
Her own fair hand had rear'd around,
Gush'd shoutingly a thousand rills,
Which as it were, in fairy bound
Embrac'd two hamlets - those our own -
Peacefully happy - yet alone -

     *       *       *       *       *

    I spoke to her of power and pride -
But mystically, in such guise,
That she might deem it naught beside
The moment's converse, in her eyes
I read (perhaps too carelessly)
A mingled feeling with my own;
The flush on her bright cheek, to me,
Seem'd to become a queenly throne
Too well, that I should let it be
A light in the dark wild, alone.

XI.

    There - in that hour - a thought came o'er
My mind, it had not known before -
To leave her while we both were young, -
To follow my high fate among
The strife of nations, and redeem
The idle words, which, as a dream
Now sounded to her heedless ear -
I held no doubt - I knew no fear
Of peril in my wild career;
To gain an empire, and throw down
As nuptial dowry - a queen's crown,
The only feeling which possest,
With her own image, my fond breast -
Who, that had known the secret thought
Of a young peasant's bosom then,
Had deem'd him, in compassion, aught
But one, whom phantasy had led
Astray from reason - Among men
Ambition is chain'd down - nor fed
(As in the desert, where the grand,
The wild, the beautiful, conspire
With their own breath to fan its fire)
With thoughts such feeling can command;
Uncheck'd by sarcasm, and scorn
Of those, who hardly will conceive
That any should become "great," born
In their own sphere - will not believe
That they shall stoop in life to one
Whom daily they are wont to see
Familiarly - whom Fortune's sun
Hath ne'er shone dazzlingly upon
Lowly - and of their own degree -

XII.

    I pictur'd to my fancy's eye
Her silent, deep astonishment,
When, a few fleeting years gone by,
(For short the time my high hope lent
To its most desperate intent,)
She might recall in him, whom Fame
Had gilded with a conquerer's name,
(With glory - such as might inspire
Perforce, a passing thought of one,
Whom she had deem'd in his own fire
Wither'd and blasted; who had gone
A traitor, violate of the truth
So plighted in his early youth,)
Her own Alexis, who should plight
The love he plighted <i>then</i> - again,
And raise his infancy's delight,
The bride and queen of Tamerlane -

XIII.

    One noon of a bright summer's day
I pass'd from out the matted bow'r
Where in a deep, still slumber lay
My Ada. In that peaceful hour,
A silent gaze was my farewell.
I had no other solace - then
T'awake her, and a falsehood tell
Of a feign'd journey, were again
To trust the weakness of my heart
To her soft thrilling voice:  To part
Thus, haply, while in sleep she dream'd
Of long delight, nor yet had deem'd
Awake, that I had held a thought
Of parting, were with madness fraught;
I knew not woman's heart, alas!
Tho' lov'd, and loving - let it pass. -

XIV.

    I went from out the matted bow'r,
And hurried madly on my way:
And felt, with ev'ry flying hour,
That bore me from my home, more gay;
There is of earth an agony
Which, ideal, still may be
The worst ill of mortality,
'Tis bliss, in its own reality,
Too real, to <i>his</i> breast who lives
Not within himself but gives
A portion of his willing soul
To God, and to the great whole -
To him, whose loving spirit will dwell
With Nature, in her wild paths; tell
Of her wond'rous ways, and telling bless
Her overpow'ring loveliness!
A more than agony to him
Whose failing sight will grow dim
With its own living gaze upon
That loveliness around: the sun -
The blue sky - the misty light
Of the pale cloud therein, whose hue
Is grace to its heav'nly bed of blue;
Dim! tho' looking on all bright!
O God! when the thoughts that may not pass
Will burst upon him, and alas!
For the flight on Earth to Fancy giv'n,
There are no words - unless of Heav'n.

XV.

      *      *      *      *      *      *

    Look 'round thee now on Samarcand,
Is she not queen of earth? her pride
Above all cities? in her hand
Their destinies? with all beside
Of glory, which the world hath known?
Stands she not proudly and alone?
And who her sov'reign? Timur he
Whom th' astonish'd earth hath seen,
With victory, on victory,
Redoubling age! and more, I ween,
The Zinghis' yet re-echoing fame.
And now what has he? what! a name.
The sound of revelry by night
Comes o'er me, with the mingled voice
Of many with a breast as light,
As if 'twere not the dying hour
Of one, in whom they did rejoice -
As in a leader, haply - Power
Its venom secretly imparts;
Nothing have I with human hearts.

XVI.

    When Fortune mark'd me for her own,
And my proud hopes had reach'd a throne
(It boots me not, good friar, to tell
A tale the world but knows too well,
How by what hidden deeds of might,
I clamber'd to the tottering height,)
I still was young; and well I ween
My spirit what it e'er had been.
My eyes were still on pomp and power,
My wilder'd heart was far away,
In vallies of the wild Taglay,
In mine own Ada's matted bow'r.
I dwelt not long in Samarcand
Ere, in a peasant's lowly guise,
I sought my long-abandon'd land,
By sunset did its mountains rise
In dusky grandeur to my eyes:
But as I wander'd on the way
My heart sunk with the sun's ray.
To him, who still would gaze upon
The glory of the summer sun,
There comes, when that sun will from him part,
A sullen hopelessness of heart.
That soul will hate the ev'ning mist
So often lovely, and will lisp
To the sound of the coming darkness (known
To those whose spirits hark'n)  as one
Who in a dream of night <i>would</i> fly
But cannot from a danger nigh.
What though the moon - the silvery moon
Shine on his path, in her high noon;
<i>Her</i> smile is chilly, and <i>her</i> beam
In that time of dreariness will seem
As the portrait of one after death;
A likeness taken when the breath
Of young life, and the fire o' the eye
<i>Had</i> lately been but had pass'd by.
'Tis thus when the lovely summer sun
Of our boyhood, his course hath run:
For all we live to know - is known;
And all we seek to keep - hath flown;
With the noon-day beauty, which is all.
Let life, then, as the day-flow'r, fall -
The trancient, passionate day-flow'r,
Withering at the ev'ning hour.

XVII.

    I reach'd my home - my home no more -
For all was flown that made it so -
I pass'd from out its mossy door,
In vacant idleness of woe.
There met me on its threshold stone
A mountain hunter, I had known
In childhood but he knew me not.
Something he spoke of the old cot:
It had seen better days, he said;
<i>There</i> rose a fountain once, and <i>there</i>
Full many a fair flow'r rais'd its head:
But she who rear'd them was long dead,
And in such follies had no part,
What was there left me <i>now</i>? despair -
A kingdom for a broken - heart.
</body>
</poem>

<section level="1">
<head>
   <toctitle>Fugitive Pieces</toctitle>
</head>
<content>

<poem id="poe2002012302">
<head>
   <title>To - -</title>
   <toctitle>To - -</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To - -</indextitle>
   <firstline>I saw thee on the bridal day</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>p. 25</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
I saw thee on the bridal day;
    When a burning blush came o'er thee,
Tho' Happiness around thee lay,
    The world all love before thee.

And, in thine eye, the kindling light
    Of young passion free
Was all on earth, my chain'd sight
   Of Loveliness might see.

That blush, I ween, was maiden shame:
    As such it well may pass:
Tho' its glow hath rais'd a fiercer flame
    In the breast of him, alas!

Who saw the on that bridal day,<note>giver ikke rigtig mening; der menes nok 'thee'. Cf. digtets første vers.</note>
    When that deep blush <i>would</i> come o'er thee, -
Tho' Happiness around thee lay;
    The world all Love before thee. -
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002011901">
<head>
   <title>Dreams</title>
   <toctitle>Dreams</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Dreams</indextitle>
   <firstline>Oh ! that my young life were a lasting dream !</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. 26-27</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
Oh ! that my young life were a lasting dream !
My spirit not awak'ning, till the beam
Of an Eternity should bring the morrow.
Yes ! tho' that long dream were of hopeless sorrow.
Twere better than the cold reality
Of waking life, to him whose heart must be,
And hath been still, upon the lovely earth,
A chaos of deep passion, from his birth.
But should it be - that dream eternally
Continuing - as dreams have been to me
In my young boyhood - should it thus be giv'n
Twere folly still to hope for higher Heav'n.
For I have revell'd when the sun was bright
In the summer sky, in dreams of living light.
And loveliness, - have left my very heart
Inclines of mine imaginary apart
From mine own home, with beings that have been
Of mine own thought - what more could I have seen ?
Twas once - and only once - and the wild hour
From my remembrance shall not pass - some pow'r
Or spell had bound me - 'twas the chilly wind
Came o'er me in the night, and left behind
Its image on my spirit - or the moon
Shone on my slumbers in her lofty noon
Too coldly - or the stars - howe'er it was
That dream was as that night-wind - let it pass.
I have <i>been</i> happy, tho' in a dream.
I have been happy - and I  love the theme :
Dreams ! in their vivid colouring of life
As in that fleeting, shadowy, misty strife
Of semblance with reality which brings
To the delirious eye, more lovely things
Of Paradise and Love - and all our own !
Than young Hope in his sunniest hour hath known.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012401">
<head>
   <title>Visit of the Dead</title>
   <toctitle>Visit of the Dead</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Visit of the Dead</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thy soul shall find itself alone</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. 27-28</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
        *         *         *         *
Thy soul shall find itself alone -
Alone of all on earth - unknown
The cause - but none are near to pry
Into thine hour of secrecy.
Be silent in that solitude,
Which is not loneliness - for then
The spirits of the dead, who stood
In life before thee, are again
In death around thee, and their will
Shall then o'ershadow thee - be still
For the night, tho' clear, shall frown:
And the stars shall look not down
From their thrones, in the dark heav'n;
With light like Hope to mortals giv'n,
But their red orbs, without beam,
To thy withering heart shall seem
As a burning, and a ferver<note><i>ferver</i>: læs: fever.</note>
Which would cling to thee forever.
But 'twill leave thee, as each star
In the morning light afar
Will fly thee - and vanish:
- But its <i>thought</i> thou can'st not banish.
The breath of God will be still;
And the wish upon the hill<note><i>wish</i>: muligvis 'wisp' eller 'mist'.</note>
By that summer breeze unbrok'n
Shall charm thee - as a token,
And a symbol which shall be
Secrecy in thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012402">
<head>
   <title>Evening Star</title>
   <toctitle>Evening Star</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Evening Star</indextitle>
   <firstline>Twas noontide of summer</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>p. 28</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
'Twas noontide of summer,
    And mid-time of night;
And stars, in their orbits,
    Shone pale, thro' the light
Of the brighter, cold moon,
    Mid planets her slaves,
Herself in the Heavens,
    Her beam on the waves.
    I gaz'd awhile
    On her cold smile;
Too cold - too cold for me -
    There pass'd, as a shroud,
    A fleecy cloud,
And I turn'd away to thee,
    Proud Evening Star,
    In thy glory afar,
And dearer thy beam shall be;
    For joy to my heart
    Is the proud part
Thou bearest in Heav'n at night,
    And more I admire
    Thy distant fire,
Than that colder, lowly light.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012403">
<head>
   <title>Imitation</title>
   <toctitle>Imitation</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Imitation</indextitle>
   <firstline>A dark unfathom'd tide</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Imitationen, som digtets titel antyder, er af <a person="byron">Byron</a>, og især <a work="byron/1817a"><i>Manfred</i></a> og <i>Dream</i>.</note>
      <note>De fleste Poe-eksperter mener at dette digt er en tidlig udgave af »A Dream Withing a Dream«.</note>
      <note>p. 29</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
A dark unfathom'd tide
Of interminable pride -
A mystery, and a dream,
Should my early life seem;
I say that dream was fraught
With a wild, and waking thought
Of beings that have been,
Which my spirit hath not seen,
Had I let them pass me by,
With a dreaming eye!
Let none of earth inherit
That vision on my spirit;
Those thoughts I would controul,
As a spell upon his soul:
For that bright hope at last
And that light time have past,
And my worldly rest hath gone
With a sight as it pass'd on
I care not tho' it perish
With a thought I then did cherish,
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012404">
<head>
   <title>Untitled</title>
   <subtitle>[Stanzas ("In youth I have known ...")]</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Untitled</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Untitled</indextitle>
   <firstline>In youth have I known one with whom the Earth</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Digtets titel er siden hen blevet kendt som »Stanzas« ("In youth I have known ..."), angivet af E. C. Stedman og G. E. Woodberry i 1894.</note>
      <note>pp. 30-32</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
<small>How often we forget all time, when lone</small>
<small>Admiring Nature's universal throne;</small>
<small>Her woods --- her wilds --- her mountains --- the intense</small>
<small>Reply of HERS to OUR intelligence!</small><note>Mottoet stammer fra Byrons <i>Island</i> (1823), Canto I.</note>

1.

In youth have I known one with whom the Earth
In secret communing held - as he with it,
In day light, and in beauty from his birth:
Whose fervid, flick'ring torch of life was lit
From the sun and stars, whence he had drawn forth
A passionate light-such for his spirit was fit -
And yet that spirit knew - not in the hour
Of its own fervor - what had o'er it power.

2.

Perhaps it may be that my mind is wrought
To a ferver by the moon beam that hangs o'er,<note><i>ferver</i>: muligvis 'fever' eller 'fervor'. Cf. samme ord i <xref poem="poe2002012403"/>.</note>
But I will half believe that wild light fraught
With more of sov'reignty than ancient lore
Hath ever told - or is it of a thought
The unembodied essence, and no more
That with a quick'ning spell doth o'er us pass
As dew of the night-time, o'er the summer grass.

3.

Doth o'er us pass, when, as th' expanding eye
To the lov'd object - so the tear to the lid
Will start, which lately slept in apathy?
And yet it need not be - (that object) hid
From us in life - but common - which doth lie
Each hour before us - but then only bid
With a strange sound, as of a harp-string broken
T' awake us - Tis a symbol and a token.

4.

Of what in other worlds shall be - and giv'n
In beauty by our God, to those alone
Who otherwise would fall from life and Heav'n
Drawn by their heart's passion, and that tone,
That high tone of the spirit which hath striv'n
Tho' not with Faith - with godliness - whose throne
With desp'rate energy t hath beaten down;
Wearing its own deep feeling as a crown.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012405">
<head>
   <title>Untitled</title>
   <subtitle>[A Dream]</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Untitled</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Untitled</indextitle>
   <firstline>A wilder'd being from my birth</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. 32-33</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
A wilder'd being from my birth
    My spirit spurn'd control,
But now, abroad on the wide earth,
    Where wand'rest thou my soul?

In visions of the dark night
    I have dream'd of joy departed -
But a waking dream of life and light
    Hath left me broken-hearted.

And what is not a dream by day
    To him whose eyes are cast
On things around him with a ray
    Turn'd back upon the past?

That holy dream - that holy dream,
    While all the world were chiding,
Hath cheer'd me as a lovely beam
    A lonely spirit guiding -

What tho' that light, thro' misty night
    So dimly shone afar-
What could there be more purely bright
    In Truth's day - star ?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012406">
<head>
   <title>Untitled</title>
   <subtitle>[The Happiest Day]</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Untitled</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Untitled</indextitle>
   <firstline>The happiest day - the happiest hour</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>pp. 33-34</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
The happiest day - the happiest hour
    My sear'd and blighted heart hath known,
The highest hope of pride, and power,
    I feel hath flown.

Of power! said I? yes! such I ween
    But they have vanish'd long alas!
The visions of my youth have been -
    But let them pass.

And, pride, what have I now with thee?
    Another brow may ev'n inherit
The venom thou hast pour'd on me -
    Be still my spirit.

The happiest day - the happiest hour
    Mine eyes shall see - have ever seen
The brightest glance of pride and power
    I feel - have been:

But were that hope of pride and power
    Now offer'd, with the pain
Ev'n <i>then</i> I felt - that brightest hour
    I would not live again:

For on its wing wall dark alloy
    And as it flutter'd - fell
An essence - powerful to destroy
    A soul that knew it well.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002012407">
<head>
   <title>The Lake</title>
   <toctitle>The Lake</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Lake</indextitle>
   <firstline>In youth's spring, it was my lot</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>p. 34</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
In youth's spring, it was my lot
To haunt of the wide earth a spot
The which I could not love the less;
So lovely was the loneliness
Of a wild lake, with black rock bound.
And the tall pines that tower'd around.
But when the night had thrown her pall
Upon that spot - as upon all,
And the wind would pass me by
In its stilly melody,
My infant spirit would awake
To the terror of the lone lake.
Yet that terror was not fright -
But a tremulous delight,
And a feeling undefin'd,
Springing from a darken'd mind.
Death was in that poison'd wave
And in its gulf a fitting grave
For him who thence could solace bring
To his dark imagining;
Whose wild'ring thought could even make
An Eden of that dim lake.
</body>
</poem>
</content>
</section>

<section level="1">
<head>
   <toctitle>Notes</toctitle>
</head>
<content>

<prose id="poe2002012408">
<head>
   <title>Endnotes</title>
   <toctitle>Endnotes</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Endnotes</indextitle>
   <notes>
      <note>Noterne er til digtet <xref poem="poe2002012301"/>.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
1.

<center>I have sent for thee holy friar.</center>

    Of the history of Tamerlane little is known; and with that little, I have taken the full liberty of a poet. - That he was descended from the family of Zinghis Khan is more than probable - but he is vulgarly supposed to have been the son of a shepherd, and to have raised himself to the throne by his own address. He died in the year 1405, in the time of Pope Innocent VII.
    How I shall account for giving him "a friar," as a death-bed confessor - I cannot exactly determine. He wanted some one to listen to his tale - and why not a friar? It does not pass the bounds of possibility - quite sufficient for my purpose - and I have at least good authority on my side for such innovations.

2.

<center>The mists of <i>the Taglay</i> have shed, &amp;c.</center>

    The mountains of Belur Taglay are a branch of the Immaus, in the southern part of Independent Tartary. - They are celebrated for the singular wildness, and beauty of their vallies.

3.

<center>            No purer thought</center>
<center>Dwelt in a <i>seraph's</i> breast than thine.</center>

    I must beg the reader's pardon for making Tamerlane, a Tartar of the fourteenth century, speak in the same language as a Boston gentleman of the nineteenth; but of the Tartar mythology we have little information.

4.

<center>Which blazes upon Edis' shrine.</center>

    A deity presiding over virtuous love, upon whose imaginary altar, a sacred fire was continually blazing.

5.

<center>----- who hardly will conceive</center>
<center>That any should become "great," born</center>
<center>Born in their own sphere.</center>

    Although Tamerlane speaks this, it is not the less true. It is a matter of the greatest difficulty to make the generality of mankind believe that one, with whom they are upon terms of intimacy, shall be called, in the world, a "great man." The reason is evident. There are few great men. Their actions are consequently viewed by the mass of the people thro' the medium of distance. - The prominent parts of their character are alone noted; and those properties, which are minute and common to every one, not being observed, seem to have no connection with a great character.

    Who ever read the private memorials, correspondence, &amp;c. which have become so common in our time, without wondering that "great men" should act and thnik "so abominably?"<note><i>thnik</i>: formentlig trykfejl; læs: "think".</note>

6.

<center>Her own Alexis who should plight, &amp;c.</center>

    That Tamerlane acquir'd his renown under a feigned name is not entirely a fiction.

7.

<center>Look 'round thee now on Samarcand.</center>

    I believe it was after the battle of Angoria that Tamerlane made Samarcand his residence. It became for a time the seat of learning and the arts.

8.

<center>And who her sov'reign? Timur, &amp;c.</center>

    He was called Timur Bek as well as Tamerlane.

9.

<center>The Zinghis' yet re-echoing fame.</center>

    The conquests of Tamerlane far exceeded those of Zinghis Khan. He boasted to have two thirds of the world at his command.

10.

<center>The sound of the coming darkness (known</center>
<center>To those whose spirits hark'n.)</center>

    I have often fancied that I could distinctly hear the sound of the darkness, as it steals over the horizon - a foolish fancy perhaps, but not more unintelligible than to see music -
"The mind the music breathing from her face."

11.

<center>Let life then, as the day-flow'r, fall.</center>

    There is a flow'r, (I have never known its botanic name,) vulgarly called the day flower. It blooms beautifully in the day-light, but withers towards evening, and by night its leaves appear totally shrivelled and dead. I have forgotten, however, to mention in the text, that it lives again in the morning. If it will not flourish in Tartary, I must be forgiven for carrying it thither.
</body>
</prose>
</content>
</section>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
