<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="poe" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="poe2001070301">
<head>
   <title>Lenore</title>
   <toctitle>Lenore</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Lenore</indextitle>
   <firstline>Ah broken is the golden bowl! the spirit flown forever!</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Findes gendigtet af Thøger Larsen som <xref poem="larsent2001070316"/> i <i>Limfjords-Sange</i> (1925).</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Ah broken is the golden bowl! the spirit flown forever!
Let the bell toll! - a saintly soul floats on the Stygian river;
And, Guy De Vere, hast <i>thou</i> no tear? - weep now or never more!
See! on yon drear and rigid bier low lies thy love, Lenore!
Come! let the burial rite be read - the funeral song be sung! -
An anthem for the queenliest dead that ever died so young -
A dirge for her the doubly dead in that she died so young.

,,Wretches! ye loved her for her wealth and hated her for her pride,
,,And when she fell in feeble health, ye blessed her - that she died!
,,How <i>shall</i> the ritual, then, be read? - the requiem how be sung
,,By you - by yours, the evil eye, - by yours, the slanderous tongue
,,That did to death the innocent that died, and died so young?''

<i>Peccavimus</i>; but rave not thus! and let a Sabbath song
Go up to God so solemnly the dead may feel so wrong!
The sweet Lenore hath ,,gone before,'' with Hope, that flew beside
Leaving thee wild for the dear child that should have been thy bride -
For her, the fair and <i>debonair</i>, that now so lowly lies,
The life upon her yellow hair but not within her eyes -
The life still there, upon her hair - the death upon her eyes.

,,Avaunt! to-night my heart is light. No dirge will I upraise,
,,But waft the angel on her flight with a Paean of old days!
,,Let <i>no</i> bell toll! - lest her sweet soul, amid its hallowed mirth,
,,Should catch the note, as it doth float - up from the damned Earth.
,,To friends above, from fiends below, the indignant ghost is riven -
,,From Hell unto a high estate far up within the Heaven -
,,From grief and groan, to a golden throne, beside the King of Heaven.''
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2001070302">
<head>
   <title>The Raven</title>
   <toctitle>The Raven</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Raven</indextitle>
   <firstline>Once upon a midnight dreary, while I pondered, weak and weary</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Udgivet 1845.</note>
      <note>Findes gendigtet af Thøger Larsen som <xref poem="larsent2001070315"/> i <i>Limfjords-Sange</i> (1925).</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Once upon a midnight dreary, while I pondered, weak and weary,
Over many a quaint and curious volume of forgotten lore,
While I nodded, nearly napping, suddenly there came a tapping,
As of some one gently rapping, rapping at my chamber door.
,,'Tis some visiter,'' I muttered, ,,tapping at my chamber door -
                         Only this, and nothing more.''

Ah, distinctly I remember it was in the bleak December,
And each separate dying ember wrought its ghost upon the floor.
Eagerly I wished the morrow; - vainly I had sought to borrow
From my books surcease of sorrow - sorrow for the lost Lenore -
For the rare and radiant maiden whom the angels name Lenore -
                         Nameless here for evermore.

And the silken sad uncertain rustling of each purple curtain
Thrilled me - filled me with fantastic terrors never felt before;
So that now, to still the beating of my heart, I stood repeating
,,'Tis some visiter entreating entrance at my chamber door -
Some late visiter entreating entrance at my chamber door; -
                         This it is, and nothing more.''

Presently my soul grew stronger; hesitating then no longer,
,,Sir,'' said I, ,,or Madam, truly your forgiveness I implore;
But the fact is I was napping, and so gently you came rapping,
And so faintly you came tapping, tapping at my chamber door,
That I scarce was sure I heard you'' - here I opened wide the door; --
                         Darkness there and nothing more.

Deep into that darkness peering, long I stood there wondering, fearing,
Doubting, dreaming dreams no mortal ever dared to dream before;
But the silence was unbroken, and the darkness gave no token,
And the only word there spoken was the whispered word, ,,Lenore!''
This I whispered, and an echo murmured back the word, ,,Lenore!'' -
                         Merely this, and nothing more.

Back into the chamber turning, all my soul within me burning,
Soon I heard again a tapping somewhat louder than before.
,,Surely,'' said I, ,,surely that is something at my window lattice;
Let me see, then, what thereat is, and this mystery explore -
Let my heart be still a moment and this mystery explore;-
                         'Tis the wind and nothing more!''

Open here I flung the shutter, when, with many a flirt and flutter,
In there stepped a stately raven of the saintly days of yore;
Not the least obeisance made he; not an instant stopped or stayed he;
But, with mien of lord or lady, perched above my chamber door -
Perched upon a bust of Pallas just above my chamber door -
                         Perched, and sat, and nothing more.

Then this ebony bird beguiling my sad fancy into smiling,
By the grave and stern decorum of the countenance it wore,
,,Though thy crest be shorn and shaven, thou,'' I said, ,,art sure no craven,
Ghastly grim and ancient raven wandering from the Nightly shore -
Tell me what thy lordly name is on the Night's Plutonian shore!''
                        Quoth the raven ,,Nevermore.''

Much I marvelled this ungainly fowl to hear discourse so plainly,
Though its answer little meaning - little relevancy bore;
For we cannot help agreeing that no living human being
Ever yet was blessed with seeing bird above his chamber door -
Bird or beast upon the sculptured bust above his chamber door,
                        With such name as ,,Nevermore.''

But the raven, sitting lonely on the placid bust, spoke only
That one word, as if his soul in that one word he did outpour.
Nothing farther then he uttered - not a feather then he fluttered -
Till I scarcely more than muttered ,,Other friends have flown before -
On the morrow <i>he</i> will leave me, as my hopes have flown before.''
                        Then the bird said ,,Nevermore.''

Startled at the stillness broken by reply so aptly spoken,
,,Doubtless,'' said I, ,,what it utters is its only stock and store
Caught from some unhappy master whom unmerciful Disaster
Followed fast and followed faster till his songs one burden bore -
Till the dirges of his Hope that melancholy burden bore
                        Of ,,Never - nevermore.''

But the raven still beguiling all my sad soul into smiling,
Straight I wheeled a cushioned seat in front of bird, and bust and door;
Then, upon the velvet sinking, I betook myself to linking
Fancy unto fancy, thinking what this ominous bird of yore -
What this grim, ungainly, ghastly, gaunt and ominous bird of yore
                        Meant in croaking ,,Nevermore.''

This I sat engaged in guessing, but no syllable expressing
To the fowl whose fiery eyes now burned into my bosom's core;
This and more I sat divining, with my head at ease reclining
On the cushion's velvet lining that the lamplght gloated o'er,
But whose velvet violet lining with the lamplight gloating o'er,
                         <i>She</i> shall press, ah, nevermore!

Then, methought, the air grew denser, perfumed from an unseen censer
Swung by Angels whose faint foot-falls tinkled on the tufted floor.
,,Wretch,'' I cried, ,,thy God hath lent thee - by these angels he hath sent thee
Respite - respite and nepenthe from thy memories of Lenore;
Quaff, oh quaff this kind nepenthe and forget this lost Lenore!''
                         Quoth the raven, ,,Nevermore.''

,,Prophet!'' said I, ,,thing of evil! - prophet still, if bird or devil! -
Whether Tempter sent, or whether tempest tossed thee here ashore,
Desolate yet all undaunted, on this desert land enchanted -
On this home by Horror haunted - tell me truly, I implore -
Is there - <i>is</i> there balm in Gilead? - tell me - tell me, I implore!''
                         Quoth the raven, ,,Nevermore.''

,,Prophet!'' said I, ,,thing of evil - prophet still, if bird or devil!
By that Heaven that bends above us - by that God we both adore -
Tell this soul with sorrow laden if, within the distant Aidenn,
It shall clasp a sainted maiden whom the angels name Lenore -
Clasp a rare and radiant maiden whom the angels name Lenore.''
                         Quoth the raven, ,,Nevermore.''

,,Be that word our sign of parting, bird or fiend!'' I shrieked, upstarting -
,,Get thee back into the tempest and the Night's Plutonian shore!
Leave no black plume as a token of that lie thy soul hath spoken!
Leave my loneliness unbroken! - quit the bust above my door!
Take thy beak from out my heart, and take thy form from off my door!''
                        Quoth the raven, ,,Nevermore.''

And the raven, never flitting, still is sitting, still is sitting
On the pallid bust of Pallas just above my chamber door;
And his eyes have all the seeming of a demon's that is dreaming,
And the lamp-light o'er him streaming throws his shadow on the floor;
And my soul from out that shadow that lies floating on the floor
                         Shall be lifted - nevermore!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2001070401">
<head>
   <title>An acrostic</title>
   <toctitle>An acrostic</toctitle>
   <indextitle>An acrostic</indextitle>
   <firstline>Elizabeth it is in vain you say</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>L.E.L. formodes at være Letitia Elizabeth Landon (<year>1802</year>-<year>1838</year>), en populær engelsk digterinde, der typisk signerede sine digte med disse initialer.</note>
      <note>Dette digt er et af mange akrostikoner, Poe skrev til fornøjelse for kvindelige beundrere. Digtet blev aldrig udgivet mens Poe endnu var i live, men blev opdaget af James H. Whitty, der i hans udgave af Poes digte fra <year>1911</year> publicerede det under titlen »From an Album«.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>akrostikon</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Elizabeth it is in vain you say
,,Love not'' - thou sayest it in so sweet a way:
In vain those words from thee or L. E. L.
Zantippe's<note>Her menes Xanthippe, Sokrates' kone.</note> talents had enforced so well:
Ah! if that language from thy heart arise,
Breathe it less gently forth - and veil thine eyes.
Endymion, recollect, when Luna tried
To cure his love - was cured of all beside -
His folly - pride - and passion - for he died.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2001070402">
<head>
   <title>Alone</title>
   <toctitle>Alone</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Alone</indextitle>
   <firstline>From childhood's hour I have not been</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Efter det originale manuskript.</note>
      <note>Poe skrev dette digt i Lucy Holmes' (senere Lucy Holmes Balderston) <a keyword="stambog">stambog</a> ca. <year>1829</year>. Digtet blev ikke udgivet i Poes levetid, og blev først publiceret af E.L. Didier i <i>Scribner's Monthly</i>, september <year>1875</year>, i form af en faksimile. Faksimilet indeholdt dog en titel og dato, der ikke er på det originale manuskript. Skepsis omkring digtets autencititet, bl.a. ansporet af denne manipulation, er dog senere blevet neddæmpet. Nu betragtes digtet som et af Poes mest afslørende værker.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
From childhood's hour I have not been
As others were - I have not seen
As others saw - I could not bring
My passions from a common spring -
From the same source I have not taken
My sorrow - I could not awaken
My heart to joy at the same tone -
And all I lov'd - <i>I</i> lov'd alone -
<i>Then</i> - in my childhood - in the dawn
Of a most stormy life - was drawn
From ev'ry depth of good and ill
The mystery which binds me still -
From the torrent, or the fountain -
From the red cliff of the mountain -
From the sun that 'round me roll'd
In its autumn tint of gold -
From the lightning in the sky
As it pass'd me flying by -
From the thunder, and the storm -
And the cloud that took the form
(When the rest of Heaven was blue)
Of a demon in my view -
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="poe2002011902">
<head>
   <title>Annabel Lee</title>
   <toctitle>Annabel Lee</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Annabel Lee</indextitle>
   <firstline>It was many and many a year ago</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <!-- Fra Griswold-ms. -->
</head>
<body>
It was many and many a year ago,
    In a kingdom by the sea,
That a maiden there lived whom you may know
    By the name of Annabel Lee; -
And this maiden she lived with no other thought
    Than to love and be loved by me.

I was a child and she was a child,
    In this kingdom by the sea;
But we loved with a love that was more than love -
    I and my Annabel Lee -
With a love that the wingéd seraphs in Heaven
    Coveted her and me.

And this was the reason that, long ago,
    In this kingdom by the sea,
A wind blew out of a cloud, chilling
    My beautiful Annabel Lee;
So that her high-born kinsmen came
    And bore her away from me,
To shut her up in a sepulchre,
    In this kingdom by the sea.

The angels, not half so happy in Heaven,
    Went envying her and me -
Yes! - that was the reason (as all men know,
    In this kingdom by the sea)
That the wind came out of the cloud by night,
    Chilling and killing my Annabel Lee.

But our love it was stronger by far than the love
    Of those who were older than we -
    Of many far wiser than we -
And neither the angels in Heaven above,
    Nor the demons down under the sea,
Can ever dissever my soul from the soul
    Of the beautiful Annabel Lee: -

For the moon never beams, without bringing me dreams
    Of the beautiful Annabel Lee;
And the stars never rise, but I feel the bright eyes
    Of the beautiful Annabel Lee: -
And so, all the night-tide, I lie down by the side
Of my darling - my darling - my life and my bride,
    In her sepulchre there by the sea -
    In her tomb by the sounding sea.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
