<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="dyer" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="dyer2003091501">
<head>
   <title>My mind to me a kingdom is</title>
   <toctitle>My mind to me a kingdom is</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My mind to me a kingdom is</indextitle>
   <firstline>My mind to me a kingdom is</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My mind to me a kingdom is;	
  Such present joys therein I find,	
That it excels all other bliss	
  That earth affords or grows by kind:	
Though much I want that most would have,
Yet still my mind forbids to crave.	
 
No princely pomp, no wealthy store,	
  No force to win the victory,	
No wily wit to salve a sore,	
  No shape to feed a loving eye;
To none of these I yield as thrall;	
For why? my mind doth serve for all.	
 
I see how plenty surfeits oft,	
  And hasty climbers soon do fall;	
I see that those which are aloft
  Mishap doth threaten most of all:	
They get with toil, they keep with fear:	
Such cares my mind could never bear.	
 
Content I live, this is my stay;	
  I seek no more than may suffice;
I press to bear no haughty sway;	
  Look, what I lack my mind supplies.	
Lo, thus I triumph like a king,	
Content with that my mind doth bring.	
 
Some have too much, yet still do crave;
  I little have, and seek no more.	
They are but poor, though much they have,	
  And I am rich with little store;	
They poor, I rich; they beg, I give;	
They lack, I leave; they pine, I live.
 
I laugh not at another\x{2019}s loss,	
  I grudge not at another\x{2019}s gain;	
No worldly waves my mind can toss;	
  My state at one doth still remain:	
I fear no foe, I fawn no friend;
I loathe not life, nor dread my end.	
 
Some weigh their pleasure by their lust,	
  Their wisdom by their rage of will;	
Their treasure is their only trust,	
  A cloakèd craft their store of skill;
But all the pleasure that I find	
Is to maintain a quiet mind.	
 
My wealth is health and perfect ease,	
  My conscience clear my chief defence;	
I neither seek by bribes to please,
  Nor by deceit to breed offence:	
Thus do I live; thus will I die;	
Would all did so as well as I!
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>

