<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="browningr" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="browning2002012901">
<head>
   <title>Rhyme for a Child Viewing a Naked Venus in a Painting of 'The Judgement of Paris'</title>
   <toctitle>Rhyme for a Child Viewing a Naked Venus in a Painting of 'The Judgement of Paris'</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Rhyme for a Child Viewing a Naked Venus in a Painting of 'The Judgement of Paris'</indextitle>
   <firstline>He gazed and gazed and gazed and gazed</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Det store indtastningsarbejde er foretaget af Brian Bentsen efter Robert Browning, <i>The Poems</i>, eds. John Pettigrew &amp; Thomas J. Collins, 2 vols., Yale University Press 1981, vol. 2, s. 958.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
       <picture src="browning2002012901-p1.jpg">Peter Paul Rubens (1577 - 1640): <i>The Judgement of Paris</i>, ca. 1597-1599, olie på lærred, 144,8×193,7cm. The National Gallery, London. <!-- NG-6379 --></picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde,side</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
He gazed and gazed and gazed and gazed,
Amazed, amazed, amazed, amazed.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningr2021102101">
<head>
    <title>Two in the Campagna</title>
    <firstline>I wonder do you feel to-day</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I
I wonder do you feel to-day
As I have felt since, hand in hand,
We sat down on the grass, to stray
In spirit better through the land,
This morn of Rome and May?

II
For me, I touched a thought, I know,
Has tantalized me many times,
(Like turns of thread the spiders throw
Mocking across our path) for rhymes
To catch at and let go.

III
Help me to hold it! First it left
The yellowing fennel, run to seed
There, branching from the brickwork's cleft,
Some old tomb's ruin: yonder weed
Took up the floating weft,

IV
Where one small orange cup amassed
Five beetles,—blind and green they grope
Among the honey-meal: and last,
Everywhere on the grassy slope
I traced it. Hold it fast!

V
The champaign with its endless fleece
Of feathery grasses everywhere!
Silence and passion, joy and peace,
An everlasting wash of air—
Rome's ghost since her decease.

VI
Such life here, through such lengths of hours,
Such miracles performed in play,
Such primal naked forms of flowers,
Such letting nature have her way
While heaven looks from its towers!

VII
How say you? Let us, O my dove,
Let us be unashamed of soul,
As earth lies bare to heaven above!
How is it under our control
To love or not to love?

VIII
I would that you were all to me,
You that are just so much, no more.
Nor yours nor mine, nor slave nor free!
Where does the fault lie? What the core
O' the wound, since wound must be?

IX
I would I could adopt your will,
See with your eyes, and set my heart
Beating by yours, and drink my fill
At your soul's springs,—your part my part
In life, for good and ill.

X
No. I yearn upward, touch you close,
Then stand away. I kiss your cheek,
Catch your soul's warmth,—I pluck the rose
And love it more than tongue can speak—
Then the good minute goes.

XI
Already how am I so far
Out of that minute? Must I go
Still like the thistle-ball, no bar,
Onward, whenever light winds blow,
Fixed by no friendly star?

XII
Just when I seemed about to learn!
Where is the thread now? Off again!
The old trick! Only I discern—
Infinite passion, and the pain
Of finite hearts that yearn.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningr2021102102">
<head>
    <title>The Last Ride together</title>
    <firstline>I said—Then, dearest, since 'tis so</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>I said</sc>—Then, dearest, since 'tis so,
Since now at length my fate I know,
Since nothing all my love avails,
Since all, my life seem'd meant for, fails,
    Since this was written and needs must be—
My whole heart rises up to bless
Your name in pride and thankfulness!
Take back the hope you gave,—I claim
Only a memory of the same,
—And this beside, if you will not blame;
    Your leave for one more last ride with me.

My mistress bent that brow of hers,
Those deep dark eyes where pride demurs
When pity would be softening through,
Fix'd me a breathing-while or two
    With life or death in the balance: right!
The blood replenish'd me again;
My last thought was at least not vain:
I and my mistress, side by side
Shall be together, breathe and ride,
So, one day more am I deified.
    Who knows but the world may end to-night?

Hush! if you saw some western cloud
All billowy-bosom'd, over-bow'd
By many benedictions—sun's
And moon's and evening-star's at once—
    And so, you, looking and loving best,
Conscious grew, your passion drew
Cloud, sunset, moonrise, star-shine too,
Down on you, near and yet more near,
Till flesh must fade for heaven was here!—
Thus leant she and linger'd—joy and fear!
    Thus lay she a moment on my breast.

Then we began to ride. My soul
Smooth'd itself out, a long-cramp'd scroll
Freshening and fluttering in the wind.
Past hopes already lay behind.
    What need to strive with a life awry?
Had I said that, had I done this,
So might I gain, so might I miss.
Might she have loved me? just as well
She might have hated, who can tell!
Where had I been now if the worst befell?
    And here we are riding, she and I.

Fail I alone, in words and deeds?
Why, all men strive and who succeeds?
We rode; it seem'd my spirit flew,
Saw other regions, cities new,
    As the world rush'd by on either side.
I thought,—All labour, yet no less
Bear up beneath their unsuccess.
Look at the end of work, contrast
The petty done, the undone vast,
This present of theirs with the hopeful past!
    I hoped she would love me; here we ride.

What hand and brain went ever pair'd?
What heart alike conceived and dared?
What act proved all its thought had been?
What will but felt the fleshly screen?
    We ride and I see her bosom heave.
There 's many a crown for who can reach.
Ten lines, a statesman's life in each!
The flag stuck on a heap of bones,
A soldier's doing! what atones?
They scratch his name on the Abbey-stones.
    My riding is better, by their leave.

What does it all mean, poet? Well,
Your brains beat into rhythm, you tell
What we felt only; you express'd
You hold things beautiful the best,
    And pace them in rhyme so, side by side.
'Tis something, nay 'tis much: but then,
Have you yourself what 's best for men?
Are you—poor, sick, old ere your time—
Nearer one whit your own sublime
Than we who never have turn'd a rhyme?
    Sing, riding 's a joy! For me, I ride.

And you, great sculptor—so, you gave
A score of years to Art, her slave,
And that 's your Venus, whence we turn
To yonder girl that fords the burn!
    You acquiesce, and shall I repine?
What, man of music, you grown gray
With notes and nothing else to say,
Is this your sole praise from a friend,
'Greatly his opera's strains intend,
But in music we know how fashions end!'
    I gave my youth: but we ride, in fine.

Who knows what 's fit for us? Had fate
Proposed bliss here should sublimate
My being—had I sign'd the bond—
Still one must lead some life beyond,
    Have a bliss to die with, dim-descried.
This foot once planted on the goal,
This glory-garland round my soul,
Could I descry such? Try and test!
I sink back shuddering from the quest.
Earth being so good, would heaven seem best?
    Now, heaven and she are beyond this ride.

And yet—she has not spoke so long!
What if heaven be that, fair and strong
At life's best, with our eyes upturn'd
Whither life's flower is first discern'd,
    We, fix'd so, ever should so abide?
What if we still ride on, we two
With life for ever old yet new,
Changed not in kind but in degree,
The instant made eternity,—
And heaven just prove that I and she
    Ride, ride together, for ever ride?
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningr2021102701">
<head>
    <title>In a Year</title>
    <firstline>Never any more</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Never any more,
      While I live,
Need I hope to see his face
      As before.
Once his love grown chill,
      Mine may strive:
Bitterly we re-embrace,
      Single still.

Was it something said,
      Something done,
Vexed him? was it touch of hand,
      Turn of head?
Strange! that very way
      Love begun:
I as little understand
      Love’s decay.

When I sewed or drew,
      I recall
How he looked as if I sung,—
      Sweetly too.
If I spoke a word,
      First of all
Up his cheek the color sprung,
      Then he heard.

Sitting by my side,
      At my feet,
So he breathed but air I breathed,
      Satisfied!
I, too, at love’s brim
      Touched the sweet:
I would die if death bequeathed
      Sweet to him.

“Speak, I love thee best!”
      He exclaimed:
“Let thy love my own foretell!”
      I confessed:
“Clasp my heart on thine
      Now unblamed,
Since upon thy soul as well
      Hangeth mine!”

Was it wrong to own,
      Being truth?
Why should all the giving prove
      His alone?
I had wealth and ease,
      Beauty, youth:
Since my lover gave me love,
      I gave these.

That was all I meant,—
      To be just,
And the passion I had raised
      To content.
Since he chose to change
      Gold for dust,
If I gave him what he praised
      Was it strange?

Would he loved me yet,
      On and on,
While I found some way undreamed—
      Paid my debt!
Gave more life and more,
      Till all gone,
He should smile—“She never seemed
      Mine before.

“What, she felt the while,
      Must I think?
Love’s so different with us men!”
      He should smile:
“Dying for my sake—
      White and pink!
Can’t we touch these bubbles then
      But they break?”

Dear, the pang is brief,
      Do thy part,
Have thy pleasure! How perplexed
      Grows belief!
Well, this cold clay clod
      Was man’s heart:
Crumble it, and what comes next?
      Is it God?
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningr2022052101">
<head>
    <title>Evelyn Hope</title>
    <firstline>Beautiful Evelyn Hope is dead!</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I.

Beautiful Evelyn Hope is dead!
    Sit and watch by her side an hour.
That is her book-shelf, this her bed;
    She plucked that piece of geranium-flower,
Beginning to die too, in the glass;
    Little has yet been changed, I think:
The shutters are shut, no light may pass
Save two long rays thro' the hinge's chink.

II.

Sixteen years old, when she died!
    Perhaps she had scarcely heard my name;
It was not her time to love; beside,
    Her life had many a hope and aim,
Duties enough and little cares,
    And now was quiet, now astir,
Till God's hand beckoned unawares,—-
    And the sweet white brow is all of her.

III.

Is it too late then, Evelyn Hope?
    What, your soul was pure and true,
The good stars met in your horoscope,
    Made you of spirit, fire and dew—-
And, just because I was thrice as old
    And our paths in the world diverged so wide,
Each was nought to each, must I be told?
    We were fellow mortals, nought beside?

IV.

No, indeed! for God above
    Is great to grant, as mighty to make,
And creates the love to reward the love:
    I claim you still, for my own love's sake!
Delayed it may be for more lives yet,
    Through worlds I shall traverse, not a few:
Much is to learn, much to forget
    Ere the time be come for taking you.

V.

But the time will come,—-at last it will,
    When, Evelyn Hope, what meant (I shall say)
In the lower earth, in  the  years  long  still,
    That body and soul so pure and gay?
Why your hair was amber, I shall divine,
    And your mouth of your own geranium's red—-
And  what  you  would  do  with  me,  in   fine,
    In the new life come in the old one's stead.

VI.

I have lived (I shall say) so much since then,
    Given up myself so many times,
Gained me the gains of various men,
    Ransacked the ages, spoiled the climes;
Yet one thing, one, in my soul's full scope,
    Either I missed or itself missed me:
And I want and find you, Evelyn Hope!
    What is the issue? let us see!

VII.

I loved you, Evelyn, all the while.
    My heart seemed full as it could hold?
There was place and to spare for the frank young smile,
    And the red young mouth, and the hair's young gold.
So, hush,—-I will give you this leaf to keep:
    See, I shut it inside the sweet cold hand!
There, that is our secret: go to sleep!
    You will wake, and remember, and understand.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="browningr2022052102">
<head>
    <title>The Lost Mistress</title>
    <firstline>All’s over, then: does truth sound bitter</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
All’s over, then: does truth sound bitter
As one at first believes?
Hark, ’tis the sparrows’ good-night twitter
About your cottage eaves!

And the leaf-buds on the vine are woolly,
I noticed that, today;
One day more bursts them open fully
– You know the red turns grey.

Tomorrow we meet the same then, dearest?
May I take your hand in mine?
Mere friends are we, – well, friends the merest
Keep much that I resign:

For each glance of the eye so bright and black,
Though I keep with heart’s endeavor, –
Your voice, when you wish the snowdrops back,
Though it stay in my soul for ever! –

Yet I will but say what mere friends say,
Or only a thought stronger;
I will hold your hand but as long as all may,
Or so very little longer!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
