<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1619" author="drayton" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Idea</title>
   <year>1619</year>
   <notes>
      <note type="credits">Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen.</note>
      <note> Kilde er <i>Poems by Michael Drayton, Esquyer</i> (1619).</note>
      <note>Kalliopes tekst ligger så nært op ad originalen som muligt; når undtages &#383; (det gamle f-lignende s) er stavemåde og tegnsætning bibeholdt og kun åbenlyse smuttere rettet.  Typografiske detaljer såsom punktum efter titler og begyndelsesord i majuskler har vi ikke efterlignet.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="1619-p1.jpg">Facsimile af titelbladet.</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="drayton2002020364">
<head>
   <title>To the Reader of these Sonnets</title>
   <toctitle>To the Reader of these Sonnets</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To the Reader of these Sonnets</indextitle>
   <firstline>Into these Loues, who but for Passion lookes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<i>Into these Loues, who but for Passion lookes,
At this first sight, here let him lay them by,
And seeke else-where, in turning other Bookes,
Which better may his labour satisfie.
No farre-fetch'd Sigh shall euer wound my Brest,
Loue from mine Eye a Teare shall neuer wring,
Nor in </i>Ah-mees<i> my whyning Sonnets drest,
(A Libertine) fantastickly I sing:
My Verse is the true image of my Mind,
Euer in motion, still desiring change;
And as thus to Varietie inclin'd,
So in all Humors sportiuely I range:
    My Muse is rightly of the </i>English<i> straine,
    That cannot long one fashion intertaine.</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020301">
<head>
   <title>I</title>
   <toctitle>1 (Like an aduenturous Sea-farer am I)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Like an aduenturous Sea-farer am I</indextitle>
   <firstline>Like an aduenturous Sea-farer am I</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Like an aduenturous Sea-farer am I,
Who hath some long and dang'rous Voyage beene,
And call'd to tell of his Discouerie,
How farre he sayl'd, what Countries he had seene,
Proceeding from the Port whence he put forth,
Shewes by his Compasse, how his Course he steer'd,
When East, when West, when South, and when by North,
As how the Pole to eu'ry place was rear'd,
What Capes he doubled, of what Continent,
The Gulphes and Straits, that strangely he had past,
Where most becalm'd, wherewith foule Weather spent,
And on what Rocks in perill to be cast?
    Thus in my Loue, Time calls me to relate
    My tedious Trauels, and oft-varying Fate.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020302">
<head>
   <title>2</title>
   <toctitle>2 (My Heart was slaine, and none but you and I)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My Heart was slaine, and none but you and I</indextitle>
   <firstline>My Heart was slaine, and none but you and I</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
My Heart was slaine, and none but you and I:
Who should I thinke the Murther should commit?
Since, but your selfe, there was no Creature by,
But onely I, guiltlesse of murth'ring it.
It slew it selfe; the Verdict on the view
Doe quit the dead, and me not accessarie:
Well, well, I feare it will be prou'd by you,
Th'euidence so great a proofe doth carrie.
But O, see, see, we need inquire no further,
Vpon your Lips the scarlet drops are found,
And in your Eye, the Boy that did the Murther,
Your Cheekes yet pale, since first he gaue the Wound.
    By this I see, how-euer things be past,
    Yet Heau'n will still haue Murther out at last.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020303">
<head>
   <title>3</title>
   <toctitle>3 (Taking my Penne, with Words to cast my Woe)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Taking my Penne, with Words to cast my Woe</indextitle>
   <firstline>Taking my Penne, with Words to cast my Woe</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Taking my Penne, with Words to cast my Woe,
Duely to count the summe of all my cares,
I finde, my Griefes innumerable growe,
The reck'nings rise to millions of Despaires,
And thus diuiding of my fatall Houres,
The paiments of my Loue, I read, and crosse,
Substracting, set my Sweets vnto my Sowres,
My Ioyes arrerage leades me to my losse;
And thus mine Eies a debtor to thine Eye,
Which by Extortion gaineth all their lookes,
My heart hath paid such grieuous Vsurie,
That all their Wealth lies in thy beauties Bookes,
    And all is Thine which hath been due to Me,
    And I a Bankrupt, quite vndone by Thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020304">
<head>
   <title>4</title>
   <toctitle>4 (Bright starre of Beauty, on whose eye-lids sit)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Bright starre of Beauty, on whose eye-lids sit</indextitle>
   <firstline>Bright starre of Beauty, on whose eye-lids sit</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Bright starre of Beauty, on whose eye-lids sit
A thousand Nimph-like and inamor'd Graces,
The Goddesses of Memory and Wit,
Which there in order take their seuerall places,
In whose deare Bosome, sweet delicious Loue
Layes downe his Quiuer, which he once did beare:
Since he that blessed Paradise did proue,
And leaues his Mothers lap to sport him there,
Let others striue to entertaine with Words,
My Soule is of a brauer Mettle made,
I hold that vile, which Vulgar wit affords;
In Me's that Faith which Time cannot inuade.
    Let what I praise, be still made good by you:
    Be you most worthy, whilst I am most true.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020305">
<head>
   <title>5</title>
   <toctitle>5 (Nothing but No and I, and I and No)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Nothing but No and I, and I and No</indextitle>
   <firstline>Nothing but No and I, and I and No</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Nothing but No and I, and I and No,
How fals it out so strangely you reply?
I tell yee (faire) Ile not be answered so,
With this affirming No, denying I.
I say, I Loue, you sleightly answere I:
I say, You Loue, you peule me out a No:
I say, I Die, you Eccho me with I:
Saue mee I Crie, you sigh me out a No;
Must Woe and I, haue naught but No and I?
No I, am I, if I no more can haue;
Answere no more, with Silence make reply,
And let me take my selfe what I doe craue,
    Let No and I, with I and you be so:
    Then answere No and I, and I and No.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020306">
<head>
   <title>6</title>
   <toctitle>6 (How many paltry, foolish, painted things)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How many paltry, foolish, painted things</indextitle>
   <firstline>How many paltry, foolish, painted things</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
How many paltry, foolish, painted things,
That now in Coaches trouble eu'ry Street,
Shall be forgotten, whom no Poet sings,
Ere they be well wrap'd in their winding Sheet?
Where I to thee Eternitie shall giue,
When nothing else remayneth of these dayes,
And Queenes hereafter shall be glad to liue
Vpon the Almes of thy superfluous prayse;
Virgins and Matrons reading these my Rimes,
Shall be so much delighted with thy story,
That they shall grieue, they liu'd not in these Times,
To haue seene thee, their Sexes onely glory:
    So shalt thou flye aboue the vulgar Throng,
    Still to suruiue in my immortall Song.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020307">
<head>
   <title>7</title>
   <toctitle>7 (Loue, in a Humor, play'd the Prodigall)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Loue, in a Humor, play'd the Prodigall</indextitle>
   <firstline>Loue, in a Humor, play'd the Prodigall</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Loue, in a Humor, play'd the Prodigall,
And bad my Senses to a solemne Feast;
Yet more to grace the Company withall,
Inuites my Heart to be the chiefest Ghest:
No other Drinke would serue this Gluttons turne,
But precious Teares distilling from mine Eyne,
Which with my Sighes this Epicure doth burne,
Quaffing Carowses in this costly Wine;
Where, in his Cups o'rcome with foule Excesse,
Straightwayes he play's a swagg'ring Ruffins part,
And at the Banquet in his Drunkennesse,
Slew his deare Friend, my kind and truest Heart:
    A gentle warning (Friends) thus may you see,
    What 'tis to keepe a Drunkard companie.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020308">
<head>
   <title>8</title>
   <toctitle>8 (There's nothing grieues me, but that Age should haste)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>There's nothing grieues me, but that Age should haste</indextitle>
   <firstline>There's nothing grieues me, but that Age should haste</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
There's nothing grieues me, but that Age should haste,
That in my dayes I may not see thee old,
That where those two cleare sparkling Eyes are plac'd,
Onely two Loope-holes, then I might behold.
That louely, arched, yuorie, polish'd Brow,
Defac'd with Wrinkles, that I might but see;
Thy daintie Hayre, so curl'd, and crisped now,
Like grizzled Mosse vpon some aged Tree;
Thy Cheeke, now flush with Roses, sunke, and leane,
Thy Lips, with age, as any Wafer thinne,
Thy Pearly Teeth out of thy Head so cleane,
That when thou feed'st, thy Nose shall touch thy Chinne:
    These Lines that now scorn'st, which should delight thee,
    Then would I make thee read, but to despight thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020309">
<head>
   <title>9</title>
   <toctitle>9 (As other Men, so I my selfe doe Muse)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As other Men, so I my selfe doe Muse</indextitle>
   <firstline>As other Men, so I my selfe doe Muse</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As other Men, so I my selfe doe Muse,
Why in this sort I wrest Inuention so,
And why these giddy Metaphors I vse,
Leauing the Path the greater part doe goe;
I will resolue you; I am Lunaticke,
And euer this in Mad-men you shall finde,
What they last thought of, when the Braine grew sicke,
In most distraction they keepe that in Minde.
Thus talking idly in this Bedlam fit,
Reason and I (you must conceiue) are twaine,
Tis nine yeeres now since first I lost my Wit,
Beare with Me then, though troubled be my Braine;
    With Diet and Correction, Men distraught,
    (Not too farre past) may to their Wits be brought.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020310">
<head>
   <title>10</title>
   <toctitle>10 (To nothing fitter can I Thee compare)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To nothing fitter can I Thee compare</indextitle>
   <firstline>To nothing fitter can I Thee compare</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
To nothing fitter can I Thee compare,
Then to the Sonne of some rich Penny-father,
Who hauing now brought on his end with Care,
Leaues to his Sonne all he had heap'd together;
This new rich Nouice, lauish of his chest,
To one Man giues, doth on another spend,
Then heere he riots, yet among the rest,
Haps to lend some to one true honest Friend.
Thy Gifts thou in Obscuritie doest waste,
False Friends thy kindnesse, borne but to deceiue Thee;
Thy Loue, that is on the vnworthy plac'd,
Time hath thy Beautie, which with Age will leaue thee;
    Onely that little which to Me was lent,
    I giue Thee backe, when all the rest is spent.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020311">
<head>
   <title>11</title>
   <toctitle>11 (You not alone, when You are still alone)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>You not alone, when You are still alone</indextitle>
   <firstline>You not alone, when You are still alone</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
You not alone, when You are still alone,
O God from You, that I could priuate be,
Since You one were, I neuer since was one,
Since You in Me, my selfe since out of Me,
Transported from my Selfe, into Your being,
Though either distant, present yet to either,
Senselesse with too much Ioy, each other seeing,
And onely absent, when Wee are together.
Giue Me my Selfe, and take your Selfe againe,
Deuise some meanes, but how I may forsake You,
So much is Mine, that doth with You remaine,
That taking what is Mine, with Me I take You;
    You doe bewitch Me, O that I could flie,
    From my Selfe You, or from your owne Selfe I.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020312">
<head>
   <title>12</title>
   <subtitle>To the Soule</subtitle>
   <toctitle>12 (That learned Father, which so firmely proues)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That learned Father, which so firmely proues</indextitle>
   <firstline>That learned Father, which so firmely proues</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="drayton2002020312-p1.jpg">Fascimile af sonet 12.</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
That learned Father, which so firmely proues
The Soule of Man immortall and diuine,
And doth the seu'rall Offices define:
<i>Anima</i>        Giues her that Name, as she the Body moues,
<i>Amor</i>         Then is she Loue, imbracing Charitie,
<i>Animus</i>       Mouing a Will in vs, it is the Mind,
<i>Mens</i>         Retayning Knowledge, still the same in kind;
<i>Memoria</i>      As intellectuall, it is Memorie,
<i>Ratio</i>        In iudging, Reason onely is her Name,
<i>Sensus</i>       In speedie apprehension, it is Sense,
<i>Conscientia</i>  In Right or Wrong, they call her Conscience,
<i>Spiritus</i>     The Spirit, when it to God-ward doth inflame:
    These of the Soule the seu'ral Functions bee,
    Which my Heart, lightned by thy Loue, doth see.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020313">
<head>
   <title>13</title>
   <subtitle>To the Shadow</subtitle>
   <toctitle>13 (Letters and Lines we see are soone defaced)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Letters and Lines we see are soone defaced</indextitle>
   <firstline>Letters and Lines we see are soone defaced</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Letters and Lines we see are soone defaced,
Metals doe waste, and fret with Cankers Rust,
The Diamond shall once consume to Dust,
And freshest Colours with foule staynes disgraced:
Paper and Inke can paint but naked Words,
To write with Bloud, of force offends the Sight;
And if with Teares I find them all too light,
And Sighes and Signes a silly Hope affords,
O sweetest Shadow, how thou seru'st my turne!
Which still shalt be, as long as there is Sunne;
Nor whilst the World is, neuer shall be done,
Whilst Moone shall shine, or any Fire shall burne:
    That eu'ry thing whence Shadow doth proceed,
    May in his Shadow my Loues storie read.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020314">
<head>
   <title>14</title>
   <toctitle>14 (If he, from Heau'n that filch'd that liuing Fire)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>If he, from Heau'n that filch'd that liuing Fire</indextitle>
   <firstline>If he, from Heau'n that filch'd that liuing Fire</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
If he, from Heau'n that filch'd that liuing Fire,
Condemn'd by <sc>Iove</sc> to endlesse Torment bee,
I greatly maruell, how you still goe free,
That farre beyond <sc>Promethevs</sc> did aspire:
The Fire he stole, although of Heau'nly kind,
Which from aboue he craftily did take,
Of liuelesse Clods, vs liuing Men to make,
He did bestow in temper of the Mind.
But you broke into Heau'ns immortall store,
Where Vertue, Honour, Wit, and Beautie lay;
Which taking thence, you haue escap'd away,
Yet stand as free as ere you did before:
    Yet old <sc>Promethevs</sc> punish'd for his Rape.
    Thus poore Theeues suffer, when the greater scape.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020315">
<head>
   <title>15</title>
   <subtitle>His Remedie for Loue</subtitle>
   <toctitle>15 (Since to obtaine thee, nothing me will sted)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Since to obtaine thee, nothing me will sted</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since to obtaine thee, nothing me will sted</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Since to obtaine thee, nothing me will sted,
I haue a Med'cine that shall cure my Loue,
The powder of her Heart dry'd, when she is dead,
That Gold nor Honour ne'r had pow'r to moue;
Mix'd with her Teares, that ne'r her true-Loue crost,
Nor at Fifteene ne'r long'd to be a Bride,
Boyl'd with her Sighes, in giuing vp the Ghost,
That for her late deceased Husband dy'd;
Into the same then let a Woman breathe,
That being chid did neuer word replie,
With one thrice-marry'd's Pray'rs, that did bequeath
A Legacie to stale Virginitie.
    If this Receit haue not the pow'r to winne me,
    Little Ile say, but thinke the Deuill's in me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020316">
<head>
   <title>16</title>
   <subtitle>An Allusion to the Ph&oelig;nix</subtitle>
   <toctitle>16 (Mongst all the Creatures in this spacious Round)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Mongst all the Creatures in this spacious Round</indextitle>
   <firstline>Mongst all the Creatures in this spacious Round</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Mongst all the Creatures in this spacious Round,
Of the Birds kind, the Ph&oelig;nix is alone,
Which best by you, of liuing Things, is knowne;
None like to that, none like to you is found:
Your Beautie is the hot and splend'rous Sunne,
The precious Spices be your chaste Desire,
Which being kindled by that heau'nly fire,
Your Life so like the Ph&oelig;nix's begun;
your selfe thus burned in that sacred flame,
With so rare sweetnesse all the Heau'ns perfuming,
Againe increasing, as you are consuming,
Onely by dying, borne the very same:
    And wing'd by Fame, you to the Starres ascend,
    So you of Time shall liue beyond the End.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020317">
<head>
   <title>17</title>
   <subtitle>To Time</subtitle>
   <toctitle>17 (Stay, speedy Time, behold, before thou passe)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Stay, speedy Time, behold, before thou passe</indextitle>
   <firstline>Stay, speedy Time, behold, before thou passe</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Stay, speedy Time, behold, before thou passe,
From Age to Age, what thou hast sought to see,
One, in whom all the Excellencies be,
In whom, Heau'n lookes it selfe as in a Glasse:
Time, looke thou too, in this Tralucent Glasse,
And thy Youth past, in this pure Mirrour see,
As the World's Beautie in his Infancie,
What it was then, and thou before it was;
Passe on, and to Posteritie tell this,
Yet see thou tell, but truly, what hath beene:
Say to our Nephewes, that thou once hast seene,
In perfect humane shape, all heau'nly Blisse;
    And bid them mourne, nay more, despaire with thee,
    That she is gone, her like againe to see.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020318">
<head>
   <title>18</title>
   <subtitle>To the Celestiall Numbers</subtitle>
   <toctitle>18 (To this our World, to Learning, and to Heauen)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To this our World, to Learning, and to Heauen</indextitle>
   <firstline>To this our World, to Learning, and to Heauen</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
To this our World, to Learning, and to Heauen,
Three Nines there are, to euery one a Nine,
One number of the Earth, the other both Diuine,
One Woman now, makes three odde Numbers euen;
Nine orders first of Angels be in Heauen,
Nine Muses doe with Learning still frequent,
These with the Gods are euer resident;
Nine worthie Women to the World were giuen:
My worthy, One to these Nine Worthies addeth,
And my faire Muse, one Muse vnto the Nine,
And my good Angell (in my Soule diuine)
With one more Order, these nine Orders gladdeth:
    My Muse, my Worthy, and my Angel then,
    Makes euery One of these three Nines a Ten.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020319">
<head>
   <title>19</title>
   <subtitle>To Humour</subtitle>
   <toctitle>19 (You cannot loue, my prettie Heart, and why?)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>You cannot loue, my prettie Heart, and why?</indextitle>
   <firstline>You cannot loue, my prettie Heart, and why?</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
You cannot loue, my prettie Heart, and why?
There was a time, You told Me that you would,
But now againe You will the same denie,
If it might please You, would to God You could;
What, will You hate? nay that You will not neither,
Nor Loue, nor Hate, how then? what will You doe?
What will You keepe a meane then betwixt either?
Or will You loue Me, and yet hate Me too?
Yet serues not This: what next, what other Shift?
You Will, and Will not, what a coyle is here?
I see Your craft, now I perceiue Your drift,
And all this while, I was mistaken there:
    Your Loue and Hate is this, I now doe proue You,
    You loue in Hate, by Hate to make Me loue You.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020320">
<head>
   <title>20</title>
   <toctitle>20 (An euill spirit your beautie haunts Me still)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>An euill spirit your beautie haunts Me still</indextitle>
   <firstline>An euill spirit your beautie haunts Me still</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
An euill spirit your beautie haunts Me still,
Where with (alas) I haue beene long possest,
Which ceaseth not to tempt Me to each Ill,
Nor giues Me once, but one poore minutes rest:
In Me it speakes, whether I Sleepe or Wake,
And when by Meanes, to driue it out I try,
With greater Torments, then it Me doth take,
And tortures Me in most extremity;
Before my Face, it layes downe my Despaires,
And hastes Me on vnto a sudden Death;
Now tempting Me, to drowne my Selfe in teares,
And then in sighing, to giue vp my breath;
    Thus am I still prouok'd, to euery Euill,
    By this good wicked Spirit, sweet Angell Deuill.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020321">
<head>
   <title>21</title>
   <toctitle>21 (A witlesse Gallant, a young Wench that woo'd)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A witlesse Gallant, a young Wench that woo'd</indextitle>
   <firstline>A witlesse Gallant, a young Wench that woo'd</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
A witlesse Gallant, a young Wench that woo'd,
(Yet his dull Spirit her not one iot could moue)
Intreated me, as e'r I wish'd his good,
To write him but one Sonnet to his Loue:
When I, as fast as e'r my Penne could trot,
Powr'd out what first from quicke Inuention came;
Nor neuer stood one word thereof to blot,
Much like his Wit, that was to vse the same:
But with my Verses he his Mistres wonne,
Who doted on the Dolt beyond all measure.
But see, for you to Heau'n for Phraze I runne,
And ransacke all <sc>Apollo's</sc> golden Treasure;
    Yet by my Froth, this Foole his Loue obtaines,
    And I lose you, for all my Wit and Paines.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020322">
<head>
   <title>22</title>
   <subtitle>To Folly</subtitle>
   <toctitle>22 (With Fooles and Children good Discretion beares)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>With Fooles and Children good Discretion beares</indextitle>
   <firstline>With Fooles and Children good Discretion beares</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
With Fooles and Children good Discretion beares;
Then honest People, beare with Loue and Me,
Nor older yet, nor wiser made by yeeres,
Amongst the rest of Fooles and Children be:
Loue still a Baby, playes with Gawdes and Toyes,
And like a Wanton, sports with eu'ry Fether;
And Ideots still are running after Boyes,
Then Fooles and Children fitt'st to goe together:
He still as young as when he first was borne,
No wiser I, then when as young as he.
You that behold vs, laugh vs not to scorne,
Giue Nature thankes, you are not such as we:
    Yet Fooles and Children sometimes tell in play,
    Some wise in show, more Fooles indeed then they.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020323">
<head>
   <title>23</title>
   <toctitle>23 (Loue banish'd Heau'n, in Earth was held in scorne)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Loue banish'd Heau'n, in Earth was held in scorne</indextitle>
   <firstline>Loue banish'd Heau'n, in Earth was held in scorne</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Loue banish'd Heau'n, in Earth was held in scorne,
Wand'ring abroad in Need and Beggerie;
And wanting Friends, though of a Goddesse borne,
Yet crau'd the Almes of such as passed by:
I, like a Man deuout, and charitable,
Clothed the Naked, lodg'd this wand'ring Ghest,
With Sighes and Teares still furnishing his Table,
With what might make the Miserable blest.
But this vngratefull, for my good desert,
Intic'd my Thoughts, against me to conspire,
Who gaue consent to steale away my Heart,
And set my Brest, his Lodging, on a fire.
    Well, well, my Friends, when Beggers grow thus bold,
    No maruell then though Charitie grow cold.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020324">
<head>
   <title>24</title>
   <toctitle>24 (I heare some say, this Man is not in loue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>I heare some say, this Man is not in loue</indextitle>
   <firstline>I heare some say, this Man is not in loue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
I heare some say, this Man is not in loue:
Who? can he loue? a likely thing, they say;
Reade but his Verse, and it will eas'ly proue.
O, iudge not rashly (gentle Sir) I pray,
Because I loosely trifle in this sort,
As one that faine his Sorrowes would beguile:
You now suppose me all this time in sport,
And please your selfe with this Conceit the while;
Yee shallow Censures, sometime see yee not,
In greatest Perils some Men pleasant be,
Where Fame by Death is onely to be got,
They resolute? so stands the case with me;
    Where other Men in depth of Passion crie,
    I laugh at Fortune, as in iest to die.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020325">
<head>
   <title>25</title>
   <toctitle>25 (O, why should Nature niggardly restraine!)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>O, why should Nature niggardly restraine!</indextitle>
   <firstline>O, why should Nature niggardly restraine!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O, why should Nature niggardly restraine!
That Foraine Nations relish not our Tongue,
Else should my Lines glide on the Waues of <i>Rhene</i>,
And crowne the <i>Piren's</i> with my liuing Song:
But bounded thus, to <i>Scotland</i> get you forth,
Thence take you Wing vnto the <i>Orcades</i>,
There let my Verse get glory in the North,
Making my Sighes to thaw the Frozen Seas;
And let the <i>Bards</i> within that <i>Irish</i> Ile,
To whom my Muse with fierie Wings shall passe,
Call backe the stiffe-neck'd Rebels from Exile,
And mollifie the slaught'ring <i>Galliglasse</i>;
    And when my flowing Numbers they rehearse,
    Let Wolues and Beares be charmed with my Verse.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020326">
<head>
   <title>26</title>
   <subtitle>To Despaire</subtitle>
   <toctitle>26 (I euer loue, where neuer Hope appeares)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>I euer loue, where neuer Hope appeares</indextitle>
   <firstline>I euer loue, where neuer Hope appeares</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
I euer loue, where neuer Hope appeares,
Yet Hope drawes on my neuer-hoping Care,
And my Liues Hope would die, but for Despaire.
My neuer-certaine Ioy breeds euer-certaine Feares,
Vncertaine Dread giues Wings vnto my Hope;
Yet my Hopes Wings are laden so with Feare,
As they cannot ascend to my Hope's Sphere;
Though Feare giues them more then a Heau'nly Scope,
Yet this large Roome is bounded with Despaire,
So my Loue is still fett'red with vaine Hope,
And Liberty depriues him of his Scope,
And thus am I imprison'd in the Aire:
    Then, sweet Despaire, awhile hold vp thy head,
    Or all my Hope for Sorrow will be dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020327">
<head>
   <title>27</title>
   <toctitle>27 (Is not Loue here, as 'tis in other Clymes)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Is not Loue here, as 'tis in other Clymes</indextitle>
   <firstline>Is not Loue here, as 'tis in other Clymes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Is not Loue here, as 'tis in other Clymes,
And diff'reth it, as doe the seu'rall Nations?
Or hath it lost the Vertue, with the Times,
Or in this Iland alt'reth with the Fashions?
Or haue our Passions lesser pow'r then theirs,
Who had lesse Art them liuely to expresse?
Is Nature growne lesse pow'rfull in their Heires,
Or in our Fathers did she more transgresse?
I am sure my Sighes come from a Heart as true,
As any Mans, that Memory can boast,
And my Respects and Seruices to you
Equall with his, that loues his Mistres most:
    Or Nature must be partiall in my Cause,
    Or onely you doe violate her Lawes.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020328">
<head>
   <title>28</title>
   <toctitle>28 (To such as say, Thy Loue I ouer-prize)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To such as say, Thy Loue I ouer-prize</indextitle>
   <firstline>To such as say, Thy Loue I ouer-prize</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
To such as say, Thy Loue I ouer-prize,
And doe not sticke to terme my Prayses folly;
Against these Folkes, that thinke themselues so wise,
I thus oppose my Reasons forces wholly;
Though I giue more then well affords my state,
In which expense, the most suppose me vaine,
Which yeelds them nothing, at the easiest rate,
Yet at this price returnes me treble gaine.
They value not, vnskilfull how to vse,
And I giue much, because I gaine thereby:
I that thus take, or they that thus refuse,
Whether are these deceiued then, or I?
    In eu'ry thing I hold this Maxim still,
    The Circumstance doth make it good, or ill.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020329">
<head>
   <title>29</title>
   <subtitle>To the Senses</subtitle>
   <toctitle>29 (When conqu'ring Loue did first my Heart assayle)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When conqu'ring Loue did first my Heart assayle</indextitle>
   <firstline>When conqu'ring Loue did first my Heart assayle</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When conqu'ring Loue did first my Heart assayle,
Vnto mine aid I summon'd eu'ry Sense,
Doubting, if that proud Tyrant should preuayle,
My Heart should suffer for mine Eyes Offence;
But he with Beautie first corrupted Sight,
My Hearing brib'd with her Tongues Harmonie,
My Taste by her sweet Lips drawne with Delight,
My Smelling wonne with her Breath's Spicerie:
But when my Touching came to play his part,
(The King of Senses, greater then the rest)
He yeelds Loue vp the Keyes vnto my Heart,
And tells the other, how they should be blest.
    And thus by those of whom I hop'd for ayd,
    To cruell Loue my Soule was first betray'd.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020330">
<head>
   <title>30</title>
   <subtitle>To the Vestals</subtitle>
   <toctitle>30 (Those Priests which first the Vestall Fire begun)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Those Priests which first the Vestall Fire begun</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those Priests which first the Vestall Fire begun</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Those Priests which first the Vestall Fire begun,
Which might be borrow'd from no Earthly flame,
Deuis'd a Vessell to receiue the Sunne,
Being stedfastly opposed to the same:
Where, with sweet Wood, layd curiously by Art,
On which the Sunne might by reflection beat,
Receiuing strength from eu'ry secret part,
The Fuell kindled with Celestiall Heat.
Thy blessed Eyes, the Sunne which lights this Fire,
Thy holy Thoughts, they be the Vestall flame,
The precious Odors be my chaste Desires,
My Brest's the Vessell, which includes the same:
    Thou art my <sc>Vesta</sc>, thou my Goddesse art,
    Thy hallow'd Temple onely is my Heart.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020331">
<head>
   <title>31</title>
   <subtitle>To the Criticke</subtitle>
   <toctitle>31 (Me thinkes I see some crooked Mimicke ieere)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Me thinkes I see some crooked Mimicke ieere</indextitle>
   <firstline>Me thinkes I see some crooked Mimicke ieere</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Me thinkes I see some crooked Mimicke ieere,
And taxe my Muse with this fantasticke Grace,
Turning my Papers, askes, What haue we heere?
Making withall some filthy Antike Face.
I feare no censure, nor what thou canst say,
Nor shall my Spirit one iot of vigour lose.
Think'st thou, my Wit shall keepe the pack-Horse Way,
That eu'ry Dudgen low Inuention goes?
Since Sonnets thus in Bundles are imprest,
And eu'ry Drudge doth dull our satiate Eare;
Think'st thou my Loue shall in those Ragges be drest,
That eu'ry Dowdy, eu'ry Trull doth weare?
    Vp, to my Pitch, no common Iudgement flyes,
    I scorne all Earthly Dung-bred Scarabies.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020332">
<head>
   <title>32</title>
   <subtitle>To the Riuer <i>Ankor</i></subtitle>
   <toctitle>32 (Our Flouds-Queen Thames, for Ships &amp; Swans is crowned)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Our Flouds-Queen Thames, for Ships &amp; Swans is crowned</indextitle>
   <firstline>Our Flouds-Queen Thames, for Ships &amp; Swans is crowned</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Our Flouds-Queen <i>Thames</i>, for Ships &amp; Swans is crowned,
And stately <i>Seuerne</i> for her Shoare is praysed,
The Crystall <i>Trent</i>, for Foords and Fish renowned,
And <i>Auons</i> Fame, to <i>Albions</i> Cliffes is raysed,
<i>Carlegion Chester</i> vaunts her holy <i>Dee</i>,
<i>Yorke</i> many Wonders of her <i>Owse</i> can tell,
The <i>Peake</i> her <i>Doue</i>, whose Bankes so fertile be,
And <i>Kent</i> will say, her <i>Medway</i> doth excell,
<i>Cotswold</i> commends her <i>Isis</i> to the <i>Tame</i>,
Our Northerne Borders boast of <i>Tweeds</i> faire Floud,
Our Westerne Parts extoll their <i>Wilis</i> Fame,
And the old <i>Lea</i> brags of the <i>Danish</i> Bloud;
    <i>Ardens</i> sweet <i>Ankor</i>, let thy glory bee,
    That faire <i>Idea</i> onely liues by thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020333">
<head>
   <title>33</title>
   <subtitle>To Imagination</subtitle>
   <toctitle>33 (Whilst yet mine Eyes doe surfet with Delight)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Whilst yet mine Eyes doe surfet with Delight</indextitle>
   <firstline>Whilst yet mine Eyes doe surfet with Delight</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Whilst yet mine Eyes doe surfet with Delight,
My wofull Heart, imprison'd in my Brest,
Wisheth to be transformed to my Sight,
That it, like those, by looking might be blest:
But whilst mine Eyes thus greedily doe gaze,
Finding their Obiects ouer-soone depart,
These now the others Happinesse doe prayse,
Wishing themselues, that they had beene my Heart;
That Eyes were Heart, or that the Heart were Eyes,
As couetous the others vse to haue:
But finding Nature their request denyes,
This to each other mutually they craue;
    That since the one cannot the other bee,
    That Eyes could thinke or that my Heart could see.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020334">
<head>
   <title>34</title>
   <subtitle>To Admiration</subtitle>
   <toctitle>34 (Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire</indextitle>
   <firstline>Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire,
Rauish'd a World beyond the farthest Thought,
And knowing more then euer hath beene taught,
That I am onely staru'd in my desire;
Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire,
Ayming at things exceeding all perfection,
To Wisedome's selfe to minister direction,
That I am onely staru'd in my desire;
Maruell not, Loue, though I thy pow'r admire,
Though my Conceit I further seeme to bend,
Than possibly Inuention can extend,
And yet am onely staru'd in my desire:
    If thou wilt wonder, here's the wonder, Loue,
    That this to me doth yet no wonder proue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020335">
<head>
   <title>35</title>
   <subtitle>To Miracle</subtitle>
   <toctitle>35 (Some misbeleeuing, and prophane in Loue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Some misbeleeuing, and prophane in Loue</indextitle>
   <firstline>Some misbeleeuing, and prophane in Loue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Some misbeleeuing, and prophane in Loue,
When I doe speake of Miracles by thee,
May say, that thou art flattered by mee,
Who onely write, my skill in Verse to proue;
See Miracles, ye vnbeleeuing, see,
A dumbe-borne Muse made to expresse the Mind,
A cripple Hand to write, yet lame by Kind,
One by thy Name, the other touching thee;
Blind were mine Eyes, till they were seene of thine,
And mine Eares deafe, by thy Fame healed bee,
My Vices cur'd, by Vertues sprung from thee,
My Hopes reuiu'd, which long in Graue had lyne:
    All vncleane Thoughts, foule Spirits cast out in mee,
    Onely by Vertue that proceeds from thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020336">
<head>
   <title>36</title>
   <subtitle><i>Cupid</i> coniured</subtitle>
   <toctitle>36 (Thou purblind Boy, since thou hast beene so slacke)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thou purblind Boy, since thou hast beene so slacke</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thou purblind Boy, since thou hast beene so slacke</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thou purblind Boy, since thou hast beene so slacke,
To wound her Heart, whose Eyes haue wounded me,
And suff'red her to glory in my Wracke,
Thus to my aid, I lastly coniure thee;
By Hellish <i>Styx</i> (by which the <sc>Thvnd'rer</sc> sweares)
By thy faire Mothers vnauoided Power,
By <sc>Hecat's</sc> Names, by <sc>Proserpine's</sc> sad Teares,
When she was rapt to the infernall Bower;
By thine owne loued <sc>Psyches</sc>, by the Fires
Spent on thine Altars, flaming vp to Heau'n;
By all true Louers Sighes, Vowes, and Desires,
By all the Wounds that euer thou hast giu'n;
    I coniure thee by all that I haue nam'd
    To make her loue, or <sc>Cvpid</sc> be thou damn'd.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020337">
<head>
   <title>37</title>
   <toctitle>37 (Deare, why should you command me to my Rest)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Deare, why should you command me to my Rest</indextitle>
   <firstline>Deare, why should you command me to my Rest</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Deare, why should you command me to my Rest,
When now the Night doth summon all to sleepe?
Me thinkes this Time becommeth Louers best;
Night was ordayn'd, together Friends to keepe:
How happy are all other liuing Things,
Which though the Day dis-ioyne by seu'rall flight,
The quiet Eu'ning yet together brings,
And each returnes vnto his Loue at Night?
O, Thou that art so courteous else to all!
Why should'st thou, Night, abuse me onely thus,
That eu'ry Creature to his kind do'st call,
And yet 'tis thou do'st onely seuer vs?
    Well could I wish, it would be euer Day,
    If when Night comes, you bid me goe away.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020338">
<head>
   <title>38</title>
   <toctitle>38 (Sitting alone, Loue bids me goe and write)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sitting alone, Loue bids me goe and write</indextitle>
   <firstline>Sitting alone, Loue bids me goe and write</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Sitting alone, Loue bids me goe and write;
Reason plucks back, commanding me to stay,
Boasting, that she doth still direct the way,
Or else Loue were vnable to indite:
Loue growing angry, vexed at the Spleene,
And scorning Reason's maymed Argument,
Straight taxeth Reason, wanting to inuent,
Where she with Loue conuersing hath not beene;
Reason reproched with this coy Disdaine,
Despiteth Loue, and laugheth at her Folly;
And Loue contemning Reasons reason wholly,
Thought it in weight too light by many a Graine:
    Reason put back, doth out of sight remoue,
    And Loue alone picks reason out of loue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020339">
<head>
   <title>39</title>
   <toctitle>39 (Some, when in Ryme, they of their Loues doe tell)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Some, when in Ryme, they of their Loues doe tell</indextitle>
   <firstline>Some, when in Ryme, they of their Loues doe tell</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Some, when in Ryme, they of their Loues doe tell,
With Flames and Lightnings their Exordiums paint,
Some call on Heauen, some inuocate on Hell,
And Fates and Furies, with their woes acquaint,
<i>Elizium</i> is too high a seate for Me,
I will not come in <i>Stix</i> or <i>Phlegeton</i>,
The thrice-three Muses but too wanton be,
Like they that Lust, I care not, I will none.
Spightfull <sc>Erinnis</sc> frights Me with her Lookes,
My man-hood dares not with foule <sc>Ate</sc> mell,
I quake to looke on <sc>Hecat's</sc> charming Bookes,
I still feare Bug-beares in <sc>Apollo's</sc> Cell.
    I passe not for <sc>Minerva</sc>, nor <sc>Astrea</sc>,
    Onely I call on my diuine <sc>Idea</sc>.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020340">
<head>
   <title>40</title>
   <toctitle>40 (My Heart the Anuile, where my Thoughts doe beate)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My Heart the Anuile, where my Thoughts doe beate</indextitle>
   <firstline>My Heart the Anuile, where my Thoughts doe beate</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
My Heart the Anuile, where my Thoughts doe beate,
My Words the Hammers, fashioning my desire,
My Brest the Forge, including all the heate,
Loue is the Fewell, which maintaines the fire;
My Sighes the Bellowes, which the Flame encreaseth,
Filling mine Eares with Noise, and Nightly groning,
Toyling with Paine, my Labour neuer ceaseth,
In grieuous Passions, my Woes still bemoning:
My Eyes with Teares against the fire striuing,
Whose scorching gleed, my heart to Cinders turneth;
But with these Drops, the Flame againe reuiuing,
Still more and more it to my torment burneth:
    With <sc>Sisiphvs</sc> thus doe I role the stone,
    And turne the Wheele with damned <sc>Ixion</sc>.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020341">
<head>
   <title>41</title>
   <subtitle>Loues Lunacie</subtitle>
   <toctitle>41 (Why doe I speake of Ioy, or write of Loue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Why doe I speake of Ioy, or write of Loue</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why doe I speake of Ioy, or write of Loue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Why doe I speake of Ioy, or write of Loue,
When my Heart is the very Den of Horror,
And in my Soule the paines of Hell I proue,
With all his Torments and Infernall terror?
What should I say? what yet remaines to doe?
My Braine is drie with weeping all too long,
My Sighes be spent in vtt'ring of my Woe,
And I want words, wherewith to tell my Wrong:
But still distracted in Loues Lunacie,
And Bedlam-like, thus rauing in my Griefe,
Now raile vpon her Haire, then on her Eye;
Now call her Goddesse, then I call her Thiefe;
    Now I deny Her, then I doe confesse Her,
    Now doe I curse Her, then againe I blesse Her.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020342">
<head>
   <title>42</title>
   <toctitle>42 (Some Men there be, which like my Method well)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Some Men there be, which like my Method well</indextitle>
   <firstline>Some Men there be, which like my Method well</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Some Men there be, which like my Method well,
And much commend the strangenesse of my Vaine:
Some say, I haue a passing pleasing Straine,
Some say, That im my Humor I excell;
Some, who not kindly rellish my Conceit,
They say (as Poets doe) I vse to faine,
And in bare words paint out my Passions paine;
Thus sundry Men their sundry Minds repeat:
I passe not, I, how Men affected bee,
Nor who commends, or discommends my Verse;
It pleaseth me, if I my Woes rehearse,
And in my Lines, if she my loue may see:
    Onely my comfort still consists in this,
    Writing her prayse, I cannot write amisse.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020343">
<head>
   <title>43</title>
   <toctitle>43 (Why should your faire Eyes with such sou'raigne grace)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Why should your faire Eyes with such sou'raigne grace</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why should your faire Eyes with such sou'raigne grace</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Why should your faire Eyes with such sou'raigne grace
Disperse their Rayes on eu'ry vulgar Spirit,
Whilst I in darkenesse, in the selfe-same place,
Get not one glance, to recompense my Merit?
So doth the Plow-man gaze the wand'ring Starre,
And onely rest contented with the Light,
That neuer learn'd what Constellations are,
Beyond the bent of his vnknowing Sight.
O, why should Beautie (Custome to obey)
To their grosse Sense apply her selfe so ill!
Would God I were as ignorant as they,
When I am made vnhappy by my skill;
    Onely compell'd on this poore good to boast,
    Heau'ns are not kind to them, that know them most.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020344">
<head>
   <title>44</title>
   <toctitle>44 (Whilst thus my Pen striues to eternize thee)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Whilst thus my Pen striues to eternize thee</indextitle>
   <firstline>Whilst thus my Pen striues to eternize thee</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Whilst thus my Pen striues to eternize thee,
Age rules my Lines with Wrinkles in my Face,
Where, in the Map of all my Miserie,
Is model'd out the World of my Disgrace;
Whilst in despite of tyrannizing Times,
<sc>Medea</sc>-like, I make thee young againe,
Proudly thou scorn'st my World-out-wearing Rimes,
And murther'st Vertue with thy coy disdaine:
And though in youth, my Youth vntimely perish,
To keepe Thee from Obliuion and the Graue,
Ensuing Ages yet my Rimes shall cherish,
When I intomb'd, my better part shall saue;
    And though this Earthly Body fade and die,
    My Name shall mount vpon Eternitie.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020345">
<head>
   <title>45</title>
   <toctitle>45 (Muses which sadly sit about my Chayre)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Muses which sadly sit about my Chayre</indextitle>
   <firstline>Muses which sadly sit about my Chayre</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Muses which sadly sit about my Chayre,
Drown'd in the Teares, extorted by my Lines,
With heauie Sighes whilst thus I breake the Ayre,
Painting my Passions in these sad Designes;
Since she disdaines to blesse my happie Verse,
The strong-built Trophies to her liuing Fame,
Euer henceforth my Bosome be your Hearse,
Wherein the World shall now intombe her Name;
Inclose my Musike, you poore senselesse Walls,
Sith she is deafe, and will not heare my Mones,
Soften your selues with eu'ry Teare that falls,
Whilst I like <sc>Orphevs</sc> sing to Trees and Stones;
    Which with my plaint seeme yet with pittie moued,
    Kinder then she whom I so long haue Loued.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020346">
<head>
   <title>46</title>
   <toctitle>46 (Plaine-path'd Experience, th'vnlearneds guide)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Plaine-path'd Experience, th'vnlearneds guide</indextitle>
   <firstline>Plaine-path'd Experience, th'vnlearneds guide</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Plaine-path'd Experience, th'vnlearneds guide,
Her simple Followers euidently shewes
Sometimes what Schoole-men scarcely can decide,
Nor yet wise Reason absolutely knowes:
In making tryall of a Murther wrought,
If the vile actors of the heynous deed
Neere the dead Body happily be brought,
Oft 't'ath been prou'd, the breathlesse Coarse will bleed.
Shes comming neere, that my poore Heart hath slaine,
Long since departed (to the World no more)
Th'ancient Wounds no longer can containe,
But fall to bleeding, as they did before:
    But what of this? Should she to death be led,
    It furthers Iustice, but helpes not the dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020347">
<head>
   <title>47</title>
   <toctitle>47 (In pride of Wit, when high desire of Fame)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In pride of Wit, when high desire of Fame</indextitle>
   <firstline>In pride of Wit, when high desire of Fame</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
In pride of Wit, when high desire of Fame,
Gaue Life and Courage to my lab'ring Pen,
And first the sound and vertue of my Name
Wonne grace and credit in the Eares of Men;
With those the thronged Theaters that presse,
I in the Circuit for the Lawrell stroue:
Where, the full Prayse I freely must confesse,
In heat of Bloud, a modest Mind might moue.
With Showts and Claps at eu'ry little pawse,
When the proud Round on eu'ry side hath rung,
Sadly I sit, vnmou'd with the Applause,
As though to me it nothing did belong:
    No publike Glorie vainely I pursue,
    All that I seeke, is to eternize you.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020348">
<head>
   <title>48</title>
   <toctitle>48 (Cupid, I hate thee, which I'de haue thee know)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Cupid, I hate thee, which I'de haue thee know</indextitle>
   <firstline>Cupid, I hate thee, which I'de haue thee know</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<sc>Cvpid</sc>, I hate thee, which I'de haue thee know,
A naked Starueling euer may'st thou be,
Poore Rogue, goe pawne thy <i>Fascia</i> and thy Bow,
For some few Ragges wherewith to couer thee;
Or if thou'lt not, thy Archerie forbeare,
To some base Rustick doe thy selfe preferre,
And when Corne's sowne, or growne into the Eare,
Practise thy Quiuer, and turne Crow-keeper;
Or being Blind (as fittest for the Trade)
Goe hyre thy selfe some bungling Harpers Boy;
They that are blind, are Minstrels often made,
So may'st thou liue, to thy faire Mothers Ioy:
    That whilst with <sc>Mars</sc> she holdeth her old Way,
    Thou, her blind Sonne, may'st sit by them, and play.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020349">
<head>
   <title>49</title>
   <toctitle>49 (Thou Leaden Braine, which censur'st what I write)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thou Leaden Braine, which censur'st what I write</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thou Leaden Braine, which censur'st what I write</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thou Leaden Braine, which censur'st what I write,
And say'st, my Lines be dull, and doe not moue;
I maruell not, thou feel'st not my Delight,
Which neuer felt'st my fierie touch of Loue:
But thou, whose Pen hath like a Packe-Horse seru'd,
Whose Stomack vnto Gall hath turn'd thy Food,
Whose Senses, like poore Pris'ners, hunger-staru'd,
Whose Griefe hath parch'd thy Body, dry'd thy Blood;
Thou which hast scorned Life, and hated Death,
And in a moment Mad, Sober, Glad, and Sorrie;
Thou which hast bann'd thy Thoughts, and curst thy Birth,
With thousand Plagues, more then in Purgatorie:
    Thou, thus whose Spirit Loue in his fire refines,
    Come thou and reade, admire, applaud my Lines.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020350">
<head>
   <title>50</title>
   <toctitle>50 (As in some Countries, farre remote from hence)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As in some Countries, farre remote from hence</indextitle>
   <firstline>As in some Countries, farre remote from hence</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As in some Countries, farre remote from hence,
The wretched Creature, destined to die,
Hauing the Iudgement due to his Offence,
By Surgeons beg'd, their Art on him to trie,
Which on the Liuing worke without remorse,
First make incision on each mast'ring Veine,
Then stanch the bleeding, then trans-pierce the Coarse,
And with their Balmes recure the Wounds againe;
Then Poyson, and with Physike him restore:
Not that they feare the hope-lesse Man to kill,
But their Experience to increase the more:
Eu'n so my Mistres workes vpon my Ill;
    By curing me, and killing me each How'r,
    Onely to shew her Beauties Sou'raigne Pow'r.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020351">
<head>
   <title>51</title>
   <toctitle>51 (Calling to minde since first my Loue begun)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Calling to minde since first my Loue begun</indextitle>
   <firstline>Calling to minde since first my Loue begun</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Calling to minde since first my Loue begun,
Th' incertaine Times oft varying in their Course,
How Things still vnexpectedly haue runne,
As't please the Fates, by their resistlesse force:
Lastly, mine Eyes amazedly haue seene
<sc>Essex</sc> great fall, <sc>Tyrone</sc> his Peace to gaine,
The quiet end of that Long-liuing Queene,
This Kings faire Entrance, and our Peace with <i>Spaine</i>,
We and the <i>Dutch</i> at length our Selues to seuer;
Thus the World doth, and euermore shall Reele:
Yet to my Goddesse am I constant euer;
How e're blind Fortune turne her giddie Wheele:
    Though Heauen and Earth, proue both to me vntrue,
    Yet am I still inuiolate to You.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020352">
<head>
   <title>52</title>
   <toctitle>52 (What? do'st thou meane to Cheate me of my Heart)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>What? do'st thou meane to Cheate me of my Heart</indextitle>
   <firstline>What? do'st thou meane to Cheate me of my Heart</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
What? do'st thou meane to Cheate me of my Hea[rt,]
To take all Mine, and giue me none againe?
Or haue thine Eyes such Magike, or that Art,
That what They get, They euer doe retaine,
Play not the Tyrant, but take some Remorse,
Rebate thy Spleene, if but for Pitties sake;
Or Cruell, if thou can'st not; let vs scorse,
And for one piece of Thine, my whole heart take.
But what of Pitty doe I speake to Thee,
Whose Brest is proofe against Complaint or Prayer?
Or can I thinke what my Reward shall be
From that proud Beauty, which was my betrayer?
    What talke I of a Heart, when thou hast none?
    Or if thou hast, it is a flinty one.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020353">
<head>
   <title>53</title>
   <subtitle>Another to the Riuer Ankor</subtitle>
   <toctitle>53 (Cleere Ankor, on whose Siluer-sanded shore)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Cleere Ankor, on whose Siluer-sanded shore</indextitle>
   <firstline>Cleere Ankor, on whose Siluer-sanded shore</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Cleere <i>Ankor</i>, on whose Siluer-sanded shore,
My Soule-shrin'd Saint, my faire <sc>Idea</sc> lies,
Oh blessed Brooke, whose milke-white Swans adore,
The Cristall streame refined by her Eyes,
Where sweet Myrrh-breathing <i>Zephire</i> in the Spring,
Gently distills his Nectar-dropping showres,
Where Nightingales in <i>Arden</i> sit and sing,
Amongst the daintie dew-impearled flowres;
Say thus faire Brooke, when thou shalt see thy Queene,
Loe, heere thy Shepheard spent his wandering yeeres;
And in these Shades, deare Nymph, he oft hath beene,
And heere to Thee he sacrific'd his Teares:
    Faire <i>Arden</i>, thou my <i>Tempe</i> art alone,
    And thou, sweet <i>Ankor</i>, art my <i>Helicon</i>.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020354">
<head>
   <title>54</title>
   <toctitle>54 (Yet reade at last the storie of my Woe)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Yet reade at last the storie of my Woe</indextitle>
   <firstline>Yet reade at last the storie of my Woe</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Yet reade at last the storie of my Woe,
The drerie abstracts of my endlesse Cares,
With my Life's Sorrow interlined so,
Smoak'd with my Sighes, and blotted with my Teares;
The sad Memorialls of my Miseries,
Pen'd in the griefe of mine afflicted Ghost,
My Liues complaint in dolefull Elegies,
With so pure Loue, as Time could neuer boast;
Receiue the Incense which I offer here,
By my strong Faith ascending to thy Fame,
My Zeale my Hope, my Vowes, my Prayse, my Pray'r,
My Soule's Oblations to thy sacred Name:
    Which Name my Muse to highest Heau'ns shall rayse,
    By chaste Desire, true Loue, and vertuous Prayse.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020355">
<head>
   <title>55</title>
   <toctitle>55 (My Faire, if thou wilt register my loue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My Faire, if thou wilt register my loue</indextitle>
   <firstline>My Faire, if thou wilt register my loue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
My Faire, if thou wilt register my loue,
A World of Volumes shall thereof arise:
Preserue my Teares, and thou thy Selfe shalt proue
A second Floud, downe rayning from mine Eyes:
Note by my Sighes, and thine Eyes shall behold
The Sun-beames smothered with immortall Smoke,
And if by Thee my Prayers may be enrol'd
They Heauen and Earth to pitty shall prouoke;
Looke Thou into my brest, and Thou shalt see
Chaste holy Vowes for my Soules sacrifice,
That Soule (sweet Maid) which so hath honor'd Thee,
Erecting Trophies to thy Sacred Eyes,
    Those Eyes to my Heart shining euer bright
    When Darknesse hath obscur'd each other Light.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020356">
<head>
   <title>56</title>
   <subtitle>An allusion to the Eaglets</subtitle>
   <toctitle>56 (When like an Eaglet I first found my Loue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When like an Eaglet I first found my Loue</indextitle>
   <firstline>When like an Eaglet I first found my Loue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When like an Eaglet I first found my Loue,
For that the vertue I thereof would know,
Vpon the Nest I set it forth, to proue
If it were of that Kingly kind, or no:
But it no sooner saw my Sunne appeare,
But on her Rayes with open Eyes it stood,
To shew, that I had hatch'd it for the Ayre,
And rightly came from that braue mounting Brood;
And when the Plumes were summ'd with sweet desire,
To proue the Pynions, it ascends the Skyes;
Doe what I could, it needsly would aspire
To my Soules Sunne, those two Celestiall Eyes:
    Thus from my Brest, where it was bred alone,
    It after thee, is like an Eaglet flowne.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020357">
<head>
   <title>57</title>
   <toctitle>57 (You best discern'd of my Minds inward Eyes)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>You best discern'd of my Minds inward Eyes</indextitle>
   <firstline>You best discern'd of my Minds inward Eyes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
You best discern'd of my Minds inward Eyes,
And yet your Graces outwardly Diuine,
Whose deare remembrance in my Bosome lyes,
Too rich a Relique for so poore a Shrine:
You, in whom Nature chose her selfe to view,
When she her owne perfection would admire,
Bestowing all her Excellence on you;
At whose pure Eyes, Loue lights his hallow'd Fire,
Eu'n as a Man that in some Trance hath seene
More then his wond'ring vtt'rance can vnfold,
That rapt in Spirit, in better Worlds hath beene,
So must your prayse distractedly be told;
    Most of all short, when I should shew you most,
    In your perfections so much am I lost.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020358">
<head>
   <title>58</title>
   <toctitle>58 (In former times, such as had store of Coyne)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In former times, such as had store of Coyne</indextitle>
   <firstline>In former times, such as had store of Coyne</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
In former times, such as had store of Coyne,
In Warres at home, or when for Conquests bound,
For feare that some their Treasure should purloyne,
Gaue it to keepe to Spirits within the Ground;
And to attend it, them as strongly ty'd
Till they return'd; Home when they neuer came,
Such as by Art to get the same haue try'd,
From the strong Spirit by no meanes force the same;
Neerer Men come, That further flyes away,
Striuing to hold it strongly in the Deepe:
Eu'n as this Spirit, so you alone doe play
With those rich Beauties Heau'n giues you to keepe:
    Pittie so left, to th'coldnesse of your Blood,
    Not to auaile you, nor doe others good.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020359">
<head>
   <title>59</title>
   <subtitle>To Prouerbe</subtitle>
   <toctitle>59 (As Loue and I, late harbour'd in one Inne)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As Loue and I, late harbour'd in one Inne</indextitle>
   <firstline>As Loue and I, late harbour'd in one Inne</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As Loue and I, late harbour'd in one Inne,
With Prouerbs thus each other intertaine:
<i>In Loue there is no lack, thus I begin,
Faire words make Fooles, replyeth he againe;
Who spares to speake, doth spare to speed (quoth I)
As well (sayth he) too forward, as too slow;
Fortune assists the boldest, I reply,
A hastie Man (quoth he) ne'r wanted Woe;
Labour is light, where Loue (quoth I) doth pay,
(Saith he) Light Burthen's heauy, if farre borne;
(Quoth I) The Maine lost, cast the By away;
You haue spunne a faire Thred, he replyes in scorne.</i>
    And hauing thus awhile each other thwarted,
    Fooles as we met, so Fooles againe we parted.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020360">
<head>
   <title>60</title>
   <toctitle>60 (Define my Weale, and tell the ioyes of Heauen)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Define my Weale, and tell the ioyes of Heauen</indextitle>
   <firstline>Define my Weale, and tell the ioyes of Heauen</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Define my Weale, and tell the ioyes of Heauen,
Expresse my Woes, and shew the paines of Hell,
Declare what Fate vnlucky Starres haue giuen,
And aske a World vpon my Life to dwell.
Make knowne the Faith, that Fortune could not moue,
Compare my Worth with others base Desert,
Let Vertue be the Touch-stone of my Loue,
So may the Heauens read wonders in my Heart;
Behold the Clouds which haue eclips'd my Sunne,
And view the Crosses which my course doe let,
Tell Me, if euer since the World begunne,
So Faire a rising, had so Foule a set:
    And see if Time (if he would striue to proue)
    Can shew a Second to so pure a Loue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020361">
<head>
   <title>61</title>
   <toctitle>61 (Since ther's no helpe, Come let vs kisse and part)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Since ther's no helpe, Come let vs kisse and part</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since ther's no helpe, Come let vs kisse and part</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="drayton2002020361-p1.jpg">Fascimile af sonet 61.</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Since ther's no helpe, Come let vs kisse and part,
Nay, I haue done: You get no more of Me,
And I am glad, yea glad withall my heart,
That thus so cleanly, I my Selfe can free,
Shake hands for euer, Cancell all our Vowes,
And when We meet at any time againe,
Be it not seene in either of our Browes,
That We one iot of former Loue reteyne;
Now at the last gaspe, of Loues latest Breath,
When his Pulse fayling, Passion speechlesse lies,
When Faith is kneeling by his bed of Death,
And Innocence is closing vp his Eyes,
    Now if thou would'st, when all haue giuen him ouer,
    From Death to Life, thou might'st him yet recouer.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020362">
<head>
   <title>62</title>
   <toctitle>62 (When first I Ended, then I first Began)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When first I Ended, then I first Began</indextitle>
   <firstline>When first I Ended, then I first Began</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When first I Ended, then I first Began,
Then more I Traueld, further from my Rest,
Where most I Lost, there most of all I Wan,
Pined with Hunger, rising from a Feast.
Me thinkes I Flie, yet want I legges to Goe,
Wise in Conceit, in Act a very sot,
Rauish'd with Ioy amid'st a hell of Woe,
What most I Seeme, that surest am I Not.
I build my Hopes a world aboue the Skie,
Yet with the Mole I creepe into the Earth,
In Plenty I am staru'd with Penurie,
And yet I Surfet in the greatest Dearth:
    I haue, I want, Despaire, and yet desire,
    Burn'd in a Sea of yce, and drown'd amidst a fire.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="drayton2002020363">
<head>
   <title>63</title>
   <toctitle>63 (Truce, gentle Loue, a Parly now I craue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Truce, gentle Loue, a Parly now I craue</indextitle>
   <firstline>Truce, gentle Loue, a Parly now I craue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Truce, gentle Loue, a Parly now I craue,
Me thinkes 'tis long since first these Warres begun,
Nor thou, nor I, the better yet can haue:
Bad is the Match, where neither partie wonne.
I offer free Conditions of faire Peace,
My Heart for Hostage that it shall remaine,
Discharge our Forces, here let Malice cease,
So for my Pledge thou giue me Pledge againe.
Or if no thing but Death will serue thy turne,
Still thirsting for subuersion of my state;
Doe what thou canst, raze, massacre, and burne;
Let the World see the vtmost of thy hate:
    I send defiance, since if ouerthrowne,
    Thou vanquishing, the Conquest is mine owne.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
