<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="gray" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="gray2001122601">
<head>
   <title>Ode on the Spring</title>
   <toctitle>Ode on the Spring</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Ode on the Spring</indextitle>
   <firstline>Lo! where the rosy-bosom'd Hours</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Lo! where the rosy-bosom'd Hours,
    Fair Venus' train appear,
Disclose the long-expecting flowers,
    And wake the purple year!
The Attic warbler pours her throat,
Responsive to the cuckoo's note,
    The untaught harmony of spring:
While whisp'ring pleasure as they fly,
Cool zephyrs thro' the clear blue sky
   Their gather'd fragrance fling.

Where'er the oak's thick branches stretch
    A broader, browner shade;
Where'er the rude and moss-grown beech
    O'er-canopies the glade,
Beside some water's rushy brink
With me the Muse shall sit, and think
    (At ease reclin'd in rustic state)
How vain the ardour of the crowd,
How low, how little are the proud,
    How indigent the great!

Still is the toiling hand of Care:
    The panting herds repose:
Yet hark, how thro' the peopled air
    The busy murmur glows!
The insect youth are on the wing,
Eager to taste the honied spring,
    And float amid the liquid noon:
Some lightly o'er the current skim,
Some show their gaily-gilded trim
    Quick-glancing to the sun.

To Contemplation's sober eye
    Such is the race of man:
And they that creep, and they that fly,
    Shall end where they began.
Alike the busy and the gay
But flutter thro' life's little day,
    In fortune's varying colours drest:
Brush'd by the hand of rough Mischance,
Or chill'd by age, their airy dance
    They leave, in dust to rest.

Methinks I hear in accents low
    The sportive kind reply:
Poor moralist! and what art thou?
    A solitary fly!
Thy joys no glitt'ring female meets,
No hive hast thou of hoarded sweets,
    No painted plumage to display:
On hasty wings thy youth is flown;
Thy sun is set, thy spring is gone—
    We frolic, while 'tis May.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="gray2019121101">
<head>
    <title>Ode to Adversity </title>
    <firstline>Daughter of Jove, relentless power</firstline>
    <!-- https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ode_to_Adversity -->
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>Daughter</sc> of Jove, relentless power,
    Thou tamer of the human breast,
  Whose iron scourge and torturing hour
    The bad affright, afflict the best!
  Bound in thy adamantine chain
  The proud are taught to taste of pain,
  And purple tyrants vainly groan
With pangs unfelt before, unpitied and alone.
 
  When first thy Sire to send on earth
    Virtue, his darling child, design’d,
  To thee he gave the heavenly birth
    And bade to form her infant mind.
  Stern, rugged Nurse! thy rigid lore
  With patience many a year she bore;
  What sorrow was, thou bad’st her know,
And from her own she learn’d to melt at others’ woe.
 
  Scared at thy frown terrific, fly
    Self-pleasing Folly’s idle brood,
  Wild Laughter, Noise, and thoughtless Joy,
    And leave us leisure to be good.
  Light they disperse, and with them go
  The summer Friend, the flattering Foe;
  By vain Prosperity received,
To her they vow their truth, and are again believed.
 
  Wisdom in sable garb array’d
    Immersed in rapturous thought profound,
  And Melancholy, silent maid,
    With leaden eye, that loves the ground,
  Still on thy solemn steps attend:
  Warm Charity, the general friend,
  With Justice, to herself severe,
And Pity dropping soft the sadly-pleasing tear.
 
  O! gently on thy suppliant’s head
    Dread Goddess, lay thy chastening hand!
  Not in thy Gorgon terrors clad,
    Nor circled with the vengeful band
  (As by the impious thou art seen)
  With thundering voice, and threatening mien,
  With screaming Horror’s funeral cry,
Despair, and fell Disease, and ghastly Poverty;—
 
  Thy form benign, O Goddess, wear,
    Thy milder influence impart,
  Thy philosophic train be there
    To soften, not to wound my heart.
  The generous spark extinct revive,
  Teach me to love and to forgive
  Exact my own defects to scan,
What others are to feel, and know myself a Man.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="gray2019122601">
<head>
    <title>Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard</title>
    <firstline>The curfew tolls the knell of parting day</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
The curfew tolls the knell of parting day,
    The lowing herd wind slowly o'er the lea,
The plowman homeward plods his weary way,
    And leaves the world to darkness and to me.

Now fades the glimm'ring landscape on the sight,
    And all the air a solemn stillness holds,
Save where the beetle wheels his droning flight,
    And drowsy tinklings lull the distant folds;

Save that from yonder ivy-mantled tow'r
    The moping owl does to the moon complain
Of such, as wand'ring near her secret bow'r,
    Molest her ancient solitary reign.

Beneath those rugged elms, that yew-tree's shade,
    Where heaves the turf in many a mould'ring heap,
Each in his narrow cell for ever laid,
    The rude forefathers of the hamlet sleep.

The breezy call of incense-breathing Morn,
    The swallow twitt'ring from the straw-built shed,
The cock's shrill clarion, or the echoing horn,
    No more shall rouse them from their lowly bed.

For them no more the blazing hearth shall burn,
    Or busy housewife ply her evening care:
No children run to lisp their sire's return,
    Or climb his knees the envied kiss to share.

Oft did the harvest to their sickle yield,
    Their furrow oft the stubborn glebe has broke;
How jocund did they drive their team afield!
    How bow'd the woods beneath their sturdy stroke!

Let not Ambition mock their useful toil,
    Their homely joys, and destiny obscure;
Nor Grandeur hear with a disdainful smile
    The short and simple annals of the poor.

The boast of heraldry, the pomp of pow'r,
    And all that beauty, all that wealth e'er gave,
Awaits alike th' inevitable hour.
    The paths of glory lead but to the grave.

Nor you, ye proud, impute to these the fault,
    If Mem'ry o'er their tomb no trophies raise,
Where thro' the long-drawn aisle and fretted vault
    The pealing anthem swells the note of praise.

Can storied urn or animated bust
    Back to its mansion call the fleeting breath?
Can Honour's voice provoke the silent dust,
    Or Flatt'ry soothe the dull cold ear of Death?

Perhaps in this neglected spot is laid
    Some heart once pregnant with celestial fire;
Hands, that the rod of empire might have sway'd,
    Or wak'd to ecstasy the living lyre.

But Knowledge to their eyes her ample page
    Rich with the spoils of time did ne'er unroll;
Chill Penury repress'd their noble rage,
    And froze the genial current of the soul.

Full many a gem of purest ray serene,
    The dark unfathom'd caves of ocean bear:
Full many a flow'r is born to blush unseen,
    And waste its sweetness on the desert air.

Some village-Hampden, that with dauntless breast
    The little tyrant of his fields withstood;
Some mute inglorious Milton here may rest,
    Some Cromwell guiltless of his country's blood.

Th' applause of list'ning senates to command,
    The threats of pain and ruin to despise,
To scatter plenty o'er a smiling land,
    And read their hist'ry in a nation's eyes,

Their lot forbade: nor circumscrib'd alone
    Their growing virtues, but their crimes confin'd;
Forbade to wade through slaughter to a throne,
    And shut the gates of mercy on mankind,

The struggling pangs of conscious truth to hide,
    To quench the blushes of ingenuous shame,
Or heap the shrine of Luxury and Pride
    With incense kindled at the Muse's flame.

Far from the madding crowd's ignoble strife,
    Their sober wishes never learn'd to stray;
Along the cool sequester'd vale of life
    They kept the noiseless tenor of their way.

Yet ev'n these bones from insult to protect,
    Some frail memorial still erected nigh,
With uncouth rhymes and shapeless sculpture deck'd,
    Implores the passing tribute of a sigh.

Their name, their years, spelt by th' unletter'd muse,
    The place of fame and elegy supply:
And many a holy text around she strews,
    That teach the rustic moralist to die.

For who to dumb Forgetfulness a prey,
    This pleasing anxious being e'er resign'd,
Left the warm precincts of the cheerful day,
    Nor cast one longing, ling'ring look behind?

On some fond breast the parting soul relies,
    Some pious drops the closing eye requires;
Ev'n from the tomb the voice of Nature cries,
    Ev'n in our ashes live their wonted fires.

For thee, who mindful of th' unhonour'd Dead
    Dost in these lines their artless tale relate;
If chance, by lonely contemplation led,
    Some kindred spirit shall inquire thy fate,

Haply some hoary-headed swain may say,
    “Oft have we seen him at the peep of dawn
Brushing with hasty steps the dews away
    To meet the sun upon the upland lawn.

“There at the foot of yonder nodding beech
    That wreathes its old fantastic roots so high,
His listless length at noontide would he stretch,
    And pore upon the brook that babbles by.

“Hard by yon wood, now smiling as in scorn,
    Mutt'ring his wayward fancies he would rove,
Now drooping, woeful wan, like one forlorn,
    Or craz'd with care, or cross'd in hopeless love.

“One morn I miss'd him on the custom'd hill,
    Along the heath and near his fav'rite tree;
Another came; nor yet beside the rill,
    Nor up the lawn, nor at the wood was he;

“The next with dirges due in sad array
    Slow thro' the church-way path we saw him borne.
Approach and read (for thou canst read) the lay,
    Grav'd on the stone beneath yon aged thorn.”

<nonum><sc>The Epitaph</sc></nonum>

<i>Here rests his head upon the lap of Earth</i>
    <i>A youth to Fortune and to Fame unknown.</i>
<i>Fair Science frown'd not on his humble birth,</i>
    <i>And Melancholy mark'd him for her own.</i>

<i>Large was his bounty, and his soul sincere,</i>
    <i>Heav'n did a recompense as largely send:</i>
<i>He gave to Mis'ry all he had, a tear,</i>
    <i>He gain'd from Heav'n ('twas all he wish'd) a friend.</i>

<i>No farther seek his merits to disclose,</i>
    <i>Or draw his frailties from their dread abode,</i>
<i>(There they alike in trembling hope repose)</i>
    <i>The bosom of his Father and his God.</i>
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
