<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="sigourney" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="sigourney2019090701">
<head>
   <title>Middle States: Niagara, the River Niagara</title>
   <firstline>Flow on forever, in thy glorious robe</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<sc>Flow</sc> on forever, in thy glorious robe	
Of terror and of beauty. Yea, flow on	
Unfathomed and resistless. God hath set	
His rainbow on thy forehead; and the cloud	
Mantled around thy feet. And he doth give	        
Thy voice of thunder power to speak of Him	
Eternally,—bidding the lip of man	
Keep silence,—and upon thy rocky altar pour	
Incense of awe-struck praise.
                    Ah! who can dare	
To lift the insect-trump of earthly hope,	        
Or love, or sorrow, mid the peal sublime	
Of thy tremendous hymn? Even Ocean shrinks	
Back from thy brotherhood, and all his waves	
Retire abashed. For he doth sometimes seem	
To sleep like a spent laborer, and recall	        
His wearied billows from their vexing play,	
And lull them to a cradle calm; but thou,	
With everlasting, undecaying tide,	
Dost rest not, night or day. The morning stars,	
When first they sang o’er young creation’s birth,	        
Heard thy deep anthem; and those wrecking fires,	
That wait the archangel’s signal to dissolve	
This solid earth, shall find Jehovah’s name	
Graven, as with a thousand diamond spears,	
On thine unending volume.
                    Every leaf,	        
That lifts itself within thy wide domain,	
Doth gather greenness from thy living spray,	
Yet tremble at the baptism. Lo!—yon birds	
Do boldly venture near, and bathe their wing	
Amid thy mist and foam. ’T is meet for them	        
To touch thy garment’s hem, and lightly stir	
The snowy leaflets of thy vapor-wreath,	
For they may sport unharmed amid the cloud,	
Or listen at the echoing gate of heaven,	
Without reproof. But as for us, it seems	        
Scarce lawful, with our broken tones, to speak	
Familiarly of thee. Methinks, to tint	
Thy glorious features with our pencil’s point,	
Or woo thee to the tablet of a song,	
Were profanation.
                Thou dost make the soul	        
A wondering witness of thy majesty,	
But as it presses with delirious joy	
To pierce thy vestibule, dost chain its step,	
And tame its rapture with the humbling view	
Of its own nothingness, bidding it stand	        
In the dread presence of the Invisible,	
As if to answer to its God through thee.    
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
