<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1833" author="tennyson" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Poems</title>
   <year>1833</year>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="tennyson2019091101">
<head>
    <title>The Lotos-eaters</title>
    <firstline>Courage! he said, and pointed toward the land</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
"Courage!" he said, and pointed toward the land, 
"This mounting wave will roll us shoreward soon." 
In the afternoon they came unto a land 
In which it seemed always afternoon. 
All round the coast the languid air did swoon, 
Breathing like one that hath a weary dream. 
Full-faced above the valley stood the moon; 
And like a downward smoke, the slender stream 
Along the cliff to fall and pause and fall did seem. 

A land of streams! some, like a downward smoke, 
Slow-dropping veils of thinnest lawn, did go; 
And some thro' wavering lights and shadows broke, 
Rolling a slumbrous sheet of foam below. 
They saw the gleaming river seaward flow 
From the inner land: far off, three mountain-tops, 
Three silent pinnacles of aged snow, 
Stood sunset-flush'd: and, dew'd with showery drops, 
Up-clomb the shadowy pine above the woven copse. 

The charmed sunset linger'd low adown 
In the red West: thro' mountain clefts the dale 
Was seen far inland, and the yellow down 
Border'd with palm, and many a winding vale 
And meadow, set with slender galingale; 
A land where all things always seem'd the same! 
And round about the keel with faces pale, 
Dark faces pale against that rosy flame, 
The mild-eyed melancholy Lotos-eaters came. 

Branches they bore of that enchanted stem, 
Laden with flower and fruit, whereof they gave 
To each, but whoso did receive of them, 
And taste, to him the gushing of the wave 
Far far away did seem to mourn and rave 
On alien shores; and if his fellow spake, 
His voice was thin, as voices from the grave; 
And deep-asleep he seem'd, yet all awake, 
And music in his ears his beating heart did make. 

They sat them down upon the yellow sand, 
Between the sun and moon upon the shore; 
And sweet it was to dream of Fatherland, 
Of child, and wife, and slave; but evermore 
Most weary seem'd the sea, weary the oar, 
Weary the wandering fields of barren foam. 
Then some one said, "We will return no more"; 
And all at once they sang, "Our island home 
Is far beyond the wave; we will no longer roam." 

<nonum><center>CHORIC SONG</center></nonum>

I 
There is sweet music here that softer falls 
Than petals from blown roses on the grass, 
Or night-dews on still waters between walls 
Of shadowy granite, in a gleaming pass; 
Music that gentlier on the spirit lies, 
Than tir'd eyelids upon tir'd eyes; 
Music that brings sweet sleep down from the blissful skies. 
Here are cool mosses deep, 
And thro' the moss the ivies creep, 
And in the stream the long-leaved flowers weep, 
And from the craggy ledge the poppy hangs in sleep." 

II 
Why are we weigh'd upon with heaviness, 
And utterly consumed with sharp distress, 
While all things else have rest from weariness? 
All things have rest: why should we toil alone, 
We only toil, who are the first of things, 
And make perpetual moan, 
Still from one sorrow to another thrown: 
Nor ever fold our wings, 
And cease from wanderings, 
Nor steep our brows in slumber's holy balm; 
Nor harken what the inner spirit sings, 
"There is no joy but calm!" 
Why should we only toil, the roof and crown of things? 

III 
Lo! in the middle of the wood, 
The folded leaf is woo'd from out the bud 
With winds upon the branch, and there 
Grows green and broad, and takes no care, 
Sun-steep'd at noon, and in the moon 
Nightly dew-fed; and turning yellow 
Falls, and floats adown the air. 
Lo! sweeten'd with the summer light, 
The full-juiced apple, waxing over-mellow, 
Drops in a silent autumn night. 
All its allotted length of days 
The flower ripens in its place, 
Ripens and fades, and falls, and hath no toil, 
Fast-rooted in the fruitful soil. 

IV 
Hateful is the dark-blue sky, 
Vaulted o'er the dark-blue sea. 
Death is the end of life; ah, why 
Should life all labour be? 
Let us alone. Time driveth onward fast, 
And in a little while our lips are dumb. 
Let us alone. What is it that will last? 
All things are taken from us, and become 
Portions and parcels of the dreadful past. 
Let us alone. What pleasure can we have 
To war with evil? Is there any peace 
In ever climbing up the climbing wave? 
All things have rest, and ripen toward the grave 
In silence; ripen, fall and cease: 
Give us long rest or death, dark death, or dreamful ease. 

V 
How sweet it were, hearing the downward stream, 
With half-shut eyes ever to seem 
Falling asleep in a half-dream! 
To dream and dream, like yonder amber light, 
Which will not leave the myrrh-bush on the height; 
To hear each other's whisper'd speech; 
Eating the Lotos day by day, 
To watch the crisping ripples on the beach, 
And tender curving lines of creamy spray; 
To lend our hearts and spirits wholly 
To the influence of mild-minded melancholy; 
To muse and brood and live again in memory, 
With those old faces of our infancy 
Heap'd over with a mound of grass, 
Two handfuls of white dust, shut in an urn of brass! 

VI 
Dear is the memory of our wedded lives, 
And dear the last embraces of our wives 
And their warm tears: but all hath suffer'd change: 
For surely now our household hearths are cold, 
Our sons inherit us: our looks are strange: 
And we should come like ghosts to trouble joy. 
Or else the island princes over-bold 
Have eat our substance, and the minstrel sings 
Before them of the ten years' war in Troy, 
And our great deeds, as half-forgotten things. 
Is there confusion in the little isle? 
Let what is broken so remain. 
The Gods are hard to reconcile: 
'Tis hard to settle order once again. 
There is confusion worse than death, 
Trouble on trouble, pain on pain, 
Long labour unto aged breath, 
Sore task to hearts worn out by many wars 
And eyes grown dim with gazing on the pilot-stars. 

VII 
But, propt on beds of amaranth and moly, 
How sweet (while warm airs lull us, blowing lowly) 
With half-dropt eyelid still, 
Beneath a heaven dark and holy, 
To watch the long bright river drawing slowly 
His waters from the purple hill— 
To hear the dewy echoes calling 
From cave to cave thro' the thick-twined vine— 
To watch the emerald-colour'd water falling 
Thro' many a wov'n acanthus-wreath divine! 
Only to hear and see the far-off sparkling brine, 
Only to hear were sweet, stretch'd out beneath the pine. 

VIII 
The Lotos blooms below the barren peak: 
The Lotos blows by every winding creek: 
All day the wind breathes low with mellower tone: 
Thro' every hollow cave and alley lone 
Round and round the spicy downs the yellow Lotos-dust is blown. 
We have had enough of action, and of motion we, 
Roll'd to starboard, roll'd to larboard, when the surge was seething free, 
Where the wallowing monster spouted his foam-fountains in the sea. 
Let us swear an oath, and keep it with an equal mind, 
In the hollow Lotos-land to live and lie reclined 
On the hills like Gods together, careless of mankind. 
For they lie beside their nectar, and the bolts are hurl'd 
Far below them in the valleys, and the clouds are lightly curl'd 
Round their golden houses, girdled with the gleaming world: 
Where they smile in secret, looking over wasted lands, 
Blight and famine, plague and earthquake, roaring deeps and fiery sands, 
Clanging fights, and flaming towns, and sinking ships, and praying hands. 
But they smile, they find a music centred in a doleful song 
Steaming up, a lamentation and an ancient tale of wrong, 
Like a tale of little meaning tho' the words are strong; 
Chanted from an ill-used race of men that cleave the soil, 
Sow the seed, and reap the harvest with enduring toil, 
Storing yearly little dues of wheat, and wine and oil; 
Till they perish and they suffer—some, 'tis whisper'd—down in hell 
Suffer endless anguish, others in Elysian valleys dwell, 
Resting weary limbs at last on beds of asphodel. 
Surely, surely, slumber is more sweet than toil, the shore 
Than labour in the deep mid-ocean, wind and wave and oar; 
O, rest ye, brother mariners, we will not wander more.     
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="tennyson2019100601">
<head>
    <title>Œnone, or the Choice of Paris</title>
    <indextitle>Oenone, or the Choice of Paris</indextitle>
    <firstline>There lies a vale in Ida, lovelier</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>There</sc> lies a vale in Ida, lovelier
Than all the valleys of Ionian hills.
The swimming vapor slopes athwart the glen,
Puts forth an arm, and creeps from pine to pine,
And loiters, slowly drawn. On either hand	        
The lawns and meadow ledges midway down
Hang rich in flowers, and far below them roar
The long brook falling through the cloven ravine
In cataract after cataract to the sea.
Behind the valley topmost Garfiarus	        
Stands up and takes the morning; but in front
The gorges, opening wide apart, reveal
Troas and Ilion’s columned citadel,
The crown of Troas.

                    Hither came at noon
Mournful Œnone, wandering forlorn	        
Of Paris, once her playmate on the hills.
Her cheek had lost the rose, and round her neck
Floated her hair or seemed to float in rest.
She, leaning on a fragment twined with vine,
Sang to the stillness, till the mountain-shade	        
Sloped downward to her seat from the upper cliff.
 
  “O mother Ida, many-fountained Ida,
Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
For now the noonday quiet holds the hill:
The grasshopper is silent in the grass:	        
The lizard, with his shadow on the stone,
Rests like a shadow, and the cicala sleeps.
The purple flowers droop; the golden bee
Is lily-cradled: I alone awake.
My eyes are full of tears, my heart of love,	        
My heart is breaking, and my eyes are dim,
And I am all aweary of my life.
 
“O mother Ida, many-fountained Ida,
Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
Hear me, O Earth, hear me, O Hills, O Caves,	        
That house the cold crowned snake! O mountain brooks,
I am the daughter of a River-God;
Hear me, for I will speak, and build up all
My sorrow with my song, as yonder wall
Rose slowly to a music slowly breathed,	        
A cloud that gathered shape: for it may be
That, while I speak of it, a little while
My heart may wander from its deeper woe.
 
  “O mother Ida, many-fountained Ida,
Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.	        
I waited underneath the dawning hills,
Aloft the mountain lawn was dewy-dark,
And dewy-dark aloft the mountain-pine:
Beautiful Paris, evil-hearted Paris,
Leading a jet-black goat white-horned, white-hoofed,	        
Came up from reedy Simois all alone.
 
  “O mother Ida, harken ere I die.
Far off the torrent called me from the cleft:
Far up the solitary morning smote
The streaks of virgin snow. With down-dropt eyes,	        
I sat alone: white-breasted like a star
Fronting the dawn he moved; a leopard skin
Drooped from his shoulder, but his sunny hair
Clustered about his temples like a god’s;
And his cheek brightened as the foam-bow brightens	        
When the wind blows the foam, and all my heart
Went forth to embrace him coming ere he came.
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
He smiled, and opening out his milk-white palm
Disclosed a fruit of pure Hesperian gold,	        
That smelt ambrosially, and while I looked
And listened, the full-flowing river of speech
Came down upon my heart.

                        “‘My own Œnone,
Beautiful-browed Œnone, my own soul,
Behold this fruit, whose gleaming rind engraven	        
“For the most fair,” would seem to award it thine.
As lovelier than whatever Oread haunt
The knolls of Ida, loveliest in all grace
Of movement, and the charm of married brows.’
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.	        
He prest the blossom of his lips to mine,
And added, ‘This was cast upon the board,
When all the full-faced presence of the God
Ranged in the halls of Peleus; whereupon
Rose feud, with question unto whom ’t were due.	        
But light-foot Iris brought it yester-eve,
Delivering that to me, by common voice
Elected umpire, Herè comes to-day
Pallas and Aphrodite, claiming each
This meed of fairest. Thou, within the cave	        
Behind yon whispering tuft of oldest pine,
Mayst well behold them unbeheld, unheard
Hear all, and see thy Paris judge of gods.’
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
It was the deep midnoon: one silvery cloud	        
Had lost his way between the piny side
Of this long glen. Then to the bower they came,
Naked they came to that smooth-swarded bower,
And at their feet the crocus brake like fire,
Violet, amaracus, and asphodel,	        
Lotos and lilies: and a wind arose,
And overhead the wandering ivy and vine,
This way and that, in many a wild festoon
Ran riot, garlanding the gnarled bough
With bunch and berry and flower through and through.	        
 
  “O mother Ida, harken ere I die.
On the tree-tops a crested peacock lit,
And o’er him flowed a golden cloud, and leaned
Upon him, slowly dropping fragrant dew.
Then first I heard the voice of her, to whom	        
Coming through Heaven, like a light that grow
Larger and clearer, with one mind the god
Rise up for reverence. She to Paris made
Proffer of royal power, ample rule
Unquestioned, overflowing revenue	        
Wherewith to embellish state, ‘from many a vale
And river-sundered champaign clothed with corn,
Or labored mines, undrainable of ore.
Honor,’ she said, ‘and homage, tax and toll,
From many an inland town and haven large,	        
Mast-thronged beneath her shadowing citadel
In glassy bays among her tallest towers.’
 
  “O mother Ida, harken ere I die.
Still she spake on, and still she spake of power,
‘Which in all action is the end of all:	        
Power fitted to the season; wisdom-bred
And throned of wisdom,—from all neighbor crown
Alliance and allegiance, till thy hand
Fail from the sceptre-staff. Such boon from me,
From me, heaven’s queen, Paris, to thee king-born,	        
A shepherd all thy life, but yet king-born,
Should come most welcome, seeing men, in power
Only, are likest gods, who have attained
Rest in a happy place and quiet seat
Above the thunder, with undying bliss,	        
In knowledge of their own supremacy.’
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
She ceased, and Paris held the costly fruit
Out at arm’s length, so much the thought of power
Flattered his spirit; but Pallas where she stood	        
Somewhat apart, her clear and bared limb
O’erthwarted with the brazen-headed spear
Upon her pearly shoulder leaning cold,
The while, above, her full and earnest eye
Over her snow-cold breast and angry cheek	        
Kept watch, waiting decision, made reply.
 
  “‘Self-reverence, self-knowledge, self-control,
These three alone lead life to sovereign power.
Yet not for power, (power of herself
Would come uncalled for,) but to live by law,	        
Acting the law we live by without fear;
And because right is right, to follow right
Were wisdom in the scorn of consequence.’
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
Again she said: ‘I woo thee not with gifts.	        
Sequel of guerdon could not alter me
To fairer. Judge thou me by what I am,
So shalt thou find me fairest.

                        Yet, indeed,
If gazing on divinity disrobed,
Thy mortal eyes are frail to judge of fair,	        
Unbiased by self-profit, O, rest thee sure
That I shall love thee well and cleave to thee,
So that my vigor, wedded to thy blood,
Shall strike within thy pulses, like a god’s,
To push thee forward through a life of shocks,	        
Dangers and deeds, until endurance grow
Sinewed with action, and the full-grown will,
Circled through all experiences, pure law,
Commeasure perfect freedom.’
                        “Here she ceased,
And Paris pondered, and I cried, ‘O Paris,	        
Give it to Pallas!’ but he heard me not,
Or hearing would not hear me, woe is me!
 
  “O mother Ida, many-fountained Ida,
Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
Idalian Aphrodite beautiful,	        
Fresh as the foam, new-bathed in Paphian wells,
With rosy slender fingers backward drew
From her warm brows and bosom her deep hair
Ambrosial, golden round her lucid throat
And shoulder: from the violets her light foot	        
Shone rosy-white, and o’er her rounded form
Between the shadows of the vine bunche
Floated the glowing sunlights, as she moved.
 
  “Dear mother Ida, harken ere I die.
She with a subtle smile in her mild eyes,	        
The herald of her triumph, drawing nigh,
Half whispered in his ear, ‘I promise thee
The fairest and most loving wife in Greece.’
She spoke and laughed: I shut my sight for fear:
But when I looked, Paris had raised his arm,	        
And I beheld great Herè’s angry eyes,
As she withdrew into the golden cloud,
And I was left alone within the bower;
And from that time to this I am alone,
And I shall be alone until I die.”    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="tennyson2019100602">
<head>
    <title>The Miller's Daughter</title>
    <firstline>It is the miller’s daughter</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
It is the miller’s daughter, 
And she is grown so dear, so dear, 
That I would be the jewel 
That trembles at her ear: 
For hid in ringlets day and night, 
I’d touch her neck so warm and white. 

And I would be the girdle 
About her dainty, dainty waist, 
And her heart would beat against me, 
In sorrow and in rest: 
And I should know if it beat right, 
I’d clasp it round so close and tight. 

And I would be the necklace, 
And all day long to fall and rise 
Upon her balmy bosom, 
With her laughter or her sighs: 
And I would lie so light, so light, 
I scarce should be unclasped at night.     
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
