<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1914" author="yeats" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Responsibilities</title>
   <year>1914</year>
   <notes>
      <note><i>Responsibilities</i> har to mottoer eller epigrafer, kilden til det første: "'In dreams begins responsibility.' / Old play" er ikke fundet, det andet parafraserer kongfuzianismens hovedværk <i>Samtalerne</i>, VII,5 (på engelsk <i>Analects</i>): "'How am I fallen from myself, for a long time now / I have not seen the Prince of Chang in my dreams' / Khoung-Fou-Tseu".</note>
      <note>Teksten følger W.B. Yeats, <i>The Poems</i>, red. Richard J. Finneran, Simon &amp; Schuster 1997, s. 99-127.</note>
      <note type="credits">Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="yeats20020216112">
<head>
   <title>Pardon, old fathers, if you still remain</title>
   <toctitle>Pardon, old fathers, if you still remain</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Pardon, old fathers, if you still remain</indextitle>
   <firstline>Pardon, old fathers, if you still remain</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Dateret "January 1914".</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>Pardon, old fathers, if you still remain
Somewhere in ear-shot for the story's end,
Old Dublin merchant ,,free of the ten and four''
Or trading out of Galway into Spain;
Old country scholar, Robert Emmet's friend,
A hundred-year-old memory to the poor;
Merchant and scholar who have left me blood
That has not passed through any huckster's loin,
Soldiers that gave, whatever die was cast:
A Butler or an Armstrong that withstood
Beside the brackish waters of the Boyne
James and his Irish when the Dutchman crossed;
Old merchant skipper that leaped overboard
After a ragged hat in Biscay Bay;
You most of all, silent and fierce old man,
Because the daily spectacle that stirred
My fancy, and set my boyish lips to say,
,,Only the wasteful virtues earn the sun'';
Pardon that for a barren passion's sake,
Although I have come close on forty-nine,
I have no child, I have nothing but a book,
Nothing but that to prove your blood and mine.</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216113">
<head>
   <title>The Grey Rock</title>
   <toctitle>The Grey Rock</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Grey Rock</indextitle>
   <firstline>Poets with whom I learned my trade</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>Poets with whom I learned my trade,
Companions of the Cheshire Cheese,
Here's an old story I've re-made,
Imagining 'twould better please
Your ears than stories now in fashion,
Though you may think I waste my breath
Pretending that there can be passion
That has more life in it than death,
And though at bottling of your wine
Old wholesome Goban had no say;
The moral's yours because it's mine.</i>

When cups went round at close of day -
Is not that how good stories run? -
The gods were sitting at the board
In their great house at Slievenamon.
They sang a drowsy song, or snored,
For all were full of wine and meat.
The smoky torches made a glare
On metal Goban'd hammered at,
On old deep silver rolling there
Or on some still unemptied cup
That he, when frenzy stirred his thews,
Had hammered out on mountain top
To hold the sacred stuff he brews
That only gods may buy of him.

Now from that juice that made them wise
All those had lifted up the dim
Imaginations of their eyes,
For one that was like woman made
Before their sleepy eyelids ran
And trembling with her passion said,
,,Come out and dig for a dead man,
Who's burrowing somewhere in the ground,
And mock him to his face and then
Hollo him on with horse and hound,
For he is the worst of all dead men.''

<i>We should be dazed and terror-struck,
If we but saw in dreams that room,
Those wine-drenched eyes, and curse our luck
That emptied all our days to come.
I knew a woman none could please,
Because she dreamed when but a child
Of men and women made like these;
And after, when her blood ran wild,
Had ravelled her own story out,
And said, ,,In two or in three years
I needs must marry some poor lout,''
And having said it, burst in tears.

Since, tavern comrades, you have died,
Maybe your images have stood,
Mere bone and muscle thrown aside,
Before that roomful or as good.
You had to face your ends when young -
'Twas wine or women, or some curse -
But never made a poorer song
That you might have a heavier purse,
Nor gave loud service to a cause
That you might have a troop of friends.
You kept the Muses' sterner laws,
And unrepenting faced your ends,
And therefore earned the right - and yet
Dowson and Johnson most I praise -
To troop with those the world's forgot,
And copy their proud steady gaze.</i>

,,The Danish troop was driven out
Between the dawn and dusk,'' she said;
,,Although the event was long in doubt,
Although the King of Ireland's dead
And half the kings, before sundown
All was accomplished.
                                  When this day
Murrough, the King of Ireland's son,
Foot after foot was giving way,
He and his best troops back to back
Had perished there, but the Danes ran,
Stricken with panic from the attack,
The shouting of an unseen man;
And being thankful Murrough found,
Led by a footsole dipped in blood
That had made prints upon the ground,
Where by old thorn-trees that man stood;
And though when he gazed here and there,
He had but gazed on thorn-trees, spoke,
"Who is the friend that seems but air
And yet could give so fine a stroke?"
Thereon a young man met his eye,
Who said, "Because she held me in
Her love, and would not have me die,
Rock-nurtured Aoife took a pin,
And pushing it into my shirt,
Promised that for a pin's sake
No man should see to do me hurt;
But there it's gone; I will not take
The fortune that had been my shame
Seeing, King's son, what wounds you have."
'Twas roundly spoke, but when night came
He had betrayed me to his grave,
For he and the King's son were dead.
I'd promised him two hundred years,
And when for all I'd done or said -
And these immortal eyes shed tears -
He claimed his country's need was most,
I'd saved his life, yet for the sake
Of a new friend he has turned a ghost.
What does he care if my heart break?
I call for spade and horse and hound
That we may harry him.'' Thereon
She cast herself upon the ground
And rent her clothes and made her moan:
,,Why are they faithless when their might
Is from the holy shades that rove
The grey rock and the windy light?
Why should the faithfullest heart most love
The bitter sweetness of false faces?
Why must the lasting love what passes,
Why are the gods by men betrayed?''

But thereon every god stood up
With a slow smile and without sound,
And stretching forth his arm and cup
To where she moaned upon the ground,
Suddenly drenched her to the skin;
And she with Goban's wine adrip,
No more remembering what had been,
Stared at the gods with laughing lip.

<i>I have kept my faith, though faith was tried,
To that rock-born, rock-wandering foot,
And the world's altered since you died,
And I am in no good repute
With the loud host before the sea,
That think sword-strokes were better meant
Than lover's music - let that be,
So that the wandering foot's content.</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216114">
<head>
   <title>To a Wealthy Man who promised a second Subscription to the Dublin Municipal Gallery if it were proved the People wanted Pictures</title>
   <toctitle>To a Wealthy Man who promised a second Subscription to the Dublin Municipal Gallery if it were proved the People wanted Pictures</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To a Wealthy Man who promised a second Subscription to the Dublin Municipal Gallery if it were proved the People wanted Pictures</indextitle>
   <firstline>You gave, but will not give again</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Dateret "December 1912".</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
You gave, but will not give again
Until enough of Paudeen's pence
By Biddy's halfpennies have lain
To be ,,some sort of evidence,''
Before you'll put your guineas down,
That things it were a pride to give
Are what the blind and ignorant town
Imagines best to make it thrive.
What cared Duke Ercole, that bid
His mummers to the market-place,
What th' onion-sellers thought or did
So that his Plautus set the pace
For the Italian comedies?
And Guidobaldo, when he made
That grammar school of courtesies
Where wit and beauty learned their trade
Upon Urbino's windy hill,
Had sent no runners to and fro
That he might learn the shepherds' will.
And when they drove out Cosimo,
Indifferent how the rancour ran,
He gave the hours they had set free
To Michelozzo's latest plan
For the San Marco Library,
Whence turbulent Italy should draw
Delight in Art whose end is peace,
In logic and in natural law
By sucking at the dugs of Greece.

Your open hand but shows our loss,
For he knew better how to live.
Let Paudeens play at pitch and toss,
Look up in the sun's eye and give
What the exultant heart calls good
That some new day may breed the best
Because you gave, not what they would,
But the right twigs for an eagle's nest!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216115">
<head>
   <title>September 1913</title>
   <toctitle>September 1913</toctitle>
   <indextitle>September 1913</indextitle>
   <firstline>What need you, being come to sense</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
What need you, being come to sense,
But fumble in a greasy till
And add the halfpence to the pence
And prayer to shivering prayer, until
You have dried the marrow from the bone;
For men were born to pray and save:
Romantic Ireland's dead and gone,
It's with O'Leary in the grave.

Yet they were of a different kind,
The names that stilled your childish play,
They have gone about the world like wind,
But little time had they to pray
For whom the hangman's rope was spun,
And what, God help us, could they save?
Romantic Ireland's dead and gone,
It's with O'Leary in the grave.

Was it for this the wild geese spread
The grey wing upon every tide;
For this that all that blood was shed,
For this Edward Fitzgerald died,
And Robert Emmet and Wolfe Tone,
All that delirium of the brave?
Romantic Ireland's dead and gone,
It's with O'Leary in the grave.

Yet could we turn the years again,
And call those exiles as they were
In all their loneliness and pain,
You'd cry, ,,Some woman's yellow hair
Has maddened every mother's son'':
They weighed so lightly what they gave.
But let them be, they're dead and gone,
They're with O'Leary in the grave.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216116">
<head>
   <title>To a Friend whose Work has come to Nothing</title>
   <toctitle>To a Friend whose Work has come to Nothing</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To a Friend whose Work has come to Nothing</indextitle>
   <firstline>Now all the truth is out</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Now all the truth is out,
Be secret and take defeat
From any brazen throat,
For how can you compete,
Being honour bred, with one
Who, were it proved he lies,
Were neither shamed in his own
Nor in his neighbours' eyes?
Bred to a harder thing
Than Triumph, turn away
And like a laughing string
Whereon mad fingers play
Amid a place of stone,
Be secret and exult,
Because of all things known
That is most difficult.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216117">
<head>
   <title>Paudeen</title>
   <toctitle>Paudeen</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Paudeen</indextitle>
   <firstline>Indignant at the fumbling wits, the obscure spite</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Indignant at the fumbling wits, the obscure spite
Of our old Paudeen in his shop, I stumbled blind
Among the stones and thorn-trees, under morning light;
Until a curlew cried and in the luminous wind
A curlew answered; and suddenly thereupon I thought
That on the lonely height where all are in God's eye,
There cannot be, confusion of our sound forgot,
A single soul that lacks a sweet crystalline cry.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216118">
<head>
   <title>To a Shade</title>
   <toctitle>To a Shade</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To a Shade</indextitle>
   <firstline>If you have revisited the town, thin Shade</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Dateret "September 29, 1913".</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If you have revisited the town, thin Shade,
Whether to look upon your monument
(I wonder if the builder has been paid)
Or happier-thoughted when the day is spent
To drink of that salt breath out of the sea
When grey gulls flit about instead of men,
And the gaunt houses put on majesty:
Let these content you and be gone again;
For they are at their old tricks yet.
                                                   A man
Of your own passionate serving kind who had brought
In his full hands what, had they only known,
Had given their children's children loftier thought,
Sweeter emotion, working in their veins
Like gentle blood, has been driven from the place,
And insult heaped upon him for his pains,
And for his open-handedness, disgrace;
Your enemy, an old foul mouth, had set
The pack upon him.
                              Go, unquiet wanderer,
And gather the Glasnevin coverlet
About your head till the dust stops your ear,
The time for you to taste of that salt breath
And listen at the corners has not come;
You had enough of sorrow before death -
Away, away! You are safer in the tomb.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216119">
<head>
   <title>When Helen lived</title>
   <toctitle>When Helen lived</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When Helen lived</indextitle>
   <firstline>We have cried in our despair</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
We have cried in our despair
That men desert,
For some trivial affair
Or noisy, insolent sport,
Beauty that we have won
From bitterest hours;
Yet we, had we walked within
Those topless towers
Where Helen waked with her boy,
Had given but as the rest
Of the men and women of Troy,
A word and a jest.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216120">
<head>
   <title>On Those that hated &bdquo;The Playboy of the Western World,&ldquo; 1907</title>
   <toctitle>On Those that hated &bdquo;The Playboy of the Western World,&ldquo; 1907</toctitle>
   <indextitle>On Those that hated &bdquo;The Playboy of the Western World,&ldquo; 1907</indextitle>
   <firstline>Once, when midnight smote the air</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Once, when midnight smote the air,
Eunuchs ran through Hell and met
On every crowded street to stare
Upon great Juan riding by:
Even like these to rail and sweat
Staring upon his sinewy thigh.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216121">
<head>
   <title>The Three Beggars</title>
   <toctitle>The Three Beggars</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Three Beggars</indextitle>
   <firstline>Though to my feathers in the wet</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>,,Though to my feathers in the wet,
I have stood here from break of day,
I have not found a thing to eat,
For only rubbish comes my way.
Am I to live on lebeen-lone?''
Muttered the old crane of Gort.
,,For all my pains on lebeen-lone?''</i>

King Guaire walked amid his court
The palace-yard and river-side
And there to three old beggars said,
,,You that have wandered far and wide
Can ravel out what's in my head.
Do men who least desire get most,
Or get the most who most desire?''
A beggar said, ,,They get the most
Whom man or devil cannot tire,
And what could make their muscles taut
Unless desire had made them so?''
But Guaire laughed with secret thought,
,,If that be true as it seems true,
One of you three is a rich man,
For he shall have a thousand pounds
Who is first asleep, if but he can
Sleep before the third noon sounds.''
And thereon, merry as a bird
With his old thoughts, King Guaire went
From river-side and palace-yard
And left them to their argument.
,,And if I win,'' one beggar said,
,,Though I am old I shall persuade
A pretty girl to share my bed'';
The second: ,,I shall learn a trade'';
The third: ,,I'll hurry to the course
Among the other gentlemen,
And lay it all upon a horse'';
The second: ,,I have thought again:
A farmer has more dignity.''
One to another sighed and cried:
The exorbitant dreams of beggary,
That idleness had borne to pride,
Sang through their teeth from noon to noon;
And when the sccond twilight brought
The frenzy of the beggars' moon
None closed his blood-shot eyes but sought
To keep his fellows from their sleep;
All shouted till their anger grew
And they were whirling in a heap.

They mauled and bit the whole night through;
They mauled and bit till the day shone;
They mauled and bit through all that day
And till another night had gone,
Or if they made a moment's stay
They sat upon their heels to rail,
And when old Guaire came and stood
Before the three to end this tale,
They were commingling lice and blood.
,,Time's up,'' he cried, and all the three
With blood-shot eyes upon him stared.
,,Time's up,'' he cried, and all the three
Fell down upon the dust and snored.

<i>,,Maybe I shall be lucky yet,
Now they are silent,'' said the crane.
,,Though to my feathers in the wet
I've stood as I were made of stone
And seen the rubbish run about,
It's certain there are trout somewhere
And maybe I shall take a trout
If but I do not seem to care.''</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216122">
<head>
   <title>The Three Hermits</title>
   <toctitle>The Three Hermits</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Three Hermits</indextitle>
   <firstline>Three old hermits took the air</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Three old hermits took the air
By a cold and desolate sea,
First was muttering a prayer,
Second rummaged for a flea;
On a windy stone, the third,
Giddy with his hundredth year,
Sang unnoticed like a bird:
,,Though the Door of Death is near
And what waits behind the door,
Three times in a single day
I, though upright on the shore,
Fall asleep when I should pray.''
So the first, but now the second:
,,We're but given what we have earned
When all thoughts and deeds are reckoned,
So it's plain to be discerned
That the shades of holy men
Who have failed, being weak of will,
Pass the Door of Birth again,
And are plagued by crowds, until
They've the passion to escape.''
Moaned the other, ,,They are thrown
Into some most fearful shape.''
But the second mocked his moan:
,,They are not changed to anything,
Having loved God once, but maybe
To a poet or a king
Or a witty lovely lady.''
While he'd rummaged rags and hair,
Caught and cracked his flea, the third,
Giddy with his hundredth year,
Sang unnoticed like a bird.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216123">
<head>
   <title>Beggar to Beggar cried</title>
   <toctitle>Beggar to Beggar cried</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Beggar to Beggar cried</indextitle>
   <firstline>Time to put off the world and go somewhere</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
,,Time to put off the world and go somewhere
And find my health again in the sea air,''
<i>Beggar to beggar cried, being frenzy-struck,</i>
,,And make my soul before my pate is bare.''

,,And get a comfortable wife and house
To rid me of the devil in my shoes,''
<i>Beggar to beggar cried, being frenzy-struck,</i>
,,And the worse devil that is between my thighs.''

,,And though I'd marry with a comely lass,
She need not be too comely - let it pass,''
<i>Beggar to beggar cried, being frenzy-struck,</i>
,,But there's a devil in a looking-glass.''

,,Nor should she be too rich, because the rich
Are driven by wealth as beggars by the itch,''
<i>Beggar to beggar cried, being frenzy-struck,</i>
,,And cannot have a humorous happy speech.''

,,And there I'll grow respected at my ease,
And hear amid the garden's nightly peace,''
<i>Beggar to beggar cried, being frenzy-struck,</i>
,,The wind-blown clamour of the barnacle-geese.''
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216124">
<head>
   <title>Running to Paradise</title>
   <toctitle>Running to Paradise</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Running to Paradise</indextitle>
   <firstline>As I came over Windy Gap</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
As I came over Windy Gap
They threw a halfpenny into my cap,
For I am running to Paradise;
And all that I need do is to wish
And somebody puts his hand in the dish
To throw me a bit of salted fish:
<i>And there the king</i> is <i>but as the beggar.</i>

My brother Mourteen is worn out
With skelping his big brawling lout,
And I am running to Paradise;
A poor life, do what he can,
And though he keep a dog and a gun,
A serving-maid and a serving-man:
<i>And there the king</i> is <i>but as the beggar.</i>

Poor men have grown to be rich men,
And rich men grown to be poor again,
And I am running to Paradise;
And many a darling wit's grown dull
That tossed a bare heel when at school,
Now it has filled a old sock full:
<i>And there the king</i> is <i>but as the beggar.</i>

The wind is old and still at play
While I must hurry upon my way.
For I am running to Paradise;
Yet never have I lit on a friend
To take my fancy like the wind
That nobody can buy or bind:
<i>And there the king</i> is <i>but as the beggar.</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216125">
<head>
   <title>The Hour before Dawn</title>
   <toctitle>The Hour before Dawn</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Hour before Dawn</indextitle>
   <firstline>A cursing rogue with a merry face</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
A cursing rogue with a merry face,
A bundle of rags upon a crutch,
Stumbled upon that windy place
Called Cruachan,<note>Pronounced as if spelt ,,Crockan'' in modern Gaelic.</note> and it was as much
As the one sturdy leg could do
To keep him upright while he cursed.
He had counted, where long years ago
Queen Maeve's nine Maines had been nursed,
A pair of lapwings, one old sheep,
And not a house to the plain's edge,
When close to his right hand a heap
Of grey stones and a rocky ledge
Reminded him that he could make,
If he but shifted a few stones,
A shelter till the daylight broke.
But while he fumbled with the stones
They toppled over; ,,Were it not
I have a lucky wooden shin
I had been hurt''; and toppling brought
Before his eyes, where stones had been,
A dark deep hollow in the rock.
He gave a gasp and thought to have fled,
Being certain it was no right rock
Because an ancient history said
Hell Mouth lay open near that place,
And yet stood still, because inside
A great lad with a beery face
Had tucked himself away beside
A ladle and a tub of beer,
And snored, no phantom by his look.
So with a laugh at his own fear
He crawled into that pleasant nook.

,,Night grows uneasy near the dawn
Till even I sleep light; but who
Has tired of his own company?
What one of Maeve's nine brawling sons
Sick of his grave has wakened me?
But let him keep his grave for once
That I may find the sleep I have lost.''

,,What care I if you sleep or wake?
But I'Il have no man call me ghost.''

,,Say what you please, but from daybreak
I'll sleep another century.''

,,And I will talk before I sleep
And drink before I talk.''
                                    And he
Had dipped the wooden ladle deep
Into the sleeper's tub of beer
Had not the sleeper started up.

,,Before you have dipped it in the beer
I dragged from Goban's mountain-top
I'll have assurance that you are able
To value beer; no half-legged fool
Shall dip his nose into my ladle
Merely for stumbling on this hole
In the bad hour before the dawn.''

,,Why beer is only beer.''
                                     ,,But say
"I'll sleep until the winter's gone,
Or maybe to Midsummer Day,"
And drink, and you will sleep that length.''

,,I'd like to sleep till winter's gone
Or till the sun is in his srrength.
This blast has chilled me to the bone.''

,,I had no better plan at first.
I thought to wait for that or this;
Maybe the weather was accursed
Or I had no woman there to kiss;
So slept for half a year or so;
But year by year I found that less
Gave me such pleasure I'd forgo
Even a half-hour's nothingness,
And when at one year's end I found
I had not waked a single minute,
I chose this burrow under ground.
I'll sleep away all time within it:
My sleep were now nine centuries
But for those mornings when I find
The lapwing at their foolish cries
And the sheep bleating at the wind
As when I also played the fool.''

The beggar in a rage began
Upon his hunkers in the hole,
,,It's plain that you are no right man
To mock at everything I love
As if it were not worth the doing.
I'd have a merry life enough
If a good Easter wind were blowing,
And though the winter wind is bad
I should not be too down in the mouth
For anything you did or said
If but this wind were in the south.''

,,You cry aloud, O would 'twere spring
Or that the wind would shift a point,
And do not know that you would bring,
If time were suppler in the joint,
Neither the spring nor the south wind
But the hour when you shall pass away
And leave no smoking wick behind,
For all life longs for the Last Day
And there's no man but cocks his ear
To know when Michael's trumpet cries
That flesh and bone may disappear,
And souls as if they were but sighs,
And there be nothing but God left;
But I alone being blessèd keep
Like some old rabbit to my cleft
And wait Him in a drunken sleep.''
He dipped his ladle in the tub
And drank and yawned and stretched him out,
The other shouted, ,,You would rob
My life of every pleasant thought
And every comfortable thing,
And so take that and that.'' Thereon
He gave him a great pummelling,
But might have pummelled at a stone
For all the sleeper knew or cared;
And after heaped up stone on stone,
And then, grown weary, prayed and cursed
And heaped up stone on stone again,
And prayed and cursed and cursed and fled
From Maeve and all that juggling plain,
Nor gave God thanks till overhead
The clouds were brightening with the dawn.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216126">
<head>
   <title>A Song from &bdquo;The Player Queen&ldquo;</title>
   <toctitle>A Song from &bdquo;The Player Queen&ldquo;</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Song from &bdquo;The Player Queen&ldquo;</indextitle>
   <firstline>My mother dandled me and sang</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My mother dandled me and sang,
,,How young it is, how young!''
And made a golden cradle
That on a willow swung.

,,He went away,'' my mother sang,
,,When I was brought to bed,''
And all the while her needle pulled
The gold and silver thread.

She pulled the thread and bit the thread
And made a golden gown,
And wept because she had dreamt that I
Was born to wear a crown.

,,When she was got,'' my mother sang,
,,I heard a sea-mew cry,
And saw a flake of the yellow foam
That dropped upon my thigh.''

How therefore could she help but braid
The gold into my hair,
And dream that I should carry
The golden top of care?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216127">
<head>
   <title>The Realists</title>
   <toctitle>The Realists</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Realists</indextitle>
   <firstline>Hope that you may understand!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Hope that you may understand!
What can books of men that wive
In a dragon-guarded land,
Paintings of the dolphin-drawn
Sea-nymphs in their pearly wagons
Do, but awake a hope to live
That had gone
With the dragons?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216128">
<head>
   <title>I. The Witch</title>
   <toctitle>I. The Witch</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Witch</indextitle>
   <firstline>Toil and grow rich</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Toil and grow rich,
What's that but to lie
With a foul witch
And after, drained dry,
To be brought
To the chamber where
Lies one long sought
With despair?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216129">
<head>
   <title>II. The Peacock</title>
   <toctitle>II. The Peacock</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Peacock</indextitle>
   <firstline>What's riches to him</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
What's riches to him
That has made a great peacock
With the pride of his eye?
The wind-beaten, stone-grey,
And desolate Three Rock
Would nourish his whim.
Live he or die
Amid wet rocks and heather,
His ghost will be gay
Adding feather to feather
For the pride of his eye.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216130">
<head>
   <title>The Mountain Tomb</title>
   <toctitle>The Mountain Tomb</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Mountain Tomb</indextitle>
   <firstline>Pour wine and dance if manhood still have pride</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Pour wine and dance if manhood still have pride,
Bring roses if the rose be yet in bloom;
The cataract smokes upon the mountain side,
Our Father Rosicross is in his tomb.

Pull down the blinds, bring fiddle and clarionet
That there be no foot silent in the room
Nor mouth from kissing, nor from wine unwet;
Our Father Rosicross is in his tomb.

In vain, in pain; the cataract still cries;
The everlasting taper lights the gloom;
All wisdom shut into his onyx eyes,
Our Father Rosicross sleeps in his tomb.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216131">
<head>
   <title>I. To a Child dancing in the Wind</title>
   <toctitle>I. To a Child dancing in the Wind</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To a Child dancing in the Wind</indextitle>
   <firstline>Dance there upon the shore</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Dance there upon the shore;
What need have you to care
For wind or water's roar?
And tumble out your hair
That the salt drops have wet;
Being young you have not known
The fool's triumph, nor yet
Love lost as soon as won,
Nor the best labourer dead
And all the sheaves to bind.
What need have you to dread
The monstrous crying of wind?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216132">
<head>
   <title>II. Two Years Later</title>
   <toctitle>II. Two Years Later</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Two Years Later</indextitle>
   <firstline>Has no one said those daring</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Has no one said those daring
Kind eyes should be more learn'd?
Or warned you how despairing
The moths are when they are burned?
I could have warned you; but you are young,
So we speak a different tongue.
O you will take whatever's offered
And dream that all the world's a friend,
Suffer as your mother suffered,
Be as broken in the end.
But I am old and you are young,
And I speak a barbarous tongue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216133">
<head>
   <title>A Memory of Youth</title>
   <toctitle>A Memory of Youth</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Memory of Youth</indextitle>
   <firstline>The moments passed as at a play</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The moments passed as at a play;
I had the wisdom love brings forth;
I had my share of mother-wit,
And yet for all that I could say,
And though I had her praise for it,
A cloud blown from the cut-throat north
Suddenly hid Love's moon away.

Believing every word I said,
I praised her body and her mind
Till pride had made her eyes grow bright,
And pleasure made her cheeks grow red,
And vanity her footfall light,
Yet we, for all that praise, could find
Nothing but darkness overhead.

We sat as silent as a stone,
We knew, though she'd not said a word,
That even the best of love must die,
And had been savagely undone
Were it not that Love upon the cry
Of a most ridiculous little bird
Tore from the clouds his marvellous moon.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216134">
<head>
   <title>Fallen Majesty</title>
   <toctitle>Fallen Majesty</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Fallen Majesty</indextitle>
   <firstline>Although crowds gathered once if she but showed her face</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Although crowds gathered once if she but showed her face,
And even old men's eyes grew dim, this hand alone,
Like some last courtier at a gypsy camping-place
Babbling of fallen majesty, records what's gone.

These lineaments, a heart that laughter has made sweet,
These, these remain, but I record what's gone. A crowd
Will gather, and not know it walks the very street
Whereon a thing once walked that seemed a burning cloud.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216135">
<head>
   <title>Friends</title>
   <toctitle>Friends</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Friends</indextitle>
   <firstline>Now must I these three praise</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Now must I these three praise -
Three women that have wrought
What joy is in my days:
One because no thought,
Nor those unpassing cares,
No, not in these fifteen
Many-times-troubled years,
Could ever come between
Mind and delighted mind;
And one because her hand
Had strength that could unbind
What none can understand,
What none can have and thrive,
Youth's dreamy load, till she
So changed me that I live
Labouring in ecstasy.
And what of her that took
All till my youth was gone
With scarce a pitying look?
How could I praise that one?
When day begins to break
I count my good and bad,
Being wakeful for her sake,
Remembering what she had,
What eagle look still shows,
While up from my heart's root
So great a sweetness flows
I shake from head to foot.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216136">
<head>
   <title>The Cold Heaven</title>
   <toctitle>The Cold Heaven</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Cold Heaven</indextitle>
   <firstline>Suddenly I saw the cold and rook-delighting heaven</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Suddenly I saw the cold and rook-delighting heaven
That seemed as though ice burned and was but the more ice,
And thereupon imagination and heart were driven
So wild that every casual thought of that and this
Vanished, and left but memories, that should be out of season
With the hot blood of youth, of love crossed long ago;
And I took all the blame out of all sense and reason,
Until I cried and trembled and rocked to and fro,
Riddled with light. Ah! when the ghost begins to quicken,
Confusion of the death-bed over, is it sent
Out naked on the roads, as the books say, and stricken
By the injustice of the skies for punishment?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216137">
<head>
   <title>That the Night come</title>
   <toctitle>That the Night come</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That the Night come</indextitle>
   <firstline>She lived in storm and strife</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
She lived in storm and strife,
Her soul had such desire
For what proud death may bring
That it could not endure
The common good of life,
But lived as 'twere a king
That packed his marriage day
With banneret and pennon,
Trumpet and kettledrum,
And the outrageous cannon,
To bundle time away
That the night come.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216138">
<head>
   <title>An Appointment</title>
   <toctitle>An Appointment</toctitle>
   <indextitle>An Appointment</indextitle>
   <firstline>Being out of heart with government</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Being out of heart with government
I took a broken root to fling
Where the proud, wayward squirrel went,
Taking delight that he could spring;
And he, with that low whinnying sound
That is like laughter, sprang again
And so to the other tree at a bound.
Nor the tame will, nor timid brain,
Nor heavy knitting of the brow
Bred that fierce tooth and cleanly limb
And threw him up to laugh on the bough;
No govermnent appointed him.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216139">
<head>
   <title>The Magi</title>
   <toctitle>The Magi</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Magi</indextitle>
   <firstline>Now as at all times I can see in the mind's eye</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Now as at all times I can see in the mind's eye,
In their stiff, painted clothes, the pale unsatisfied ones
Appear and disappear in the blue depth of the sky
With all their ancient faces like rain-beaten stones,
And all their helms of Silver hovering side by side,
And all their eyes still fixed, hoping to find once more,
Being by Calvary's turbulence unsatisfied,
The uncontrollable mystery on the bestial floor.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216140">
<head>
   <title>The Dolls</title>
   <toctitle>The Dolls</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Dolls</indextitle>
   <firstline>A doll in the doll-maker's house</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
A doll in the doll-maker's house
Looks at the cradle and bawls:
,,That is an insult to us.''
But the oldest of all the dolls,
Who had seen, being kept for show,
Generations of his sort,
Out-screams the whole shelf: ,,Although
There's not a man can report
Evil of this place,
The man and the woman bring
Hither, to our disgrace,
A noisy and filthy thing.''
Hearing him groan and stretch
The doll-maker's wife is aware
Her husband has heard the wretch,
And crouched by the arm of his chair,
She murmurs into his ear,
Head upon shoulder leant:
,,My dear, my dear, O dear,
It was an accident.''
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216141">
<head>
   <title>A Coat</title>
   <toctitle>A Coat</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Coat</indextitle>
   <firstline>I made my song a coat</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I made my song a coat
Covered with embroideries
Out of old mythologies
From heel to throat;
But he fools caught it,
Wore it in the world's eyes
As though they'd wrought it.
Song, let them take it,
For there's more enterprise
In walking naked.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="yeats20020216142">
<head>
   <title>While I, that reed-throated whisperer</title>
   <toctitle>While I, that reed-throated whisperer</toctitle>
   <indextitle>While I, that reed-throated whisperer</indextitle>
   <firstline>While I, that reed-throated whisperer</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>While I, that reed-throated whisperer
Who comes at need, although not now as once
A clear articulation in the air,
But inwardly, surmise companions
Beyond the fling of the dull ass's hoof,
- Ben Johnson's phrase - and find when June is come
At Kyle-na-no under that ancient roof
A sterner conscience and a friendlier home,
I can forgive even that wrong of wrongs,
Those undreamt accidents that have made me
- Seeing that Fame has perished this long while,
Being but a part of ancient ceremony -
Notorious, till all my priceless things
Are but a post the passing dogs defile.</i>
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
