<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="shakespeare" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="shakespeare2019010901">
<head>
   <title>Funeral Song</title>
   <firstline>Fear no more the heat o' the sun</firstline>
   <notes>
       <note>Fra <i>Cymbeline</i>, Akt IV, Scene 2.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Fear no more the heat o' the sun,
Nor the furious winters rages;
Thou thy worldly task hast done,
Home art gone and ta'en thy wages;
Golden lads and girls all must,
As chimney-sweepers, come to dust.

Fear no more the frown o' the great,
Thou art past the tyrants stoke;
Care no more to clothe and eat;
To thee the reed is as the oak;
The sceptre, learning, physic, must
All follow this, and come to dust.

Fear no more the lightning-flash,
Nor the all-dreaded thunder-stone;
Fear not slander, censure rash;
Thou hast finish'd joy and moan;
All lovers young, all lovers must
Consign to thee, and come to dust.

No exorciser harm thee!
Nor no witchcraft charm thee!
Ghost unlaid forbear thee!
Nothing ill come near thee!
Quiet consummation have;
And renowned be thy grave.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare2019011001">
<head>
   <title>Willow Song</title>
   <firstline>The poor soul sat sighing by a sycamore tree</firstline>
   <notes>
       <note>Desdemonas sang fra <i>Othello</i>, Akt IV, Scene 3.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The poor soul sat sighing by a sycamore tree,
(Sing all a green willow, willow willow willow,)
With his hand in his bosom and his head upon his knee.
(Oh willow, willow, willow 
Shall be my garland.)

He sighed in his singing and made a great moan...
I am dead to all pleasure, my true love she is gone...

The mute bird sat by him was made tame by his moans...
The true tears fell from him, would have melted the stones...

Come all you forsaken and mourn you with me...
Who speaks of a false love, mine’s falser than she...

Let love no more boast her in palace nor bower...
It buds, but it blasteth ere it be a flower...

Though fair and more false, I die with thy wound...
Thou hast lost the truest lover that goes upon the ground, sing...

Let nobody chide her, her scorns I approve...
She was born to be false, and I to die for her love...

Take this for my farewell and latest adieu...
Write this on my tomb, that in love I was true...    
</body>
</poem>


</workbody>
</kalliopework>
