<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="sonnets" author="shakespeare" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Shakespeare's Sonnets</title>
   <year>1609</year>
   <notes>
      <note>Endnu ufærdig.</note>
      <note>Kalliope bringer Shakespeares sonetter i to forskellige udgaver: under hver digttitel er først en version der nøje følger originalens stavemåde (moderniseret er kun typografiske særheder som langt s ( &#383; ) og ligaturer) og dernæst en moderniseret tekst følgende nutidig engelsk retskrivning; ude i højre side af skærmen kan nysgerrige også se en faksimilie af den pågældende sonet som den tager sig ud i originalen, <i>Shake-speares Sonnets</i> fra 1609. (forkortet <biblio>Q</biblio>)<br/>Den ofte ret vilkårlige tegnsætning er nænsomt og i stilhed blevet rettet lidt til, dog uden at nogen konsekvent modernisering er tilstræbt. Alle ændringer i tekstforlæggets ordlyd (emendationer) er omhyggeligt anført i de enkelte sonetters noter; f.eks. betyder "1 monuments] <biblio>Malone</biblio>; monument <biblio>Q</biblio>" ud for sonnet 55, at i den øverste teksts linie 1 hvor vi har "Monuments", der har <biblio>Q</biblio> "Monument", og at rettelsen skyldes Edmond Malone. - Alt disse noter kan med fordel ignoreres, de ødelægger læseoplevelsen og er kun medtaget for fuldstændighedens skyld.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnets-tit.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<prose id="shakespeare2001060201">
<head>
   <title>[Dedication]</title>
   <toctitle>[Dedication]</toctitle>
   <indextitle>[Dedication]</indextitle>
   <notes>
      <note>Denne sære dedikation, rimeligvis signeret af udgiveren Thomas Thorpe, forbliver et mysterium trods mange lærde og sindrige udredninger. Hvem er denne Mr. W.H.? Spidskandidaterne er William Herbert, third Earl of Pembroke og Henry Wriothesley, third Earl of Southampton.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnets-ded.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
<center>TO.THE.ONLIE.BEGETTER.OF.
THESE.INSVING.SONNETS.
Mr. W.H. ALL.HAPINESSE.
AND.THAT.ETERNITIE.
PROMISED.
BY.
OVR.EVER-LIVING.POET.
WISHETH.
THE.WELL-WISHING.
ADVENTVRER.IN.
SETTING.
FORTH.</center>
                                                        T.T.
</body>
</prose>

<poem id="shakespeare0001">
<head>
   <title>1</title>
   <toctitle>1 (From fairest creatures we desire increase)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>From fairest creatures we desire increase</indextitle>
   <firstline>From fairest creatures we desire increase</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>1] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; <sc>Shake-speares, / <i>sonnets.</i></sc> <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-001.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
From fairest creatures we desire increase,
That thereby beauties <i>Rose</i> might neuer die,
But as the riper should by time decease,
His tender heire might beare his memory:
But thou contracted to thine owne bright eyes,
Feed'st thy lights flame with selfe substantiall fewell,
Making a famine where aboundance lies,
Thy selfe thy foe, to thy sweet selfe too cruell:
Thou that art now the worlds fresh ornament,
And only herauld to the gaudy spring,
Within thine owne bud buriest thy content,
And, tender chorle, makst wast in niggarding:<note>And, ... chorle, <biblio>Capell</biblio>; And ... chorle <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
    Pitty the world, or else this glutton be,
    To eate the worlds due, by the graue and thee.

---

<resetnum/>From fairest creatures we desire increase,
That thereby beauty's rose might never die,
But as the riper should by time decease,
His tender heir might bear his memory:
But thou, contracted to thine own bright eyes,
Feed'st thy light's flame with self-substantial fuel,
Making a famine where abundance lies,
Thyself thy foe, to thy sweet self too cruel:
Thou that art now the world's fresh ornament,
And only herald to the gaudy spring,
Within thine own bud buriest thy content,
And, tender churl, mak'st waste in niggarding:
    Pity the world, or else this glutton be,
    To eat the world's due, by the grave and thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0002">
<head>
   <title>2</title>
   <toctitle>2 (When fortie Winters shall beseige thy brow)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When fortie Winters shall beseige thy brow</indextitle>
   <firstline>When fortie Winters shall beseige thy brow</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>4 totter'd] <biblio>Q</biblio>; tatter'd <biblio>Gildon</biblio> - tottered <i>er en afvigende form af</i> tattered, <i>ikke en fejl.</i></note>
      <note>Sonnet 2 kendes også fra manuskripter der af skriftkloge skønnes til ikke at være blot afledede af <biblio>Q</biblio> og derfor har selvstændig autoritet. Den her bragte tekst er taget fra manuskriptet kaldet "W" - almindeligt accepteret som den mest pålidelige version - undtagen titlen, som er lånt fra andre manuskripter.<br/>Spes Altera = det andet håb, <i>citerer Vergils Aeneide, XII, l. 168.</i><br/>2 that] y<sup>t</sup><br/>6 the] y<sup>e</sup></note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-002.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-002b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When fortie Winters shall beseige thy brow,
And digge deep trenches in thy beauties field,
Thy youthes proud liuery, so gaz'd on now,
Wil be a totter'd weed of smal worth held:
Then being askt, where all thy beautie lies,
Where all the treasure of thy lusty daies,
To say within thine owne deepe sunken eyes,
Were an all-eating shame, and thriftlesse praise.
How much more praise deseru'd thy beauties vse,
If thou couldst answere, this faire child of mine
Shall sum my count, and make my old excuse,
Proouing his beautie by succession thine.
    This were to be new made when thou art ould,
    And see thy blood warme when thou feel'st it could.

---

<resetnum/>When forty winters shall besiege thy brow,
And dig deep trenches in thy beauty's field,
Thy youth's proud livery, so gazed on now,
Will be a tottered weed of small worth held:
Then being asked, where all thy beauty lies,
Where all the treasure of thy lusty days,
To say within thine own deep-sunken eyes,
Were an all-eating shame, and thriftless praise.
How much more praise deserved thy beauty's use,
If thou couldst answer, ,,This fair child of mine
Shall sum my count, and make my old excuse,''
Proving his beauty by succession thine.
    This were to be new made when thou art old,
    And see thy blood warm when thou feel'st it cold.

---

<nonum><b>Spes Altera</b></nonum>

<resetnum/>When forty winters shall beseige thy brow
And trench deepe furrowes in that louely feild
Thy youthes faire liuery so accounted now
Shall bee like rotten weeds of no worth held
Then beeing askt where all thy bewty lyes
Where all the lustre of thy youthfull dayes
To say within these hollow suncken eyes
Were an all-eaten truth, &amp; worthlesse prayse
O how much better were thy bewtyes vse
If thou couldst say this pretty child of mine
Saues my account &amp; makes my old excuse
Making his bewty by succession thine
    This were to bee new borne when thou art old
    And see thy bloud warme when thou feelst it cold
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0003">
<head>
   <title>3</title>
   <toctitle>3 (Looke in thy glasse and tell the face thou vewest)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Looke in thy glasse and tell the face thou vewest</indextitle>
   <firstline>Looke in thy glasse and tell the face thou vewest</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-003.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Looke in thy glasse and tell the face thou vewest,
Now is the time that face should forme an other,
Whose fresh repaire if now thou not renewest,
Thou doo'st beguile the world, vnblesse some mother.
For where is she so faire whose vn-eard wombe
Disdaines the tillage of thy husbandry?
Or who is he so fond will be the tombe
Of his selfe loue to stop posterity?
Thou art thy mothers glasse, and she in thee
Calls backe the louely Aprill of her prime;
So thou through windowes of thine age shalt see,
Dispight of wrinkles, this thy goulden time.
    But if thou liue remembred not to be,
    Die single and thine Image dies with thee.

---

<resetnum/>Look in thy glass and tell the face thou viewest,
Now is the time that face should form another,
Whose fresh repair if now thou not renewest,
Thou dost beguile the world, unbless some mother.
For where is she so fair whose uneared womb
Disdains the tillage of thy husbandry?
Or who is he so fond will be the tomb
Of his self-love to stop posterity?
Thou art thy mother's glass, and she in thee
Calls back the lovely April of her prime;
So thou through windows of thine age shalt see,
Despite of wrinkles, this thy golden time.
    But if thou live remembered not to be,
    Die single and thine image dies with thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0004">
<head>
   <title>4</title>
   <toctitle>4 (Vnthrifty louelinesse, why dost thou spend)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Vnthrifty louelinesse, why dost thou spend</indextitle>
   <firstline>Vnthrifty louelinesse, why dost thou spend</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-004.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Vnthrifty louelinesse, why dost thou spend
Vpon thy selfe thy beauties legacy?
Natures bequest giues nothing but doth lend,
And being franck she lends to those are free:
Then, beautious nigard, why doost thou abuse
The bountious largesse giuen thee to giue?
Profitles vserer, why doost thou vse
So great a summe of summes yet can'st not liue?
For hauing traffike with thy selfe alone,
Thou of thy selfe thy sweet selfe dost deceaue,
Then how when nature calls thee to be gone,
What acceptable <i>Audit</i> can'st thou leaue?
    Thy vnus'd beauty must be tomb'd with thee,
    Which vsed liues th'executor to be.

---

<resetnum/>Unthrifty loveliness, why dost thou spend
Upon thyself thy beauty's legacy?
Nature's bequest gives nothing, but doth lend,
And being frank she lends to those are free:
Then, beauteous niggard, why dost thou abuse
The bounteous largess given thee to give?
Profitless usurer, why dost thou use
So great a sum of sums yet canst not live?
For having traffic with thyself alone,
Thou of thyself thy sweet self dost deceive,
Then how when nature calls thee to be gone,
What acceptable audit canst thou leave?
    Thy unused beauty must be tombed with thee,
    Which used lives th'executor to be.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0005">
<head>
   <title>5</title>
   <toctitle>5 (Those howers that with gentle worke did frame)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Those howers that with gentle worke did frame</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those howers that with gentle worke did frame</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-005.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-005b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Those howers that with gentle worke did frame
The louely gaze where euery eye doth dwell
Will play the tirants to the very same,
And that vnfaire which fairely doth excell:
For neuer resting time leads Summer on
To hidious winter and confounds him there,
Sap checkt with frost and lustie leau's quite gon,
Beauty ore-snow'd and barenes euery where;<note>barenes] <biblio>Q</biblio>; Barenness <biblio>Gildon</biblio></note>
Then were not summers distillation left
A liquid prisoner pent in walls of glasse,
Beauties effect with beauty were bereft,
Nor it nor noe remembrance what it was.
    But flowers distil'd, though they with winter meete,
    Leese but their show, their substance still liues sweet.

---

<resetnum/>Those hours that with gentle work did frame
The lovely gaze where every eye doth dwell
Will play the tyrants to the very same,
And that unfair which fairly doth excel:
For never-resting time leads summer on
To hideous winter and confounds him there,
Sap checked with frost and lusty leaves quite gone,
Beauty o'ersnowed and bareness everywhere;
Then were not summer's distillation left
A liquid prisoner pent in walls of glass,
Beauty's effect with beauty were bereft,
Nor it nor no remembrance what it was.
    But flowers distilled, though they with winter meet,
    Leese but their show, their substance still lives sweet.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0006">
<head>
   <title>6</title>
   <toctitle>6 (Then let not winters wragged hand deface)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Then let not winters wragged hand deface</indextitle>
   <firstline>Then let not winters wragged hand deface</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-006.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Then let not winters wragged hand deface<note>wragged] <biblio>Q</biblio>; rugged <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
In thee thy summer ere thou be distil'd:
Make sweet some viall; treasure thou some place
With beauties treasure ere it be selfe kil'd:<note>beauties] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; beautits <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
That vse is not forbidden vsery
Which happies those that pay the willing lone;
That's for thy selfe to breed an other thee,
Or ten times happier be it ten for one;
Ten times thy selfe were happier then thou art,
If ten of thine ten times refigur'd thee:
Then what could death doe if thou should'st depart,
Leauing thee liuing in posterity?
    Be not selfe-wild for thou art much too faire
    To be deaths conquest and make wormes thine heire.

---

<resetnum/>Then let not winter's ragged hand deface
In thee thy summer ere thou be distilled:
Make sweet some vial; treasure thou some place
With beauty's treasure ere it be self-killed:
That use is not forbidden usury
Which happies those that pay the willing loan;
That's for thyself to breed another thee,
Or ten times happier be it ten for one;
Ten times thyself were happier than thou art,
If ten of thine ten times refigured thee:
Then what could death do if thou shouldst depart,
Leaving thee living in posterity?
    Be not self-willed, for thou art much too fair
    To be death's conquest and make worms thine heir.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0007">
<head>
   <title>7</title>
   <toctitle>7 (Loe in the Orient when the gracious light)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Loe in the Orient when the gracious light</indextitle>
   <firstline>Loe in the Orient when the gracious light</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-007.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-007b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Loe in the Orient when the gracious light
Lifts vp his burning head, each vnder eye
Doth homage to his new appearing sight,
Seruing with lookes his sacred maiesty;
And hauing climb'd the steepe vp heauenly hill,
Resembling strong youth in his middle age,
Yet mortall lookes adore his beauty still,
Attending on his goulden pilgrimage:
But when from high-most pich with wery car,
Like feeble age he reeleth from the day,
The eyes (fore dutious) now conuerted are<note>fore dutious] <biblio>Q</biblio>; 'fore dutious <biblio>Malone</biblio></note>
From his low tract and looke an other way:
    So thou, thy selfe out-going in thy noon,
    Vnlok'd on diest vnlesse thou get a sonne.

---

<resetnum/>Lo in the orient when the gracious light
Lifts up his burning head, each under eye
Doth homage to his new-appearing sight,
Serving with looks his sacred majesty;
And having climbed the steep-up heavenly hill,
Resembling strong youth in his middle age,
Yet mortal looks adore his beauty still,
Attending on his golden pilgrimage:
But when from highmost pitch with weary car,
Like feeble age he reeleth from the day,
The eyes, fore duteous, now converted are
From his low tract and look another way:
    So thou, thyself out-going in thy noon,
    Unlooked on diest unless thou get a son.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0008">
<head>
   <title>8</title>
   <toctitle>8 (Musick to heare, why hear'st thou musick sadly?)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Musick to heare, why hear'st thou musick sadly?</indextitle>
   <firstline>Musick to heare, why hear'st thou musick sadly?</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Som appendix er tilføjet en version der sandsynligvis stammer fra et manuskript ældre end <biblio>Q</biblio> (og dets tekstforlæg).<br/>In laudem Music[a]e et opprobrium Contemptori[s] eiusdem <i>betyder omtrent</i> Til musikkens lovprisning og forhånelse af dens foragter.</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-008.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Musick to heare, why hear'st thou musick sadly?
Sweets with sweets warre not, ioy delights in ioy:
Why lou'st thou that which thou receaust not gladly,
Or else receau'st with pleasure thine annoy?
If the true concord of well tuned sounds,
By vnions married, do offend thine eare,
They do but sweetly chide thee, who confounds
In singlenesse the parts that thou should'st beare:
Marke how one string sweet husband to an other,
Strikes each in each by mutuall ordering;
Resembling sier, and child, and happy mother,
Who all in one, one pleasing note do sing:
    Whose speechlesse song being many, seeming one,
    Sings this to thee, thou single wilt proue none.

---

<resetnum/>Music to hear, why hear'st thou music sadly?
Sweets with sweets war not, joy delights in joy:
Why lov'st thou that which thou receiv'st not gladly,
Or else receiv'st with pleasure thine annoy?
If the true concord of well-tuned sounds,
By unions married, do offend thine ear,
They do but sweetly chide thee, who confounds
In singleness the parts that thou shouldst bear:
Mark how one string, sweet husband to another,
Strikes each in each by mutual ordering;
Resembling sire, and child, and happy mother,
Who all in one, one pleasing note do sing:
    Whose speechless song being many, seeming one,
    Sings this to thee, ,,Thou single wilt prove none.''

---

<nonum><b>In laudem Musice et opprobrium Contemptorii eiusdem</b></nonum>

<resetnum/>1

Musicke to heare, why hearest thou Musicke sadly
Sweete with sweetes warre not, Joy delightes in Joy
Why louest thou that which thou receauest not gladly
or else receauest with pleasure thine annoy

2

If the true Concord of well tuned Soundes
By Vnions maried doe offend thy eare
They doe but sweetlie chide thee, whoe confoundes
In singlenes a parte, which thou shouldst beare

3

Marke howe one stringe, sweet husband to another
Strikes each on each, by mutuall orderinge
Resemblinge Childe, &amp; Syer, and happy Mother
Which all in one, this single note dothe singe
    whose speechlesse songe beeinge many seeming one
    Singes this to thee, Thou single, shalt proue none
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0009">
<head>
   <title>9</title>
   <toctitle>9 (Is it for feare to wet a widdowes eye)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Is it for feare to wet a widdowes eye</indextitle>
   <firstline>Is it for feare to wet a widdowes eye</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-009.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Is it for feare to wet a widdowes eye<note>Is it] <biblio>Q</biblio>; It is <biblio>Benson</biblio></note>
That thou consum'st thy selfe in single life?
Ah, if thou issulesse shalt hap to die,
The world will waile thee like a makelesse wife;
The world wilbe thy widdow and still weepe
That thou no forme of thee hast left behind,
When euery priuat widdow well may keepe,
By childrens eyes, her husbands shape in minde:
Looke what an vnthrift in the world doth spend
Shifts but his place, for still the world inioyes it;
But beauties waste hath in the world an end,
And kept vnvsde the vser so destroyes it:
    No loue toward others in that bosome sits
    That on himselfe such murdrous shame commits.

---

<resetnum/>Is it for fear to wet a widow's eye
That thou consum'st thyself in single life?
Ah, if thou issueless shalt hap to die,
The world will wail thee like a makeless wife;
The world will be thy widow and still weep
That thou no form of thee hast left behind,
When every private widow well may keep,
By children's eyes, her husband's shape in mind:
Look what an unthrift in the world doth spend
Shifts but his place, for still the world enjoys it;
But beauty's waste hath in the world an end,
And kept unused the user so destroys it:
    No love toward others in that bosom sits
    That on himself such murd'rous shame commits.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0010">
<head>
   <title>10</title>
   <toctitle>10 (For shame deny that thou bear'st loue to any)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>For shame deny that thou bear'st loue to any</indextitle>
   <firstline>For shame deny that thou bear'st loue to any</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-010.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
For shame deny that thou bear'st loue to any,
Who for thy selfe art so vnprouident.
Graunt if thou wilt, thou art belou'd of many,
But that thou none lou'st is most euident:
For thou art so possest with murdrous hate,
That gainst thy selfe thou stickst not to conspire,
Seeking that beautious roofe to ruinate
Which to repaire should be thy chiefe desire:
O change thy thought, that I may change my minde.
Shall hate be fairer log'd then gentle loue?
Be as thy presence is, gracious and kind,
Or to thy selfe at least kind harted proue,
    Make thee an other selfe for loue of me,
    That beauty still may liue in thine or thee.

---

<resetnum/>For shame deny that thou bear'st love to any,
Who for thyself art so unprovident.
Grant if thou wilt, thou art beloved of many,
But that thou none lov'st is most evident:
For thou art so possessed with murd'rous hate,
That 'gainst thyself thou stick'st not to conspire,
Seeking that beauteous roof to ruinate
Which to repair should be thy chief desire:
O change thy thought, that I may change my mind.
Shall hate be fairer lodged than gentle love?
Be as thy presence is, gracious and kind,
Or to thyself at least kind-hearted prove,
    Make thee another self for love of me,
    That beauty still may live in thine or thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0011">
<head>
   <title>11</title>
   <toctitle>11 (As fast as thou shalt wane, so fast thou grow'st)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As fast as thou shalt wane, so fast thou grow'st</indextitle>
   <firstline>As fast as thou shalt wane, so fast thou grow'st</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-011.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As fast as thou shalt wane so fast thou grow'st
In one of thine, from that which thou departest,
And that fresh bloud which yongly thou bestow'st
Thou maist call thine, when thou from youth conuertest.
Herein liues wisdome, beauty, and increase,
Without this, follie, age, and could decay;<note>this,] <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; this <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
If all were minded so, the times should cease,
And threescoore yeare would make the world away:
Let those whom nature hath not made for store,
Harsh, featurelesse, and rude, barrenly perrish:
Looke whom she best indow'd, she gaue the more;<note>the] <biblio>Q</biblio>; thee <biblio>Sewell</biblio></note>
Which bountious guift thou shouldst in bounty cherrish.
    She caru'd thee for her seale, and ment therby,
    Thou shouldst print more, not let that coppy die.<note>not] <biblio>Q</biblio>; nor <biblio>Murden</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>As fast as thou shalt wane so fast thou grow'st
In one of thine, from that which thou departest,
And that fresh blood which youngly thou bestow'st
Thou mayst call thine, when thou from youth convertest.
Herein lives wisdom, beauty, and increase,
Without this, folly, age, and cold decay;
If all were minded so, the times should cease,
And threescore year would make the world away:
Let those whom nature hath not made for store,
Harsh, featureless, and rude, barrenly perish:
Look whom she best endowed, she gave the more;
Which bounteous gift thou shouldst in bounty cherish.
    She carved thee for her seal, and meant thereby,
    Thou shouldst print more, not let that copy die.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0012">
<head>
   <title>12</title>
   <toctitle>12 (When I doe count the clock that tels the time)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When I doe count the clock that tels the time</indextitle>
   <firstline>When I doe count the clock that tels the time</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-012.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-012b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When I doe count the clock that tels the time,
And see the braue day sunck in hidious night;
When I behold the violet past prime,
And sable curls all siluer'd ore with white;<note>all siluer'd ore] <biblio>Malone</biblio>; or siluer'd ore <biblio>Q</biblio>; o'er-silver'd all <biblio>Verity</biblio> <i>conj.</i>; are silver'd o'er <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; ensiluer'd ore <biblio>Wells</biblio>; o'er-silver'd o'er <biblio>Harrison</biblio>. - <i>Malones rettelse støttes af linie 7</i> all girded up (<i>en sådan gentagelse, yndet af Shakespeare som virkemiddel, bliver sjovt nok for nogle udgivere et vægtigt argument</i> mod <biblio>Malone</biblio>).</note>
When lofty trees I see barren of leaues,
Which erst from heat did canopie the herd,
And Sommers greene all girded vp in sheaues
Borne on the beare with white and bristly beard:
Then of thy beauty do I question make
That thou among the wastes of time must goe,
Since sweets and beauties do them-selues forsake,
And die as fast as they see others grow,
    And nothing gainst Times sieth can make defence
    Saue breed to braue him, when he takes thee hence.

---

<resetnum/>When I do count the clock that tells the time,
And see the brave day sunk in hideous night;
When I behold the violet past prime,
And sable curls all silvered o'er with white;
When lofty trees I see barren of leaves,
Which erst from heat did canopy the herd,
And summer's green all girded up in sheaves
Borne on the bier with white and bristly beard:
Then of thy beauty do I question make
That thou among the wastes of time must go,
Since sweets and beauties do themselves forsake,
And die as fast as they see others grow,
    And nothing 'gainst time's scythe can make defence
    Save breed to brave him, when he takes thee hence.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0013">
<head>
   <title>13</title>
   <toctitle>13 (O that you were your selfe, but, loue, you are)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>O that you were your selfe, but, loue, you are</indextitle>
   <firstline>O that you were your selfe, but, loue, you are</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-013.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O that you were your selfe, but, loue, you are
No longer yours then you your selfe here liue;
Against this cumming end you should prepare,
And your sweet semblance to some other giue.
So should that beauty which you hold in lease
Find no determination, then you were
Your selfe again after your selfes decease,<note>Your selfe] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; You selfe <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
When your sweet issue your sweet forme should beare.
Who lets so faire a house fall to decay,
Which husbandry in honour might vphold
Against the stormy gusts of winters day
And barren rage of deaths eternall cold?
    O none but vnthrifts, deare my loue you know,
    You had a Father, let your Son say so.

---

<resetnum/>O that you were yourself, but, love, you are
No longer yours than you yourself here live;
Against this coming end you should prepare,
And your sweet semblance to some other give.
So should that beauty which you hold in lease
Find no determination, then you were
Yourself again after yourself's decease,
When your sweet issue your sweet form should bear.
Who lets so fair a house fall to decay,
Which husbandry in honour might uphold
Against the stormy gusts of winter's day
And barren rage of death's eternal cold?
    O none but unthrifts, dear my love you know,
    You had a father, let your son say so.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0014">
<head>
   <title>14</title>
   <toctitle>14 (Not from the stars do I my iudgement plucke)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Not from the stars do I my iudgement plucke</indextitle>
   <firstline>Not from the stars do I my iudgement plucke</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-014.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-014b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Not from the stars do I my iudgement plucke,
And yet me thinkes I haue Astronomy,
But not to tell of good, or euil lucke,
Of plagues, of dearths, or seasons quallity;<note>seasons] <biblio>Q</biblio>; seasons' <biblio>Capell</biblio>; season's <biblio>Dyce</biblio></note>
Nor can I fortune to breefe mynuits tell,
Pointing to each his thunder, raine and winde,<note>Pointing] <biblio>Q</biblio>; 'Pointing <biblio>Walker</biblio> <i>conj.</i></note>
Or say with Princes if it shal go wel
By oft predict that I in heauen finde.<note>oft] <biblio>Q</biblio>; ought <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; aught <biblio>Duncan-Jones</biblio></note>
But from thine eies my knowledge I deriue,
And, constant stars, in them I read such art
As truth and beautie shal together thriue,
If from thy selfe to store thou wouldst conuert:
    Or else of thee this I prognosticate,
    Thy end is Truthes and Beauties doome and date.

---

<resetnum/>Not from the stars do I my judgement pluck,
And yet methinks I have astronomy,
But not to tell of good or evil luck,
Of plagues, of dearths, or seasons' quality;
Nor can I fortune to brief minutes tell,
Pointing to each his thunder, rain and wind,
Or say with princes if it shall go well
By oft predict that I in heaven find.
But from thine eyes my knowledge I derive,
And, constant stars, in them I read such art
As truth and beauty shall together thrive
If from thyself to store thou wouldst convert:
    Or else of thee this I prognosticate,
    Thy end is truth's and beauty's doom and date.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0015">
<head>
   <title>15</title>
   <toctitle>15 (When I consider euery thing that growes)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When I consider euery thing that growes</indextitle>
   <firstline>When I consider euery thing that growes</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-015.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When I consider euery thing that growes
Holds in perfection but a little moment,
That this huge stage presenteth nought but showes
Whereon the Stars in secret influence comment;
When I perceiue that men as plants increase,
Cheared and checkt euen by the selfe-same skie,
Vaunt in their youthfull sap, at height decrease,
And were their braue state out of memory;
Then the conceit of this inconstant stay
Sets you, most rich in youth, before my sight,
Where wastfull time debateth with decay
To change your day of youth to sullied night;
    And all in war with Time for loue of you,
    As he takes from you, I ingraft you new.

---

<resetnum/>When I consider every thing that grows
Holds in perfection but a little moment,
That this huge stage presenteth nought but shows
Whereon the stars in secret influence comment;
When I perceive that men as plants increase,
Cheered and checked even by the self-same sky,
Vaunt in their youthful sap, at height decrease,
And wear their brave state out of memory;
Then the conceit of this inconstant stay
Sets you, most rich in youth, before my sight,
Where wasteful time debateth with decay
To change your day of youth to sullied night;
    And all in war with time for love of you,
    As he takes from you, I engraft you new.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0016">
<head>
   <title>16</title>
   <toctitle>16 (But wherefore do not you a mightier waie)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>But wherefore do not you a mightier waie</indextitle>
   <firstline>But wherefore do not you a mightier waie</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-016.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
But wherefore do not you a mightier waie
Make warre vppon this bloudie tirant time?
And fortifie your selfe in your decay
With meanes more blessed then my barren rime?
Now stand you on the top of happie houres,
And many maiden gardens yet vnset,
With vertuous wish would beare your liuing flowers,<note>your] <biblio>Q</biblio>; you <biblio>Lintott</biblio></note>
Much liker then your painted counterfeit:
So should the lines of life that life repaire,
Which this Times pensel or my pupill pen<note>this Times pensel ... pen] <biblio>Tucker</biblio>; this (Times pensel ... pen) <biblio>Q</biblio>; this, - time's pencil, ... pen, - <biblio>Capell</biblio>; this (Time's Pencil) ... Pen, <biblio>Sewell</biblio>; this, Time's pencil, ... pen, <biblio>Malone</biblio>; this Time's Pencil, ... Pen, <biblio>Gildon</biblio></note>
Neither in inward worth nor outward faire
Can make you liue your selfe in eies of men:
    To giue away your selfe, keeps your selfe still,
    And you must liue drawne by your owne sweet skill.

---

<resetnum/>But wherefore do not you a mightier way
Make war upon this bloody tyrant time?
And fortify yourself in your decay
With means more blessed than my barren rhyme?
Now stand you on the top of happy hours,
And many maiden gardens yet unset,
With virtuous wish would bear your living flowers,
Much liker than your painted counterfeit:
So should the lines of life that life repair,
Which this time's pencil or my pupil pen
Neither in inward worth nor outward fair
Can make you live yourself in eyes of men:
    To give away yourself keeps yourself still,
    And you must live drawn by your own sweet skill.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0017">
<head>
   <title>17</title>
   <toctitle>17 (Who will beleeue my verse in time to come)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Who will beleeue my verse in time to come</indextitle>
   <firstline>Who will beleeue my verse in time to come</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-017.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-017b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Who will beleeue my verse in time to come
If it were fild with your most high deserts?
Though yet heauen knowes it is but as a tombe
Which hides your life, and shewes not halfe your parts:
If I could write the beauty of your eyes,
And in fresh numbers number all your graces,
The age to come would say, this Poet lies,
Such heauenly touches nere toucht earthly faces.
So should my papers (yellowed with their age)
Be scorn'd, like old men of lesse truth then tongue,
And your true rights be termd a Poets rage,
And stretched miter of an Antique song:
    But were some childe of yours aliue that time,
    You should liue twise, in it and in my rime.<note>twise, in it] <biblio>Wright</biblio>; twise in it, <biblio>Q</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>Who will believe my verse in time to come
If it were filled with your most high deserts?
Though yet heaven knows it is but as a tomb
Which hides your life, and shows not half your parts:
If I could write the beauty of your eyes,
And in fresh numbers number all your graces,
The age to come would say, ,,This poet lies,
Such heavenly touches ne'er touched earthly faces.''
So should my papers, yellowed with their age,
Be scorned, like old men of less truth than tongue,
And your true rights be termed a poet's rage,
And stretched metre of an antique song:
    But were some child of yours alive that time,
    You should live twice, in it and in my rhyme.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0018">
<head>
   <title>18</title>
   <toctitle>18 (Shall I compare thee to a Summers day?)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Shall I compare thee to a Summers day?</indextitle>
   <firstline>Shall I compare thee to a Summers day?</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-018.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Shall I compare thee to a Summers day?
Thou art more louely and more temperate:
Rough windes do shake the darling buds of Maie,
And Sommers lease hath all too short a date:
Sometime too hot the eye of heauen shines,
And often is his gold complexion dimm'd,
And euery faire from faire some-time declines,
By chance or natures changing course vntrim'd:
But thy eternall Sommer shall not fade,
Nor loose possession of that faire thou ow'st,
Nor shall death brag thou wandr'st in his shade,
When in eternall lines to time thou grow'st:
    So long as men can breath or eyes can see,
    So long liues this, and this giues life to thee.

---

<resetnum/>Shall I compare thee to a summer's day?
Thou art more lovely and more temperate:
Rough winds do shake the darling buds of May,
And summer's lease hath all too short a date:
Sometime too hot the eye of heaven shines,
And often is his gold complexion dimmed,
And every fair from fair sometime declines,
By chance or nature's changing course untrimmed:
But thy eternal summer shall not fade,
Nor lose possession of that fair thou ow'st,
Nor shall death brag thou wand'rest in his shade,
When in eternal lines to time thou grow'st:
    So long as men can breathe or eyes can see,
    So long lives this, and this gives life to thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0019">
<head>
   <title>19</title>
   <toctitle>19 (Deuouring time, blunt thou the Lyons pawes)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Deuouring time, blunt thou the Lyons pawes</indextitle>
   <firstline>Deuouring time, blunt thou the Lyons pawes</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-019.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-019b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Deuouring time, blunt thou the Lyons pawes,
And make the earth deuoure her owne sweet brood;
Plucke the keene teeth from the fierce Tygers yawes,
And burne the long liu'd Ph&aelig;nix in her blood;
Make glad and sorry seasons as thou fleet'st,<note>fleet'st] <biblio>Q</biblio>; fleets <biblio>Dyce</biblio></note>
And do what ere thou wilt, swift-footed time,
To the wide world and all her fading sweets:
But I forbid thee one most hainous crime,
O carue not with thy howers my loues faire brow,
Nor draw noe lines there with thine antique pen;
Him in thy course vntainted doe allow
For beauties patterne to succeding men.
    Yet doe thy worst ould Time, dispight thy wrong,
    My loue shall in my verse euer liue young.

---

<resetnum/>Devouring time, blunt thou the lion's paws,
And make the earth devour her own sweet brood;
Pluck the keen teeth from the fierce tiger's jaws,
And burn the long-lived Phoenix in her blood;
Make glad and sorry seasons as thou fleet'st,
And do whate'er thou wilt, swift-footed time,
To the wide world and all her fading sweets:
But I forbid thee one most heinous crime,
O carve not with thy hours my love's fair brow,
Nor draw no lines there with thine antique pen;
Him in thy course untainted do allow
For beauty's pattern to succeeding men.
    Yet do thy worst old Time, despite thy wrong,
    My love shall in my verse ever live young.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0020">
<head>
   <title>20</title>
   <toctitle>20 (A womans face with natures owne hande painted)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A womans face with natures owne hande painted</indextitle>
   <firstline>A womans face with natures owne hande painted</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-020.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
A womans face with natures owne hande painted
Haste thou, the Master Mistris of my passion;
A womans gentle hart, but not acquainted
With shifting change as is false womens fashion;
An eye more bright then theirs, lesse false in rowling,
Gilding the obiect where-vpon it gazeth;
A man in hew all <i>Hews</i> in his controwling,
Which steales mens eyes and womens soules amaseth.
And for a woman wert thou first created,
Till nature as she wrought thee fell a dotinge,
And by addition me of thee defeated,
By adding one thing to my purpose nothing.
    But since she prickt thee out for womens pleasure,
    Mine be thy loue and thy loues vse their treasure.

---

<resetnum/>A woman's face with nature's own hand painted
Hast thou, the master mistress of my passion;
A woman's gentle heart, but not acquainted
With shifting change as is false women's fashion;
An eye more bright than theirs, less false in rolling,
Gilding the object whereupon it gazeth;
A man in hue all hues in his controlling,
Which steals men's eyes and women's souls amazeth.
And for a woman wert thou first created,
Till nature as she wrought thee fell a-doting,
And by addition me of thee defeated,
By adding one thing to my purpose nothing.
    But since she pricked thee out for women's pleasure,
    Mine be thy love and thy love's use their treasure.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0021">
<head>
   <title>21</title>
   <toctitle>21 (So is it not with me as with that Muse)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>So is it not with me as with that Muse</indextitle>
   <firstline>So is it not with me as with that Muse</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-021.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
So is it not with me as with that Muse,
Stird by a painted beauty to his verse,
Who heauen it selfe for ornament doth vse,
And euery faire with his faire doth reherse,
Making a coopelment of proud compare
With Sunne and Moone, with earth and seas rich gems,
With Aprills first borne flowers and all things rare
That heauens ayre in this huge rondure hems;
O let me true in loue but truly write,<note>me ... love] <biblio>Q</biblio>; me, ... love, <biblio>Gildon</biblio></note>
And then beleeue me, my loue is as faire
As any mothers childe, though not so bright
As those gould candells fixt in heauens ayer:
    Let them say more that like of heare-say well,
    I will not prayse that purpose not to sell.

---

<resetnum/>So is it not with me as with that muse,
Stirred by a painted beauty to his verse,
Who heaven itself for ornament doth use,
And every fair with his fair doth rehearse,
Making a couplement of proud compare
With sun and moon, with earth and sea's rich gems,
With April's first-born flowers and all things rare
That heaven's air in this huge rondure hems;
O let me true in love but truly write,
And then believe me, my love is as fair
As any mother's child, though not so bright
As those gold candles fixed in heaven's air:
    Let them say more that like of hearsay well,
    I will not praise that purpose not to sell.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0022">
<head>
   <title>22</title>
   <toctitle>22 (My glasse shall not perswade me I am ould)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My glasse shall not perswade me I am ould</indextitle>
   <firstline>My glasse shall not perswade me I am ould</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-022.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
My glasse shall not perswade me I am ould,
So long as youth and thou are of one date,
But when in thee times forrwes I behould,
Then look I death my daies should expiate:
For all that beauty that doth couer thee
Is but the seemely rayment of my heart,
Which in thy brest doth liue, as thine in me,
How can I then be elder then thou art?
O therefore, loue, be of thy selfe so wary
As I not for my selfe, but for thee will,
Bearing thy heart, which I will keepe so chary
As tender nurse her babe from faring ill:
    Presume not on thy heart when mine is slaine,
    Thou gau'st me thine not to giue backe againe.

---

<resetnum/>My glass shall not persuade me I am old,
So long as youth and thou are of one date,
But when in thee time's furrows I behold,
Then look I death my days should expiate:
For all that beauty that doth cover thee
Is but the seemly raiment of my heart,
Which in thy breast doth live, as thine in me,
How can I then be elder than thou art?
O therefore, love, be of thyself so wary
As I not for myself, but for thee will,
Bearing thy heart, which I will keep so chary
As tender nurse her babe from faring ill:
    Presume not on thy heart when mine is slain,
    Thou gav'st me thine not to give back again.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0023">
<head>
   <title>23</title>
   <toctitle>23 (As an vnperfect actor on the stage)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As an vnperfect actor on the stage</indextitle>
   <firstline>As an vnperfect actor on the stage</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-023.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As an vnperfect actor on the stage,
Who with his feare is put besides his part,
Or some fierce thing repleat with too much rage,
Whose strengths abondance weakens his owne heart;
So I for feare of trust, forget to say
The perfect ceremony of loues right,<note><i>Skriftsproget var på Shakespeares tid elastisk nok til at</i> right <i>her også kunne læses som</i> rite.</note>
And in mine owne loues strength seeme to decay,
Ore-charg'd with burthen of mine owne loues might:
O let my books be then the eloquence<note>books] <biblio>Q</biblio>; looks <biblio>Sewell</biblio></note>
And domb presagers of my speaking brest,
Who pleade for loue, and look for recompence,
More then that tonge that more hath more exprest.
    O learne to read what silent loue hath writ,
    To heare with eies belongs to loues fine wit.<note>with ... wit] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; wit ... wiht <biblio>Q</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>As an unperfect actor on the stage,
Who with his fear is put besides his part,
Or some fierce thing replete with too much rage,
Whose strength's abundance weakens his own heart;
So I for fear of trust, forget to say
The perfect ceremony of love's rite,
And in mine own love's strength seem to decay,
O'ercharged with burden of mine own love's might:
O let my books be then the eloquence
And dumb presagers of my speaking breast,
Who plead for love, and look for recompense,
More than that tongue that more hath more expressed.
    O learn to read what silent love hath writ,
    To hear with eyes belongs to love's fine wit.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0024">
<head>
   <title>24</title>
   <toctitle>24 (Mine eye hath play'd the painter and hath stelld)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Mine eye hath play'd the painter and hath stelld</indextitle>
   <firstline>Mine eye hath play'd the painter and hath stelld</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-024.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-024b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Mine eye hath play'd the painter and hath steeld<note>steeld] <biblio>Q</biblio>; stell'd <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
Thy beauties forme in table of my heart;
My body is the frame wherein ti's held,
And perspectiue it is best Painters art;
For through the Painter must you see his skill
To finde where your true Image pictur'd lies,
Which in my bosomes shop is hanging stil,
That hath his windowes glazed with thine eyes:
Now see what good-turnes eyes for eies haue done,
Mine eyes haue drawne thy shape, and thine for me
Are windowes to my brest, where-through the Sun
Delights to peepe, to gaze therein on thee;
    Yet eyes this cunning want to grace their art,
    They draw but what they see, know not the hart.

---

<resetnum/>Mine eye hath played the painter and hath steeled
Thy beauty's form in table of my heart;
My body is the frame wherein 'tis held,
And perspective it is best painter's art;
For through the painter must you see his skill
To find where your true image pictured lies,
Which in my bosom's shop is hanging still,
That hath his windows glazed with thine eyes:
Now see what good turns eyes for eyes have done,
Mine eyes have drawn thy shape, and thine for me
Are windows to my breast, wherethrough the sun
Delights to peep, to gaze therein on thee;
    Yet eyes this cunning want to grace their art,
    They draw but what they see, know not the heart.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0025">
<head>
   <title>25</title>
   <toctitle>25 (Let those who are in fauor with their stars)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Let those who are in fauor with their stars</indextitle>
   <firstline>Let those who are in fauor with their stars</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-025.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Let those who are in fauor with their stars,
Of publike honour and proud titles bost,
Whilst I whome fortune of such tryumph bars,
Vnlookt for ioy in that I honour most;
Great Princes fauorites their fair leaues spread
But as the Marygold at the suns eye,
And in them-selues their pride lies buried,
For at a frowne they in their glory die.
The painefull warrier famosed for fight,<note>fight] <biblio>Theobald</biblio> <i>conj.</i>; worth <biblio>Q</biblio> - worth <i>i l. 9 rimer ikke med</i> quite <i>i l. 11, som det ellers sømmer sig for rim, så udgivere har foreslået enten at ændre</i> worth <i>til</i> fight (<biblio>Theobald</biblio> <i>conj.</i>) <i>eller</i> might (<biblio>Capell</biblio>), <i>eller at ændre</i> quite <i>til</i> forth (<biblio>Theobald</biblio> <i>conj.</i>); fight <i>sandsynliggøres af alliterationen med digtets mange betydende f-ord, der så ligesom tilspidses i l. 9., men på den anden side er </i> worth <i>en urimelig fejllæsning af</i> fight; <i>det kan jo også tænkes at Shakespeare her ganske simpelt havde glemt at rime, og så er enhver "rettelse" blot en anmassende forskønnelse.</i></note>
After a thousand victories once foild,
Is from the booke of honour rased quite,
And all the rest forgot for which he toild:
    Then happy I that loue and am beloued
    Where I may not remoue, nor be remoued.

---

<resetnum/>Let those who are in favour with their stars
Of public honour and proud titles boast,
Whilst I whom fortune of such triumph bars,
Unlooked for joy in that I honour most;
Great princes' favourites their fair leaves spread
But as the marigold at the sun's eye,
And in themselves their pride lies buried,
For at a frown they in their glory die.
The painful warrior famoused for fight,
After a thousand victories once foiled,
Is from the book of honour razed quite,
And all the rest forgot for which he toiled:
    Then happy I that love and am beloved
    Where I may not remove, nor be removed.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0026">
<head>
   <title>26</title>
   <toctitle>26 (Lord of my loue, to whome in vassalage)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Lord of my loue, to whome in vassalage</indextitle>
   <firstline>Lord of my loue, to whome in vassalage</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-026.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-026b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Lord of my loue, to whome in vassalage
Thy merrit hath my dutie strongly knit,
To thee I send this written ambassage
To witnesse duty, not to shew my wit;
Duty so great, which wit so poore as mine
May make seeme bare, in wanting words to shew it,
But that I hope some good conceipt of thine
In thy soules thought (all naked) will bestow it:
Til whatsoeuer star that guides my mouing,
Points on me gratiously with faire aspect,
And puts apparrell on my tottered louing,
To show me worthy of thy sweet respect;<note>thy] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; their <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
    Then may I dare to boast how I doe loue thee,
    Til then, not show my head where thou maist proue me.

---

<resetnum/>Lord of my love, to whom in vassalage
Thy merit hath my duty strongly knit,
To thee I send this written embassage
To witness duty, not to show my wit;
Duty so great, which wit so poor as mine
May make seem bare, in wanting words to show it,
But that I hope some good conceit of thine
In thy soul's thought, all naked, will bestow it:
Till whatsoever star that guides my moving
Points on me graciously with fair aspect,
And puts apparel on my tottered loving,
To show me worthy of thy sweet respect;
    Then may I dare to boast how I do love thee,
    Till then, not show my head where thou mayst prove me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0027">
<head>
   <title>27</title>
   <toctitle>27 (Weary with toyle, I hast me to my bed)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Weary with toyle, I hast me to my bed</indextitle>
   <firstline>Weary with toyle, I hast me to my bed</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-027.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Weary with toyle, I hast me to my bed,
The deare repose for lims with trauaill tired,
But then begins a iourny in my head
To worke my mind, when boddies work's expired:
For then my thoughts (from far where I abide)<note>from far] <biblio>Q</biblio>; far from <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
Intend a zelous pilgrimage to thee,
And keepe my drooping eye-lids open wide,
Looking on darknes which the blind doe see;
Saue that my soules imaginary sight
Presents thy shaddoe to my sightles view,<note>thy] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; their <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
Which like a iewell (hunge in gastly night)<note>(hunge ... night)] <biblio>Q</biblio>; hunge ... night, <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
Makes blacke night beautious, and her old face new.
    Loe thus by day my lims, by night my mind,
    For thee, and for my selfe, noe quiet finde.

---

<resetnum/>Weary with toil, I haste me to my bed,
The dear repose for limbs with travel tired,
But then begins a journey in my head
To work my mind, when body's work's expired:
For then my thoughts, from far where I abide,
Intend a zealous pilgrimage to thee,
And keep my drooping eyelids open wide,
Looking on darkness which the blind do see;
Save that my soul's imaginary sight
Presents thy shadow to my sightless view,
Which like a jewel, hung in ghastly night,
Makes black night beauteous, and her old face new.
    Lo thus by day my limbs, by night my mind,
    For thee, and for myself, no quiet find.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0028">
<head>
   <title>28</title>
   <toctitle>28 (How can I then returne in happy plight)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How can I then returne in happy plight</indextitle>
   <firstline>How can I then returne in happy plight</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-028.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
How can I then returne in happy plight
That am debard the benefit of rest?
When daies oppression is not eazd by night,
But day by night and night by day oprest?
And each (though enimes to ethers raigne)<note>ethers] <biblio>Q</biblio>; either's <biblio>Malone</biblio>; others <biblio>Benson</biblio>; other's <biblio>Gildon</biblio>. <i>Læs:</i> each other's.</note>
Doe in consent shake hands to torture me,
The one by toyle, the other to complaine
How far I toyle, still farther off from thee.
I tell the Day, to please him, thou art bright,
And do'st him grace when clouds doe blot the heauen:
So flatter I the swart complexiond night,
When sparkling stars twire not thou guil'st the eauen.<note>guil'st] <biblio>Q</biblio> - <i>muligvis en fejl for</i> g(u)ild'st <i>men nok snarere en afvigende stavemåde.</i></note><note>the] <biblio>Sewell</biblio>; th' <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
    But day doth daily draw my sorrowes longer,<note>longer ... length ... stronger] <biblio>Q</biblio>; longer ... strength ... stronger <biblio>Capell</biblio>; stronger ... length ... longer <biblio>Capell</biblio> <i>conj.</i></note>
    And night doth nightly make greefes length seeme stronger.<note>greefes] <biblio>Q</biblio>; grief's <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; griefs' <biblio>Evans</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>How can I then return in happy plight
That am debarred the benefit of rest?
When day's oppression is not eased by night,
But day by night and night by day oppressed?
And each, though enemies to either's reign,
Do in consent shake hands to torture me,
The one by toil, the other to complain
How far I toil, still farther off from thee.
I tell the day, to please him, thou art bright,
And dost him grace when clouds do blot the heaven:
So flatter I the swart-complexioned night,
When sparkling stars twire not thou gild'st the even.
    But day doth daily draw my sorrows longer,
    And night doth nightly make grief's length seem stronger.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0029">
<head>
   <title>29</title>
   <toctitle>29 (When in disgrace with Fortune and mens eyes)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When in disgrace with Fortune and mens eyes</indextitle>
   <firstline>When in disgrace with Fortune and mens eyes</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-029.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-029b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When in disgrace with Fortune and mens eyes
I all alone beweepe my out-cast state,
And trouble deafe heauen with my bootlesse cries,
And looke vpon my selfe and curse my fate,
Wishing me like to one more rich in hope,
Featur'd like him, like him with friends possest,
Desiring this mans art, and that mans skope,
With what I most inioy contented least;
Yet in these thoughts my selfe almost despising,
Haply I thinke on thee, and then my state<note>state (Like ... arising ... earth)] <biblio>Malone</biblio>; state, (Like ... arising) ... earth <biblio>Q</biblio>; State, Like ... Lark, ... arising ... Earth <biblio>Gildon</biblio></note>
(Like to the Larke at breake of daye arising
From sullen earth) sings himns at Heauens gate,
    For thy sweet loue remembred such welth brings
    That then I skorne to change my state with Kings.<note>Kings] <biblio>Q</biblio>; kings' <biblio>Wells</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>When in disgrace with fortune and men's eyes
I all alone beweep my outcast state,
And trouble deaf heaven with my bootless cries,
And look upon myself and curse my fate,
Wishing me like to one more rich in hope,
Featured like him, like him with friends possessed,
Desiring this man's art, and that man's scope,
With what I most enjoy contented least;
Yet in these thoughts myself almost despising,
Haply I think on thee, and then my state,
Like to the lark at break of day arising
From sullen earth, sings hymns at heaven's gate,
    For thy sweet love remembered such wealth brings
    That then I scorn to change my state with kings.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0030">
<head>
   <title>30</title>
   <toctitle>30 (When to the Sessions of sweet silent thought)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When to the Sessions of sweet silent thought</indextitle>
   <firstline>When to the Sessions of sweet silent thought</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-030.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When to the Sessions of sweet silent thought
I summon vp remembrance of things past,
I sigh the lacke of many a thing I sought,
And with old woes new waile my deare times waste;<note>times] <biblio>Q</biblio>; time's <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; times' <biblio>Dyce</biblio></note>
Then can I drowne an eye (vn-vs'd to flow)
For precious friends hid in deaths dateles night,
And weepe a fresh loues long since canceld woe,
And mone th'expence of many a vannisht sight.
Then can I greeue at greeuances fore-gon,
And heauily from woe to woe tell ore
The sad account of fore-bemoned mone,
Which I new pay as if not payd before.
    But if the while I thinke on thee (deare friend)
    All losses are restord, and sorrowes end.

---

<resetnum/>When to the sessions of sweet silent thought
I summon up remembrance of things past,
I sigh the lack of many a thing I sought,
And with old woes new wail my dear time's waste;
Then can I drown an eye, unused to flow,
For precious friends hid in death's dateless night,
And weep afresh love's long since cancelled woe,
And moan th'expense of many a vanished sight.
Then can I grieve at grievances foregone,
And heavily from woe to woe tell o'er
The sad account of fore-bemoaned moan,
Which I new pay as if not paid before.
    But if the while I think on thee, dear friend,
    All losses are restored, and sorrows end.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0031">
<head>
   <title>31</title>
   <toctitle>31 (Thy bosome is indeared with all hearts)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thy bosome is indeared with all hearts</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thy bosome is indeared with all hearts</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-031.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-031b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thy bosome is indeared with all hearts
Which I by lacking haue supposed dead,
And there raignes Loue and all Loues louing parts,
And all those friends which I thought buried.
How many a holy and obsequious teare
Hath deare religious loue stolne from mine eye,
As interest of the dead, which now appeare
But things remou'd that hidden in thee lie.<note>thee] <biblio>Gildon</biblio>; there <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
Thou art the graue where buried loue doth liue,
Hung with the tropheis of my louers gon,
Who all their parts of me to thee did giue;
That due of many, now is thine alone.
    Their images I lou'd, I view in thee,
    And thou (all they) hast all the all of me.

---

<resetnum/>Thy bosom is endeared with all hearts
Which I by lacking have supposed dead,
And there reigns love and all love's loving parts,
And all those friends which I thought buried.
How many a holy and obsequious tear
Hath dear religious love stol'n from mine eye,
As interest of the dead, which now appear
But things removed that hidden in thee lie.
Thou art the grave where buried love doth live,
Hung with the trophies of my lovers gone,
Who all their parts of me to thee did give;
That due of many, now is thine alone.
    Their images I loved, I view in thee,
    And thou, all they, hast all the all of me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0032">
<head>
   <title>32</title>
   <toctitle>32 (If thou suruiue my well contented daie)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>If thou suruiue my well contented daie</indextitle>
   <firstline>If thou suruiue my well contented daie</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-032.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
If thou suruiue my well contented daie,
When that churle death my bones with dust shall couer,
And shalt by fortune once more re-suruay
These poore rude lines of thy deceased Louer:
Compare them with the bett'ring of the time,
And though they be out-stript by euery pen,
Reserue them for my loue, not for their rime,
Exceeded by the hight of happier men.
Oh then voutsafe me but this louing thought:
Had my friends Muse growne with this growing age,
A dearer birth then this his loue had brought
To march in ranckes of better equipage:
    But since he died and Poets better proue,
    Theirs for their stile Ile read, his for his loue.<note>Ile] ?; ile <biblio>Q</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>If thou survive my well-contented day,
When that churl death my bones with dust shall cover,
And shalt by fortune once more re-survey
These poor rude lines of thy deceased lover:
Compare them with the bett'ring of the time,
And though they be outstripped by every pen,
Reserve them for my love, not for their rhyme,
Exceeded by the height of happier men.
O then vouchsafe me but this loving thought:
,,Had my friend's muse grown with this growing age,
A dearer birth than this his love had brought
To march in ranks of better equipage:
    But since he died and poets better prove,
    Theirs for their style I'll read, his for his love.''
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0033">
<head>
   <title>33</title>
   <toctitle>33 (Full many a glorious morning haue I seene)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Full many a glorious morning haue I seene</indextitle>
   <firstline>Full many a glorious morning haue I seene</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-033.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Full many a glorious morning haue I seene
Flatter the mountaine tops with soueraine eie,
Kissing with golden face the meddowes greene,
Guilding pale streames with heauenly alcumy;
Anon permit the basest cloudes to ride
With ougly rack on his celestiall face,
And from the for-lorne world his visage hide,
Stealing vnseene to west with this disgrace:
Euen so my Sunne one early morne did shine
With all triumphant splendor on my brow,
But out alack, he was but one houre mine,
The region cloude hath mask'd him from me now.
    Yet him for this, my loue no whit disdaineth:
    Suns of the world may staine, when heauens sun staineth.<note>when ... staineth] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; whê ... stainteh <biblio>Q</biblio></note>

---

<resetnum/>Full many a glorious morning have I seen
Flatter the mountain tops with sovereign eye,
Kissing with golden face the meadows green,
Gilding pale streams with heavenly alchemy;
Anon permit the basest clouds to ride
With ugly rack on his celestial face,
And from the forlorn world his visage hide,
Stealing unseen to west with this disgrace:
Even so my sun one early morn did shine
With all triumphant splendour on my brow;
But out alack, he was but one hour mine,
The region cloud hath masked him from me now.
    Yet him for this, my love no whit disdaineth:
    Suns of the world may stain, when heaven's sun staineth.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0034">
<head>
   <title>34</title>
   <toctitle>34 (Why didst thou promise such a beautious day)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Why didst thou promise such a beautious day</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why didst thou promise such a beautious day</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-034.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Why didst thou promise such a beautious day,
And make me trauaile forth without my cloake,
To let bace cloudes ore-take me in my way,
Hiding thy brau'ry in their rotten smoke?
Tis not enough that through the cloude thou breake,
To dry the raine on my storme-beaten face,
For no man well of such a salue can speake
That heales the wound and cures not the disgrace;
Nor can thy shame giue phisicke to my griefe,
Though thou repent, yet I haue still the losse,
Th'offenders sorrow lends but weake reliefe
To him that beares the strong offenses crosse.<note>crosse] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; losse <biblio>Q</biblio>. <i>Det virker forkert med</i> losse <i>både i linje 10 og 12, selvom gentagelsen kunne være en bevidst fremhævende effekt; rettelsen til</i> crosse <i>støttes dog af <xref poem="shakespeare0042"/> hvor samme rim bruges, endda i de samme linjer.</i></note>
    Ah but those teares are pearle which thy loue sheeds,
    And they are ritch, and ransome all ill deeds.

---

<resetnum/>Why didst thou promise such a beauteous day,
And make me travail forth without my cloak,
To let base clouds o'ertake me in my way,
Hiding thy brav'ry in their rotten smoke?
'Tis not enough that through the cloud thou break,
To dry the rain on my storm-beaten face,
For no man well of such a salve can speak
That heals the wound and cures not the disgrace;
Nor can thy shame give physic to my grief,
Though thou repent, yet I have still the loss,
Th'offender's sorrow lends but weak relief
To him that bears the strong offence's cross.
    Ah, but those tears are pearl which thy love sheds,
    And they are rich, and ransom all ill deeds.
</body>
</poem>

<!-- # her -->

<poem id="shakespeare0035">
<head>
   <title>35</title>
   <toctitle>35 (No more bee greeu'd at that which thou hast done)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>No more bee greeu'd at that which thou hast done</indextitle>
   <firstline>No more bee greeu'd at that which thou hast done</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>8 thy ... thy] their ... their - <i>en anden mulig rettelse</i>: these ... these</note>
   </notes>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-035.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
No more bee greeu'd at that which thou hast done,
Roses haue thornes, and siluer fountaines mud,
Cloudes and eclipses staine both Moone and Sunne,
And loathsome canker liues in sweetest bud.
All men make faults, and euen I in this,
Authorizing thy trespas with compare,
My selfe corrupting saluing thy amisse,
Excusing thy sins more then thy sins are:
For to thy sensuall fault I bring in sence;
Thy aduerse party is thy Aduocate,
And gainst my selfe a lawfull plea commence:
Such ciuill war is in my loue and hate
    That I an accessary needs must be
    To that sweet theefe which sourely robs from me.

---

<resetnum/>No more be grieved at that which thou hast done,
Roses have thorns, and silver fountains mud,
Clouds and eclipses stain both moon and sun,
And loathsome canker lives in sweetest bud.
All men make faults, and even I in this,
Authorizing thy trespass with compare,
Myself corrupting salving thy amiss,
Excusing thy sins more than thy sins are:
For to thy sensual fault I bring in sense;
Thy adverse party is thy advocate,
And 'gainst myself a lawful plea commence:
Such civil war is in my love and hate
    That I an accessory needs must be
    To that sweet thief which sourly robs from me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0036">
<head>
   <title>36</title>
   <toctitle>36 (Let me confesse that we two must be twaine)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Let me confesse that we two must be twaine</indextitle>
   <firstline>Let me confesse that we two must be twaine</firstline>
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-036.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Let me confesse that we two must be twaine,
Although our vndeuided loues are one;
So shall those blots that do with me remaine,
Without thy helpe, by me be borne alone.
In our two loues there is but one respect,
Though in our liues a seperable spight,
Which though it alter not loues sole effect,
Yet doth it steale sweet houres from loues delight,
I may not euer-more acknowledge thee,
Least my bewailed guilt should do thee shame,
Nor thou with publike kindnesse honour me,
Vnlesse thou take that honour from thy name:
    But doe not so, I loue thee in such sort,
    As thou being mine, mine is thy good report.

---

<resetnum/>Let me confess that we two must be twain,
Although our undivided loves are one;
So shall those blots that do with me remain,
Without thy help, by me be borne alone.
In our two loves there is but one respect,
Though in our lives a separable spite,
Which, though it alter not love's sole effect,
Yet doth it steal sweet hours from love's delight.
I may not evermore acknowledge thee,
Lest my bewailed guilt should do thee shame,
Nor thou with public kindness honour me,
Unless thou take that honour from thy name:
    But do not so, I love thee in such sort,
    As thou being mine, mine is thy good report.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0037">
<head>
   <title>37</title>
   <toctitle>37 (As a decrepit father takes delight)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>As a decrepit father takes delight</indextitle>
   <firstline>As a decrepit father takes delight</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>7 thy] their</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
As a decrepit father takes delight
To see his actiue childe do deeds of youth,
So I, made lame by Fortunes dearest spight,
Take all my comfort of thy worth and truth.
For whether beauty, birth, or wealth, or wit,
Or any of these all, or all, or more,
Intitled in thy parts, do crowned sit,
I make my loue ingrafted to this store:
So then I am not lame, poore, nor dispis'd,
Whilst that this shadow doth such substance giue
That I in thy abundance am suffic'd,
And by a part of all thy glory liue:
    Looke what is best, that best I wish in thee,
    This wish I haue, then ten times happy me.

---

<resetnum/>As a decrepit father takes delight
To see his active child do deeds of youth,
So I, made lame by fortune's dearest spite,
Take all my comfort of thy worth and truth.
For whether beauty, birth, or wealth, or wit,
Or any of these all, or all, or more,
Entitled in thy parts do crowned sit,
I make my love engrafted to this store:
So then I am not lame, poor, nor despised,
Whilst that this shadow doth such substance give
That I in thy abundance am sufficed,
And by a part of all thy glory live:
    Look what is best, that best I wish in thee,
    This wish I have, then ten times happy me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0038">
<head>
   <title>38</title>
   <toctitle>38 (How can my Muse want subiect to inuent)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How can my Muse want subiect to inuent</indextitle>
   <firstline>How can my Muse want subiect to inuent</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
How can my Muse want subiect to inuent
While thou dost breath that poor'st into my verse
Thine owne sweet argument, to excellent
For euery vulgar paper to rehearse?
Oh giue thy selfe the thankes if ought in me
Worthy perusal stand against thy sight,
For who's so dumbe that cannot write to thee,
When thou thy selfe dost giue inuention light?
Be thou the tenth Muse, ten times more in worth
Then those old nine which rimers inuocate,
And he that calls on thee, let him bring forth
Eternal numbers to out-liue long date.
    If my slight Muse doe please these curious daies,
    The paine be mine, but thine shal be the praise.

---

<resetnum/>How can my muse want subject to invent
While thou dost breathe, that pour'st into my verse
Thine own sweet argument, too excellent
For every vulgar paper to rehearse?
O give thyself the thanks, if aught in me
Worthy perusal stand against thy sight,
For who's so dumb, that cannot write to thee,
When thou thyself dost give invention light?
Be thou the tenth muse, ten times more in worth
Than those old nine which rhymers invocate,
And he that calls on thee, let him bring forth
Eternal numbers to outlive long date.
    If my slight muse do please these curious days,
    The pain be mine, but thine shall be the praise.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0039">
<head>
   <title>39</title>
   <toctitle>39 (Oh how thy worth with manners may I singe)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Oh how thy worth with manners may I singe</indextitle>
   <firstline>Oh how thy worth with manners may I singe</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>12 dost <i>skal måske være</i> doth</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Oh how thy worth with manners may I singe,
When thou art all the better part of me?
What can mine owne praise to mine owne selfe bring;
And what is't but mine owne when I praise thee?
Euen for this, let vs deuided liue,
And our deare loue loose name of single one,
That by this seperation I may giue
That due to thee which thou deseru'st alone.
Oh absence what a torment wouldst thou proue,
Were it not thy soure leisure gaue sweet leaue
To entertaine the time with thoughts of loue,
Which time and thoughts so sweetly dost deceiue,
    And that thou teachest how to make one twaine
    By praising him here who doth hence remaine.

---

<resetnum/>O how thy worth with manners may I sing,
When thou art all the better part of me?
What can mine own praise to mine own self bring,
And what is't but mine own, when I praise thee?
Even for this, let us divided live,
And our dear love lose name of single one,
That by this separation I may give
That due to thee which thou deserv'st alone.
O absence, what a torment wouldst thou prove,
Were it not thy sour leisure gave sweet leave
To entertain the time with thoughts of love,
Which time and thoughts so sweetly dost deceive,
    And that thou teachest how to make one twain
    By praising him here who doth hence remain.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0040">
<head>
   <title>40</title>
   <toctitle>40 (Take all my loues, my loue, yea take them all)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Take all my loues, my loue, yea take them all</indextitle>
   <firstline>Take all my loues, my loue, yea take them all</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>7 thy selfe] this selfe</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Take all my loues, my loue, yea take them all;
What hast thou then more then thou hadst before?
No loue, my loue, that thou maist true loue call,
All mine was thine, before thou hadst this more:
Then if for my loue thou my loue receiuest,
I cannot blame thee, for my loue thou vsest;
But yet be blam'd, if thou thy selfe deceauest
By wilfull taste of what thy selfe refusest.
I doe forgiue thy robb'rie, gentle theefe,
Although thou steale thee all my pouerty;
And yet loue knowes it is a greater griefe
To beare loues wrong then hates knowne iniury.
    Lasciuious grace, in whom all il wel showes,
    Kill me with spights, yet we must not be foes.

---

<resetnum/>Take all my loves, my love; yea, take them all;
What hast thou then more than thou hadst before?
No love, my love, that thou mayst true love call,
All mine was thine, before thou hadst this more:
Then if for my love thou my love receivest,
I cannot blame thee, for my love thou usest;
But yet be blamed, if thou thyself deceivest
By wilful taste of what thyself refusest.
I do forgive thy robb'ry, gentle thief,
Although thou steal thee all my poverty;
And yet love knows it is a greater grief
To bear love's wrong than hate's known injury.
    Lascivious grace, in whom all ill well shows,
    Kill me with spites, yet we must not be foes.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0041">
<head>
   <title>41</title>
   <toctitle>41 (Those pretty wrongs that liberty commits)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Those pretty wrongs that liberty commits</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those pretty wrongs that liberty commits</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Those pretty wrongs that liberty commits
When I am some-time absent from thy heart,
Thy beautie,and thy yeares full well befits,
For still temptation followes where thou art.
Gentle thou art, and therefore to be wonne,
Beautious thou art, therefore to be assailed;
And when a woman woes, what womans sonne
Will sourely leaue her till he haue preuailed?
Aye me, but yet thou mightst my seate forbeare,
And chide thy beauty, and thy straying youth,
Who lead thee in their ryot euen there
Where thou art forst to breake a two-fold truth:
    Hers by thy beauty tempting her to thee,
    Thine by thy beautie beeing false to me.

---

<resetnum/>Those petty wrongs that liberty commits
When I am sometime absent from thy heart,
Thy beauty and thy years full well befits,
For still temptation follows where thou art.
Gentle thou art, and therefore to be won,
Beauteous thou art, therefore to be assailed;
And when a woman woos, what woman's son
Will sourly leave her till he have prevailed?
Ay me, but yet thou mightst my seat forbear,
And chide thy beauty and thy straying youth,
Who lead thee in their riot even there
Where thou art forced to break a twofold truth:
    Hers by thy beauty tempting her to thee,
    Thine by thy beauty being false to me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0042">
<head>
   <title>42</title>
   <toctitle>42 (That thou hast her it is not all my griefe)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That thou hast her it is not all my griefe</indextitle>
   <firstline>That thou hast her it is not all my griefe</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
That thou hast her it is not all my griefe,
And yet it may be said I lou'd her deerely;
That she hath thee is of my wayling cheefe,
A losse in loue that touches me more neerely.
Louing offendors, thus I will excuse yee:
Thou doost loue her, because thou knowst I loue her;
And for my sake euen so doth she abuse me,
Suffring my friend for my sake to approoue her;
If I loose thee, my losse is my loues gaine,
And loosing her, my friend hath found that losse;
Both finde each other, and I loose both twaine,
And both for my sake lay on me this crosse.
    But here's the ioy, my friend and I are one;
    Sweete flattery, then she loues but me alone.

---

<resetnum/>That thou hast her it is not all my grief,
And yet it may be said I loved her dearly;
That she hath thee is of my wailing chief,
A loss in love that touches me more nearly.
Loving offenders, thus I will excuse ye:
Thou dost love her, because thou know'st I love her,
And for my sake even so doth she abuse me,
Suff'ring my friend for my sake to approve her;
If I lose thee, my loss is my love's gain,
And losing her, my friend hath found that loss;
Both find each other, and I lose both twain,
And both for my sake lay on me this cross.
    But here's the joy, my friend and I are one;
    Sweet flattery, then she loves but me alone.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0043">
<head>
   <title>43</title>
   <toctitle>43 (When most I winke, then doe mine eyes best see)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When most I winke, then doe mine eyes best see</indextitle>
   <firstline>When most I winke, then doe mine eyes best see</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>11 thy] their</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When most I winke, then doe mine eyes best see,
For all the day they view things vnrespected,
But when I sleepe, in dreames they looke on thee,
And darkely bright, are bright in darke directed.
Then thou whose shaddow shaddowes doth make bright,
How would thy shadowes forme forme happy show
To the cleere day with thy much cleerer light,
When to vn-seeing eyes thy shade shines so?
How would (I say) mine eyes be blessed made
By looking on thee in the liuing day,
When in dead night thy faire imperfect shade
Through heauy sleepe on sightlesse eyes doth stay?
    All dayes are nights to see till I see thee,
    And nights bright daies when dreams do shew thee me.

---

<resetnum/>When most I wink, then do mine eyes best see,
For all the day they view things unrespected,
But when I sleep, in dreams they look on thee,
And darkly bright, are bright in dark directed.
Then thou whose shadow shadows doth make bright,
How would thy shadow's form form happy show
To the clear day with thy much clearer light,
When to unseeing eyes thy shade shines so?
How would, I say, mine eyes be blessed made
By looking on thee in the living day,
When in dead night thy fair imperfect shade
Through heavy sleep on sightless eyes doth stay?
    All days are nights to see till I see thee,
    And nights bright days when dreams do show thee me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0044">
<head>
   <title>44</title>
   <toctitle>44 (If the dull substance of my flesh were thought)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>If the dull substance of my flesh were thought</indextitle>
   <firstline>If the dull substance of my flesh were thought</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
If the dull substance of my flesh were thought,
Iniurious distance should not stop my way,
For then, dispight of space, I would be brought
From limits farre remote, where thou doost stay;
No matter then although my foote did stand
Vpon the farthest earth remoou'd from thee,
For nimble thought can iumpe both sea and land
As soone as thinke the place where he would be.
But ah, thought kills me that I am not thought,
To leape large lengths of miles when thou art gone,
But that so much of earth and water wrought,
I must attend times leasure with my mone.
    Receiuing naughts by elements so sloe
    But heauie teares, badges of eithers woe.

---

<resetnum/>If the dull substance of my flesh were thought,
Injurious distance should not stop my way,
For then, despite of space, I would be brought
From limits far remote, where thou dost stay;
No matter then although my foot did stand
Upon the farthest earth removed from thee,
For nimble thought can jump both sea and land
As soon as think the place where he would be.
But ah, thought kills me that I am not thought,
To leap large lengths of miles when thou art gone,
But that so much of earth and water wrought,
I must attend time's leisure with my moan.
    Receiving naughts by elements so slow
    But heavy tears, badges of either's woe.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0045">
<head>
   <title>45</title>
   <toctitle>45 (The other two, slight ayre, and purging fire)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The other two, slight ayre, and purging fire</indextitle>
   <firstline>The other two, slight ayre, and purging fire</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>12 thy] their</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
The other two, slight ayre, and purging fire,
Are both with thee, where euer I abide:
The first my thought, the other my desire,
These present absent with swift motion slide;
For when these quicker Elements are gone
In tender Embassie of loue to thee,
My life being made of foure, with two alone
Sinkes downe to death, opprest with melancholie,
Vntill liues composition be recured
By those swift messengers return'd from thee,
Who euen but now come back againe assured
Of thy faire health, recounting it to me.
    This told, I ioy, but then no longer glad,
    I send them back againe and straight grow sad.

---

<resetnum/>The other two, slight air, and purging fire,
Are both with thee, wherever I abide;
The first my thought, the other my desire,
These present absent with swift motion slide;
For when these quicker elements are gone
In tender embassy of love to thee,
My life, being made of four, with two alone
Sinks down to death, oppressed with melancholy,
Until life's composition be recured
By those swift messengers returned from thee,
Who even but now come back again assured
Of thy fair health, recounting it to me.
    This told, I joy, but then no longer glad,
    I send them back again and straight grow sad.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0046">
<head>
   <title>46</title>
   <toctitle>46 (Mine eye and heart are at a mortall warre)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Mine eye and heart are at a mortall warre</indextitle>
   <firstline>Mine eye and heart are at a mortall warre</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>3,8,13,14 thy] their</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Mine eye and heart are at a mortall warre
How to deuide the conquest of thy sight;
Mine eye, my heart thy pictures sight would barre,
My heart, mine eye the freedome of that right,
My heart doth plead that thou in him doost lye,
(A closet neuer pearst with christall eyes)
But the defendant doth that plea deny,
And sayes in him thy faire appearance lyes.
To side this title is impannelled
A quest of thoughts, all tennants to the heart,
And by their verdict is determined
The cleere eyes moyitie, and the deare hearts part.
    As thus, mine eyes due is thy outward part,
    And my hearts right, thy inward loue of heart.

---

<resetnum/>Mine eye and heart are at a mortal war
How to divide the conquest of thy sight;
Mine eye, my heart thy picture's sight would bar,
My heart, mine eye the freedom of that right,
My heart doth plead that thou in him dost lie,
A closet never pierced with crystal eyes;
But the defendant doth that plea deny,
And says in him thy fair appearance lies.
To 'cide this title is empanelled
A quest of thoughts, all tenants to the heart,
And by their verdict is determined
The clear eye's moiety, and the dear heart's part.
    As thus, mine eye's due is thy outward part,
    And my heart's right, thy inward love of heart.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0047">
<head>
   <title>47</title>
   <toctitle>47 (Betwixt mine eye and heart a league is tooke)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Betwixt mine eye and heart a league is tooke</indextitle>
   <firstline>Betwixt mine eye and heart a league is tooke</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>10 Thy selfe ... art] Thy seife ... are<br/>11 noe] nor</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Betwixt mine eye and heart a league is tooke,
And each doth good turnes now vnto the other;
When that mine eye is famisht for a looke,
Or heart in loue with sighes himselfe doth smother;
With my loues picture then my eye doth feast,
And to the painted banquet bids my heart;
An other time mine eye is my hearts guest,
And in his thoughts of loue doth share a part.
So either by thy picture or my loue,
Thy selfe away, art present still with me,
For thou noe farther then my thoughts canst moue,
And I am still with them, and they with thee;
    Or if they sleepe, thy picture in my sight
    Awakes my heart to hearts and eyes delight.

---

<resetnum/>Betwixt mine eye and heart a league is took,
And each doth good turns now unto the other;
When that mine eye is famished for a look,
Or heart in love with sighs himself doth smother,
With my love's picture then my eye doth feast,
And to the painted banquet bids my heart;
Another time mine eye is my heart's guest,
And in his thoughts of love doth share a part.
So either by thy picture or my love,
Thyself away, art present still with me,
For thou no further than my thoughts canst move,
And I am still with them and they with thee;
    Or if they sleep, thy picture in my sight
    Awakes my heart to heart's and eye's delight.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0048">
<head>
   <title>48</title>
   <toctitle>48 (How carefull was I when I tooke my way)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How carefull was I when I tooke my way</indextitle>
   <firstline>How carefull was I when I tooke my way</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
How carefull was I when I tooke my way,
Each trifle vnder truest barres to thrust,
That to my vse it might vn-vsed stay
From hands of falsehood, in sure wards of trust;
But thou, to whom my iewels trifles are,
Most worthy comfort, now my greatest griefe,
Thou best of deerest, and mine onely care,
Art left the prey of euery vulgar theefe.
Thee haue I not lockt vp in any chest,
Saue where thou art not, though I feele thou art,
Within the gentle closure of my brest,
From whence at pleasure thou maist come and part;
    And euen thence thou wilt be stolne I feare,
    For truth prooues theeuish for a prize so deare.

---

<resetnum/>How careful was I when I took my way,
Each trifle under truest bars to thrust,
That to my use it might unused stay
From hands of falsehood, in sure wards of trust;
But thou, to whom my jewels trifles are,
Most worthy comfort, now my greatest grief,
Thou best of dearest, and mine only care,
Art left the prey of every vulgar thief.
Thee have I not locked up in any chest,
Save where thou art not, though I feel thou art,
Within the gentle closure of my breast,
From whence at pleasure thou mayst come and part;
    And even thence thou wilt be stol'n, I fear,
    For truth proves thievish for a prize so dear.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0049">
<head>
   <title>49</title>
   <toctitle>49 (Against that time (if euer that time come))</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Against that time (if euer that time come)</indextitle>
   <firstline>Against that time (if euer that time come)</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Against that time (if euer that time come)
When I shall see thee frowne on my defects,
When as thy loue hath cast his vtmost summe,
Cauld to that audite by aduis'd respects;
Against that time when thou shalt strangely passe,
And scarcely greete me with that sunne thine eye,
When loue conuerted from the thing it was
Shall reasons finde of setled grauitie;
Against that time do I insconce me here
Within the knowledge of mine own desart,
And this my hand, against my selfe vpreare,
To guard the lawfull reasons on thy part;
    To leaue poore me, thou hast the strength of lawes,
    Since why to loue, I can alledge no cause.

---

<resetnum/>Against that time, if ever that time come,
When I shall see thee frown on my defects,
Whenas thy love hath cast his utmost sum,
Called to that audit by advised respects;
Against that time when thou shalt strangely pass,
And scarcely greet me with that sun thine eye,
When love converted from the thing it was
Shall reasons find of settled gravity;
Against that time do I ensconce me here
Within the knowledge of mine own desert,
And this my hand against myself uprear,
To guard the lawful reasons on thy part;
    To leave poor me, thou hast the strength of laws,
    Since why to love, I can allege no cause.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0050">
<head>
   <title>50</title>
   <toctitle>50 (How heauie doe I iourney on the way)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How heauie doe I iourney on the way</indextitle>
   <firstline>How heauie doe I iourney on the way</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>6 duly <i>er muligvis en fejl for</i> dully, <i>hvis da ikke begge læsemåder er gyldige</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
How heauie doe I iourney on the way,
When what I seeke (my wearie trauels end)
Doth teach that ease and that repose to say,
Thus farre the miles are measurde from thy friend.
The beast that beares me, tired with my woe,
Plods duly on, to beare that waight in me,
As if by some instinct the wretch did know
His rider lou'd not speed being made from thee;
The bloody spurre cannot prouoke him on
That some-times anger thrusts into his hide,
Which heauily he answers with a grone,
More sharpe to me then spurring to his side,
    For that same grone doth put this in my mind,
    My greefe lies onward and my ioy behind.

---

<resetnum/>How heavy do I journey on the way,
When what I seek, my weary travel's end,
Doth teach that ease and that repose to say,
,,Thus far the miles are measured from thy friend.''
The beast that bears me, tired with my woe,
Plods dully on, to bear that weight in me,
As if by some instinct the wretch did know
His rider loved not speed being made from thee;
The bloody spur cannot provoke him on
That sometimes anger thrusts into his hide,
Which heavily he answers with a groan,
More sharp to me than spurring to his side,
    For that same groan doth put this in my mind,
    My grief lies onward and my joy behind.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0051">
<head>
   <title>51</title>
   <toctitle>51 (Thus can my loue excuse the slow offence)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thus can my loue excuse the slow offence</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thus can my love excuse the slow offence</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>3 should] shoulld<br/>10 perfectst] perfects</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thus can my loue excuse the slow offence
Of my dull bearer, when from thee I speed;
From where thou art, why should I hast me thence?
Till I returne, of posting is noe need.
O what excuse will my poore beast then find,
When swift extremity can seeme but slow?
Then should I spurre though mounted on the wind;
In winged speed no motion shall I know;
Then can no horse with my desire keepe pace;
Therefore desire (of perfectst loue being made)
Shall naigh noe dull flesh in his fiery race,
But loue, for loue, thus shall excuse my iade:
    Since from thee going, he went wilfull slow,
    Towards thee ile run, and giue him leaue to goe.

---

<resetnum/>Thus can my love excuse the slow offence
Of my dull bearer, when from thee I speed;
From where thou art, why should I haste me thence?
Till I return, of posting is no need.
O what excuse will my poor beast then find,
When swift extremity can seem but slow?
Then should I spur, though mounted on the wind;
In winged speed no motion shall I know;
Then can no horse with my desire keep pace;
Therefore desire, of perfect'st love being made,
Shall neigh no dull flesh in his fiery race,
But love, for love, thus shall excuse my jade:
    Since from thee going he went wilful slow,
    Towards thee I'll run, and give him leave to go.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0052">
<head>
   <title>52</title>
   <toctitle>52 (So am I as the rich whose blessed key)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>So am I as the rich whose blessed key</indextitle>
   <firstline>So am I as the rich whose blessed key</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
So am I as the rich whose blessed key
Can bring him to his sweet vp-locked treasure,
The which he will not eu'ry hower suruay,
For blunting the fine point of seldome pleasure.
Therefore are feasts so sollemne and so rare,
Since sildom comming in the long yeare set,
Like stones of worth they thinly placed are,
Or captaine Iewells in the carconet.
So is the time that keepes you as my chest,
Or as the ward-robe which the robe doth hide,
To make some speciall instant speciall blest,
By new vnfoulding his imprison'd pride.
    Blessed are you whose worthinesse giues skope,
    Being had to tryumph, being lackt to hope.

---

<resetnum/>So am I as the rich whose blessed key
Can bring him to his sweet up-locked treasure,
The which he will not every hour survey,
For blunting the fine point of seldom pleasure.
Therefore are feasts so solemn and so rare,
Since seldom coming in the long year set,
Like stones of worth they thinly placed are,
Or captain jewels in the carcanet.
So is the time that keeps you as my chest,
Or as the wardrobe which the robe doth hide,
To make some special instant special blessed,
By new unfolding his imprisoned pride.
    Blessed are you whose worthiness gives scope,
    Being had to triumph, being lacked to hope.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0053">
<head>
   <title>53</title>
   <toctitle>53 (What is your substance, whereof are you made)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>What is your substance, whereof are you made</indextitle>
   <firstline>What is your substance, whereof are you made</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
What is your substance, whereof are you made,
That millions of strange shaddowes on you tend?
Since euery one hath euery one one shade,
And you, but one, can euery shaddow lend;
Describe <i>Adonis</i>, and the counterfet
Is poorely immitated after you;
On <i>Hellens</i> cheeke all art of beautie set,
And you in <i>Grecian</i> tires are painted new;
Speake of the spring, and foyzon of the yeare,
The one doth shaddow of your beautie show,
The other as your bountie doth appeare,
And you in euery blessed shape we know.
    In all externall grace you haue some part,
    But you like none, none you, for constant heart.

---

<resetnum/>What is your substance, whereof are you made,
That millions of strange shadows on you tend?
Since every one hath every one one shade,
And you, but one, can every shadow lend;
Describe Adonis, and the counterfeit
Is poorly imitated after you;
On Helen's cheek all art of beauty set,
And you in Grecian tires are painted new;
Speak of the spring, and foison of the year,
The one doth shadow of your beauty show,
The other as your bounty doth appear,
And you in every blessed shape we know.
    In all external grace you have some part,
    But you like none, none you, for constant heart.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0054">
<head>
   <title>54</title>
   <toctitle>54 (Oh how much more doth beautie beautious seeme)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Oh how much more doth beautie beautious seeme</indextitle>
   <firstline>Oh how much more doth beautie beautious seeme</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Oh how much more doth beautie beautious seeme
By that sweet ornament which truth doth giue;
The Rose lookes faire, but fairer we it deeme
For that sweet odor, which doth in it liue;
The Canker bloomes haue full as deepe a die
As the perfumed tincture of the Roses,
Hang on such thornes, and play as wantonly,
When sommers breath their masked buds discloses;
But for their virtue only is their show,
They liue vnwoo'd, and vnrespected fade,
Die to themselues. Sweet Roses doe not so,
Of their sweet deathes, are sweetest odors made:
    And so of you, beautious and louely youth,
    When that shall vade, by verse distils your truth.

---

<resetnum/>O how much more doth beauty beauteous seem
By that sweet ornament which truth doth give;
The rose looks fair, but fairer we it deem
For that sweet odour which doth in it live;
The canker blooms have full as deep a dye
As the perfumed tincture of the roses,
Hang on such thorns, and play as wantonly,
When summer's breath their masked buds discloses;
But for their virtue only is their show,
They live unwooed, and unrespected fade,
Die to themselves. Sweet roses do not so,
Of their sweet deaths are sweetest odours made;
    And so of you, beauteous and lovely youth,
    When that shall vade, by verse distils your truth.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0055">
<head>
   <title>55</title>
   <toctitle>55 (Not marble, nor the guilded monuments)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Not marble, nor the guilded monuments</indextitle>
   <firstline>Not marble, nor the guilded monuments</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>1 monuments] <biblio>Malone</biblio>; monument <biblio>Q</biblio><br/>9 enmity] emnity</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Not marble, nor the guilded monuments
Of Princes shall out-liue this powrefull rime,
But you shall shine more bright in these contents
Then vnswept stone, besmeer'd with sluttish time.
When wastefull warre shall <i>Statues</i> ouer-turne,
And broiles roote out the worke of masonry,
Nor <i>Mars</i> his sword, nor warres quick fire shall burne
The liuing record of your memory.
Gainst death and all obliuious enmity
Shall you pace forth, your praise shall stil finde roome,
Euen in the eyes of all posterity
That weare this world out to the ending doome.
    So til the iudgement that your selfe arise,
    You liue in this, and dwell in louers eies.

---

<resetnum/>Not marble, nor the gilded monuments
Of princes shall outlive this powerful rhyme,
But you shall shine more bright in these contents
Than unswept stone, besmeared with sluttish time.
When wasteful war shall statues overturn
And broils root out the work of masonry,
Nor Mars his sword, nor war's quick fire, shall burn
The living record of your memory.
'Gainst death and all oblivious enmity
Shall you pace forth, your praise shall still find room,
Even in the eyes of all posterity
That wear this world out to the ending doom.
    So till the judgment that yourself arise,
    You live in this, and dwell in lovers' eyes.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0056">
<head>
   <title>56</title>
   <toctitle>56 (Sweet loue renew thy force, be it not said)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sweet loue renew thy force, be it not said</indextitle>
   <firstline>Sweet loue renew thy force, be it not said</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>13 Or] As<br/>14 Sommers] Sômers</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Sweet loue renew thy force, be it not said
Thy edge should blunter be then apetite,
Which but too daie by feeding is alaied,
To morrow sharpned in his former might.
So loue be thou, although too daie thou fill
Thy hungrie eies, euen till they winck with fulnesse,
Too morrow see againe, and doe not kill
The spirit of Loue with a perpetual dulnesse:
Let this sad <i>Intrim</i> like the Ocean be
Which parts the shore, where two contracted new
Come daily to the banckes, that when they see
Returne of loue, more blest may be the view;
    Or cal it Winter, which being ful of care,
    Makes Sommers welcome, thrice more wish'd, more rare.

---

<resetnum/>Sweet love, renew thy force, be it not said
Thy edge should blunter be than appetite,
Which but today by feeding is allayed,
Tomorrow sharpened in his former might;
So, love, be thou, although today thou fill
Thy hungry eyes even till they wink with fullness,
Tomorrow see again, and do not kill
The spirit of love with a perpetual dullness;
Let this sad interim like the ocean be
Which parts the shore, where two contracted new
Come daily to the banks, that when they see
Return of love, more blessed may be the view;
    Or call it winter, which being full of care,
    Makes summer's welcome thrice more wished, more rare.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0057">
<head>
   <title>57</title>
   <toctitle>57 (Being your slaue what should I doe but tend)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Being your slaue what should I doe but tend</indextitle>
   <firstline>Being your slaue what should I doe but tend</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Being your slaue what should I doe but tend,
Vpon the houres, and times of your desire?
I haue no precious time at al to spend,
Nor seruices to doe til you require;
Nor dare I chide the world without end houre,
Whilst I (my soueraine) watch the clock for you,
Nor thinke the bitternesse of absence sowre
When you haue bid your seruant once adieue;
Nor dare I question with my iealious thought
Where you may be, or your affaires suppose,
But like a sad slaue stay and thinke of nought,
Saue where you are, how happy you make those.
    So true a foole is loue, that in your Will,
    (Though you doe any thing) he thinkes no ill.

---

<resetnum/>Being your slave, what should I do but tend
Upon the hours and times of your desire?
I have no precious time at all to spend,
Nor services to do till you require;
Nor dare I chide the world-without-end hour
Whilst I, my sovereign, watch the clock for you,
Nor think the bitterness of absence sour
When you have bid your servant once adieu;
Nor dare I question with my jealous thought
Where you may be, or your affairs suppose,
But like a sad slave stay and think of naught,
Save, where you are, how happy you make those.
    So true a fool is love, that in your will,
    Though you do anything, he thinks no ill.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0058">
<head>
   <title>58</title>
   <toctitle>58 (That God forbid, that made me first your slaue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That God forbid, that made me first your slaue</indextitle>
   <firstline>That God forbid, that made me first your slaue</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
That God forbid, that made me first your slaue,
I should in thought controule your times of pleasure,
Or at your hand th' account of houres to craue,
Being your vassail bound to staie your leisure.
Oh let me suffer (being at your beck)
Th' imprison'd absence of your libertie,
And patience tame, to sufferance bide each check,
Without accusing you of iniury.
Be where you list, your charter is so strong,
That you your selfe may priuiledge your time
To what you will, to you it doth belong,
Your selfe to pardon of selfe-doing crime.
    I am to waite, though waiting so be hell,
    Not blame your pleasure be it ill or well.

---

<resetnum/>That god forbid, that made me first your slave,
I should in thought control your times of pleasure,
Or at your hand th'account of hours to crave,
Being your vassal bound to stay your leisure.
O let me suffer, being at your beck,
Th'imprisoned absence of your liberty,
And patience tame, to sufferance bide each check,
Without accusing you of injury.
Be where you list, your charter is so strong,
That you yourself may privilege your time
To what you will, to you it doth belong
Yourself to pardon of self-doing crime.
    I am to wait, though waiting so be hell,
    Not blame your pleasure be it ill or well.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0059">
<head>
   <title>59</title>
   <toctitle>59 (If there bee nothing new, but that which is)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>If there bee nothing new, but that which is</indextitle>
   <firstline>If there bee nothing new, but that which is</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>1 there] their</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
If there bee nothing new, but that which is,
Hath beene before, how are our braines beguild,
Which laboring for inuention beare amisse
The second burthen of a former child?
Oh that record could with a back-ward looke,
Euen of fiue hundreth courses of the Sunne,
Show me your image in some antique booke,
Since minde at first in carrecter was done,
That I might see what the old world could say
To this composed wonder of your frame;
Whether we are mended, or where better they,
Or whether reuolution be the same.
    Oh sure I am the wits of former daies
    To subiects worse haue giuen admiring praise.

---

<resetnum/>If there be nothing new, but that which is
Hath been before, how are our brains beguiled,
Which labouring for invention, bear amiss
The second burden of a former child?
O that record could with a backward look,
Even of five hundred courses of the sun,
Show me your image in some antique book,
Since mind at first in character was done,
That I might see what the old world could say
To this composed wonder of your frame;
Whether we are mended, or where better they,
Or whether revolution be the same.
    O sure I am the wits of former days
    To subjects worse have given admiring praise.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0060">
<head>
   <title>60</title>
   <toctitle>60 (Like as the waues make towards the pibled shore)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Like as the waues make towards the pibled shore</indextitle>
   <firstline>Like as the waues make towards the pibled shore</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Like as the waues make towards the pibled shore,
So do our minuites hasten to their end,
Each changing place with that which goes before,
In sequent toile all forwards do contend.
Natiuity, once in the maine of light,
Crawles to maturity, wherewith being crown'd,
Crooked eclipses gainst his glory fight,
And time that gaue, doth now his gift confound.
Time doth transfixe the florish set on youth,
And delues the paralels in beauties brow,
Feedes on the rarities of natures truth,
And nothing stands but for his sieth to mow.
    And yet to times in hope, my verse shall stand
    Praising thy worth, dispight his cruell hand.

---

<resetnum/>Like as the waves make towards the pebbled shore,
So do our minutes hasten to their end,
Each changing place with that which goes before,
In sequent toil all forwards do contend.
Nativity, once in the main of light,
Crawls to maturity, wherewith being crowned
Crooked eclipses 'gainst his glory fight,
And time that gave doth now his gift confound.
Time doth transfix the flourish set on youth,
And delves the parallels in beauty's brow,
Feeds on the rarities of nature's truth,
And nothing stands but for his scythe to mow.
    And yet to times in hope my verse shall stand,
    Praising thy worth, despite his cruel hand.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0061">
<head>
   <title>61</title>
   <toctitle>61 (Is it thy wil, thy Image should keepe open)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Is it thy wil, thy Image should keepe open</indextitle>
   <firstline>Is it thy wil, thy Image should keepe open</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Is it thy wil, thy Image should keepe open
My heauy eielids to the weary night?
Dost thou desire my slumbers should be broken,
While shadowes like to thee do mocke my sight?
Is it thy spirit that thou send'st from thee
So farre from home into my deeds to prye,
To find out shames and idle houres in me,
The skope and tenure of thy Ielousie?
O no, thy loue, though much, is not so great;
It is my loue that keepes mine eie awake,
Mine owne true loue that doth my rest defeat,
To plaie the watch-man euer for thy sake.
    For thee watch I, whilst thou dost wake elsewhere,
    From me farre of, with others all to neere.

---

<resetnum/>Is it thy will thy image should keep open
My heavy eyelids to the weary night?
Dost thou desire my slumbers should be broken,
While shadows like to thee do mock my sight?
Is it thy spirit that thou send'st from thee
So far from home into my deeds to pry,
To find out shames and idle hours in me,
The scope and tenor of thy jealousy?
O no, thy love, though much, is not so great;
It is my love that keeps mine eye awake,
Mine own true love that doth my rest defeat,
To play the watchman ever for thy sake.
    For thee watch I, whilst thou dost wake elsewhere,
    From me far off, with others all too near.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0062">
<head>
   <title>62</title>
   <toctitle>62 (Sinne of selfe-loue possesseth al mine eie)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sinne of selfe-loue possesseth al mine eie</indextitle>
   <firstline>Sinne of selfe-loue possesseth al mine eie</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>13 Tis] T'is</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Sinne of selfe-loue possesseth al mine eie,
And all my soule, and al my euery part;
And for this sinne there is no remedie,
It is so grounded inward in my heart.
Me thinkes no face so gratious is as mine,
No shape so true, no truth of such account,
And for my selfe mine owne worth do define,
As I all other in all worths surmount.
But when my glasse shewes me my selfe indeed,
Beated and chopt with tand antiquitie,
Mine owne selfe loue quite contrary I read;
Selfe, so selfe louing, were iniquity;
    Tis thee (my selfe) that for my selfe I praise,
    Painting my age with beauty of thy daies.

---

<resetnum/>Sin of self-love possesseth all mine eye,
And all my soul, and all my every part;
And for this sin there is no remedy,
It is so grounded inward in my heart.
Methinks no face so gracious is as mine,
No shape so true, no truth of such account,
And for myself mine own worth do define,
As I all other in all worths surmount.
But when my glass shows me myself indeed,
Beated and chopped with tanned antiquity,
Mine own self-love quite contrary I read;
Self, so self-loving, were iniquity;
    'Tis thee, myself, that for myself I praise,
    Painting my age with beauty of thy days.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0063">
<head>
   <title>63</title>
   <toctitle>63 (Against my loue shall be as I am now)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Against my loue shall be as I am now</indextitle>
   <firstline>Against my loue shall be as I am now</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Against my loue shall be as I am now
With times iniurious hand chrusht and ore-worne,
When houres haue dreind his blood and fild his brow
With lines and wrincles, when his youthfull morne
Hath trauaild on to Ages steepie night,
And all those beauties whereof now he's King
Are vanishing, or vanisht out of sight,
Stealing away the treasure of his Spring;
For such a time do I now fortifie
Against confounding Ages cruell knife,
That he shall neuer cut from memory
My sweet loues beauty, though my louers life.
    His beautie shall in these blacke lines be seene,
    And they shall liue, and he in them still greene.

---

<resetnum/>Against my love shall be as I am now,
With time's injurious hand crushed and o'erworn,
When hours have drained his blood and filled his brow
With lines and wrinkles, when his youthful morn
Hath travailed on to age's steepy night,
And all those beauties whereof now he's king
Are vanishing, or vanished out of sight,
Stealing away the treasure of his spring;
For such a time do I now fortify
Against confounding age's cruel knife,
That he shall never cut from memory
My sweet love's beauty, though my lover's life.
    His beauty shall in these black lines be seen,
    And they shall live, and he in them still green.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0064">
<head>
   <title>64</title>
   <toctitle>64 (When I haue seene by times fell hand defaced)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When I haue seene by times fell hand defaced</indextitle>
   <firstline>When I haue seene by times fell hand defaced</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When I haue seene by times fell hand defaced
The rich proud cost of outworne buried age;
When sometime loftie towers I see downe rased,
And brasse eternall slaue to mortall rage;
When I haue seene the hungry Ocean gaine
Aduantage on the Kingdome of the shoare,
And the firme soile win of the watry maine,
Increasing store with losse, and losse with store.
When I haue seene such interchange of state,
Or state it selfe confounded, to decay,
Ruine hath taught me thus to ruminate,
That Time will come and take my loue away.
    This thought is as a death which cannot choose
    But weepe to haue that which it feares to loose.

---

<resetnum/>When I have seen by time's fell hand defaced
The rich proud cost of outworn buried age;
When sometime lofty towers I see down razed,
And brass eternal slave to mortal rage;
When I have seen the hungry ocean gain
Advantage on the kingdom of the shore,
And the firm soil win of the wat'ry main,
Increasing store with loss, and loss with store;
When I have seen such interchange of state,
Or state itself confounded, to decay,
Ruin hath taught me thus to ruminate,
That time will come and take my love away.
    This thought is as a death, which cannot choose
    But weep to have that which it fears to lose.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0065">
<head>
   <title>65</title>
   <toctitle>65 (Since brasse, nor stone, nor earth, nor boundlesse sea)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Since brasse, nor stone, nor earth, nor boundlesse sea</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since brasse, nor stone, nor earth, nor boundlesse sea</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>12 ore] or; of</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Since brasse, nor stone, nor earth, nor boundlesse sea,
But sad mortallity ore-swaies their power,
How with this rage shall beautie hold a plea,
Whose action is no stronger then a flower?
O how shall summers hunny breath hold out
Against the wrackfull siedge of battring dayes,
When rocks impregnable are not so stoute,
Nor gates of steele so strong but time decayes?
O fearefull meditation; where, alack,
Shall times best Iewell from times chest lie hid?
Or what strong hand can hold his swift foote back,
Or who his spoile ore beautie can forbid?
    O none, vnlesse this miracle haue might,
    That in black inck my loue may still shine bright.

---

<resetnum/>Since brass, nor stone, nor earth, nor boundless sea,
But sad mortality o'er-sways their power,
How with this rage shall beauty hold a plea,
Whose action is no stronger than a flower?
O how shall summer's honey breath hold out
Against the wrackful siege of batt'ring days,
When rocks impregnable are not so stout,
Nor gates of steel so strong but time decays?
O fearful meditation; where, alack,
Shall time's best jewel from time's chest lie hid?
Or what strong hand can hold his swift foot back,
Or who his spoil o'er beauty can forbid?
    O none, unless this miracle have might,
    That in black ink my love may still shine bright.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0066">
<head>
   <title>66</title>
   <toctitle>66 (Tyr'd with all these for restfull death I cry)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Tyr'd with all these for restfull death I cry</indextitle>
   <firstline>Tyr'd with all these for restfull death I cry</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Tyr'd with all these for restfull death I cry,
As to behold desert a begger borne,
And needie Nothing trimd in iollitie,
And purest faith vnhappily forsworne,
And gilded honor shamefully misplast,
And maiden vertue rudely strumpeted,
And right perfection wrongfully disgrac'd,
And strength by limping sway disabled,
And arte made tung-tide by authoritie,
And Folly (Doctor-like) controuling skill,
And simple-Truth miscalde Simplicitie,
And captiue-good attending Captaine ill.
    Tyr'd with all these, from these would I be gone,
    Saue that to dye, I leaue my loue alone.

---

<resetnum/>Tired with all these for restful death I cry,
As to behold desert a beggar born,
And needy nothing trimmed in jollity,
And purest faith unhappily forsworn,
And guilded honour shamefully misplaced,
And maiden virtue rudely strumpeted,
And right perfection wrongfully disgraced,
And strength by limping sway disabled,
And art made tongue-tied by authority,
And folly, doctor-like, controlling skill,
And simple truth miscalled simplicity,
And captive good attending captain ill.
    Tired with all these, from these would I be gone,
    Save that to die, I leave my love alone.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0067">
<head>
   <title>67</title>
   <toctitle>67 (Ah, wherefore with infection should he liue)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Ah, wherefore with infection should he liue</indextitle>
   <firstline>Ah, wherefore with infection should he liue</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>6 seeing] <biblio>Q</biblio>; seeming <biblio>Oxf</biblio> 12 proud] <biblio>Q</biblio>; prov'd <biblio>Capell</biblio>; 'prived <biblio>Kerrigan</biblio></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Ah, wherefore with infection should he liue,
And with his presence grace impietie,
That sinne by him aduantage should atchiue,
And lace it selfe with his societie?
Why should false painting immitate his cheeke,
And steale dead seeing of his liuing hew?
Why should poore beautie indirectly seeke
Roses of shaddow, since his Rose is true?
Why should he liue, now nature banckrout is,
Beggerd of blood to blush through liuely vaines?
For she hath no exchecker now but his,
And proud of many, liues vpon his gaines.
    O him she stores, to show what welth she had,
    In daies long since, before these last so bad.

---

<resetnum/>Ah, wherefore with infection should he live,
And with his presence grace impiety,
That sin by him advantage should achieve,
And lace itself with his society?
Why should false painting imitate his cheek,
And steal dead seeing of his living hue?
Why should poor beauty indirectly seek
Roses of shadow, since his rose is true?
Why should he live, now nature bankrupt is,
Beggared of blood to blush through lively veins?
For she hath no exchequer now but his,
And proud of many, lives upon his gains.
    O him she stores, to show what wealth she had,
    In days long since, before these last so bad.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0068">
<head>
   <title>68</title>
   <toctitle>68 (Thus is his cheeke the map of daies out-worne)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thus is his cheeke the map of daies out-worne</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thus is his cheeke the map of daies out-worne</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>2 dy'd] dy'ed<br/>7 second] scond</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thus is his cheeke the map of daies out-worne,
When beauty liu'd and dy'd as flowers do now,
Before these bastard signes of faire were borne,
Or durst inhabit on a liuing brow;
Before the goulden tresses of the dead,
The right of sepulchers, were shorne away,
To liue a second life on second head,
Ere beauties dead fleece made another gay:
In him those holy antique howers are seene,
Without all ornament, it selfe and true,
Making no summer of an others greene,
Robbing no ould to dresse his beauty new;
    And him as for a map doth Nature store,
    To shew faulse Art what beauty was of yore.

---

<resetnum/>Thus is his cheek the map of days outworn,
When beauty lived and died as flowers do now,
Before the bastard signs of fair were born,
Or durst inhabit on a living brow;
Before the golden tresses of the dead,
The right of sepulchres, were shorn away,
To live a second life on second head,
Ere beauty's dead fleece made another gay:
In him those holy antique hours are seen,
Without all ornament, itself and true,
Making no summer of another's green,
Robbing no old to dress his beauty new;
    And him as for a map doth nature store,
    To show false art what beauty was of yore.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0069">
<head>
   <title>69</title>
   <toctitle>69 (Those parts of thee that the worlds eye doth view)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Those parts of thee that the worlds eye doth view</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those parts of thee that the worlds eye doth view</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>3 due] end<br/>5 Thy] Their<br/>14 soyle] solye</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Those parts of thee that the worlds eye doth view
Want nothing that the thought of hearts can mend;
All toungs (the voice of soules) giue thee that due,
Vttring bare truth, euen so as foes Commend.
Thy outward thus with outward praise is crownd,
But those same toungs that giue thee so thine owne,
In other accents doe this praise confound,
By seeing farther then the eye hath showne;
They looke into the beauty of thy mind,
And that in guesse they measure by thy deeds;
Then churls their thoughts (although their eies were kind)
To thy faire flower ad the rancke smell of weeds.
    But why thy odor matcheth not thy show,
    The soyle is this, that thou doest common grow.

---

<resetnum/>Those parts of thee that the world's eye doth view
Want nothing that the thought of hearts can mend;
All tongues, the voice of souls, give thee that due,
Utt'ring bare truth, even so as foes commend.
Thy outward thus with outward praise is crowned,
But those same tongues that give thee so thine own,
In other accents do this praise confound,
By seeing further than the eye hath shown;
They look into the beauty of thy mind,
And that in guess they measure by thy deeds;
Then churls their thoughts - although their eyes were kind -
To thy fair flower add the rank smell of weeds.
    But why thy odour matcheth not thy show,
    The soil is this, that thou dost common grow.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0070">
<head>
   <title>70</title>
   <toctitle>70 (That thou are blam'd shall not be thy defect)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That thou are blam'd shall not be thy defect</indextitle>
   <firstline>That thou are blam'd shall not be thy defect</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>6 Thy] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; Their <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
That thou are blam'd shall not be thy defect,
For slanders marke was euer yet the faire;
The ornament of beauty is suspect,
A Crow that flies in heauens sweetest ayre.
So thou be good, slander doth but approue
Thy worth the greater beeing woo'd of time;
For Canker vice the sweetest buds doth loue,
And thou present'st a pure vnstayined prime.
Thou hast past by the ambush of young daies,
Either not assayld, or victor beeing charg'd;
Yet this thy praise cannot be soe thy praise,
To tye vp enuy, euermore inlarged.
    If some suspect of ill maskt not thy show,
    Then thou alone kingdomes of hearts shouldst owe.

---

<resetnum/>That thou art blamed shall not be thy defect,
For slander's mark was ever yet the fair;
The ornament of beauty is suspect,
A crow that flies in heaven's sweetest air.
So thou be good, slander doth but approve
Thy worth the greater, being wooed of time;
For canker vice the sweetest buds doth love,
And thou present'st a pure unstained prime.
Thou hast passed by the ambush of young days,
Either not assailed, or victor, being charged;
Yet this thy praise cannot be so thy praise,
To tie up envy, evermore enlarged.
    If some suspect of ill masked not thy show,
    Then thou alone kingdoms of hearts shouldst owe.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0071">
<head>
   <title>71</title>
   <toctitle>71 (Noe Longer mourne for me when I am dead)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Noe Longer mourne for me when I am dead</indextitle>
   <firstline>Noe Longer mourne for me when I am dead</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Noe Longer mourne for me when I am dead
Then you shall heare the surly sullen bell
Giue warning to the world that I am fled
From this vile world with vildest wormes to dwell;
Nay, if you read this line, remember not
The hand that writ it, for I loue you so,
That I in your sweet thoughts would be forgot,
If thinking on me then should make you woe.
O if (I say) you looke vpon this verse,
When I (perhaps) compounded am with clay,
Do not so much as my poore name reherse,
But let your loue euen with my life decay;
    Least the wise world should looke into your mone,
    And mocke you with me after I am gon.

---

<resetnum/>No longer mourn for me when I am dead
Than you shall hear the surly sullen bell
Give warning to the world that I am fled
From this vile world, with vilest worms to dwell;
Nay, if you read this line, remember not
The hand that writ it, for I love you so,
That I in your sweet thoughts would be forgot,
If thinking on me then should make you woe.
O if, I say, you look upon this verse,
When I, perhaps, compounded am with clay,
Do not so much as my poor name rehearse,
But let your love even with my life decay;
    Lest the wise world should look into your moan,
    And mock you with me after I am gone.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0072">
<head>
   <title>72</title>
   <toctitle>72 (O Least the world should taske you to recite)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>O Least the world should taske you to recite</indextitle>
   <firstline>O Least the world should taske you to recite</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>3 forget] for get</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O Least the world should taske you to recite
What merit liu'd in me that you should loue
After my death (deare loue) forget me quite,
For you in me can nothing worthy proue;
Vnlesse you would deuise some vertuous lye,
To doe more for me then mine owne desert,
And hang more praise vpon deceased I
Then nigard truth would willingly impart;
O least your true loue may seeme falce in this,
That you for loue speake well of me vntrue,
My name be buried where my body is,
And liue no more to shame nor me, nor you.
    For I am shamd by that which I bring forth,
    And so should you, to loue things nothing worth.

---

<resetnum/>O, lest the world should task you to recite
What merit lived in me that you should love
After my death, dear love, forget me quite,
For you in me can nothing worthy prove;
Unless you would devise some virtuous lie,
To do more for me than mine own desert,
And hang more praise upon deceased I
Than niggard truth would willingly impart;
O, lest your true love may seem false in this,
That you for love speak well of me untrue,
My name be buried where my body is,
And live no more to shame nor me, nor you.
    For I am shamed by that which I bring forth,
    And so should you, to love things nothing worth.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0073">
<head>
   <title>73</title>
   <toctitle>73 (That time of yeeare thou maist in me behold)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>That time of yeeare thou maist in me behold</indextitle>
   <firstline>That time of yeeare thou maist in me behold</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>4 ruin'd] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; rn'wd <biblio>Q</biblio>; Barren'd of quires <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
That time of yeeare thou maist in me behold,
When yellow leaues, or none, or few doe hange
Vpon those boughes which shake against the could,
Bare ruin'd quiers, where late the sweet birds sang.
In me thou seest the twi-light of such day,
As after Sun-set fadeth in the West,
Which by and by blacke night doth take away,
Deaths second selfe that seals vp all in rest.
In me thou seest the glowing of such fire,
That on the ashes of his youth doth lye,
As the death bed, whereon it must expire,
Consum'd with that which it was nurrisht by.
    This thou perceu'st, which makes thy loue more strong,
    To loue that well, which thou must leaue ere long.

---

<resetnum/>That time of year thou mayst in me behold,
When yellow leaves, or none, or few, do hang
Upon those boughs which shake against the cold,
Bare ruined choirs, where late the sweet birds sang.
In me thou seest the twilight of such day,
As after sunset fadeth in the west,
Which by and by black night doth take away,
Death's second self, that seals up all in rest;
In me thou seest the glowing of such fire,
That on the ashes of his youth doth lie,
As the deathbed, whereon it must expire,
Consumed with that which it was nourished by.
    This thou perceiv'st, which makes thy love more strong,
    To love that well, which thou must leave ere long.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0074">
<head>
   <title>74</title>
   <toctitle>74 (But be contented when that fell arest)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>But be contented when that fell arest</indextitle>
   <firstline>But be contented when that fell arest</firstline>
   <!--
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-074.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-074b.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   -->
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
But be contented when that fell arest
With out all bayle shall carry me away,
My life hath in this line some interest,
Which for memoriall still with thee shall stay.
When thou reuewest this, thou doest reuew
The very part was consecrate to thee.
The earth can haue but earth, which is his due,
My spirit is thine the better part of me,
So then thou hast but lost the dregs of life,
The pray of wormes, my body being dead,
The coward conquest of a wretches knife,
To base of thee to be remembred.
    The worth of that, is that which it containes,
    And that is this, and this with thee remaines.

---

<resetnum/>But be contented when that fell arrest
Without all bail shall carry me away,
My life hath in this line some interest,
Which for memorial still with thee shall stay.
When thou reviewest this, thou dost review
The very part was consecrate to thee.
The earth can have but earth, which is his due,
My spirit is thine, the better part of me;
So then thou hast but lost the dregs of life,
The prey of worms, my body being dead,
The coward conquest of a wretch's knife,
Too base of thee to be remembered.
    The worth of that, is that which it contains,
    And that is this, and this with thee remains.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0075">
<head>
   <title>75</title>
   <toctitle>75 (So are you to my thoughts as food to life)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>So are you to my thoughts as food to life</indextitle>
   <firstline>So are you to my thoughts as food to life</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
So are you to my thoughts as food to life,
Or as sweet season'd shewers are to the ground;
And for the peace of you I hold such strife,
As twixt a miser and his wealth is found;
Now proud as an inioyer, and anon
Doubting the filching age will steale his treasure,
Now counting best to be with you alone,
Then betterd that the world may see my pleasure,<note>betterd] <biblio>Q</biblio>; better <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
Some-time all ful with feasting on your sight,
And by and by cleane starued for a looke,
Possessing or pursuing no delight
Saue what is had, or must from you be tooke.
    Thus do I pine and surfet day by day,
    Or gluttoning on all, or all away.

---

<resetnum/>So are you to my thoughts as food to life,
Or as sweet seasoned showers are to the ground;
And for the peace of you I hold such strife
As 'twixt a miser and his wealth is found;
Now proud as an enjoyer, and anon
Doubting the filching age will steal his treasure,
Now counting best to be with you alone,
Then bettered that the world may see my pleasure,
Sometime all full with feasting on your sight,
And by and by clean starved for a look,
Possessing or pursuing no delight
Save what is had, or must from you be took.
    Thus do I pine and surfeit day by day,
    Or gluttoning on all, or all away.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0076">
<head>
   <title>76</title>
   <toctitle>76 (Why is my verse so barren of new pride)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Why is my verse so barren of new pride</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why is my verse so barren of new pride</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Why is my verse so barren of new pride,
So far from variation or quicke change?
Why with the time do I not glance aside
To new found methods, and to compounds strange?
Why write I still all one, euer the same,
And keepe inuention in a noted weed,
That euery word doth almost tel my name,<note>tel] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; fel <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
Shewing their birth, and where they did proceed?
O know sweet loue I alwaies write of you,
And you and loue are still my argument;
So all my best is dressing old words new,
Spending againe what is already spent:
    For as the Sun is daily new and old,
    So is my loue still telling what is told.

---

<resetnum/>Why is my verse so barren of new pride,
So far from variation or quick change?
Why with the time do I not glance aside
To new-found methods and to compounds strange?
Why write I still all one, ever the same,
And keep invention in a noted weed,
That every word almost doth tell my name,
Showing their birth, and where they did proceed?
O know, sweet love, I always write of you,
And you and love are still my argument;
So all my best is dressing old words new,
Spending again what is already spent:
    For as the sun is daily new and old,
    So is my love still telling what is told.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0077">
<head>
   <title>77</title>
   <toctitle>77 (Thy glasse will shew thee how thy beauties were)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thy glasse will shew thee how thy beauties were</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thy glasse will shew thee how thy beauties were</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Thy glasse will shew thee how thy beauties were,
Thy dyall how thy pretious mynuits waste,
The vacant leaues thy mindes imprint will beare,<note>The] <biblio>Q</biblio>; These <biblio>Capell</biblio></note>
And of this booke, this learning maist thou taste.
The wrinckles which thy glasse will truly show,
Of mouthed graues will giue thee memorie,
Thou by thy dyals shady stealth maist know,
Times theeuish progresse to eternitie.
Looke what thy memorie cannot containe,
Commit to these waste blanks, and thou shalt finde<note>blanks] <biblio>Capell</biblio>; blacks <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
Those children nurst, deliuerd from thy braine,
To take a new acquaintance of thy minde.
    These offices, so oft as thou wilt looke,
    Shall profit thee, and much inrich thy booke.

---

<resetnum/>Thy glass will show thee how thy beauties wear,
Thy dial how thy precious minutes waste,
The vacant leaves thy mind's imprint will bear,
And of this book, this learning mayst thou taste:
The wrinkles which thy glass will truly show
Of mouthed graves will give thee memory;
Thou by thy dial's shady stealth mayst know
Time's thievish progress to eternity;
Look what thy memory can not contain,
Commit to these waste blanks, and thou shalt find
Those children nursed, delivered from thy brain,
To take a new acquaintance of thy mind.
    These offices, so oft as thou wilt look,
    Shall profit thee, and much enrich thy book.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0078">
<head>
   <title>78</title>
   <toctitle>78 (So oft haue I inuok'd thee for my Muse)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>So oft haue I inuok'd thee for my Muse</indextitle>
   <firstline>So oft haue I inuok'd thee for my Muse</firstline>
   <!--
   <pictures>
      <picture src="sonnets/sonnet-078.jpg">Faksimile</picture>
   </pictures>
   -->
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
So oft haue I inuok'd thee for my Muse,
And found such faire assistance in my verse,
As euery <i>Alien</i> pen hath got my vse,
And vnder thee their poesie disperse.
Thine eyes, that taught the dumbe on high to sing,
And heauie ignorance aloft to flie,
Haue added fethers to the learneds wing,
And giuen grace a double Maiestie.
Yet be most proud of that which I compile,
Whose influence is thine, and borne of thee;
In others workes thou doost but mend the stile,
And Arts with thy sweete graces graced be.
    But thou art all my art, and doost aduance,
    As high as learning, my rude ignorance.

---

<resetnum/>So oft have I invoked thee for my muse,
And found such fair assistance in my verse,
As every alien pen hath got my use,
And under thee their poesy disperse.
Thine eyes, that taught the dumb on high to sing,
And heavy ignorance aloft to fly,
Have added feathers to the learned's wing,
And given grace a double majesty.
Yet be most proud of that which I compile,
Whose influence is thine, and born of thee;
In others' works thou dost but mend the style,
And arts with thy sweet graces graced be.
    But thou art all my art, and dost advance,
    As high as learning, my rude ignorance.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0079">
<head>
   <title>79</title>
   <toctitle>79 (Whilst I alone did call vpon thy ayde)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Whilst I alone did call vpon thy ayde</indextitle>
   <firstline>Whilst I alone did call vpon thy ayde</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Whilst I alone did call vpon thy ayde,
My verse alone had all thy gentle grace,
But now my gracious numbers are decayde,
And my sick Muse doth giue an other place.
I grant (sweet loue) thy louely argument
Deserues the trauaile of a worthier pen,
Yet what of thee thy Poet doth inuent
He robs thee of, and payes it thee againe;
He lends thee vertue, and he stole that word
From thy behauiour; beautie doth he giue
And found it in thy cheeke; he can affoord
No praise to thee, but what in thee doth liue.
    Then thanke him not for that which he doth say,
    Since what he owes thee, thou thy selfe doost pay.

---

<resetnum/>Whilst I alone did call upon thy aid,
My verse alone had all thy gentle grace,
But now my gracious numbers are decayed,
And my sick muse doth give another place.
I grant, sweet love, thy lovely argument
Deserves the travail of a worthier pen;
Yet what of thee thy poet doth invent
He robs thee of, and pays it thee again;
He lends thee virtue, and he stole that word
From thy behavior; beauty doth he give,
And found it in thy cheek; he can afford
No praise to thee, but what in thee doth live.
    Then thank him not for that which he doth say,
    Since what he owes thee, thou thyself dost pay.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0080">
<head>
   <title>80</title>
   <toctitle>80</toctitle>
   <indextitle>80</indextitle>
   <firstline>O how I faint when I of you do write</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
O how I faint when I of you do write,
Knowing a better spirit doth vse your name,
And in the praise thereof spends all his might,
To make me toung-tide speaking of your fame.
But since your worth (wide as the Ocean is)
The humble as the proudest saile doth beare,
My sawsie barke (inferior farre to his)
On your broad maine doth wilfully appeare.
Your shallowest helpe will hold me vp a floate,
Whilst he vpon your soundlesse deepe doth ride,
Or (being wrackt) I am a worthlesse bote,
He of tall building, and of goodly pride.
    Then if he thriue and I be cast away,<note>if] <biblio>Benson</biblio>; If <biblio>Q</biblio></note>
    The worst was this, my loue was my decay.

---

<resetnum/>O how I faint when I of you do write,
Knowing a better spirit doth use your name,
And in the praise thereof spends all his might,
To make me tongue-tied speaking of your fame.
But since your worth, wide as the ocean is,
The humble as the proudest sail doth bear,
My saucy bark, inferior far to his,
On your broad main doth wilfully appear.
Your shallowest help will hold me up afloat,
Whilst he upon your soundless deep doth ride,
Or, being wracked, I am a worthless boat,
He of tall building, and of goodly pride.
    Then if he thrive and I be cast away,
    The worst was this, my love was my decay.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0081">
<head>
   <title>81</title>
   <toctitle>81</toctitle>
   <indextitle>81</indextitle>
   <firstline>Or I shall live, your epitaph to make</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Or I shall live, your epitaph to make;
Or you survive, when I in earth am rotten;
From hence your memory death cannot take,
Although in me each part will be forgotten.
Your name from hence immortal life shall have,
Though I, once gone, to all the world must die;
The earth can yield me but a common grave,
When you entombed in men's eyes shall lie.
Your monument shall be my gentle verse,
Which eyes not yet created shall o'er-read,
And tongues to be your being shall rehearse,
When all the breathers of this world are dead.
    You still shall live, such virtue hath my pen,
    Where breath most breathes, even in the mouths of men.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0082">
<head>
   <title>82</title>
   <toctitle>82</toctitle>
   <indextitle>82</indextitle>
   <firstline>I grant thou wert not married to my Muse</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>I grant thou wert not married to my Muse,
And therefore mayst without attaint o'erlook
The dedicated words which writers use
Of their fair subject, blessing every book.
Thou art as fair in knowledge as in hue,
Finding thy worth a limit past my praise,
And therefore art enforced to seek anew
Some fresher stamp of the time-bettering days,
And do so love; yet when they have devised
What strained touches rhetoric can lend,
Thou, truly fair, wert truly sympathized
In true plain words, by thy true-telling friend;
    And their gross painting might be better used
    Where cheeks need blood; in thee it is abused.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0083">
<head>
   <title>83</title>
   <toctitle>83</toctitle>
   <indextitle>83</indextitle>
   <firstline>I never saw that you did painting need</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>I never saw that you did painting need,
And therefore to your fair no painting set;
I found (or thought I found) you did exceed
The barren tender of a poet's debt;
And therefore have I slept in your report,
That you yourself, being extant, well might show
How far a modern quill doth come too short,
Speaking of worth, what worth in you doth grow.
This silence for my sin you did impute,
Which shall be most my glory, being dumb;
For I impair not beauty, being mute,
When others would give life, and bring a tomb.
    There lives more life in one of your fair eyes
    Than both your poets can in praise devise.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0084">
<head>
   <title>84</title>
   <toctitle>84</toctitle>
   <indextitle>84</indextitle>
   <firstline>Who is it that says most? Which can say more</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Who is it that says most? Which can say more,
Than this rich praise: that you alone are you,
In whose confine immured is the store
Which should example where your equal grew?
Lean penury within that pen doth dwell
That to his subject lends not some small glory;
But he that writes of you, if he can tell
That you are you, so dignifies his story.
Let him but copy what in you is writ,
Not making worse what nature made so clear,
And such a counterpart shall fame his wit,
Making his style admired everywhere.
    You to your beauteous blessings add a curse,
    Being fond on praise, which makes your praises worse.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0085">
<head>
   <title>85</title>
   <toctitle>85</toctitle>
   <indextitle>85</indextitle>
   <firstline>My tongue-tied Muse in manners holds her still</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>My tongue-tied Muse in manners holds her still,
While comments of your praise richly compiled
Reserve their character with golden quill,
And precious phrase by all the Muses filed;
I think good thoughts, whilst other write good words,
And like unlettered clerk still cry "Amen"
To every hymn that able spirit affords
In polished form of well-refined pen.
Hearing you praised, I say, "'Tis so, 'tis true,"
And to the most of praise add something more;
But that is in my thought, whose love to you
(Though words come hindmost) holds his rank before;
    Then others for the breath of words respect,
    Me for my dumb thoughts, speaking in effect.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0086">
<head>
   <title>86</title>
   <toctitle>86</toctitle>
   <indextitle>86</indextitle>
   <firstline>Was it the proud full sail of his great verse</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Was it the proud full sail of his great verse,
Bound for the prize of all-too-precious you,
That did my ripe thoughts in my brain in-hearse,
Making their tomb the womb wherein they grew?
Was it his spirit, by spirits taught to write
Above a mortal pitch, that struck me dead?
No, neither he, nor his compeers by night,
Giving him aid, my verse astonished.
He, nor that affable familiar ghost
Which nightly gulls him with intelligence,
As victors of my silence cannot boast;
I was not sick of any fear from thence.
    But when your countenance filled up his line,
    Then lacked I matter, that enfeebled mine.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0087">
<head>
   <title>87</title>
   <toctitle>87</toctitle>
   <indextitle>87</indextitle>
   <firstline>Farewell, thou art too dear for my possessing</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Farewell, thou art too dear for my possessing,
And like enough thou knowst thy estimate;
The charter of thy worth gives thee releasing;
My bonds in thee are all determinate.
For how do I hold thee but by thy granting,
And for that riches where is my deserving?
The cause of this fair gift in me is wanting,
And so my patent back again is swerving.
Thyself thou gav'st, thy own worth then not knowing,
Or me, to whom thou gav'st it, else mistaking;
So thy great gift upon misprision growing
Comes home again, on better judgement making.
    Thus have I had thee as a dream doth flatter,
    In sleep a king, but waking no such matter.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0088">
<head>
   <title>88</title>
   <toctitle>88</toctitle>
   <indextitle>88</indextitle>
   <firstline>When thou shalt be disposed to set me light</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>When thou shalt be disposed to set me light
And place my merit in the eye of scorn,
Upon thy side, against myself, I'll fight,
And prove thee virtuous, though thou art forsworn;
With mine own weakness being best acquainted,
Upon thy part I can set down a story
Of faults concealed, wherein I am attainted,
That thou, in losing me, shalt win much glory;
And I by this will be a gainer too,
For bending all my loving thoughts on thee,
The injuries that to myself I do,
Doing thee vantage, double vantage me:
    Such is my love, to thee I so belong,
    That for thy right myself will bear all wrong.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0089">
<head>
   <title>89</title>
   <toctitle>89</toctitle>
   <indextitle>89</indextitle>
   <firstline>Say that thou didst forsake me for some fault</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Say that thou didst forsake me for some fault,
And I will comment upon that offence;
Speak of my lameness, and I straight will halt,
Against thy reasons making no defence.
Thou canst not, love, disgrace me half so ill,
To set a form upon desired change,
As I'll myself disgrace, knowing thy will;
I will acquaintance strangle and look strange,
Be absent from thy walks, and in my tongue
Thy sweet beloved name no more shall dwell,
Lest I, too much profane, should do it wrong,
And haply of our old acquaintance tell.
    For thee, against myself I'll vow debate;
    For I must ne'er love him whom thou dost hate.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0090">
<head>
   <title>90</title>
   <toctitle>90</toctitle>
   <indextitle>90</indextitle>
   <firstline>Then hate me when thou wilt, if ever, now</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Then hate me when thou wilt, if ever, now,
Now, while the world is bent my deeds to cross,
Join with the spite of fortune, make me bow,
And do not drop in for an after-loss.
Ah, do not, when my heart hath 'scaped this sorrow,
Come in the rearward of a conquered woe;
Give not a windy night a rainy morrow,
To linger out a purposed overthrow.
If thou wilt leave me, do not leave me last,
When other petty griefs have done their spite;
But in the onset come, so shall I taste
At first the very worst of fortune's might;
    And other strains of woe, which now seem woe,
    Compared with loss of thee, will not seem so.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0091">
<head>
   <title>91</title>
   <toctitle>91</toctitle>
   <indextitle>91</indextitle>
   <firstline>Some glory in their birth, some in their skill</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Some glory in their birth, some in their skill,
Some in their wealth, some in their bodies' force,
Some in their garments, though new-fangled ill,
Some in their hawks and hounds, some in their horse,
And every humour hath his adjunct pleasure,
Wherein it finds a joy above the rest;
But these particulars are not my measure;
All these I better in one general best.
Thy love is better than high birth to me,
Richer than wealth, prouder than garments' cost,
Of more delight than hawks or horses be;
And having thee, of all men's pride I boast -
    Wretched in this alone, that thou mayst take
    All this away, and me most wretched make.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0092">
<head>
   <title>92</title>
   <toctitle>92</toctitle>
   <indextitle>92</indextitle>
   <firstline>But do thy worst to steal thyself away</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>But do thy worst to steal thyself away;
For term of life thou art assured mine,
And life no longer than thy love will stay,
For it depends upon that love of thine.
Then need I not to fear the worst of wrongs,
When in the least of them my life hath end;
I see a better state to me belongs
Than that which on thy humour doth depend.
Thou canst not vex me with inconstant mind,
Since that my life on thy revolt doth lie.
O what a happy title do I find,
Happy to have thy love, happy to die!
    But what's so blessed fair that fears no blot?
    Thou mayst be false, and yet I know it not.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0093">
<head>
   <title>93</title>
   <toctitle>93</toctitle>
   <indextitle>93</indextitle>
   <firstline>So shall I live, supposing thou art true</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>So shall I live, supposing thou art true,
Like a deceived husband; so love's face
May still seem love to me, though altered new,
Thy looks with me, thy heart in other place;
For there can live no hatred in thine eye,
Therefore in that I cannot know thy change.
In many's looks the false heart's history
Is writ in moods and frowns and wrinkles strange;
But heaven in thy creation did decree
That in thy face sweet love should ever dwell;
Whate'er thy thoughts or thy heart's workings be,
Thy looks should nothing thence but sweetness tell.
    How like Eve's apple doth thy beauty grow,
    if thy sweet virtue answer not thy show.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0094">
<head>
   <title>94</title>
   <toctitle>94</toctitle>
   <indextitle>94</indextitle>
   <firstline>They that have power to hurt, and will do none</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>They that have power to hurt, and will do none,
That do not do the thing they most do show,
Who, moving others, are themselves as stone,
Unmoved, cold, and to temptation slow:
They rightly do inherit heaven's graces,
And husband nature's riches from expense;
They are the lords and owners of their faces,
Others, but stewards of their excellence.
The summer's flower is to the summer sweet,
Though to itself it only live and die,
But if that flower with base infection meet,
The basest weed outbraves his dignity:
    For sweetest things turn sourest by their deeds;
    Lilies that fester smell far worse than weeds.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0095">
<head>
   <title>95</title>
   <toctitle>95</toctitle>
   <indextitle>95</indextitle>
   <firstline>How sweet and lovely dost thou make the shame</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>How sweet and lovely dost thou make the shame
Which like a canker in the fragrant rose
Doth spot the beauty of thy budding name:
O in what sweets dost thou thy sins enclose!
That tongue that tells the story of thy days,
Making lascivious comments on thy sport,
Cannot dispraise; but in a kind of praise,
Naming thy name, blesses an ill report.
O what a mansion have those vices got,
Which for their habitation chose out thee,
Where beauty's veil doth cover every blot,
And all things turn to fair that eyes can see!
    Take heed, dear heart, of this large privilege;
    The hardest knife ill used doth lose his edge.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0096">
<head>
   <title>96</title>
   <toctitle>96</toctitle>
   <indextitle>96</indextitle>
   <firstline>Some say thy fault is youth, some wantonness</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Some say thy fault is youth, some wantonness;
Some say thy grace is youth and gentle sport;
Both grace and faults are loved of more and less;
Thou mak'st faults graces, that to thee resort:
As on the finger of a throned queen
The basest jewel will be well esteemed,
So are those errors that in thee are seen
To truths translated, and for true things deemed.
How many lambs might the stern wolf betray
If like a lamb he could his looks translate?
How many gazers mightst thou lead away
If thou wouldst use the strength of all thy state?
    But do not so; I love thee in such sort,
    As thou being mine, mine is thy good report.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0097">
<head>
   <title>97</title>
   <toctitle>97</toctitle>
   <indextitle>97</indextitle>
   <firstline>How like a winter hath my absence been</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>How like a winter hath my absence been
From thee, the pleasure of the fleeting year!
What freezings have I felt, what dark days seen,
What old December's bareness everywhere!
And yet this time removed was summer's time,
The teeming autumn big with rich increase
Bearing the wanton burden of the prime,
Like widowed wombs after their lords' decease:
Yet this abundant issue seemed to me
But hope of orphans, and unfathered fruit;
For summer and his pleasures wait on thee,
And thou away, the very birds are mute;
    Or if they sing, 'tis with so dull a cheer
    That leaves look pale, dreading the winter's near.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0098">
<head>
   <title>98</title>
   <toctitle>98</toctitle>
   <indextitle>98</indextitle>
   <firstline>From you have I been absent in the spring</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>From you have I been absent in the spring,
When proud pied April dressed in all his trim,
Hath put a spirit of youth in everything,
That heavy Saturn laughed, and leaped with him.
Yet nor the lays of birds, nor the sweet smell
Of different flowers in odour and in hue,
Could make me any summer's story tell,
Or from their proud lap pluck them where they grew;
Nor did I wonder at the lily's white,
Nor praise the deep vermilion in the rose;
They were but sweet, but figures of delight,
Drawn after you, you pattern of all those.
    Yet seemed it winter still, and, you away,
    As with your shadow I with these did play.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0099">
<head>
   <title>99</title>
   <toctitle>99</toctitle>
   <indextitle>99</indextitle>
   <firstline>The forward violet thus did I chide</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>The forward violet thus did I chide:
"Sweet thief, whence didst thou steal thy sweet that smells,
If not from my love's breath? The purple pride
Which on thy soft cheek for complexion dwells
In my love's veins thou hast too grossly dyed."
The lily I condemned for thy hand,
And buds of marjoram had stol'n thy hair;
The roses fearfully on thorns did stand,
One blushing shame, another white despair;
A third, nor red, nor white, had stol'n of both,
And to his robb'ry had annexed thy breath;
But for his theft, in pride of all his growth,
A vengeful canker ate him up to death.
    More flowers I noted, yet I none could see,
    But sweet, or colour, it had stol'n from thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0100">
<head>
   <title>100</title>
   <toctitle>100</toctitle>
   <indextitle>100</indextitle>
   <firstline>Where art thou, Muse, that thou forget'st so long</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Where art thou, Muse, that thou forget'st so long
To speak of that which gives thee all thy might?
Spend'st thou thy fury on some worthless song,
Dark'ning thy power to lend base subjects light?
Return, forgetful Muse, and straight redeem,
In gentle numbers, time so idly spent;
Sing to the ear that doth thy lays esteem,
And gives thy pen both skill and argument.
Rise, resty Muse: my love's sweet face survey,
If Time have any wrinkle graven there;
If any, be a satire to decay,
And make Time's spoils despised everywhere:
    Give my love fame faster than Time wastes life,
    So thou prevent'st his scythe and crooked knife.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0101">
<head>
   <title>101</title>
   <toctitle>101</toctitle>
   <indextitle>101</indextitle>
   <firstline>O truant Muse, what shall be thy amends</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O truant Muse, what shall be thy amends
For thy neglect of truth in beauty dyed?
Both truth and beauty on my love depends;
So dost thou, too, and therein dignified:
Make answer, Muse, wilt thou not haply say,
"Truth needs no colour with his colour fixed;
Beauty no pencil, beauty's truth to lay,
But best is best if never intermixed?"
Because he needs no praise, wilt thou be dumb?
Excuse not silence so, for't lies in thee
To make him much outlive a gilded tomb,
And to be praised of ages yet to be.
    Then do thy office, Muse: I teach thee how
    To make him seem long hence as he shows now.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0102">
<head>
   <title>102</title>
   <toctitle>102</toctitle>
   <indextitle>102</indextitle>
   <firstline>My love is strength'ned, though more weak in seeming</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>My love is strength'ned, though more weak in seeming;
I love not less, though less the show appear.
That love is merchandised, whose rich esteeming
The owner's tongue doth publish everywhere.
Our love was new, and then but in the spring,
When I was wont to greet it with my lays,
As Philomel in summer's front doth sing,
And stops her pipe in growth of riper days.
Not that the summer is less pleasant now
Than when her mournful hymns did hush the night;
But that wild music burdens every bough,
And sweets grown common lose their dear delight:
    Therefore, like her, I sometime hold my tongue,
    Because I would not dull you with my song.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0103">
<head>
   <title>103</title>
   <toctitle>103</toctitle>
   <indextitle>103</indextitle>
   <firstline>Alack, what poverty my Muse brings forth</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Alack, what poverty my Muse brings forth,
That, having such a scope to show her pride,
The argument all bare is of more worth
Than when it hath my added praise beside.
O blame me not if I no more can write!
Look in your glass, and there appears a face
That overgoes my blunt invention quite,
Dulling my lines, and doing me disgrace.
Were it not sinful, then, striving to mend,
To mar the subject that before was well?
For to no other pass my verses tend
Than of your graces and your gifts to tell;
    And more, much more, than in my verse can sit
    Your own glass shows you, when you look in it.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0104">
<head>
   <title>104</title>
   <toctitle>104</toctitle>
   <indextitle>104</indextitle>
   <firstline>To me, fair friend, you never can be old</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>To me, fair friend, you never can be old;
For as you were when first your eye I eyed,
Such seems your beauty still: three winters cold
Have from the forests shook three summers' pride;
Three beauteous springs to yellow autumn turned
In process of the seasons have I seen;
Three April perfumes in three hot Junes burned,
Since first I saw you fresh, which yet are green.
Ah, yet doth beauty, like a dial hand,
Steal from his figure, and no pace perceived;
So your sweet hue, which methinks still doth stand,
Hath motion, and mine eye may be deceived;
    For fear of which, hear this, thou age unbred,
    Ere you were born was beauty's summer dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0105">
<head>
   <title>105</title>
   <toctitle>105</toctitle>
   <indextitle>105</indextitle>
   <firstline>Let not my love be called idolatry</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Let not my love be called idolatry,
Nor my beloved as an idol show,
Since all alike my songs and praises be,
To one, of one, still such, and ever so.
Kind is my love today, tomorrow kind,
Still constant in a wondrous excellence;
Therefore my verse to constancy confined,
One thing expressing, leaves out difference.
Fair, kind and true is all my argument;
Fair, kind, and true, varying to other words,
And in this change is my invention spent,
Three themes in one, which wondrous scope affords.
    Fair, kind, and true have often lived alone,
    Which three, till now never kept seat in one.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0106">
<head>
   <title>106</title>
   <toctitle>106</toctitle>
   <indextitle>106</indextitle>
   <firstline>When in the chronicle of wasted time</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>When in the chronicle of wasted time
I see descriptions of the fairest wights,
And beauty making beautiful old rhyme,
In praise of ladies dead, and lovely knights;
Then in the blazon of sweet beauty's best,
Of hand, of foot, of lip, of eye, of brow,
I see their antique pen would have expressed
Even such a beauty as you master now:
So all their praises are but prophecies
Of this our time, all you prefiguring;
And for they looked but with divining eyes
They had not skill enough your worth to sing;
    For we which now behold these present days
    Had eyes to wonder, but lack tongues to praise.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0107">
<head>
   <title>107</title>
   <toctitle>107</toctitle>
   <indextitle>107</indextitle>
   <firstline>Not mine own fears, nor the prophetic soul</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Not mine own fears, nor the prophetic soul
Of the wide world, dreaming on things to come,
Can yet the lease of my true love control,
Supposed as forfeit to a confined doom.
The mortal moon hath her eclipse endured,
And the sad augurs mock their own presage;
Uncertainties now crown themselves assured,
And peace proclaims olives of endless age.
Now with the drops of this most balmy time
My love looks fresh, and death to me subscribes,
Since 'spite of him I'll live in this poor rhyme,
While he insults o'er dull and speechless tribes;
    And thou in this shalt find thy monument,
    When tyrants' crests and tombs of brass are spent.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0108">
<head>
   <title>108</title>
   <toctitle>108</toctitle>
   <indextitle>108</indextitle>
   <firstline>What's in the brain that ink may character</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>What's in the brain that ink may character
Which hath not figured to thee my true spirit?
What's new to speak, what new to register,
That may express my love, or thy dear merit?
Nothing, sweet boy; but yet, like prayers divine,
I must each day say o'er the very same,
Counting no old thing old; thou mine, I thine,
Even as when first I hallowed thy fair name:
So that eternal love, in love's fresh case,
Weighs not the dust and injury of age,
Nor gives to necessary wrinkles place
But makes antiquity for aye his page,
    Finding the first conceit of love there bred,
    Where time and outward form would show it dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0109">
<head>
   <title>109</title>
   <toctitle>109</toctitle>
   <indextitle>109</indextitle>
   <firstline>O never say that I was false of heart</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O never say that I was false of heart,
Though absence seemed my flame to qualify;
As easy might I from myself depart
As from my soul which in thy breast doth lie:
That is my home of love; if I have ranged,
Like him that travels I return again,
Just to the time, not with the time exchanged,
So that myself bring water for my stain;
Never believe, though in my nature reigned
All frailties that besiege all kinds of blood,
That it could so preposterously be stained,
To leave for nothing all thy sum of good:
    For nothing this wide universe I call,
    Save thou, my rose; in it thou art my all.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0110">
<head>
   <title>110</title>
   <toctitle>110</toctitle>
   <indextitle>110</indextitle>
   <firstline>Alas, 'tis true, I have gone here and there</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Alas, 'tis true, I have gone here and there,
And made myself a motley to the view,
Gored mine own thoughts, sold cheap what is most dear,
Made old offences of affections new.
Most true it is that I have looked on truth
Askance and strangely; but by all above,
These blenches gave my heart another youth,
And worse essays proved thee my best of love.
Now all is done, save what shall have no end;
Mine appetite I never more will grind
On newer proof, to try an older friend,
A god in love, to whom I am confined:
    Then give me welcome, next my heaven the best,
    Even to thy pure and most most loving breast.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0111">
<head>
   <title>111</title>
   <toctitle>111</toctitle>
   <indextitle>111</indextitle>
   <firstline>O, for my sake do you with Fortune chide</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O, for my sake do you with Fortune chide,
The guilty goddess of my harmful deeds,
That did not better for my life provide
Than public means, which public manners breeds;
Thence comes it that my name receives a brand,
And almost thence my nature is subdued
To what it works in, like the dyer's hand;
Pity me, then, and wish I were renewed,
Whilst like a willing patient I will drink
Potions of eisell 'gainst my strong infection;
No bitterness that I will bitter think,
Nor double penance to correct correction.
    Pity me then, dear friend, and I assure ye,
    Even that your pity is enough to cure me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0112">
<head>
   <title>112</title>
   <toctitle>112</toctitle>
   <indextitle>112</indextitle>
   <firstline>Your love and pity doth th'impression fill</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Your love and pity doth th'impression fill
Which vulgar scandal stamped upon my brow;
For what care I who calls me well or ill
So you o'er-green my bad, my good allow?
You are my all-the-world, and I must strive
To know my shames and praises from your tongue;
None else to me, nor I to none, alive,
That my steeled sense o'er-changes right or wrong.
In so profound abysm I throw all care
Of others' voices, that my adder's sense
To critic and to flatterer stopped are.
Mark how with my neglect I do dispense:
    You are so strongly in my purpose bred
    That all the world besides me thinks you're dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0113">
<head>
   <title>113</title>
   <toctitle>113</toctitle>
   <indextitle>113</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since I left you, mine eye is in my mind</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Since I left you, mine eye is in my mind,
And that which governs me to go about
Doth part his function, and is partly blind;
Seems seeing, but effectually is out;
For it no form delivers to the heart
Of bird, of flower, or shape, which it doth latch;
Of his quick objects hath the mind no part,
Nor his own vision holds what it doth catch:
For if it see the rud'st or gentlest sight,
The most sweet-favoured or deformed'st creature,
The mountain, or the sea, the day, or night,
The crow, or dove, it shapes them to your feature.
    Incapable of more, replete with you,
    My most true mind thus maketh mine untrue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0114">
<head>
   <title>114</title>
   <toctitle>114</toctitle>
   <indextitle>114</indextitle>
   <firstline>Or whether doth my mind, being crowned with you</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Or whether doth my mind, being crowned with you,
Drink up the monarch's plague, this flattery?
Or whether shall I say mine eye saith true,
And that your love taught it this alchemy,
To make of monsters and things indigest
Such cherubins as your sweet self resemble,
Creating every bad a perfect best
As fast as objects to his beams assemble?
O, 'tis the first, 'tis flatt'ry in my seeing,
And my great mind most kingly drinks it up:
Mine eye well knows what with his gust is greeing,
And to his palate doth prepare the cup.
    If it be poisoned, 'tis the lesser sin,
    That mine eye loves it and doth first begin.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0115">
<head>
   <title>115</title>
   <toctitle>115</toctitle>
   <indextitle>115</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those lines that I before have writ do lie</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Those lines that I before have writ do lie,
Even those that said I could not love you dearer;
Yet then my judgement knew no reason why
My most full flame should afterwards burn clearer.
But reckoning Time, whose millioned accidents
Creep in 'twixt vows, and change decrees of kings,
Tan sacred beauty, blunt the sharp'st intents,
Divert strong minds to th' course of alt'ring things;
Alas, why, fearing of Time's tyranny,
Might I not then say, "Now I love you best,"
When I was certain o'er uncertainty,
Crowning the present, doubting of the rest?
    Love is a babe; then might I not say so,
    To give full growth to that which still doth grow?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0116">
<head>
   <title>116</title>
   <toctitle>116</toctitle>
   <indextitle>116</indextitle>
   <firstline>Let me not to the marriage of true minds</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Let me not to the marriage of true minds
Admit impediments; love is not love
Which alters when it alteration finds,
Or bends with the remover to remove.
O no, it is an ever-fixed mark,
That looks on tempests and is never shaken;
It is the star to every wand'ring bark,
Whose worth's unknown, although his height be taken.
Love's not Time's fool, though rosy lips and cheeks
Within his bending sickle's compass come;
Love alters not with his brief hours and weeks,
But bears it out even to the edge of doom.
    If this be error and upon me proved,
    I never writ, nor no man ever loved.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0117">
<head>
   <title>117</title>
   <toctitle>117</toctitle>
   <indextitle>117</indextitle>
   <firstline>Accuse me thus: that I have scanted all</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Accuse me thus: that I have scanted all
Wherein I should your great deserts repay,
Forgot upon your dearest love to call,
Whereto all bonds do tie me day by day;
That I have frequent been with unknown minds
And given to time your own dear-purchased right;
That I have hoisted sail to all the winds
Which should transport me farthest from your sight.
Book both my wilfulness and errors down,
And on just proof surmise accumulate;
Bring me within the level of your frown,
But shoot not at me in your wakened hate:
    Since my appeal says I did strive to prove
    The constancy and virtue of your love.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0118">
<head>
   <title>118</title>
   <toctitle>118</toctitle>
   <indextitle>118</indextitle>
   <firstline>Like as, to make our appetites more keen</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Like as, to make our appetites more keen,
With eager compounds we our palate urge;
As, to prevent our maladies unseen,
We sicken to shun sickness when we purge;
Even so, being full of your ne'er-cloying sweetness,
To bitter sauces did I frame my feeding,
And, sick of welfare, found a kind of meetness
To be diseased ere that there was true needing.
Thus policy in love, t'anticipate
The ills that were not, grew to faults assured,
And brought to medicine a healthful state
Which, rank of goodness, would by ill be cured;
    But thence I learn, and find the lesson true,
    Drugs poison him that so fell sick of you.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0119">
<head>
   <title>119</title>
   <toctitle>119</toctitle>
   <indextitle>119</indextitle>
   <firstline>What potions have I drunk of Siren tears</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>What potions have I drunk of Siren tears
Distilled from limbecks foul as hell within,
Applying fears to hopes, and hopes to fears,
Still losing when I saw myself to win?
What wretched errors hath my heart committed,
Whilst it hath thought itself so blessed never?
How have mine eyes out of their spheres been fitted
In the distraction of this madding fever?
O benefit of ill: now I find true
That better is by evil still made better,
And ruined love when it is built anew
Grows fairer than at first, more strong, far greater:
    So I return rebuked to my content,
    And gain by ill thrice more than I have spent.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0120">
<head>
   <title>120</title>
   <toctitle>120</toctitle>
   <indextitle>120</indextitle>
   <firstline>That you were once unkind befriends me now</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>That you were once unkind befriends me now,
And for that sorrow, which I then did feel,
Needs must I under my transgression bow,
Unless my nerves were brass or hammered steel:
For if you were by my unkindness shaken,
As I by yours, you've passed a hell of time,
And I, a tyrant, have no leisure taken
To weigh how once I suffered in your crime.
O that our night of woe might have rememb'red
My deepest sense how hard true sorrow hits,
And soon to you, as you to me then, tend'red
The humble salve which wounded bosoms fits!
    But that your trespass now becomes a fee;
    Mine ransoms yours, and yours must ransom me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0121">
<head>
   <title>121</title>
   <toctitle>121</toctitle>
   <indextitle>121</indextitle>
   <firstline>Tis better to be vile than vile esteemed</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>'Tis better to be vile than vile esteemed,
When not to be, receives reproach of being,
And the just pleasure lost, which is so deemed
Not by our feeling, but by others' seeing.
For why should others' false adulterate eyes
Give salutation to my sportive blood?
Or on my frailties why are frailer spies,
Which in their wills count bad what I think good?
No, I am that I am, and they that level
At my abuses reckon up their own;
I may be straight, though they themselves be bevel.
By their rank thoughts my deeds must not be shown,
    Unless this general evil they maintain:
    All men are bad, and in their badness reign.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0122">
<head>
   <title>122</title>
   <toctitle>122</toctitle>
   <indextitle>122</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thy gift, thy tables, are within my brain</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Thy gift, thy tables, are within my brain
Full charactered with lasting memory,
Which shall above that idle rank remain
Beyond all date, even to eternity;
Or at the least, so long as brain and heart
Have faculty by nature to subsist;
Till each to razed oblivion yield his part
Of thee, thy record never can be missed.
That poor retention could not so much hold,
Nor need I tallies thy dear love to score;
Therefore to give them from me was I bold,
To trust those tables that receive thee more;
    To keep an adjunct to remember thee
    Were to import forgetfulness in me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0123">
<head>
   <title>123</title>
   <toctitle>123</toctitle>
   <indextitle>123</indextitle>
   <firstline>No! Time, thou shalt not boast that I do change</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>No! Time, thou shalt not boast that I do change;
Thy pyramids, built up with newer might,
To me are nothing novel, nothing strange;
They are but dressings of a former sight:
Our dates are brief, and therefore we admire
What thou dost foist upon us that is old,
And rather make them born to our desire
Than think that we before have heard them told:
Thy registers and thee I both defy,
Not wond'ring at the present, nor the past,
For thy records, and what we see doth lie,
Made more or less by thy continual haste:
    This I do vow, and this shall ever be,
    I will be true despite thy scythe and thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0124">
<head>
   <title>124</title>
   <toctitle>124</toctitle>
   <indextitle>124</indextitle>
   <firstline>If my dear love were but the child of state</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>If my dear love were but the child of state,
It might, for Fortune's bastard, be unfathered,
As subject to Time's love or to Time's hate,
Weeds among weeds, or flowers with flowers gathered.
No, it was builded far from accident;
It suffers not in smiling pomp, nor falls
Under the blow of thralled discontent,
Whereto th'inviting time our fashion calls:
It fears not policy, that heretic,
Which works on leases of short-numb'red hours,
But all alone stands hugely politic,
That it nor grows with heat, nor drowns with showers.
    To this I witness call the fools of Time,
    Which die for goodness, who have lived for crime.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0125">
<head>
   <title>125</title>
   <toctitle>125</toctitle>
   <indextitle>125</indextitle>
   <firstline>Were't aught to me I bore the canopy</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Were't aught to me I bore the canopy,
With my extern the outward honouring,
Or laid great bases for eternity,
Which prove more short than waste or ruining?
Have I not seen dwellers on form and favour
Lose all, and more, by paying too much rent,
For compound sweet forgoing simple savour,
Pitiful thrivers, in their gazing spent?
No, let me be obsequious in thy heart,
And take thou my oblation, poor but free,
Which is not mixed with seconds, knows no art,
But mutual render, only me for thee.
    Hence, thou suborned informer, a true soul
    When most impeached, stands least in thy control.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0126">
<head>
   <title>126</title>
   <toctitle>126</toctitle>
   <indextitle>126</indextitle>
   <firstline>O thou my lovely Boy, who in thy power</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O thou my lovely Boy, who in thy power
Dost hold Time's fickle glass, his sickle hour,
Who hast by waning grown, and therein show'st
Thy lovers withering, as thy sweet self grow'st;
If Nature, sovereign mistress over wrack,
As thou goest onwards still will pluck thee back,
She keeps thee to this purpose: that her skill
May Time disgrace, and wretched minutes kill.
Yet fear her, O thou minion of her pleasure:
She may detain, but not still keep, her treasure!
Her audit, though delayed, answered must be,
And her quietus is to render thee.
   (&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;)
   (&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;)
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0127">
<head>
   <title>127</title>
   <toctitle>127</toctitle>
   <indextitle>127</indextitle>
   <firstline>In the old age black was not counted fair</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>In the old age black was not counted fair,
Or if it were, it bore not beauty's name;
But now is black beauty's successive heir,
And beauty slandered with a bastard shame:
For since each hand hath put on nature's power,
Fairing the foul with art's false borrowed face,
Sweet beauty hath no name, no holy bower,
But is profaned, if not lives in disgrace.
Therefore my mistress' brows are raven black,
Her eyes so suited, and they mourners seem
At such who, not born fair, no beauty lack,
Sland'ring creation with a false esteem;
    Yet so they mourn, becoming of their woe,
    That every tongue says beauty should look so.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0128">
<head>
   <title>128</title>
   <toctitle>128</toctitle>
   <indextitle>128</indextitle>
   <firstline>How oft when thou, my music, music play'st</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>How oft when thou, my music, music play'st
Upon that blessed wood whose motion sounds
With thy sweet fingers, when thou gently sway'st
The wiry concord that mine ear confounds,
Do I envy those jacks that nimble leap,
To kiss the tender inward of thy hand,
Whilst my poor lips, which should that harvest reap,
At the wood's boldness by thee blushing stand?
To be so tickled they would change their state
And situation with those dancing chips,
O'er whom thy fingers walk with gentle gait,
Making dead wood more blessed than living lips.
    Since saucy jacks so happy are in this,
    Give them thy fingers, me thy lips to kiss.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0129">
<head>
   <title>129</title>
   <toctitle>129</toctitle>
   <indextitle>129</indextitle>
   <firstline>Th'expense of spirit in a waste of shame</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Th'expense of spirit in a waste of shame
Is lust in action; and till action, lust
Is perjured, murd'rous, bloody, full of blame,
Savage, extreme, rude, cruel, not to trust;
Enjoyed no sooner but despised straight;
Past reason hunted, and no sooner had,
Past reason hated as a swallowed bait,
On purpose laid to make the taker mad;
Mad in pursuit, and in possession so,
Had, having, and in quest to have, extreme;
A bliss in proof, and proved, a very woe;
Before, a joy proposed; behind, a dream.
    All this the world well knows, yet none knows well
    To shun the heaven that leads men to this hell.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0130">
<head>
   <title>130</title>
   <toctitle>130</toctitle>
   <indextitle>130</indextitle>
   <firstline>My mistress' eyes are nothing like the sun</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>My mistress' eyes are nothing like the sun;
Coral is far more red than her lips' red;
If snow be white, why then her breasts are dun;
If hairs be wires, black wires grow on her head;
I have seen roses damasked, red and white,
But no such roses see I in her cheeks;
And in some perfumes is there more delight
Than in the breath that from my mistress reeks.
I love to hear her speak, yet well I know
That music hath a far more pleasing sound;
I grant I never saw a goddess go;
My mistress, when she walks treads on the ground.
    And yet, by heaven, I think my love as rare
    As any she belied with false compare.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0131">
<head>
   <title>131</title>
   <toctitle>131</toctitle>
   <indextitle>131</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thou art as tyrannous, so as thou art</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Thou art as tyrannous, so as thou art,
As those whose beauties proudly make them cruel;
For well thou knowst, to my dear doting heart
Thou art the fairest and most precious jewel.
Yet in good faith some say, that thee behold,
Thy face hath not the power to make love groan;
To say they err, I dare not be so bold,
Although I swear it to myself alone;
And to be sure that is not false, I swear
A thousand groans but thinking on thy face;
One on another's neck do witness bear
Thy black is fairest in my judgement's place.
    In nothing art thou black save in thy deeds,
    And thence this slander, as I think, proceeds.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0132">
<head>
   <title>132</title>
   <toctitle>132</toctitle>
   <indextitle>132</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thine eyes I love, and they, as pitying me</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Thine eyes I love, and they, as pitying me,
Knowing thy heart torments me with disdain,
Have put on black, and loving mourners be,
Looking with pretty ruth upon my pain;
And truly, not the morning sun of heaven
Better becomes the grey cheeks of the East,
Nor that full star that ushers in the even
Doth half that glory to the sober West
As those two mourning eyes become thy face:
O let it then as well beseem thy heart
To mourn for me, since mourning doth thee grace,
And suit thy pity like in every part:
    Then will I swear beauty herself is black,
    And all they foul that thy complexion lack.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0133">
<head>
   <title>133</title>
   <toctitle>133</toctitle>
   <indextitle>133</indextitle>
   <firstline>Beshrew that heart that makes my heart to groan</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Beshrew that heart that makes my heart to groan
For that deep wound it gives my friend and me;
Is't not enough to torture me alone,
But slave to slavery my sweet'st friend must be?
Me from myself thy cruel eye hath taken,
And my next self thou harder hast engrossed:
Of him, myself and thee I am forsaken,
A torment thrice threefold thus to be crossed.
Prison my heart in thy steel bosom's ward;
But then my friend's heart let my poor heart bail.
Whoe'er keeps me, let my heart be his guard;
Thou canst not then use rigour in my jail.
    And yet thou wilt, for I being pent in thee,
    Perforce am thine, and all that is in me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0134">
<head>
   <title>134</title>
   <toctitle>134</toctitle>
   <indextitle>134</indextitle>
   <firstline>So now I have confessed that he is thine</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>So now I have confessed that he is thine,
And I myself am mortgaged to thy will,
Myself I'll forfeit, so that other mine
Thou wilt restore to be my comfort still;
But thou wilt not, nor he will not be free,
For thou art covetous, and he is kind;
He learned but surety-like to write for me,
Under that bond that him as fast doth bind.
The statute of thy beauty thou wilt take,
Thou usurer, that put'st forth all to use,
And sue a friend, came debtor for my sake:
So him I lose through my unkind abuse.
    Him have I lost; thou hast both him and me;
    He pays the whole, and yet am I not free.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0135">
<head>
   <title>135</title>
   <toctitle>135</toctitle>
   <indextitle>135</indextitle>
   <firstline>Whoever hath her wish, thou hast thy Will</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Whoever hath her wish, thou hast thy Will,
And Will to boot, and Will in overplus;
More than enough am I, that vex thee still,
To thy sweet will making addition thus.
Wilt thou, whose will is large and spacious,
Not once vouchsafe to hide my will in thine?
Shall will in others seem right gracious,
And in my will no fair acceptance shine?
The sea, all water, yet receives rain still,
And in abundance addeth to his store;
So thou, being rich in Will, add to thy Will
One will of mine, to make thy large Will more:
    Let no unkind, no fair beseechers kill;
    Think all but one, and me in that one Will.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0136">
<head>
   <title>136</title>
   <toctitle>136</toctitle>
   <indextitle>136</indextitle>
   <firstline>If thy soul check thee that I come so near</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>If thy soul check thee that I come so near,
Swear to thy blind soul that I was thy Will,
And will, thy soul knows, is admitted there;
Thus far for love my love-suit sweet fulfil.
Will will fulfil the treasure of thy love,
Ay, fill it full with wills, and my will one;
In things of great receipt with ease we prove
Among a number one is reckoned none.
Then in the number let me pass untold,
Though in thy store's account I one must be.
For nothing hold me, so it please thee hold
That nothing, me a something sweet to thee.
    Make but my name thy love, and love that still;
    And then thou lov'st me, for my name is Will.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0137">
<head>
   <title>137</title>
   <toctitle>137</toctitle>
   <indextitle>137</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thou blind fool Love, what dost thou to mine eyes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Thou blind fool Love, what dost thou to mine eyes,
That they behold, and see not what they see?
They know what beauty is, see where it lies,
Yet what the best is, take the worst to be.
If eyes corrupt by over-partial looks,
Be anchored in the bay where all men ride,
Why of eyes' falsehood hast thou forged hooks,
Whereto the judgement of my heart is tied?
Why should my heart think that a several plot
Which my heart knows the wide world's common place?
Or mine eyes, seeing this, say this is not,
To put fair truth upon so foul a face?
    In things right true my heart and eyes have erred,
    And to this false plague are they now transferred.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0138">
<head>
   <title>138</title>
   <toctitle>138 (When my loue sweares that she is made of truth)</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When my loue sweares that she is made of truth</indextitle>
   <firstline>When my loue sweares that she is made of truth</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note><i>Sonnet 138 og 144 blev oprindeligt udgivet i 1599 som de to første digte af</i> The Passionate Pilgrime, <i>altså ti år før</i> <biblio>Q</biblio>. <i>Teksten er her nøjagtigt gengivet fra første udgave, mens faksimilen er taget fra anden udgave (også 1599); afvigelserne de to udgaver imellem er ubetydelige, bortset fra l. 11.</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
When my loue sweares that she is made of truth,
I do beleeue her though I know she lyes,
That she might thinke me some vntuterd youth,
Vnlearned in the worlds false subtilties.
Thus vainely thinking that she thinkes me young,
Although she knowes my dayes are past the best,
Simply I credit her false speaking tongue,
On both sides thus is simple truth supprest:
But wherefore sayes she not she is vniust?
And wherefore say not I that I am old?
O loues best habit is in seeming trust,
And age in loue, loues not t'haue yeares told.
    Therefore I lye with her, and she with me,
    And in our faults by lyes we flattered be.

---

<resetnum/>When my love swears that she is made of truth,
I do believe her, though I know she lies,
That she might think me some untutored youth,
Unlearned in the world's false subtleties.
Thus vainly thinking that she thinks me young,
Although she knows my days are past the best,
Simply I credit her false-speaking tongue;
On both sides thus is simple truth suppressed.
But wherefore says she not she is unjust?
And wherefore say not I that I am old?
O love's best habit is in seeming trust,
And age in love loves not t'have years told:
    Therefore I lie with her, and she with me,
    And in our faults by lies we flattered be.

---

<nonum>[The Passionate Pilgrime (1599), I]</nonum>

<resetnum/>When my Loue sweares that she is made of truth,
I do beleeue her (though I know she lies)
That she might thinke me some vntutor'd youth,
Vnskilful in the worlds false forgeries.
Thus vainly thinking that she thinkes me young,
Although I know my yeares be past the best:
I smiling, credite her false speaking toung,
Outfacing faults in loue, with loues ill rest.
But wherefore sayes my loue that she is young?
And wherefore say not I, that I am old:
O, Loues best habit's in a soothing toung,
And Age in Loue, loues not to haue yeares told.
    Therfore I'le lye with Loue, and loue with me,
    Since that our faultes in loue thus smother'd be.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0139">
<head>
   <title>139</title>
   <toctitle>139</toctitle>
   <indextitle>139</indextitle>
   <firstline>O call not me to justify the wrong</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O call not me to justify the wrong
That thy unkindness lays upon my heart;
Wound me not with thine eye, but with thy tongue;
Use power with power, and slay me not by art.
Tell me thou lov'st elsewhere; but in my sight,
Dear heart, forbear to glance thine eye aside.
What need'st thou wound with cunning, when thy might
Is more than my o'er-pressed defence can bide?
Let me excuse thee: ah, my love well knows
Her pretty looks have been mine enemies,
And therefore from my face she turns my foes
That they elsewhere might dart their injuries.
    Yet do not so, but since I am near slain,
    Kill me outright with looks, and rid my pain.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0140">
<head>
   <title>140</title>
   <toctitle>140</toctitle>
   <indextitle>140</indextitle>
   <firstline>Be wise as thou art cruel, do not press</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Be wise as thou art cruel, do not press
My tongue-tied patience with too much disdain,
Lest sorrow lend me words, and words express
The manner of my pity-wanting pain.
If I might teach thee wit, better it were,
Though not to love, yet, love to tell me so,
As testy sick men, when their deaths be near,
No news but health from their physicians know:
For if I should despair, I should grow mad,
And in my madness might speak ill of thee;
Now this ill-wresting world is grown so bad,
Mad slanderers by mad ears believed be.
    That I may not be so, nor thou belied,
    Bear thine eyes straight, though thy proud heart go wide.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0141">
<head>
   <title>141</title>
   <toctitle>141</toctitle>
   <indextitle>141</indextitle>
   <firstline>In faith, I do not love thee with mine eyes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>In faith, I do not love thee with mine eyes,
For they in thee a thousand errors note;
But 'tis my heart that loves what they despise,
Who in despite of view is pleased to dote.
Nor are mine ears with thy tongue's tune delighted,
Nor tender feeling to base touches prone,
Nor taste, nor smell, desire to be invited
To any sensual feast with thee alone:
But my five wits, nor my five senses, can
Dissuade one foolish heart from serving thee,
Who leaves unswayed the likeness of a man,
Thy proud heart's slave and vassal wretch to be:
    Only my plague thus far I count my gain,
    That she that makes me sin, awards me pain.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0142">
<head>
   <title>142</title>
   <toctitle>142</toctitle>
   <indextitle>142</indextitle>
   <firstline>Love is my sin, and thy dear virtue hate</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Love is my sin, and thy dear virtue hate,
Hate of my sin, grounded on sinful loving;
O but with mine compare thou thine own state,
And thou shalt find it merits not reproving;
Or if it do, not from those lips of thine,
That have profaned their scarlet ornaments,
And sealed false bonds of love as oft as mine,
Robbed others' beds' revenues of their rents.
Be it lawful I love thee as thou lov'st those
Whom thine eyes woo, as mine importune thee,
Root pity in thy heart, that when it grows,
Thy pity may deserve to pitied be.
    If thou dost seek to have what thou dost hide,
    By self-example mayst thou be denied.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0143">
<head>
   <title>143</title>
   <toctitle>143</toctitle>
   <indextitle>143</indextitle>
   <firstline>Lo, as a careful housewife runs to catch</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Lo, as a careful housewife runs to catch
One of her feathered creatures broke away,
Sets down her babe, and makes all swift dispatch
In pursuit of the thing she would have stay;
Whilst her neglected child holds her in chase,
Cries to catch her whose busy care is bent
To follow that which flies before her face,
Not prizing her poor infant's discontent:
So run'st thou after that which flies from thee,
Whilst I, thy babe, chase thee afar behind.
But if thou catch thy hope, turn back to me,
And play the mother's part, kiss me, be kind:
    So will I pray that thou mayst have thy Will,
    If thou turn back and my loud crying still.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0144">
<head>
   <title>144</title>
   <toctitle>144</toctitle>
   <indextitle>144</indextitle>
   <firstline>Two loves I have, of comfort and despair</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Two loues I haue of comfort and dispaire,
Which like two spirits do sugiest me still,
The better angell is a man right faire:
The worser spirit a woman collour'd il.
To win me soone to hell my femall euill,
Tempteth my better angel from my sight,
And would corrupt my saint to be a diuel:
Wooing his purity with her fowle pride.
And whether that my angel be turn'd finde,
Suspect I may, yet not directly tell,
But being both from me both to each friend,
I gesse one angel in an others hel.
    Yet this shal I nere know but liue in doubt,
    Till my bad angel fire my good one out.

---

<resetnum/>Two loves I have, of comfort and despair,
Which, like two spirits, do suggest me still:
The better angel is a man right fair,
The worser spirit a woman coloured ill.
To win me soon to hell my female evil
Tempteth my better angel from my side,
And would corrupt my saint to be a devil,
Wooing his purity with her foul pride;
And whether that my angel be turned fiend
Suspect I may, yet not directly tell;
But being both from me both to each friend,
I guess one angel in another's hell.
    Yet this shall I ne'er know, but live in doubt,
    Till my bad angel fire my good one out.

---

<nonum>[The Passionate Pilgrime (1599), I]</nonum>

<resetnum/>Two loues I haue, of Comfort and Despaire,
That like two Spirits, do suggest me still:
My better Angell, is a Man (right faire)
My worser spirite a Woman (colour'd ill.)
To win me soone to hell, my Female euill
Tempteth my better Angell from my side:
And would corrupt my Saint to be a Diuell,
Wooing his puritie with her faire pride.
And whether that my Angell be turnde feend,
Suspect I may (yet not directly tell:)
For being both to me: both, to each friend,
I ghesse one Angell in anothers hell:
    The truth I shall not know, but liue in dout,
    Till my bad Angell fire my good one out.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0145">
<head>
   <title>145</title>
   <toctitle>145</toctitle>
   <indextitle>145</indextitle>
   <firstline>Those lips that Love's own hand did make</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Those lips that Love's own hand did make
Breathed forth the sound that said "I hate,"
To me, that languished for her sake;
But when she saw my woeful state,
Straight in her heart did mercy come,
Chiding that tongue that, ever sweet,
Was used in giving gentle doom,
And taught it thus anew to greet:
"I hate" she altered with an end
That followed it as gentle day
Doth follow night, who like a fiend
From heaven to hell is flown away.
    "I hate" from "hate" away she threw,
    And saved my life, saying "not you."
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0146">
<head>
   <title>146</title>
   <toctitle>146</toctitle>
   <indextitle>146</indextitle>
   <firstline>Poor soul, the centre of my sinful earth</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Poor soul, the centre of my sinful earth,
Feeding these rebel powers that thee array,
Why dost thou pine within and suffer dearth,
Painting thy outward walls so costly gay?
Why so large cost, having so short a lease,
Dost thou upon thy fading mansion spend?
Shall worms, inheritors of this excess,
Eat up thy charge? Is this thy body's end?
Then soul, live thou upon thy servant's loss,
And let that pine to aggravate thy store;
Buy terms divine in selling hours of dross,
Within be fed, without be rich no more:
    So shalt thou feed on Death, that feeds on men,
    And Death once dead, there's no more dying then.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0147">
<head>
   <title>147</title>
   <toctitle>147</toctitle>
   <indextitle>147</indextitle>
   <firstline>My love is as a fever, longing still</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>My love is as a fever, longing still
For that which longer nurseth the disease,
Feeding on that which doth preserve the ill,
Th'uncertain sickly appetite to please:
My reason, the physician to my love,
Angry that his prescriptions are not kept,
Hath left me, and I, desperate, now approve
Desire is death, which physic did except.
Past cure I am, now reason is past care,
And frantic mad with ever more unrest;
My thoughts and my discourse as madmen's are,
At random from the truth vainly expressed:
    For I have sworn thee fair, and thought thee bright,
    Who art as black as hell, as dark as night.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0148">
<head>
   <title>148</title>
   <toctitle>148</toctitle>
   <indextitle>148</indextitle>
   <firstline>O me! What eyes hath Love put in my head</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O me! What eyes hath Love put in my head,
Which have no correspondence with true sight?
Or if they have, where is my judgement fled,
That censures falsely what they see aright?
If that be fair whereon my false eyes dote,
What means the world to say it is not so?
If it be not, then love doth well denote,
Love's eye is not so true as all men's: no,
How can it? O how can Love's eye be true,
That is so vexed with watching and with tears?
No marvel then though I mistake my view:
The sun itself sees not, till heaven clears.
    O cunning Love, with tears thou keep'st me blind,
    Lest eyes well seeing thy foul faults should find.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0149">
<head>
   <title>149</title>
   <toctitle>149</toctitle>
   <indextitle>149</indextitle>
   <firstline>Canst thou, O cruel, say I love thee not</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Canst thou, O cruel, say I love thee not,
When I against myself with thee partake?
Do I not think on thee, when I forgot
Am of myself, all, tyrant, for thy sake?
Who hateth thee, that I do call my friend?
On whom frown'st thou, that I do fawn upon?
Nay, if thou lour'st on me, do I not spend
Revenge upon myself with present moan?
What merit do I in myself respect
That is so proud thy service to despise,
When all my best doth worship thy defect,
Commanded by the motion of thine eyes?
    But, love, hate on; for now I know thy mind:
    Those that can see thou lov'st, and I am blind.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0150">
<head>
   <title>150</title>
   <toctitle>150</toctitle>
   <indextitle>150</indextitle>
   <firstline>O from what power hast thou this powerful might</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>O from what power hast thou this powerful might,
With insufficiency my heart to sway,
To make me give the lie to my true sight,
And swear that brightness doth not grace the day?
Whence hast thou this becoming of things ill,
That in the very refuse of thy deeds
There is such strength and warrantise of skill
That in my mind thy worst all best exceeds?
Who taught thee how to make me love thee more,
The more I hear and see just cause of hate?
O, though I love what others do abhor,
With others thou shouldst not abhor my state:
    If thy unworthiness raised love in me,
    More worthy I to be beloved of thee.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0151">
<head>
   <title>151</title>
   <toctitle>151</toctitle>
   <indextitle>151</indextitle>
   <firstline>Love is too young to know what conscience is</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Love is too young to know what conscience is:
Yet who knows not conscience is born of love?
Then, gentle cheater, urge not my amiss,
Lest guilty of my faults thy sweet self prove;
For, thou betraying me, I do betray
My nobler part to my gross body's treason;
My soul doth tell my body that he may
Triumph in love; flesh stays no father reason,
But rising at thy name doth point out thee
As his triumphant prize, proud of this pride:
He is contented thy poor drudge to be,
To stand in thy affairs, fall by thy side.
    No want of conscience hold it that I call
    Her "love" for whose dear love I rise and fall.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0152">
<head>
   <title>152</title>
   <toctitle>152</toctitle>
   <indextitle>152</indextitle>
   <firstline>In loving thee thou knowst I am forsworn</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>In loving thee thou knowst I am forsworn;
But thou art twice forsworn to me love swearing,
In act thy bed-vow broke and new faith torn,
In vowing new hate after new love bearing.
But why of two oaths' breach do I accuse thee,
When I break twenty? I am perjured most,
For all my vows are oaths but to misuse thee,
And all my honest faith in thee is lost:
For I have sworn deep oaths of thy deep kindness,
Oaths of thy love, thy truth, thy constancy,
And to enlighten thee gave eyes to blindness,
Or made them swear against the thing they see:
    For I have sworn thee fair: more perjured eye,
    To swear against the truth so foul a lie.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0153">
<head>
   <title>153</title>
   <toctitle>153</toctitle>
   <indextitle>153</indextitle>
   <firstline>Cupid laid by his brand, and fell asleep</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>Cupid laid by his brand, and fell asleep;
A maid of Dian's this advantage found,
And his love-kindling fire did quickly steep
In a cold valley-fountain of that ground,
Which borrowed from this holy fire of Love
A dateless lively heat still to endure,
And grew a seething bath, which yet men prove
Against strange maladies a sovereign cure:
But at my mistress' eye Love's brand new fired,
The boy for trial needs would touch my breast;
I, sick withal, the help of bath desired,
And thither hied, a sad distempered guest,
    But found no cure; the bath for my help lies
    Where Cupid got new fire: my mistress' eyes.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="shakespeare0154">
<head>
   <title>154</title>
   <toctitle>154</toctitle>
   <indextitle>154</indextitle>
   <firstline>The little Love-god lying once asleep</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2,korrektur3,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
---

<resetnum/>The little Love-god lying once asleep,
Laid by his side his heart-inflaming brand,
Whilst many nymphs, that vowed chaste life to keep,
Came tripping by; but in her maiden hand
The fairest votary took up that fire
Which many legions of true hearts had warmed;
And so the general of hot desire
Was sleeping by a virgin hand disarmed.
This brand she quenched in a cool well by,
Which from Love's fire took heat perpetual,
Growing a bath and healthful remedy
For men diseased; but I, my mistress' thrall,
    Came there for cure, and this by that I prove:
    Love's fire heats water, water cools not love.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
