<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="howard" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <notes>
      <note>Alle Howards (eller som han også kaldes: Surreys) digte følger enten den autoritative udgave ved Emrys Jones, eller også er de taget direkte fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany</i> (en digtantologi udgivet første gang i 1557). Hvis et digt forefindes både i manuskript og i Tottels antologi er begge tekster medtaget fordi de ofte varierer meget fra hinanden, variationer der, rimeligvis, skyldes Richard Tottel og altså ikke har noget med Howard at gøre; i de tilfælde står manuskriptversionen altid øverst med Tottel-teksten som et appendix nedenunder. Den specielle stavemåde vil nok irritere en "moderne læser", men prøv at læs højt for dig selv; mange af de sære stavemåder er "fonetisk korrekte", f.eks. er "raine" (dvs. "reign") ingen forhindring når man blot hører ordet og ellers har konteksten med.</note>
      <note type="credits">Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="howard2002031701">
<head>
   <title>When ragyng loue with extreme payne</title>
   <toctitle>When ragyng loue with extreme payne</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When ragyng loue with extreme payne</indextitle>
   <firstline>When ragyng loue with extreme payne</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 14-15.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>The louer comforteth himself with the worthinesse of his loue</i>.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
When ragyng loue with extreme payne
Most cruelly distrains my hart:
When that my teares, as floudes of rayne,
Beare witnes of my wofull smart:
When sighes haue wasted so my breath,
That I lye at the poynte of death:

I call to minde the nauye greate,
That the Grekes brought to Troye towne:
And how the boysteous windes did beate
Their shyps, and rente their sayles adowne,
Till Agamemnons daughters bloode
Appeasde the goddes, that them withstode.

And how that in those ten yeres warre,
Full many a bloudye dede was done,
And many a lord, that came full farre,
There caught his bane (alas) to sone:
And many a good knight ouerronne,
Before the Grekes had Helene wonne.

Then thinke I thus: sithe suche repayre,
So longe time warre of valiant men,
Was all to winne a ladye fayre:
Shall I not learne to suffer then,
And thinke my life well spent to be,
Seruyng a worthier wight than she?

Therfore I neuer will repent,
But paynes contented stil endure.
For like as when, rough winter spent,
The pleasant spring straight draweth in vre:
So after ragyng stormes of care
Joyful at length may be my fare.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031702">
<head>
   <title>The soote season, that bud and blome furth bringes</title>
   <toctitle>The soote season, that bud and blome furth bringes</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The soote season, that bud and blome furth bringes</indextitle>
   <firstline>The soote season, that bud and blome furth bringes</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 4.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>Description of Spring, wherin eche thing renewes, saue onelie the louer</i>.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
The soote season, that bud and blome furth bringes,
With grene hath clad the hill and eke the vale:
The nightingale with fethers new she singes:
The turtle to her make hath tolde her tale:
Somer is come, for euery spray nowe springes,
The hart hath hong his olde hed on the pale:
The buck in brake his winter cote he flinges:
The fishes flote with newe repaired scale:
The adder all her sloughe awaye she slinges:
The swift swalow pursueth the flyes smale:
The busy bee her honye now she minges:
Winter is worne that was the flowers bale:
And thus I see among these pleasant thinges
Eche care decayes, and yet my sorow springes.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031704">
<head>
   <title>Set me wheras the sonne dothe perche the grene</title>
   <toctitle>Set me wheras the sonne dothe perche the grene</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Set me wheras the sonne dothe perche the grene</indextitle>
   <firstline>Set me wheras the sonne dothe perche the grene</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 2-3, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 11.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Set me wheras the sonne dothe perche the grene,
Or whear his beames may not dissolve the ise;
In temprat heat wheare he is felt and sene;
With prowde people, in presence sad and wyse;
Set me in base, or yet in highe degree,
In the long night, or in the shortyst day,
In clere weather, or whear mysts thikest be,
In loste yowthe, or when my heares be grey;
Set me in earthe, in heaven, or yet in hell,
In hill, in dale, or in the fowming floode;
Thrawle, or at large, alive whersoo I dwell,
Sike, or in healthe, in yll fame or in good:
Yours will I be, and with that onely thought
Comfort my self when that my hape is nowght.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Vow to loue faithfully howsoeuer he be rewarded</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>Set me wheras the sunne doth parche the grene,
Or where his beames do not dissolue the yse:
In temperate heate where he is felt and sene:
In presence prest of people madde or wise.
Set me in hye, or yet in lowe degree:
In longest night, or in the shortest daye:
In clearest skye, or where clowdes thickest be:
In lusty youth, or when my heeres are graye.
Set me in heauen, in earth, or els in hell,
In hyll, or dale, or in the fomyng flood:
Thrall, or at large, aliue where so I dwell:
Sicke, or in health: in euyll fame, or good.
Hers will I be, and onely with this thought
Content my selfe, although my chaunce be nought.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031703">
<head>
   <title>Love that doth raine and live within my thought</title>
   <toctitle>Love that doth raine and live within my thought</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Love that doth raine and live within my thought</indextitle>
   <firstline>Love that doth raine and live within my thought</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 3, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 8.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Love that doth raine and live within my thought,
And buylt his seat within my captyve brest,
Clad in the armes wherin with me he fowght
Oft in my face he doth his banner rest.
But she that tawght me love and suffre paine,
My doubtfull hope and eke my hote desire
With shamfast looke to shadoo and refrayne,
Her smyling grace convertyth streight to yre.
And cowarde love than to the hert apace
Taketh his flight where he doth lorke and playne
His purpose lost, and dare not show his face.
For my lordes gylt thus fawtless byde I payine;
Yet from my lorde shall not my foote remove.
Sweet is the death that taketh end by love.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Complaint of a louer rebuked</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>Loue, that liueth, and reigneth in my thought,
That built his seat within my captiue brest,
Clad in the armes, wherin with me he fought,
Oft in my face he doth his banner rest.
She, that me taught to loue, and suffer payne,
My doutfull hope, and eke my hote desyre,
With shamefast cloke to shadowe, and refraine,
Her smilyng grace conuerteth straight to yre.
And cowarde Loue then to the hart apace
Taketh his flight, whereas he lurkes, and plaines
His purpose lost, and dare not shewe his face.
For my lordes gilt thus faultlesse byde I paynes.
Yet from my lorde shall not my foote remoue.
Swete is his death, that takes his end by loue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031705">
<head>
   <title>In Cypres springes, wheras dame Venus dwelt</title>
   <toctitle>In Cypres springes, wheras dame Venus dwelt</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In Cypres springes, wheras dame Venus dwelt</indextitle>
   <firstline>In Cypres springes, wheras dame Venus dwelt</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 3, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 9.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
In Cypres springes, wheras dame Venus dwelt,
A well so hote that who so tastes the same,
Were he of stone, as thawed yse shuld melt,
And kindled fynde his brest with secret flame;
Whose moist poison dissolved hath my hate.
This creping fier my cold lymms so oprest
That in the hart that harbred fredom late
Endles dispaire long thraldom hath imprest.
One eke so cold in froson snow is found,
Whose chilling venume of repugnaunt kind
The fervent heat doth quenche of Cupides wound,
And with the spote of change infects the mynd;
Whereof my deer hath tasted to my payne.
My service thus is growne into disdayne.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Complaint of the louer disdained</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>In Ciprus, springes (whereas dame Venus dwelt)
A well so hote, that whoso tastes the same,
Were he of stone, as thawed yse should melt,
And kindled fynde his brest with fired flame.
Whose moyst poyson dissolued hath my hate.
This creeping fire my colde lims so opprest,
That in the hart that harborde freedome late,
Endlesse despeyre longe thraldome hath imprest.
An other so colde in frozen yse is founde,
Whose chilling venom of repugnant kynde
The feruent heat doth quenche of Cupides wounde:
And with the spot of change infectes the minde:
Whereof my dere hath tasted, to my paine.
My seruice thus is growen into disdaine.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031706">
<head>
   <title>I never saw youe, madam, laye aparte</title>
   <toctitle>I never saw youe, madam, laye aparte</toctitle>
   <indextitle>I never saw youe, madam, laye aparte</indextitle>
   <firstline>I never saw youe, madam, laye aparte</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 4, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 11-12.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
I never saw youe, madam, laye aparte
Your cornet black in colde nor yet in heate
Sythe first ye knew of my desire so greate
which other fances chased cleane from my harte.
Whiles to my self I did the thought reserve
That so unware did wounde my wofull brest
Pytie I saw within your hart dyd rest;
But since ye knew I did youe love and serve
Your golden treese was clad alway in blacke,
Your smilyng lokes were hid thus evermore,
All that withdrawne that I did crave so sore.
So doth this cornet goveme me alacke,
In sommere sonne, in winter breath of frost;
Of your faire eies whereby the light is lost.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Complaint that his ladie after she knew of his loue kept her face alway hidden from him</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>I neuer sawe my Ladye laye apart
Her cornet blacke, in colde nor yet in heate,
Sith first she knew my griefe was growen so great,
Which other fansies driueth from my hart
That to my selfe I do the thought reserue,
The which vnwares did wounde my wofull brest:
But on her face mine eyes mought neuer rest,
Yet, sins she knew I did her loue and serue
Her golden tresses cladde alway with blacke,
Her smilyng lokes that hid thus euermore,
And that restraines whiche I desire so sore.
So dothe this cornet gouerne me alacke:
In somer, sunne: in winters breath, a frost:
Wherby the light of her faire lokes I lost.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031707">
<head>
   <title>Alas so all thinges nowe doe holde their peace</title>
   <toctitle>Alas so all thinges nowe doe holde their peace</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Alas so all thinges nowe doe holde their peace</indextitle>
   <firstline>Alas so all thinges nowe doe holde their peace</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 10.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>A complaint by night of the louer not beloued</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
Alas so all thinges nowe doe holde their peace.
Heauen and earth disturbed in nothing:
The beastes, the ayer, the birdes their song doe cease:
The nightes chare the starres aboute dothe bring:
Calme is the Sea, the waues worke lesse and lesse:
So am not I, whom loue alas doth wring,
Bringing before my face the great encrease
Of my desires, whereat I wepe and syng,
In ioye and wo, as in a doutfull ease.
For my swete thoughtes sometyme doe pleasure bring:
But by and by the cause of my disease
Geues me a pang, that inwardly dothe sting,
When that I thinke what griefe it is againe,
To liue and lacke the thing should ridde my paine.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031708">
<head>
   <title>The golden gift that Nature did thee geve</title>
   <toctitle>The golden gift that Nature did thee geve</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The golden gift that Nature did thee geve</indextitle>
   <firstline>The golden gift that Nature did thee geve</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 12.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>Request to his loue to ioyne bountie with beautie</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
The golden gift that nature did thee geue,
To fasten frendes, and fede them at thy wyll,
With fourme and fauour, taught me to beleue,
How thou art made to shew her greatest skill.
Whose hidden vertues are not so vnknowen,
But liuely domes might gather at the first
Where beautye so her perfect seede hath sowen,
Of other graces folow nedes there must.
Now certesse Ladie, sins all this is true,
That from aboue thy gyftes are thus elect:
Do not deface them than with fansies newe,
Nor chaunge of mindes let not thy minde infect:
But mercy him thy frende, that doth thee serue,
Who seekes alway thine honour to preserue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031709">
<head>
   <title>From Tuscan cam my ladies worthi race</title>
   <toctitle>From Tuscan cam my ladies worthi race</toctitle>
   <indextitle>From Tuscan cam my ladies worthi race</indextitle>
   <firstline>From Tuscan cam my ladies worthi race</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 5, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 9.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
From Tuscan cam my ladies worthi race;
Faire Florence was sometime her auncient seate;
The westorne ile, whose pleasaunt showre doth face
Wylde Chambares cliffes, did geve her lyvely heate.
Fostred she was with mylke of Irishe brest;
Her syer an erle, hir dame of princes bloud;
From tender yeres in Britaine she doth rest,
With a kinges child, where she tastes gostly foode.
Honsdon did furst present her to myn eyen:
Bryght ys her hew, and Geraldine she hight;
Hampton me tawght to wishe her furst for myne,
And Windsor, alas, doth chase me from her sight.
Bewty of kind, her vertues from above;
Happy ys he that may obtaine her love.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Description and praise of his loue Geraldine</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>From Tuskane came my Ladies worthy race:
Faire Florence was sometyme her auncient seate:
The Western yle, whose pleasaunt shore dothe face
Wilde Cambers clifs, did geue her liuely heate:
Fostered she was with milke of Irishe brest:
Her sire, an Erle: her dame, of princes blood.
From tender yeres, in Britain she doth rest,
With kinges childe, where she tasteth costly food.
Honsdon did first present her to mine yien:
Bright is her hewe, and Geraldine she hight.
Hampton me taught to wishe her first for mine:
And Windsor, alas, dothe chase me from her sight.
Her beauty of kind her vertues from aboue.
Happy is he, that can obtaine her loue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031710">
<head>
   <title>The fansy, which that I haue serued long</title>
   <toctitle>The fansy, which that I haue serued long</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The fansy, which that I haue serued long</indextitle>
   <firstline>The fansy, which that I haue serued long</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 31.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>The fansie of a weried louer</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
   <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
The fansy, which that I haue serued long,
That hath alway bene enmy to myne ease,
Semed of late to rue vpon my wrong,
And bad me flye the cause of my misease.
And I forthwith dyd prease out of the throng,
That thought by flight my painfull hart to please
Som other way: tyll I saw faith more strong:
And to my self I sayd: alas, those dayes
In vayn were spent, to runne the race so long.
And with that thought, I met my guyde, that playn
Out of the way wherin I wandred wrong,
Brought me amiddes the hylles, in base Bullayn:
Where I am now, as restlesse to remayn,
Against my will, full pleased with my payn.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031711">
<head>
   <title>The sonne hath twyse brought forthe the tender grene</title>
   <toctitle>The sonne hath twyse brought forthe the tender grene</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The sonne hath twyse brought forthe the tender grene</indextitle>
   <firstline>The sonne hath twyse brought forthe the tender grene</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 6-7, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 3-4.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
The sonne hath twyse brought forthe the tender grene,
    And cladd the yerthe in livelye lustynes;
    Ones have the wyndes the trees dispoyled clene,
And now agayne begynnes their cruelnes,
    Sins I have hidd under my brest the harme
    That never shall recover helthfulnes.
The wynters hurt recovers with the warme;
    The perched grene restored is with shade:
    What warmth, alas, may sarve for to disarme
The froosyn hart that my inflame hath made?
    What colde agayne is hable to restore
    My freshe grene yeres that wither thus and faade?
Alas, I see nothinge to hurt so sore
    But tyme somtyme reduceth a retourne;
    Yet tyme my harme increseth more and more,
And semes to have my cure allwayes in skorne.
    Straunge kynd of death, in lief that I doo trye:
    At hand to melt, farr of in flame to bourne;
And like as time list to my cure aply,
    So doth eche place my comfort cleane refuse.
    Eche thing alive that sees the heaven with eye
With cloke of night maye cover and excuse
    Him self from travaile of the dayes unrest,
    Save I, alas, against all others use,
That then sturre upp the torment of my brest
    To curse eche starr as cawser of my faat.
    And when the sonne hath eke the darke represt
And brought the daie, it doth nothing abaat
    The travaile of my endles smart and payne.
    For then, as one that hath the light in haat,
I wishe for night, more covertlye to playne
    And me withdrawe from everie haunted place,
    Lest in my chere my chaunce should pere to playne;
And with my mynd I measure paas by paas
    To seke that place where I my self hadd lost,
    That daye that I was tangled in that laase,
In seming slacke that knytteth ever most;
    But never yet the trayvaile of my thought
    Of better state could catche a cawse to bost.
For yf I fynde somtyme that I have sought,
    Those starres by whome I trusted of the port,
    My sayles do fall, and I advaunce right nought,
As anchord fast; my sprites do all resort
    To stand atgaas, and sinke in more and more
    The deadlye harme which she doth take in sport.
Loo, yf I seke, how I do fynd my sore!
    And yf I flye, I carrey with me still
    The venymd shaft which dothe his force restore
By hast of flight. And I maye playne my fill
    Unto my self, oneles this carefull song
    Prynt in your hert some percell of my will.
For I, alas, in sylence all to long
    Of myne old hurt yet fele the wound but grene.
    Rue on my lief, or elles your crewell wrong
Shall well appeare, and by my deth be sene.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Descripcion of the restlesse state of a louer, with sute to his ladie, to rue on his diyng hart</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>The sonne hath twise brought furth his tender grene,
And clad the earth in liuely lustinesse:
Ones haue the windes the trees despoiled clene,
And new again begins their cruelnesse,
Since I haue hid vnder my brest the harm
That neuer shall recouer healthfulnesse.
The winters hurt recouers with the warm:
The parched grene restored is with shade.
What warmth (alas) may serue for to disarm
The frosen hart that mine in flame hath made?
What colde againe is able to restore
My fresh grene yeares, that wither thus and fade?
Alas, I se, nothing hath hurt so sore,
But time in time reduceth a returne:
In time my harm increaseth more and more,
And semes to haue my cure alwaies in scorne.
Strange kindes of death, in life that I doe trie,
At hand to melt, farre of in flame to burne.
And like as time list to my cure aply,
So doth eche place my comfort cleane refuse.
All thing aliue, that seeth the heauens with eye,
With cloke of night may couer, and excuse
It self from trauail of the dayes vnrest,
Saue I, alas, against all others vse,
That then stirre vp the tormentes of my brest,
And curse eche sterre as causer of my fate.
And when the sonne hath eke the dark opprest,
And brought the day, it doth nothing abate
The trauailes of mine endles smart and payn,
For then, as one that hath the light in hate,
I wish for night, more couertly to playn,
And me withdraw from euery haunted place,
Lest by my chere my chance appere to playn:
And in my minde I measure pace by pace,
To seke the place where I my self had lost,
That day that I was tangled in the lace,
In semyng slack that knitteth euer most:
But neuer yet the trallaile of my thought
Of better state coulde catche a cause to bost.
For if I found sometime that I haue sought,
Those sterres by whome I trusted of the porte,
My sayles doe fall, and I aduance right nought,
As ankerd fast, my spretes doe all resorte
To stande agazed, and sinke in more and more
The deadly harme which she dothe take in sport.
Lo, if I seke, how I doe finde my sore:
And yf I flee I carie with me still
The venomde shaft, whiche dothe his force restore
By hast of flight, and I may plaine my fill
Vnto my selfe, vnlesse this carefull song
Printe in your harte some parcell of my tene
For I, alas, in silence all to long
Of mynr olde hurte yet fele the wounde but grene.
Rue of my life: or els your cruell wronge
Shall well appere, and by my death be sene.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031712">
<head>
   <title>Geue place ye louers, here before</title>
   <toctitle>Geue place ye louers, here before</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Geue place ye louers, here before</indextitle>
   <firstline>Geue place ye louers, here before</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Teksten er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 19-20.</note>
      <note>Tottel gav digtet overskriften <i>A praise of his loue: wherin he reproueth them that compare their Ladies with his</i></note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
Geue place ye louers, here before
That spent your bostes and bragges in vaine:
My Ladies beawtie passeth more
The best of yours, I dare well sayen,
Than doth the sonne, the candle light:
Or brightest day, the darkest night.

And thereto hath a trothe as iust,
As had Penelope the fayre.
For what she saith, ye may it trust,
As it by writing sealed were.
And vertues hath she many moe,
Than I with pen haue skill to showe.

I coulde rehearse, if that I wolde,
The whole effect of natures plaint,
When she had lost the perfit mold,
The like to whom she could not paint:
With wringyng handes howe she dyd cry,
And what she said, I know it, I.

I knowe, she swore with ragyng mynd:
Her kingdom onely set apart,
There was no losse, by lawe of kind,
That could haue gone so nere her hart.
And this was chiefly all her payne:
She coulde not make the lyke agayne.

Sith nature thus gaue her the prayse,
To be the chiefest worke she wrought:
In faith, me thinke, some better waies
On your behalfe might well be sought,
Then to compare (as ye haue done)
To matche the candle with the sonne.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="howard2002031713">
<head>
   <title>Suche waiwarde waies hath love that moste parte in discorde</title>
   <toctitle>Suche waiwarde waies hath love that moste parte in discorde</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Suche waiwarde waies hath love that moste parte in discorde</indextitle>
   <firstline>Suche waiwarde waies hath love that moste parte in discorde</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Den første og mest pålidelige tekst følger <i>Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey: Poems</i>, red. Emrys Jones, Clarendon Press 1964, s. 8-10, og teksten nedenunder er fra <i>Tottel's Miscellany (1557-1587)</i>, red. Hyder E. Rollins, 2 bind, Harvard University Press 1965, b. 1, s. 5-6.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1,kilde</quality>
</head>
<body>
    Suche waiwarde waies hath love that moste parte in discorde;
Our willes do stand wherby our hartes but seldom dooth accorde.
    Disceyte is his delight, and to begyle and mocke
The symple hertes which he doth stryke with froward dyvers stroke.
    He cawseth hertes to rage with golden burninge darte,
And doth alaye with ledden cold agayne the tothers harte.
    Hot gleames of burning fyre and easye sparkes of flame
In balaunce of unegall weight he pondereth by ame.
    From easye fourde, where I might wade and passe full well,
He me withdrawes, and doth me drive into the darke diep well;
    And me withholdes where I am cald and offerd place,
And wooll that still my mortall foo I do beseche of grace.
    He lettes me to pursue a conquest well nere woon,
To follow where my paynes were spilt or that my sute begune.
    Lo, by these rules I know how sone a hart can turne
From warr to peace, from trewce to stryf, and so again returne.
    I know how to convert my will in others lust;
Of litle stuff unto my self to weyve a webb of trust;
    And how to hide my harme with soft dissembled chere,
When in my face the paynted thoughtes wolde owtwardlye appere.
    I know how that the blood forsakes the faas for dredd,
And how by shame it staynes agayne the cheke with flaming redd.
    I know under the grene the serpent how he lurckes;
The hamer of the restles forge I know eke how yt workes.
    I know, and can be roote, the tale that I wold tell,
But ofte the wordes come forth a wrye of hym that loveth well.
    I know in heat and cold the lover how he shakes,
In singinge how he can complayne, in sleaping how he wakes,
    To languishe without ache, sickles for to consume,
A thousand thinges for to devyse resolving all hys fume.
    And thoughe he lyke to see his ladies face full sore,
Such pleasure as delightes his eye doth not his health restore.
    I know to seke the tracke of my desyred foo,
And feare to fynd that I do seke; but chefelye this I know,
    That lovers must transforme into the thing beloved,
And live (alas, who colde beleve?) with spryte from lief removed.
    I know in hart ye sighes and lawghters of the splene
At ones to chaunge my state, my will, and eke my colour clene.
    I know how to disceyve myself withouten helpp,
And how the lyon chastysed is by beating of the whelpp.
    In standing nere my fyer, I know how that I frese;
Farr of, to burn; in both to wast, and so my lief to lese.
    I know how love doth rage uppon the yeldon mynd,
How small a nett may take and mashe a harte of gentle kynd;
    With seldome tasted swete, to season heaps of gall,
Revyved with a glyns of grace olde sorowes to let fall.
    The hidden traynes I know, and secret snares of love;
How sone a loke may prynt a thought that never will remove.
    That slipper state I know, those sodayne tournes from welthe,
That doubtfull hope, that certayne woo, and sure dispaire of helthe.

<nonum>---</nonum>

<wrap><b>Description of the fickle affections panges and sleightes of loue</b></wrap>

<resetnum/>    Suche waiward waies hath loue, that most part in discord
Our willes do stand, whereby our hartes but seldom doe accord.
    Disceit is his delight, and to begile, and mock
The simple hartes whom he doth strike with froward diuers strok.
    He makes the one to rage with golden burning dart,
And doth alay with leaden colde agayn the other hart.
    Whote glemes of burnyng fire, and easy sparkes of flame
In balance of vnegall weight he pondereth by aime.
    From easy forde, where I might wade and passe ful wel,
He me withdrawes, and doth me driue into a depe dark hel,
    And me withholdes where I am calde and offred place,
And willes me that my mortall foe I doe beseke of grace:
    He lettes me to pursue a conquest welnere wonne,
To folow where my paines were lost ere that my suite begonne.
    So by this meanes I know how soone a hart may turne
From warre to peace, from truce to strife, and so again returne,
    I know how to content my self in others lust,
Of litle stuffe vnto my self to weaue a webbe of trust:
    And how to hide my harmes with soft dissembling chere,
When in my face the painted thoughtes would outwardly apere.
    I know how that the blood forsakes the face for dred:
And how by shame it staines again the chekes with flaming red.
    I know vnder the grene the serpent how he lurkes.
The hammer of the restles forge I wote eke how it wurkes.
    I know and can by roate the tale that I would tel:
But oft the wordes come furth awrie of him that loueth wel.
    I know in heat and colde the louer how he shakes:
In singing how he doth complain, in slepyng how he wakes:
    To languish without ache, sicklesse for to consume:
A thousand thinges for to deuise resoluing all in fume.
    And though he list to se his ladies grace ful sore,
Such pleasures as delight the eye doe not his health restore.
    I know to seke the track of my desired foe,
And feare to finde that I do seke. But chiefly this I know,
    That louers must transforme into the thing beloued,
And liue (alas who would beleue?) with sprite from life remoued,
    I know in harty sighes, and laughters of the splene
At once to change my state, my wyll, and eke my coloure clene.
    I know how to deceaue my self with others help:
And how the Lion chastised is by beating of the whelp.
    In standyng nere my fire I know how that I freze.
Farre of I burne, in both I wast, and so my life I leze.
    I know how loue doth rage vpon a yelding mynde:
How smal a net may take and meash a hart of gentle kinde:
    Or els with seldom swete to season heapes of gall,
Reuiued with a glimse of grace olde sorowes to let fall,
    The hidden traines I know, and secret snares of loue:
How soone a loke wil printe a thought, that neuer may remoue.
    The slipper state I know, the sodain turnes from wealth,
The doubtful hope, the certain woe, and sure despeire of health.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
