<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="wolfe" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="wolfe2019090701">
<head>
   <title>The Burial of Sir John Moore after Corunna</title>
   <subtitle>1817</subtitle>
   <firstline></firstline>
</head>
<body>
Not a drum was heard, not a funeral note,
As his corse to the rampart we hurried;
Not a soldier discharged his farewell shot
O’er the grave where our hero we buried.

We buried him darkly at dead of night,
The sods with our bayonets turning;
By the struggling moonbeam’s misty light
And the lantern dimly burning.

No useless coffin enclosed his breast,
Nor in sheet nor in shroud we wound him,
But he lay like a warrior taking his rest
With his martial cloak around him.

Few and short were the prayers we said,
And we spoke not a word of sorrow;
But we steadfastly gazed on the face that was dead,
And we bitterly thought of the morrow.

We thought, as we hollowed his narrow bed
And smoothed down his lonely pillow,
That the foe and the stranger would tread o’er his head,
And we far away on the billow!

Lightly they’ll talk of the spirit that’s gone
And o’er his cold ashes upbraid him,
But little he’ll reck, if they let him sleep on
In the grave where a Briton has laid him.

But half of our heavy task was done
When the clock struck the hour for retiring;
And we heard the distant and random gun
That the foe was sullenly firing.

Slowly and sadly we laid him down,
From the field of his fame fresh and gory;
We carved not a line, and we raised not a stone,
But left him alone with his glory.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="wolfe2019090702">
<head>
    <title>Song</title>
    <firstline>Go, forget me—why should sorrow</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Go, forget me—why should sorrow 
  O'er that brow a shadow fling? 
Go, forget me—and to-morrow 
  Brightly smile and sweetly sing. 
Smile—though I shall not be near thee; 
Sing—though I shall never hear thee; 
  May thy soul with pleasure shine 
  Lasting as the gloom of mine! 
      Go, forget me, etc. 

Like the Sun, thy presence glowing 
  Clothes the meanest things in light; 
And when thou, like him, art going. 
  Loveliest objects fade in night. 
All things looked so bright about thee, 
That they nothing seem without thee ; 
  By that pure and lucid mind 
  Earthly things were too refined. 
      Like the Sun, etc. 

Go, thou vision wildly gleaming, 
  Softly on my soul that fell; 
Go, for me no longer beaming— 
  Hope and Beauty! fare ye well! 
Go, and all that once delighted 
Take, and leave me all benighted : 
Glory's burning—generous swell, 
  Fancy and the Poet's shell. 
      Go, thou vision, etc.     
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
