<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="wordsworth" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="wordsworth2001062401">
<head>
   <title>She was a Phantom of delight</title>
   <toctitle>She was a Phantom of delight</toctitle>
   <indextitle>She was a Phantom of delight</indextitle>
   <firstline>She was a Phantom of delight</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
She was a Phantom of delight
When first she gleamed upon my sight;
A lovely Apparition, sent
To be a moment's ornament;
Her eyes as stars of Twilight fair;
Like Twilight's, too, her dusky hair;
But all things else about her drawn
From May-time and the cheerful Dawn;
A dancing Shape, an Image gay,
To haunt, to startle, and way-lay.
I saw her upon nearer view,
A Spirit, yet a Woman too!
Her household motions light and free,
And steps of virgin-liberty;
A countenance in which did meet
Sweet records, promises as sweet;
A Creature not too bright or good
For human nature's daily food;
For transient sorrows, simple wiles,
Praise, blame, love, kisses, tears, and smiles.
And now I see with eye serene
The very pulse of the machine;
A Being breathing thoughtful breath,
A Traveller between life and death;
The reason firm, the temperate will,
Endurance, foresight, strength, and skill;
A perfect Woman, nobly planned,
To warn, to comfort, and command;
And yet a Spirit still, and bright
With something of angelic light.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062402">
<head>
   <title>The world is too much with us</title>
   <toctitle>The world is too much with us</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The world is too much with us</indextitle>
   <firstline>The world is too much with us: late and soon</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
The world is too much with us: late and soon,
Getting and spending, we lay waste our powers:
Little we see in Nature that is ours;
We have given our hearts away, a sordid boon!
This Sea that bares her bosom to the moon;
The winds that will be howling at all hours,
And are up-gathered now like sleeping flowers;
For this, for everything, we are out of tune;
It moves us not. - Great God! I'd rather be
A Pagan suckled in a creed outworn;
So might I, standing on this pleasant lea,
Have glimpses that would make me less forlorn;
Have sight of Proteus rising from the sea;
Or hear old Triton blow his wreathed horn.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062403">
<head>
   <title>London 1802</title>
   <toctitle>London 1802</toctitle>
   <indextitle>London 1802</indextitle>
   <firstline>Milton! thou shouldst be living at this hour</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Milton! thou shouldst be living at this hour:
England hath need of thee: she is a fen
Of stagnant waters: altar, sword, and pen,
Fireside, the heroic wealth of hall and bower,
Have forfeited their ancient English dower
Of inward happiness. We are selfish men;
Oh! raise us up, return to us again;
And give us manners, virtue, freedom, power.
Thy soul was like a Star, and dwelt apart;
Thou hadst a voice whose sound was like the sea:
Pure as the naked heavens, majestic, free,
So didst thou travel on life's common way,
In cheerful godliness; and yet the heart
The lowliest duties on herself did lay.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062404">
<head>
   <title>A Slumber Did My Spirit Seal</title>
   <toctitle>A Slumber Did My Spirit Seal</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Slumber Did My Spirit Seal</indextitle>
   <firstline>A slumber did my spirit seal</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
A slumber did my spirit seal;
I had no human fears;
She seemed a thing that could not feel
The touch of earthly years.

No motion has she now, no force;
She neither hears nor sees;
Rolled round in earth's diurnal course,
With rocks, and stones, and trees.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062405">
<head>
   <title>Composed Upon Westminster Bridge Sept. 3, 1802</title>
   <toctitle>Composed Upon Westminster Bridge Sept. 3, 1802</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Composed Upon Westminster Bridge Sept. 3, 1802</indextitle>
   <firstline>Earth has not anything to show more fair</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Earth has not anything to show more fair:
Dull would he be of soul who could pass by
A sight so touching in its majesty:
This city now doth, like a garment wear
The beauty of the morning; silent, bare,
Ships, towers, domes, theatres, and temples lie
Open unto the fields, and to the sky;
All bright and glittering in the smokeless air.
Never did sun more beautifully steep
In his first splendour, valley, rock, or hill;
Ne'er saw I, never felt, a calm so deep!
The river glideth at his own sweet will:
Dear God! the very houses seem asleep;
And all that mighty heart is lying still!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062406">
<head>
   <title>Daffodils</title>
   <toctitle>Daffodils</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Daffodils</indextitle>
   <firstline>I wandered lonely as a cloud</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
I wandered lonely as a cloud
That floats on high o'er vales and hills,
When all at once I saw a crowd,
A host, of golden daffodils;
Beside the lake, beneath the trees,
Fluttering and dancing in the breeze.

Continuous as the stars that shine
And twinkle on the milky way,
They stretched in never-ending line
Along the margin of a bay:
Ten thousand saw I at a glance,
Tossing their heads in sprightly dance.

The waves beside them danced; but they
Out-did the sparkling waves in glee:
A poet could not but be gay,
In such a jocund company:
I gazed - and gazed - but little thought
What wealth the show to me had brought:

For oft, when on my couch I lie
In vacant or in pensive mood,
They flash upon that inward eye
Which is the bliss of solitude;
And then my heart with pleasure fills,
And dances with the daffodils.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062407">
<head>
   <title>She Dwelt Among the Untrodden Ways</title>
   <toctitle>She Dwelt Among the Untrodden Ways</toctitle>
   <indextitle>She Dwelt Among the Untrodden Ways</indextitle>
   <firstline>She dwelt among the untrodden ways</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
She dwelt among the untrodden ways
Beside the springs of Dove,
A Maid whom there were none to praise
And very few to love:

A violet by a mossy stone
Half hidden from the eye!
- Fair as a star, when only one
Is shining in the sky.

She lived unknown, and few could know
When Lucy ceased to be;
But she is in her grave, and, oh,
The difference to me!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062408">
<head>
   <title>My heart leaps up when I behold</title>
   <toctitle>My heart leaps up when I behold</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My heart leaps up when I behold</indextitle>
   <firstline>My heart leaps up when I behold</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
My heart leaps up when I behold
A rainbow in the sky:
So was it when my life began;
So is it now I am a man;
So be it when I shall grow old,
Or let me die!
The Child is father of the Man;
I could wish my days to be
Bound each to each by natural piety.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2001062409">
<head>
   <title>Not Love, not War, nor the tumultuous swell</title>
   <toctitle>Not Love, not War, nor the tumultuous swell</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Not Love, not War, nor the tumultuous swell</indextitle>
   <firstline>Not Love, not War, nor the tumultuous swell</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Not Love, not War, nor the tumultuous swell,
Of civil conflict, nor the wrecks of change,
Nor Duty struggling with afflictions strange -
Not these 'alone' inspire the tuneful shell;
But where untroubled peace and concord dwell,
There also is the Muse not loth to range,
Watching the twilight smoke of cot or grange,
Skyward ascending from a woody dell.
Meek aspirations please her, lone endeavour,
And sage content, and placid melancholy;
She loves to gaze upon a crystal river -
Diaphanous because it travels slowly;
Soft is the music that would charm for ever;
The flower of sweetest smell is shy and lowly.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2019090901">
<head>
    <title>Where lies the Land to which yon Ship must go?</title>
    <firstline>Where lies the Land to which yon Ship must go?</firstline>
    <keywords>sonnet</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>Where</sc> lies the Land to which yon Ship must go?
Festively she puts forth in trim array;
As vigorous as a Lark at break of day:
Is she for tropic suns, or polar snow?
What boots the enquiry? Neither friend nor foe
She cares for; let her travel where she may,
She finds familiar names, a beaten way
Ever before her, and a wind to blow.
Yet still I ask, what Haven is her mark?
And, almost as it was when ships were rare,
From time to time, like Pilgrims, here and there
Crossing the waters; doubt, and something dark,
Of the old Sea some reverential fear,
Is with me at thy farewell, joyous Bark!

</poetry>
</body>
</text>


<text id="wordsworth2020042301">
<head>
    <title>The Happy Warrior</title>
    <firstline>Tis, finally, the man, who, lifted high</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
'Tis, finally, the man, who, lifted high,
Conspicuous object in a nation's eye,
Or left unthought of in obscurity,
Who, with a toward or untoward lot,
Prosperous or adverse, to his wish or not,--
Plays, in the many games of life, that one
Where what he most doth value must be won;
Whom neither shape of danger can dismay,
Nor thought of tender happiness betray;
Who, not content that former work stand fast,
Looks forward, persevering to the last,
From well to better, daily self-surpast;
Who, whether praise of him must walk the earth
Forever, and to noble deeds give birth,
Or he must fall, to sleep without his fame,
And leave a dead, unprofitable name--
Finds comfort in himself and in his cause,
And, while the mortal mist is gathering, draws
His breath in confidence of Heaven's applause:
This is the happy warrior; this is he
That every man in arms should wish to be.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2021101701">
<head>
    <title>Strange fits of passion I have known</title>
    <firstline>Strange fits of passion I have known</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Strange fits of passion I have known,
And I will dare to tell,
But in the lover's ear alone,
What once to me befel.

When she I lov'd, was strong and gay
And like a rose in June,
I to her cottage bent my way,
Beneath the evening moon.

Upon the moon I fix'd my eye,
All over the wide lea;
My horse trudg'd on, and we drew nigh
Those paths so dear to me.

And now we reach'd the orchard plot,
And, as we climb'd the hill,
Towards the roof of Lucy's cot
The moon descended still.

In one of those sweet dreams I slept,
Kind Nature's gentlest boon!
And, all the while, my eyes I kept
On the descending moon.

My horse mov'd on; hoof after hoof
He rais'd and never stopp'd:
When down behind the cottage roof
At once the planet dropp'd.

What fond and wayward thoughts will slide
Into a Lover's head—
"O mercy!" to myself I cried,
"If Lucy should be dead!"
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="wordsworth2021101901">
<head>
    <title>Surprized by joy</title>
    <firstline>Surprized by joy—impatient as the Wind</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Surprized by joy—impatient as the Wind
I wished to share the transport–Oh! with whom
But Thee, long buried in the silent Tomb,
That spot which no vicissitude can find?
Love, faithful love recalled thee to my mind –
But how could I forget thee?—Through what power,
Even for the least division of an hour,
Have I been so beguiled as to be blind
To my most grievous loss?—That thought’s return
Was the worst pang that sorrow ever bore,
Save one, one only, when I stood forlorn,
Knowing my heart’s best treasure was no more;
That neither present time, nor years unborn
Could to my sight that heavenly face restore.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
