<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="pope" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="pope2001062401">
<head>
   <title>The universal prayer</title>
   <toctitle>The universal prayer</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The universal prayer</indextitle>
   <firstline>Father of All! in every Age</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Father of All! in every Age,
In every Clime ador'd,
By Saint, by Savage, and by Sage,
Jehovah, Jove, or Lord!

Thou Great First Cause, least Understood!
Who all my Sense confin'd
To know but this, - that Thou art Good,
And that my self am blind:

Yet gave me, in this dark Estate,
To see the Good from Ill;
And binding Nature fast in Fate,
Left free the Human Will.

What Conscience dictates to be done,
Or warns me not to doe,
This, teach me more than Hell to shun,
That, more than Heav'n pursue.

What Blessings thy free Bounty gives,
Let me not cast away;
For God is pay'd when Man receives,
T' enjoy, is to obey.

Yet not to Earth's contracted Span,
Thy Goodness let me bound;
Or think Thee Lord alone of Man,
When thousand Worlds are round.

Let not this weak, unknowing hand
Presume Thy Bolts to throw,
And deal Damnation round the land,
On each I judge thy Foe.

If I am right, oh teach my heart
Still in the right to say;
If I am wrong, Thy Grace impart
To find that better Way.

Save me alike from foolish Pride,
Or impious Discontent,
At ought thy Wisdom has deny'd,
Or ought thy Goodness lent.

Teach me to feel another's Woe;
To hide the Fault I see;
That Mercy I to others show,
That Mercy show to me.

Mean tho' I am, not wholly so
Since quicken'd by thy Breath,
O lead me wheresoe'er I go,
Thro' this day's Life, or Death:

This day, be Bread and Peace my Lot;
All else beneath the Sun,
Thou know'st if best bestow'd, or not;
And let Thy Will be done.

To Thee, whose Temple is all Space,
Whose Altar, Earth, Sea, Skies:
One Chorus let all Being raise!
All Nature's Incense rise!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2001062402">
<head>
   <title>Ode on solitude</title>
   <toctitle>Ode on solitude</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Ode on solitude</indextitle>
   <firstline>Happy the man, whose wish and care</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <keywords>ode</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Happy the man, whose wish and care
A few paternal acres bound,
Content to breathe his native air,
In his own ground.

Whose herds with milk, whose fields with bread,
Whose flocks supply him with attire,
Whose trees in summer yield him shade,
In winter fire.

Blest! who can unconcern'dly find
Hours, days, and years slide soft away,
In health of body, peace of mind,
Quiet by day,

Sound sleep by night; study and ease
Together mix'd; sweet recreation,
And innocence, which most doth please,
With meditation.

Thus let me live, unseen, unknown;
Thus unlamented let me dye;
Steal from the world, and not a stone
Tell where I lye.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2001062403">
<head>
   <title>Epitaph.</title>
   <subtitle>On John Lord Caryll</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Epitaph.</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Epitaph.</indextitle>
   <firstline>A manly Form; a bold, yet modest mind</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
A manly Form; a bold, yet modest mind;
Sincere, tho' prudent; constant, yet resign'd;
Honour unchang'd; a Principle profest;
Fix'd to one side, but mod'rate to the rest;
An honest Courtier, and a Patriot too;
Just to his Prince, and to his Country true:
All these were join'd in one, yet fail'd to save
The Wise, the Learn'd, the Virtuous, and the Brave;
Lost, like the common Plunder of the Grave!
Ye Few, whom better Genius does inspire,
Exalted Souls, inform'd with purer Fire!
Go now, learn all vast Science can impart;
Go fathom Nature, take the Heights of Art!
Rise higher yet: learn ev'n yourselves to know;
Nay, to yourselves alone that knowledge owe.
Then, when you seem above mankind to soar,
Look on this marble, and be vain no more!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2001062404">
<head>
   <title>On a lady who P---st at the tragedy of Cato</title>
   <toctitle>On a lady who P---st at the tragedy of Cato</toctitle>
   <indextitle>On a lady who P---st at the tragedy of Cato</indextitle>
   <firstline>While maudlin Whigs deplor'd their Cato's Fate</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
While maudlin Whigs deplor'd their <i>Cato's</i> Fate,
Still with dry Eyes the Tory <i>Celia</i> sate,
But while her Pride forbids her Tears to flow,
The gushing Waters find a Vent below:
Tho' secret, yet with copious Grief she mourns,
Like twenty River-Gods with all their Urns.
Let others screw their Hypocritick Face,
She shews her Grief in a sincerer Place;
There Nature reigns, and Passion void of Art,
For that Road leads directly to the Heart.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2001062405">
<head>
   <title>To Mr. John Moore, Author of the Celebrated Worm-Powder</title>
   <toctitle>To Mr. John Moore, Author of the Celebrated Worm-Powder</toctitle>
   <indextitle>To Mr. John Moore, Author of the Celebrated Worm-Powder</indextitle>
   <firstline>How much, egregious Moor, are we</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
How much, egregious <i>Moor</i>, are we
Deceiv'd by Shews and Forms!
Whate'er we think, whate'er we see,
All Humankind are Worms.

Man is a very Worm by Birth,
Vile Reptile, weak, and vain!
A while he crawls upon the Earth,
Then shrinks to Earth again.

That Woman is a Worm we find,
E'er since our Grandame's Evil;
She first convers'd with her own Kind,
That antient Worm, the Devil.

The Learn'd themselves we Book-Worms name;
The Blockhead is a Slow-worm;
The Nymph whose Tail is all on Flame
Is aptly term'd a Glow-worm:

The Fops are painted Butterflies,
That flutter for a Day;
First from a Worm they take their Rise,
And in a Worm decay:

The Flatterer an Earwig grows;
Thus Worms suit all Conditions;
Misers are Muckworms, Silk-worms Beaus,
And Death-watches Physicians.

That Statesmen have the Worm, is seen
By all their winding Play;
Their Conscience is a Worm within,
That gnaws them Night and Day.

Ah <i>Moore</i>! thy skill were well employ'd,
And greater Gain would rise,
if thou could'st make the Courtier void
The Worm that never dies!

O learned Friend of <i>Abchurch-Lane</i>,
Who sett'st our Entrails free!
Vain is thy Art, thy Powder vain,
Since Worms shall eat ev'n thee.

Our Fate thou ounly can'st adjourn
Some few short Years, no more!
Ev'n <i>Button's</i> Wits to Worms shall turn,
Who Maggots were before.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2001062406">
<head>
   <title>Bounce to Fop</title>
   <subtitle>An heroick epistle from a dog at Twickenham to a dog at court</subtitle>
   <toctitle>Bounce to Fop</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Bounce to Fop</indextitle>
   <firstline>To thee, sweet Fop, these Lines I send</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
To thee, sweet <i>Fop</i>, these Lines I send,
Who, tho' no Spaniel, am a Friend.
Tho, once my Tail in wanton play,
Now frisking this, and then that way,
Chanc'd, with a Touch of just the Tip,
To hurt your Lady-lap-dog-ship;
Yet thence to think I'd bite your Head off!
Sure <i>Bounce</i> is one you never read of.

FOP! you can dance, and make a Leg,
Can fetch and carry, cringe and beg,
And (what's the Top of all your Tricks)
Can stoop to pick up <i>Strings</i> and <i>Sticks</i>.
We Country Dogs love nobler Sport,
And scorn the Pranks of Dogs at Court.
Fye, naughty Fop! where e'er you come
To f---t and p---ss about the Room,
To lay your Head in every Lap,
And, when they think not of you - snap!
The worst that Envy, or that Spite
E'er said of me, is, I can bite:
That sturdy Vagrants, Rogues in Rags,
Who poke at me, can make no Brags;
And that to towze such Things as <i>flutter</i>,
To honest <i>Bounce</i> is Bread and Butter.

While you, and every courtly Fop,
Fawn on the Devil for a Chop,
I've the Humanity to hate
A Butcher, tho' he brings me Meat;
And let me tell you, have a Nose,
(Whatever stinking Fops suppose)
That under Cloth of Gold or Tissue,
Can smell a Plaister, or an Issue.

Your pilf'ring Lord, with simple Pride,
May wear a Pick-lock at his Side;
My Master wants no Key of State,
For <i>Bounce</i> can keep his House and Gate.

When all such Dogs have had their Days,
As knavish <i>Pams</i>, and fawning <i>Trays</i>;
When pamper'd <i>Cupids</i>, bestly <i>Veni's</i>,
And motly, squinting <i>Harvequini's</i>,
Shall lick no more their Lady's Br---,
But die of Looseness, Claps, or Itch;
Fair <i>Thames</i> from either ecchoing Shoare
Shall hear, and dread my manly Roar.

See <i>Bounce</i>, like <i>Berecynthia</i>, crown'd
With thund'ring Offspring all around,
Beneath, beside me, and a top,
A hundred Sons! and not one <i>Fop</i>.

Before my Children set your Beef,
Not one true <i>Bounce</i> will be a Thief;
Not one without Permission feed,
(Tho' some of F---'s hungry Breed)
But whatsoe'er the Father's Race,
From me they suck a little Grace.
While your fine Whelps learn all to steal,
Bred up by Hand and Chick and Veal.

My Eldest-born resides not far,
Where shines great <i>Strafford's</i> glittering Star:
My second (Child of Fortune!) waits
At <i>Burlington's</i> Palladian Gates:
A third majestically stalks
(Happiest of Dogs!) in <i>Cobham's</i> Walks:
One ushers Friends to <i>Bathurst's</i> Door;
One fawns, at <i>Oxford's</i>, on the Poor.

Nobles, who Arms or Arts adorn,
Wait for my Infants yet unborn.
None but a Peer of Wit and Grace,
Can hope a Puppy of my Race.

And O! wou'd Fate the Bliss decree
To mine (a Bliss too great for me)
That two, my tallest Sons, might grace
Attending each with stately Pace,
<i>Iulus'</i> Side, as erst <i>Evander's</i>,
To keep off Flatt'rers, Spies, and Panders,
To let no noble Slave come near,
And scare Lord <i>Fannys</i> from his Ear:
Then might a Royal Youth, and true,
Enjoy at least a Friend - or two:
A Treasure, which, of Royal kind,
Few but Himself deserve to find.

Then <i>Bounce</i> ('tis all that <i>Bounce</i> can crave)
Shall wag her Tail within the Grave.

And tho' no Doctors, Whig, or Tory ones,
Except the Sect of <i>Pythagoreans</i>,
Have Immortality assign'd
To any Beast, but <i>Dryden's</i> Hind:
Yet Master <i>Pope</i>, whom Truth and Sense
Shall call their Friend some Ages hence,
Tho' now on loftier Themes he sings
Than to bestow a Word on <i>Kings</i>,
Has sworn by <i>Sticks</i> (the Poet's Oath,
And Dread of Dogs and Poets both)
Man and his Works he'll soon renounce,
And roar in Numbers worthy <i>Bounce</i>.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>
<text id="pope2019122501">
<head>
    <title>Windsor Forest</title>
    <firstline>Thy forests, Windsor! and thy green retreats</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Thy forests, Windsor! and thy green retreats,
At once the Monarch's and the Muse's seats,
Invite my lays. Be present, sylvan maids!
Unlock your springs, and open all your shades.
Granville commands; your aid O Muses bring!
What Muse for Granville can refuse to sing?
The groves of Eden, vanish'd now so long,
Live in description, and look green in song:
These, were my breast inspir'd with equal flame,
Like them in beauty, should be like in fame.
Here hills and vales, the woodland and the plain,
Here earth and water, seem to strive again;
Not Chaos like together crush'd and bruis'd,
But as the world, harmoniously confus'd:
Where order in variety we see,
And where, tho' all things differ, all agree.
Here waving groves a checquer'd scene display,
And part admit, and part exclude the day;
As some coy nymph her lover's warm address
Nor quite indulges, nor can quite repress.
There, interspers'd in lawns and opening glades,
Thin trees arise that shun each other's shades.
Here in full light the russet plains extend;
There wrapt in clouds the blueish hills ascend.
Ev'n the wild heath displays her purple dyes,
And 'midst the desart fruitful fields arise,
That crown'd with tufted trees and springing corn,
Like verdant isles the sable waste adorn.
Let India boast her plants, nor envy we
The weeping amber or the balmy tree,
While by our oaks the precious loads are born,
And realms commanded which those trees adorn.
Not proud Olympus yields a nobler sight,
Tho' Gods assembled grace his tow'ring height,
Than what more humble mountains offer here,
Where, in their blessings, all those Gods appear.
See Pan with flocks, with fruits Pomona crown'd,
Here blushing Flora paints th' enamel'd ground,
Here Ceres' gifts in waving prospect stand,
And nodding tempt the joyful reaper's hand;
Rich Industry sits smiling on the plains,
And peace and plenty tell, a Stuart reigns.
Not thus the land appear'd in ages past,
A dreary desart and a gloomy waste,
To savage beasts and savage laws a prey,
And kings more furious and severe than they;
Who claim'd the skies, dispeopled air and floods,
The lonely lords of empty wilds and woods:
Cities laid waste, they storm'd the dens and caves,
(For wiser brutes were backward to be slaves):
What could be free, when lawless beasts obey'd,
And ev'n the elements a Tyrant sway'd?
In vain kind seasons swell'd the teeming grain,
Soft show'rs distill'd, and suns grew warm in vain;
The swain with tears his frustrate labour yields,
And famish'd dies amidst his ripen'd fields.
What wonder then, a beast or subject slain
Were equal crimes in a despotick reign?
Both doom'd alike, for sportive Tyrants bled,
But that the subject starv'd, the beast was fed.
Proud Nimrod first the bloody chace began,
A mighty hunter, and his prey was man:
Our haughty Norman boasts that barb'rous name,
And makes his trembling slaves the royal game.
The fields are ravish'd from th' industrious swains,
From men their cities, and from Gods their fanes:
The levell'd towns with weeds lie cover'd o'er;
The hollow winds thro' naked temples roar;
Round broken columns clasping ivy twin'd;
O'er heaps of ruin stalk'd the stately hind;
The fox obscene to gaping tombs retires,
And savage howlings fill the sacred quires.
Aw'd by his Nobles, by his Commons curst,
Th' Oppressor rul'd tyrannic where he durst,
Stretch'd o'er the Poor and Church his iron rod,
And serv'd alike his Vassals and his God.
Whom ev'n the Saxon spar'd, and bloody Dane,
The wanton victims of his sport remain.
But see, the man who spacious regions gave
A waste for beasts, himself deny'd a grave!
Stretch'd on the lawn, his second hope survey,
At once the chaser, and at once the prey:
Lo Rufus, tugging at the deadly dart,
Bleeds in the forest, like a wounded hart.
Succeeding Monarchs heard the subjects cries,
Nor saw displeas'd the peaceful cottage rise.
Then gath'ring flocks on unknown mountains fed,
O'er sandy wilds were yellow harvests spread,
The forests wonder'd at th' unusual grain,
And secret transport touch'd the conscious swain.
Fair Liberty, Britannia's Goddess, rears
Her chearful head, and leads the golden years.
Ye vig'rous swains! while youth ferments your blood,
And purer spirits swell the sprightly flood,
Now range the hills, the thickest woods beset,
Wind the shrill horn, or spread the waving net.
When milder autumn summer's heat succeeds,
And in the new-shorn field the partridge feeds,
Before his lord the ready spaniel bounds,
Panting with hope, he tries the furrow'd grounds;
But when the tainted gales the game betray,
Couch'd close he lies, and meditates the prey:
Secure they trust th' unfaithful field, beset,
Till hov'ring o'er 'em sweeps the swelling net.
Thus (if small things we may with great compare)
When Albion sends her eager sons to war,
Some thoughtless Town, with ease and plenty blest,
Near, and more near, the closing lines invest;
Sudden they seize th' amaz'd, defenceless prize,
And high in air Britannia's standard flies.
See! from the brake the whirring pheasant springs,
And mounts exulting on triumphant wings:
Short is his joy; he feels the fiery wound,
Flutters in blood, and panting beats the ground.
Ah! what avail his glossy, varying dyes,
His purple crest, and scarlet-circled eyes,
The vivid green his shining plumes unfold,
His painted wings, and breast that flames with gold?
Nor yet, when moist Arcturus clouds the sky,
The woods and fields their pleasing toils deny.
To plains with well-breath'd beagles we repair,
And trace the mazes of the circling hare:
(Beasts, urg'd by us, their fellow-beasts pursue,
And learn of man each other to undo.)
With slaught'ring guns th' unweary'd fowler roves,
When frosts have whiten'd all the naked groves;
Where doves in flocks the leafless trees o'ershade,
And lonely woodcocks haunt the wat'ry glade.
He lifts the tube, and levels with his eye;
Strait a short thunder breaks the frozen sky:
Oft', as in airy rings they skim the heath,
The clam'rous plovers feel the leaden death:
Oft', as the mounting larks their notes prepare,
They fall, and leave their little lives in air.
In genial spring, beneath the quiv'ring shade,
Where cooling vapours breathe along the mead,
The patient fisher takes his silent stand,
Intent, his angle trembling in his hand;
With looks unmov'd, he hopes the scaly breed,
And eyes the dancing cork, and bending reed.
Our plenteous streams a various race supply,
The bright-ey'd perch with fins of Tyrian dye,
The silver eel, in shining volumes roll'd,
The yellow carp, in scales bedrop'd with gold,
Swift trouts, diversify'd with crimson stains,
And pykes, the tyrants of the watry plains.
Now Cancer glows with Phoebus' fiery car;
The youth rush eager to the sylvan war,
Swarm o'er the lawns, the forest walks surround,
Rouze the fleet hart, and chear the opening hound.
Th' impatient courser pants in ev'ry vein,
And pawing, seems to beat the distant plain;
Hills, vales, and floods appear already cross'd,
And e'er he starts, a thousand steps are lost.
See! the bold youth strain up the threat'ning steep,
Rush thro' the thickets, down the valleys sweep,
Hang o'er their coursers heads with eager speed,
And earth rolls back beneath the flying steed.
Let old Arcadia boast her ample plain,
Th' immortal huntress, and her virgin-train;
Nor envy, Windsor! since thy shades have seen
As bright a Goddess, and as chaste a Queen;
Whose care, like hers, protects the sylvan reign,
The Earth's fair light, and Empress of the main.
Here, as old bards have sung, Diana stray'd,
Bath'd in the springs, or sought the cooling shade;
Here arm'd with silver bows, in early dawn,
Her buskin'd Virgins trac'd the dewy lawn.
Above the rest a rural nymph was fam'd,
Thy offspring, Thames! the fair Lodona nam'd;
(Lodona's fate, in long oblivion cast,
The Muse shall sing, and what she sings shall last.)
Scarce could the Goddess from her nymph be known,
But by the crescent and the golden zone.
She scorn'd the praise of beauty, and the care,
A belt her waist, a fillet binds her hair,
A painted quiver on her shoulder sounds,
And with her dart the flying deer she wounds.
It chanc'd, as eager of the chace, the maid
Beyond the forest's verdant limits stray'd,
Pan saw and lov'd, and burning with desire
Pursu'd her flight, her flight increas'd his fire.
Not half so swift the trembling doves can fly,
When the fierce eagle cleaves the liquid sky;
Not half so swiftly the fierce eagle moves,
When thro' the clouds he drives the trembling doves;
As from the God she flew with furious pace,
Or as the God, more furious, urg'd the chace.
Now fainting, sinking, pale, the nymph appears;
Now close behind, his sounding steps she hears;
And now his shadow reach'd her as she run,
His shadow lengthen'd by the setting sun;
And now his shorter breath, with sultry air,
Pants on her neck, and fans her parting hair.
In vain on father Thames she call'd for aid,
Nor could Diana help her injur'd maid.
Faint, breathless, thus she pray'd, nor pray'd in vain;
'Ah Cynthia! ah tho' banish'd from thy train,
'Let me, O let me, to the shades repair,
'My native shades there weep, and murmur there.
She said, and melting as in tears she lay,
In a soft, silver stream dissolv'd away.
The silver stream her virgin coldness keeps,
For ever murmurs, and for ever weeps;
Still bears the name the hapless virgin bore,
And bathes the forest where she rang'd before.
In her chaste current oft' the Goddess laves,
And with celestial tears augments the waves.
Oft' in her glass the musing shepherd spies
The headlong mountains and the downward skies,
The watry landskip of the pendant woods,
And absent trees that tremble in the floods;
In the clear azure gleam the flocks are seen,
And floating forests paint the waves with green.
Thro' the fair scene rowl slow the ling'ring streams,
Then foaming pour along, and rush into the Thames.
Thou too, great father of the British floods!
With joyful pride survey'st our lofty woods;
Where tow'ring oaks their spreading honours rear,
And future navies on thy shores appear.
Not Neptune's self from all his streams receives
A wealthier tribute, than to thine he gives.
No seas so rich, so gay no banks appear,
No lake so gentle, and no spring so clear.
Not fabled Po more swells the poet's lays,
While thro' the skies his shining current strays,
Than thine, which visits Windsor's fam'd abodes,
To grace the mansion of our earthly Gods:
Nor all his stars a brighter lustre show,
Than the fair nymphs that grace thy side below:
Here Jove himself, subdu'd by beauty still,
Might change Olympus for a nobler hill.
Happy the man whom this bright Court approves,
His Sov'reign favours, and his Country loves:
Happy next him, who to these shades retires,
Whom Nature charms, and whom the Muse inspires;
Whom humbler joys of home-felt quiet please,
Successive study, exercise, and ease.
He gathers health from herbs the forest yields,
And of their fragrant physic spoils the fields:
With chymic art exalts the min'ral pow'rs,
And draws the aromatic souls of flow'rs:
Now marks the course of rolling orbs on high;
O'er figur'd worlds now travels with his eye:
Of ancient writ unlocks the learned store,
Consults the dead, and lives past ages o'er:
Or wand'ring thoughtful in the silent wood,
Attends the duties of the wise and good,
T'observe a mean, be to himself a friend,
To follow nature, and regard his end;
Or looks on heav'n with more than mortal eyes,
Bids his free soul expatiate in the skies,
Amid her kindred stars familiar roam,
Survey the region, and confess her home!
Such was the life great Scipio once admir'd,
Thus Atticus, and Trumbal thus retir'd.
Ye sacred Nine! that all my soul possess,
Whose raptures fire me, and whose visions bless,
Bear me, oh bear me to sequester'd scenes,
The bow'ry mazes, and surrounding greens;
To Thames's banks which fragrant breezes fill,
Or where ye Muses sport on Cooper's hill.
(On Cooper's hill eternal wreaths shall grow,
While lasts the mountain, or while Thames shall flow)
I seem thro' consecrated walks to rove,
I hear soft music die along the grove;
Led by the sound, I roam from shade to shade,
By god-like Poets venerable made:
Here his first lays majestic Denham sung;
There the last numbers flow'd from Cowley's tongue.
O early lost! what tears the river shed,
When the sad pomp along his banks was led?
His drooping swans on ev'ry note expire,
And on his willows hung each Muse's lyre.
Since fate relentless stop'd their heav'nly voice,
No more the forests ring, or groves rejoice;
Who now shall charm the shades, where Cowley strung
His living harp, and lofty Denham sung?
But hark! the groves rejoice, the forest rings!
Are these reviv'd? or is it Granville sings?
'Tis yours, my Lord, to bless our soft retreats,
And call the Muses to their ancient seats;
To paint anew the flow'ry sylvan scenes,
To crown the forests with immortal greens,
Make Windsor-hills in lofty numbers rise,
And lift her turrets nearer to the skies;
To sing those honours you deserve to wear,
And add new lustre to her silver star.
Here noble Surrey felt the sacred rage,
Surrey, the Granville of a former age:
Matchless his pen, victorious was his lance,
Bold in the lists, and graceful in the dance:
In the same shades the Cupids tun'd his lyre,
To the same notes, of love, and soft desire:
Fair Geraldine, bright object of his vow,
Then fill'd the groves, as heav'nly Myra now.
Oh would'st thou sing what Heroes Windsor bore,
What Kings first breath'd upon her winding shore,
Or raise old warriours, whose ador'd remains
In weeping vaults her hallow'd earth contains!
With Edward's acts adorn the shining page,
Stretch his long triumphs down thro' ev'ry age,
Draw Monarchs chain'd, and Cressi's glorious field,
The lillies blazing on the regal shield:
Then, from her roofs when Verrio's colours fall,
And leave inanimate the naked wall,
Still in thy song should vanquish'd France appear,
And bleed for ever under Britain's spear.
Let softer strains ill-fated Henry mourn,
And palms eternal flourish round his urn,
Here o'er the martyr-King the marble weeps,
And fast beside him, once-fear'd Edward sleeps:
Whom not th' extended Albion could contain,
From old Belerium to the northern main,
The grave unites; where ev'n the Great find rest,
And blended lie th' oppressor and th' opprest!
Make sacred Charles's tomb for ever known,
(Obscure the place, and un-inscrib'd the stone)
Oh fact accurst! what tears has Albion shed,
Heav'ns, what new wounds! and how her old have bled?
She saw her sons with purple deaths expire,
Her sacred domes involv'd in rolling fire,
A dreadful series of intestine wars,
Inglorious triumphs, and dishonest scars.
At length great Anna said 'Let Discord cease!'
She said, the World obey'd, and all was Peace!
In that blest moment, from his oozy bed
Old father Thames advanc'd his rev'rend head.
His tresses drop'd with dews, and o'er the stream
His shining horns diffus'd a golden gleam:
Grav'd on his urn, appear'd the Moon that guides
His swelling waters, and alternate tydes;
The figur'd streams in waves of silver roll'd,
And on their banks Augusta rose in gold.
Around his throne the sea-born brothers stood,
Who swell with tributary urns his flood:
First the fam'd authors of his ancient name,
The winding Isis and the fruitful Tame:
The Kennet swift, for silver eels renown'd;
The Loddon slow, with verdant alders crown'd;
Cole, whose clear streams his flow'ry islands lave;
And chalky Wey, that rolls a milky wave:
The blue, transparent Vandalis appears;
The gulphy Lee his sedgy tresses rears;
And sullen Mole, that hides his diving flood;
And silent Darent, stain'd with Danish blood.
High in the midst, upon his urn reclin'd,
(His sea-green mantle waving with the wind)
The God appear'd: he turn'd his azure eyes
Where Windsor-domes and pompous turrets rise;
Then bow'd and spoke; the winds forget to roar,
And the hush'd waves glide softly to the shore.
Hail, sacred Peace! hail long-expected days,
That Thames's glory to the stars shall raise!
Tho' Tyber's streams immortal Rome behold,
Tho' foaming Hermus swells with tydes of gold,
From heav'n itself tho' sev'n-fold Nilus flows,
And harvests on a hundred realms bestows;
These now no more shall be the Muse's themes,
Lost in my fame, as in the sea their streams.
Let Volga's banks with iron squadrons shine,
And groves of lances glitter on the Rhine,
Let barb'rous Ganges arm a servile train;
Be mine the blessings of a peaceful reign.
No more my sons shall dye with British blood
Red Iber's sands, or Ister's foaming flood;
Safe on my shore each unmolested swain
Shall tend the flocks, or reap the bearded grain;
The shady empire shall retain no trace
Of war or blood, but in the sylvan chace;
The trumpet sleep, while chearful horns are blown,
And arms employ'd on birds and beasts alone.
Behold! th' ascending Villa's on my side,
Project long shadows o'er the crystal tyde.
Behold! Augusta's glitt'ring spires increase,
And temples rise, the beauteous works of Peace.
I see, I see where two fair cities bend
Their ample bow, a new White-ball ascend!
There mighty nations shall enquire their doom,
The world's great Oracle in times to come;
There Kings shall sue, and suppliant States be seen
Once more to bend before a British Queen.
Thy trees, fair Windsor! now shall leave their woods,
And half thy forests rush into my floods,
Bear Britain's thunder, and her Cross display,
To the bright regions of the rising day;
Tempt icy seas, where scarce the waters roll,
Where clearer flames glow round the frozen Pole;
Or under southern skies exalt their sails,
Led by new stars, and borne by spicy gales!
For me the balm shall bleed, and amber flow,
The coral redden, and the ruby glow,
The pearly shell its lucid globe infold,
And Phoebus warm the ripening ore to gold.
The time shall come, when free as seas or wind
Unbounded Thames shall flow for all mankind,
Whole nations enter with each swelling tyde,
And seas but join the regions they divide;
Earth's distant ends our glory shall behold,
And the new world launch forth to seek the old.
Then ships of uncouth form shall stem the tyde,
And feather'd people croud my wealthy side,
And naked youths and painted chiefs admire
Our speech, our colour, and our strange attire!
Oh stretch thy reign, fair Peace! from shore to shore,
'Till Conquest cease, and slav'ry be no more;
'Till the freed Indians in their native groves
Reap their own fruits, and woo their sable loves,
Peru once more a race of Kings behold,
And other Mexico's be roof'd with gold.
Exil'd by thee from earth to deepest hell,
In brazen bonds shall barb'rous Discord dwell:
Gigantic Pride, pale Terror, gloomy Care,
And mad Ambition, shall attend her there:
There purple Vengeance bath'd in gore retires,
Her weapons blunted, and extinct her fires:
There hateful Envy her own snakes shall feel,
And Persecution mourn her broken wheel:
There Faction roar, Rebellion bite her chain,
And gasping Furies thirst for blood in vain.
Here cease thy flight, nor with unhallow'd lays
Touch the fair fame of Albion's golden days:
The thoughts of Gods let Granville's verse recite,
And bring the scenes of opening fate to light.
My humble Muse, in unambitious strains,
Paints the green forests and the flow'ry plains,
Where Peace descending bids her olives spring,
And scatters blessings from her dove-like wing.
Ev'n I more sweetly pass my careless days,
Pleas'd in the silent shade with empty praise;
Enough for me, that to the list'ning swains
First in these fields I sung the sylvan strains.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2020052101">
<head>
    <suptitle>Paraphrases from Chaucer</suptitle>
    <title>January and May</title>
    <subtitle>or, The Merchant’s Tale</subtitle>
    <firstline>There liv’d in Lombardy, as authors write</firstline>
    <keywords>chaucer</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>There</sc> liv’d in Lombardy, as authors write,
In days of old, a wise and worthy Knight;
Of gentle manners, as of gen’rous race,
Blest with much sense, more riches, and some grace:
Yet, led astray by Venus’ soft delights,
He scarce could rule some idle appetites:
For long ago, let priests say what they could,
Weak sinful laymen were but flesh and blood.
  But in due time, when sixty years were o’er,
He vow’d to lead this vicious life no more;
Whether pure holiness inspired his mind,
Or dotage turn’d his brain, is hard to find;
But his high courage prick’d him forth to wed,
And try the pleasures of a lawful bed.
This was his nightly dream, his daily care,
And to the heav’nly Powers his constant prayer,
Once, ere he died, to taste the blissful life
Of a kind husband and a loving wife.
  These thoughts he fortified with reasons still
(For none want reasons to confirm their will).
Grave authors say, and witty poets sing,
That honest wedlock is a glorious thing:
But depth of judgment most in him appears
Who wisely weds in his maturer years.
Then let him choose a damsel young and fair,
To bless his age, and bring a worthy heir;
To soothe his cares, and, free from noise and strife,
Conduct him gently to the verge of life.
Let sinful bachelors their woes deplore,
Full well they merit all they feel, and more:
Unaw’d by precepts, human or divine,
Like birds and beasts, promiscuously they join;
Nor know to make the present blessing last,
To hope the future, or esteem the past;
But vainly boast the joys they never tried,
And find divulged the secrets they would hide.
The married man may bear his yoke with ease,
Secure at once himself and Heav’n to please;
And pass his inoffensive hours away,
In bliss all night, and innocence all day:
Tho’ fortune change, his constant spouse remains,
Augments his joys, or mitigates his pains.
  But what so pure which envious tongues will spare?
Some wicked Wits have libell’d all the Fair.
With matchless impudence they style a wife
The dear-bought curse and lawful plague of life,
A bosom serpent, a domestic evil,
A night-invasion, and a midday-devil.
Let not the wise these sland’rous words regard,
But curse the bones of ev’ry lying bard.
All other goods by Fortune’s hand are giv’n,
A wife is the peculiar gift of Heav’n.
Vain Fortune’s favours, never at a stay,
Like empty shadows pass and glide away;
One solid comfort, our eternal wife,
Abundantly supplies us all our life:
This blessing lasts (if those who try say true)
As long as heart can wish—and longer too.
  Our grandsire Adam, ere of Eve possess’d,
Alone, and ev’n in Paradise unbless’d,
With mournful looks the blissful scene survey’d,
And wander’d in the solitary shade.
The Maker saw, took pity, and bestow’d
Woman, the last, the best reserv’d of God.
  A Wife! ah gentle Deities! can he
That has a wife e’er feel adversity?
Would men but follow what the sex advise,
All things would prosper, all the world grow wise.
’T was by Rebecca’s aid that Jacob won
His father’s blessing from an elder son:
Abusive Nabal ow’d his forfeit life
To the wise conduct of a prudent wife:
Heroic Judith, as old Hebrews show,
Preserv’d the Jews, and slew th’ Assyrian foe:
At Hester’s suit the persecuting sword
Was sheath’d, and Israel liv’d to bless the Lord.
  These weighty motives January the sage
Maturely ponder’d in his riper age;
And charm’d with virtuous joys, and sober life,
Would try that Christian comfort call’d a wife.
His friends were summon’d on a point so nice
To pass their judgment, and to give advice;
But fix’d before, and well resolv’d was he
(As men that ask advice are wont to be).
  ‘My friends,’ he cried (and cast a mournful look
Around the room, and sigh’d before he spoke),
‘Beneath the weight of threescore years I bend,
And, worn with cares, am hastening to my end.
How I have liv’d, alas! you know too well—
In worldly follies which I blush to tell;
But gracious Heav’n has oped my eyes at last,
With due regret I view my vices past,
And, as the precept of the church decrees,
Will take a wife, and live in holy ease.
But since by counsel all things should be done,
And many heads are wiser still than one;
Choose you for me, who best shall be content
When my desire’s approv’d by your consent.
  ‘One caution yet is needful to be told,
To guide your choice; this wife must not be old:
There goes a saying, and ’t was shrewdly said,
Old fish at table, but young flesh in bed.
My soul abhors the tasteless dry embrace
Of a stale virgin with a winter face:
In that cold season Love but treats his guest
With bean-straw, and tough forage at the best.
No crafty widows shall approach my bed;
Those are too wise for bachelors to wed.
As subtle clerks by many schools are made,
Twice married dames are mistresses o’ th’ trade:
But young and tender virgins, ruled with ease,
We form like wax, and mould them as we please.
  ‘Conceive me, Sirs, nor take my sense amiss;
’T is what concerns my soul’s eternal bliss;
Since if I found no pleasure in my spouse,
As flesh is frail, and who (God help me) knows?
Then should I live in lewd adultery,
And sink downright to Satan when I die:
Or were I curs’d with an unfruitful bed,
The righteous end were lost for which I wed;
To raise up seed to bless the Powers above,
And not for pleasure only, or for love.
Think not I dote; ’t is time to take a wife,
When vig’rous blood forbids a chaster life:
Those that are blest with store of grace divine,
May live like saints by Heav’n’s consent and mine.
  ‘And since I speak of wedlock, let me say,
(As, thank my stars, in modest truth I may)
My limbs are active, still I ’m sound at heart,
And a new vigour springs in ev’ry part.
Think not my virtue lost, tho’ time has shed
These rev’rend honours on my hoary head:
Thus trees are crown’d with blossoms white as snow,
The vital sap then rising from below.
Old as I am, my lusty limbs appear
Like winter-greens, that flourish all the year.
Now, Sirs, you know to what I stand inclin’d,
Let ev’ry friend with freedom speak his mind.’
  He said; the rest in diff’rent parts divide;
The knotty point was urged on either side:
Marriage, the theme on which they all declaim’d,
Some prais’d with wit, and some with reason blamed.
Till, what with proofs, objections, and replies,
Each wondrous positive and wondrous wise,
There fell between his brothers a debate:
Placebo this was call’d, and Justin that.
  First to the knight Placebo thus begun,
(Mild were his looks, and pleasing was his tone)
‘Such prudence, Sir, in all your words appears,
As plainly proves Experience dwells with years!
Yet you pursue sage Solomon’s advice,
To work by counsel when affairs are nice:
But, with the wise man’s leave, I must protest,
So may my soul arrive at ease and rest,
As still I hold your own advice the best.
  ‘Sir, I have liv’d a courtier all my days,
And studied men, their manners, and their ways;
And have observ’d this useful maxim still,
To let my betters always have their will.
  ‘Nay, if my lord affirm’d that black was white,
My word was this, “Your Honour ’s in the right.”
Th’ assuming Wit, who deems himself so wise
As his mistaken patron to advise,
Let him not dare to vent his dangerous thought;
A noble fool was never in a fault.
This, Sir, affects not you, whose ev’ry word
Is weigh’d with judgment, and befits a Lord:
Your will is mine; and is (I will maintain)
Pleasing to God, and should be so to Man;
At least your courage all the world must praise,
Who dare to wed in your declining days.
Indulge the vigour of your mounting blood,
And let gray fools be indolently good,
Who, past all pleasure, damn the joys of sense,
With rev’rend Dulness and grave Impotence.’
  Justin, who silent sate, and heard the man,
Thus with a philosophic frown began:
  ‘A heathen author, of the first degree,
(Who, tho’ not Faith, had Sense as well as we)
Bids us be certain our concerns to trust
To those of gen’rous principles and just.
The venture’s greater, I ’ll presume to say,
To give your person, than your goods away:
And therefore, Sir, as you regard your rest,
First learn your lady’s qualities at least:
Whether she ’s chaste or rampant, proud or civil,
Meek as a saint, or haughty as the devil;
Whether an easy, fond, familiar Fool,
Or such a Wit as no man e’er can rule.
’T is true, perfection none must hope to find
In all this world, much less in womankind;
But if her virtue prove the larger share,
Bless the kind Fates and think your fortune rare.
Ah, gentle Sir, take warning of a friend,
Who knows too well the state you thus commend;
And spite of all his praises must declare,
All he can find is bondage, cost, and care.
Heav’n knows I shed full many a private tear,
And sigh in silence lest the world should hear;
While all my friends applaud my blissful life,
And swear no mortal’s happier in a wife:
Demure and chaste as any vestal nun,
The meekest creature that beholds the sun!
But by th’ immortal Powers I feel the pain,
And he that smarts has reason to complain.
Do what you list, for me; you must be sage,
And cautious sure; for wisdom is in age:
But at these years to venture on the Fair!
By him who made the ocean, earth, and air,
To please a wife, when her occasions call,
Would busy the most vig’rous of us all.
And trust me, sir, the chastest you can choose,
Will ask observance, and exact her dues.
If what I speak my noble lord offend,
My tedious sermon here is at an end.’
  ‘’T is well, ’t is wondrous well,’ the Knight replies,
‘Most worthy kinsman, faith, you ’re mighty wise!
We, Sirs, are fools; and must resign the cause
To heath’nish authors, proverbs, and old saws.’
He spoke with scorn, and turn’d another way:
‘What does my friend, my dear Placebo, say?’
  ‘I say,’ quoth he, ‘by Heav’n the man’s to blame,
To slander wives, and wedlock’s holy name.’
  At this the council rose without delay;
Each, in his own opinion, went his way;
With full consent, that, all disputes appeas’d,
The Knight should marry when and where he pleas’d.
  Who now but January exults with joy?
The charms of wedlock all his soul employ:
Each nymph by turns his wavering mind possess’d,
And reign’d the short-lived tyrant of his breast;
Whilst fancy pictured ev’ry lively part,
And each bright image wander’d o’er his heart.
Thus, in some public forum fix’d on high,
A mirror shows the figures moving by;
Still one by one, in swift succession, pass
The gliding shadows o’er the polish’d glass.
This lady’s charms the nicest could not blame,
But vile suspicions had aspers’d her fame;
That was with Sense, but not with Virtue blest;
And one had Grace that wanted all the rest.
Thus doubting long what nymph he should obey,
He fix’d at last upon the youthful May.
Her faults he knew not (Love is always blind),
But every charm revolv’d within his mind:
Her tender age, her form divinely fair,
Her easy motion, her attractive air,
Her sweet behaviour, her enchanting face,
Her moving softness, and majestic grace.
  Much in his prudence did our Knight rejoice,
And thought no mortal could dispute his choice:
Once more in haste he summon’d ev’ry friend,
And told them all their pains were at an end.
‘Heav’n, that (said he) inspired me first to wed,
Provides a consort worthy of my bed:
Let none oppose th’ election, since on this
Depends my quiet and my future bliss.
  ‘A dame there is, the darling of my eyes,
Young, beauteous, artless, innocent, and wise;
Chaste, tho’ not rich; and, tho’ not nobly born,
Of honest parents, and may serve my turn.
Her will I wed, if gracious Heav’n so please,
To pass my age in sanctity and ease;
And thank the Powers, I may possess alone
The lovely prize, and share my bliss with none!
If you, my friends, this virgin can procure,
My joys are full, my happiness is sure.
  ‘One only doubt remains: full oft, I ’ve heard,
By casuists grave and deep divines averr’d,
That ’t is too much for human race to know
The bliss of Heav’n above and earth below:
Now should the nuptial pleasures prove so great,
To match the blessings of the future state,
Those endless joys were ill exchanged for these:
Then clear this doubt, and set my mind at ease.’
  This Justin heard, nor could his spleen control,
Touch’d to the quick, and tickled at the soul.
‘Sir Knight,’ he cried, ‘if this be all you dread,
Heav’n put it past a doubt whene’er you wed;
And to my fervent prayers so far consent,
That, ere the rites are o’er, you may repent!
Good Heav’n, no doubt, the nuptial state approves,
Since it chastises still what best it loves.
  ‘Then be not, Sir, abandon’d to despair;
Seek, and perhaps you ’ll find among the Fair
One that may do your business to a hair;
Not ev’n in wish your happiness delay,
But prove the scourge to lash you on your way:
Then to the skies your mounting soul shall go,
Swift as an arrow soaring from the bow!
Provided still, you moderate your joy,
Nor in your pleasures all your might employ:
Let Reason’s rule your strong desires abate,
Nor please too lavishly your gentle mate.
Old wives there are, of judgment most acute,
Who solve these questions beyond all dispute;
Consult with those, and be of better cheer;
Marry, do penance, and dismiss your fear.’
  So said, they rose, nor more the work delay’d:
The match was offer’d, the proposals made.
The parents, you may think, would soon comply;
The old have int’rest ever in their eye.
Nor was it hard to move the lady’s mind;
When Fortune favours, still the Fair are kind.
  I pass each previous settlement and deed,
Too long for me to write, or you to read;
Nor will with quaint impertinence display
The pomp, the pageantry, the proud array.
The time approach’d; to church the parties went,
At once with carnal and devout intent:
Forth came the priest, and bade th’ obedient wife
Like Sarah or Rebecca lead her life;
Then pray’d the Powers the fruitful bed to bless,
And make all sure enough with holiness.
  And now the palace gates are open’d wide,
The guests appear in order, side by side,
And, placed in state, the bridegroom and the bride.
The breathing flute’s soft notes are heard around,
And the shrill trumpets mix their silver sound;
The vaulted roofs with echoing music ring,
These touch the vocal stops, and those the trembling string.
Not thus Amphion tuned the warbling lyre,
Nor Joab the sounding clarion could inspire,
Nor fierce Theodamas, whose sprightly strain
Could swell the soul to rage, and fire the martial train.
  Bacchus himself, the nuptial feast to grace,
(So poets sing) was present on the place:
And lovely Venus, Goddess of Delight,
Shook high her flaming torch in open sight,
And danced around, and smiled on ev’ry Knight:
Pleas’d her best servant would his courage try,
No less in wedlock than in liberty.
Full many an age old Hymen had not spied
So kind a bridegroom, or so bright a bride.
Ye Bards! renown’d among the tuneful throng
For gentle lays, and joyous nuptial song,
Think not your softest numbers can display
The matchless glories of this blissful day;
The joys are such as far transcend your rage,
When tender youth has wedded stooping age.
  The beauteous dame sat smiling at the board,
And darted am’rous glances at her lord.
Not Hester’s self, whose charms the Hebrews sing,
E’er look’d so lovely on her Persian King:
Bright as the rising sun in summer’s day,
And fresh and blooming as the month of May!
The joyful knight survey’d her by his side,
Nor envied Paris with his Spartan bride:
Still as his mind revolv’d with vast delight
Th’ entrancing raptures of th’ approaching night,
Restless he sat, invoking every Power
To speed his bliss, and haste the happy hour.
Meantime the vig’rous dancers beat the ground,
And songs were sung, and flowing bowls went round.
With od’rous spices they perfumed the place,
And mirth and pleasure shone in ev’ry face.
  Damian alone, of all the menial train,
Sad in the midst of triumphs, sigh’d for pain,
Damian alone, the Knight’s obsequious Squire,
Consumed at heart, and fed a secret fire.
His lovely mistress all his soul possess’d;
He look’d, he languish’d, and could take no rest:
His task perform’d, he sadly went his way,
Fell on his bed, and loath’d the light of day:
There let him lie; till his relenting dame
Weep in her turn, and waste in equal flame.
  The weary sun, as learned poets write,
Forsook th’ horizon, and roll’d down the light;
While glitt’ring stars his absent beams supply,
And night’s dark mantle overspread the sky.
Then rose the guests, and as the time required,
Each paid his thanks, and decently retired.
  The foe once gone, our Knight prepared t’ undress,
So keen he was, and eager to possess:
But first thought fit th’ assistance to receive,
Which grave physicians scruple not to give:
Satyrion near, with hot eringoes stood,
Cantharides, to fire the lazy blood,
Whose use old Bards describe in luscious rhymes,
And Critics learn’d explain to modern times.
  By this the sheets were spread, the bride undress’d,
The room was sprinkled, and the bed was bless’d.
What next ensued beseems not me to say;
’T is sung, he labour’d till the dawning day;
Then briskly sprung from bed, with heart so light,
As all were nothing he had done by night,
And sipp’d his cordial as he sat upright.
He kiss’d his balmy spouse with wanton play,
And feebly sung a lusty roundelay:
Then on the couch his weary limbs he cast;
For ev’ry labour must have rest at last.
  But anxious cares the pensive Squire opprest,
Sleep fled his eyes, and Peace forsook his breast;
The raging flames that in his bosom dwell,
He wanted art to hide, and means to tell:
Yet hoping time th’ occasion might betray,
Composed a sonnet to the lovely May;
Which, writ and folded with the nicest art,
He wrapt in silk, and laid upon his heart.
  When now the fourth revolving day was run,
(’T was June, and Cancer had receiv’d the sun)
Forth from her chamber came the beauteous bride;
The good old Knight mov’d slowly by her side.
High mass was sung; they feasted in the hall;
The servants round stood ready at their call.
The Squire alone was absent from the board,
And much his sickness griev’d his worthy lord,
Who pray’d his spouse, attended with her train,
To visit Damian, and divert his pain.
Th’ obliging dames obey’d with one consent:
They left the hall, and to his lodging went.
The female tribe surround him as he lay,
And close beside him sat the gentle May:
Where, as she tried his pulse, he softly drew
A heaving sigh, and cast a mournful view!
Then gave his bill, and bribed the Powers divine,
With secret vows to favour his design.
  Who studies now but discontented May?
On her soft couch uneasily she lay:
The lumpish husband snored away the night,
Till coughs awaked him near the morning light.
What then he did, I ’ll not presume to tell,
Nor if she thought herself in Heav’n or Hell:
Honest and dull in nuptial bed they lay,
Till the bell toll’d, and all arose to pray.
  Were it by forceful Destiny decreed,
Or did from Chance, or Nature’s power proceed;
Or that some star, with aspect kind to love,
Shed its selectest influence from above;
Whatever was the cause, the tender dame
Felt the first motions of an infant flame;
Receiv’d th’ impressions of the lovesick Squire,
And wasted in the soft infectious fire.
  Ye Fair, draw near, let May’s example move
Your gentle minds to pity those who love!
Had some fierce tyrant in her stead been found,
The poor adorer sure had hang’d or drown’d:
But she, your sex’s mirror, free from pride,
Was much too meek to prove a homicide.
  But to my tale:—Some sages have defin’d
Pleasure the sov’reign bliss of humankind:
Our Knight (who studied much, we may suppose)
Derived his high philosophy from those;
For, like a prince, he bore the vast expense
Of lavish pomp, and proud magnificence:
His house was stately, his retinue gay.
Large was his train, and gorgeous his array.
His spacious garden, made to yield to none,
Was compass’d round with walls of solid stone;
Priapus could not half describe the grace
(Tho’ God of gardens) of this charming place:
A place to tire the rambling wits of France
In long descriptions, and exceed Romance:
Enough to shame the gentlest bard that sings
Of painted meadows, and of purling springs.
  Full in the centre of the flowery ground
A crystal fountain spread its streams around,
The fruitful banks with verdant laurels crown’d:
About this spring (if ancient Fame say true)
The dapper Elves their moonlight sports pursue:
Their pygmy King, and little fairy Queen,
In circling dances gambol’d on the green,
While tuneful sprites a merry concert made,
And airy music warbled thro’ the shade.
  Hither the noble Knight would oft repair
(His scene of pleasure, and peculiar care);
For this he held it dear, and always bore
The silver key that lock’d the garden door.
To this sweet place in summer’s sultry heat
He used from noise and bus’ness to retreat;
And here in dalliance spend the livelong day,
Solus cum sola, with his sprightly May:
For whate’er work was undischarg’d abed,
The duteous Knight in this fair garden sped.
  But ah! what mortal lives of bliss secure?
How short a space our worldly joys endure!
O Fortune, fair, like all thy treach’rous kind,
But faithless still, and wav’ring as the wind!
O painted monster, form’d mankind to cheat,
With pleasing poison, and with soft deceit!
This rich, this am’rous, venerable Knight,
Amidst his ease, his solace, and delight,
Struck blind by thee, resigns his days to grief,
And calls on death, the wretch’s last relief.
  The rage of jealousy then seiz’d his mind,
For much he fear’d the faith of womankind.
His wife, not suffer’d from his side to stray,
Was captive kept; he watch’d her night and day,
Abridg’d her pleasures, and confin’d her sway.
Full oft in tears did hapless May complain,
And sigh’d full oft; but sigh’d and wept in vain;
She look’d on Damian with a lover’s eye;
For oh, ’t was fix’d; she must possess or die!
Nor less impatience vex’d her am’rous Squire,
Wild with delay, and burning with desire.
Watch’d as she was, yet could he not refrain
By secret writing to disclose his pain:
The dame by signs reveal’d her kind intent,
Till both were conscious what each other meant,
  Ah! gentle Knight, what would thy eyes avail,
Tho’ they could see as far as ships can sail?
’T is better, sure, when blind, deceiv’d to be,
Than be deluded when a man can see!
  Argus himself, so cautious and so wise,
Was overwatch’d, for all his hundred eyes:
So many an honest husband may, ’t is known,
Who, wisely, never thinks the case his own.
  The dame at last, by diligence and care,
Procured the key her Knight was wont to bear;
She took the wards in wax before the fire,
And gave th’ impression to the trusty Squire.
By means of this some wonder shall appear,
Which, in due place and season, you may hear.
Well sung sweet Ovid, in the days of yore,
What sleight is that which love will not explore!
And Pyramus and Thisbe plainly show
The feats true lovers, when they list, can do:
Tho’ watch’d and captive, yet in spite of all,
They found the art of kissing thro’ a wall.
  But now no longer from our tale to stray,
It happ’d, that once upon a summer’s day
Our rev’rend Knight was urged to am’rous play:
He rais’d his spouse ere matin-bell was rung,
And thus his morning canticle he sung:
  ‘Awake, my love, disclose thy radiant eyes;
Arise, my wife, my beauteous lady, rise!
Hear how the doves with pensive notes complain,
And in soft murmurs tell the trees their pain:
The winter’s past; the clouds and tempests fly;
The sun adorns the fields, and brightens all the sky.
Fair without spot, whose ev’ry charming part
My bosom wounds, and captivates my heart!
Come, and in mutual pleasures let ’s engage,
Joy of my life, and comfort of my age.’
  This heard, to Damian straight a sign she made
To haste before; the gentle Squire obey’d:
Secret and undescried he took his way,
And ambush’d close behind an arbour lay.
  It was not long ere January came,
And hand in hand with him his lovely dame;
Blind as he was, not doubting all was sure,
He turn’d the key, and made the gate secure.
  ‘Here let us walk,’ he said, ‘observ’d by none,
Conscious of pleasures to the world unknown:
So may my soul have joy, as thou, my wife,
Art far the dearest solace of my life;
And rather would I choose, by Heav’n above,
To die this instant, than to lose thy love.
Reflect what truth was in my passion shown,
When, unendow’d, I took thee for my own,
And sought no treasure but thy heart alone.
Old as I am, and now deprived of sight,
Whilst thou art faithful to thy own true Knight,
Nor age, nor blindness, robs me of delight.
Each other loss with patience I can bear,
The loss of thee is what I only fear.
  ‘Consider then, my lady and my wife,
The solid comforts of a virtuous life.
As first, the love of Christ himself you gain;
Next, your own honour undefiled mountain;
And, lastly, that which sure your mind must move,
My whole estate shall gratify your love:
Make your own terms, and ere to-morrow’s sun
Displays his light, by Heav’n it shall be done
I seal the contract with a holy kiss,
And will perform—by this, my dear, and this.
Have comfort, Spouse, nor think thy lord unkind;
’T is love, not jealousy, that fires my mind:
For when thy charms my sober thoughts engage,
And join’d to them my own unequal age,
From thy dear side I have no power to part,
Such secret transports warm my melting heart.
For who that once possess’d those heav’nly charms,
Could live one moment absent from thy arms?’
  He ceas’d, and May with modest grace replied
(Weak was her voice, as while she spoke she cried):
‘Heav’n knows (with that a tender sigh she drew)
I have a soul to save as well as you;
And, what no less you to my charge commend,
My dearest honour, will to death defend.
To you in holy church I gave my hand,
And join’d my heart in wedlock’s sacred band:
Yet after this, if you distrust my care,
Then hear, my lord, and witness what I swear:
  First may the yawning earth her bosom rend,
And let me hence to Hell alive descend;
Or die the death I dread no less than Hell,
Sew’d in a sack, and plunged into a well;
Ere I my fame by one lewd act disgrace,
Or once renounce the honour of my race.
For know, Sir Knight, of gentle blood I came;
I loathe a whore, and startle at the name.
But jealous men on their own crimes reflect,
And learn from thence their ladies to suspect:
Else why these needless cautions, Sir, to me?
These doubts and fears of female constancy?
This chime still rings in every lady’s ear,
The only strain a wife must hope to hear.’
  Thus while she spoke a sidelong glance she cast,
Where Damain kneeling worship’d as she past.
She saw him watch the motions of her eye,
And singled out a pear tree planted nigh:
’T was charged with fruit that made a goodly show,
And hung with dangling pears was every bough.
Thither th’ obsequious Squire address’d his pace,
And climbing, in the summit took his place;
The Knight and Lady walk’d beneath in view,
Where let us leave them, and our tale pursue.
  ’T was now the season when the glorious sun
His heav’nly progress through the Twins had run;
And Jove, exalted, his mild influence yields,
To glad the glebe, and paint the flowery fields:
Clear was the day, and Phœbus, rising bright,
Had streak’d the azure firmament with light;
He pierc’d the glitt’ring clouds with golden streams,
And warm’d the womb of earth with genial beams.
  It so befell, in that fair morning tide
The fairies sported on the garden side,
And in the midst their monarch and his bride.
So featly tripp’d the light-foot Ladies round,
The Knights so nimbly o’er the greensward bound,
That scarce they bent the flowers, or touch’d the ground.
The dances ended, all the fairy train
For pinks and daisies search’d the flowery plain,
While on a bank reclin’d of rising green,
Thus, with a frown, the King bespoke his Queen.
‘’T is too apparent, argue what you can,
The treachery you women use to man:
A thousand authors have this truth made out,
And sad experience leaves no room for doubt.
  ‘Heav’n rest thy spirit, noble Solomon,
A wiser Monarch never saw the sun:
All wealth, all honours, the supreme degree
Of earthly bliss, was well bestow’d on thee!
For sagely hast thou said, “Of all mankind,
One only just, and righteous, hope to find:
But shouldst thou search the spacious world around,
Yet one good woman is not to be found.”
  ‘Thus says the King who knew your wickedness;
The son of Sirach testifies no less.
So may some wildfire on your bodies fall,
Or some devouring plague consume you all;
As well you view the lecher in the tree,
And well this honourable Knight you see:
But since he ’s blind and old (a helpless case),
His Squire shall cuckold him before your face.
  ‘Now by my own dread Majesty I swear,
And by this awful sceptre which I bear,
No impious wretch shall ’scape unpunish’d long,
That in my presence offers such a wrong.
I will this instant undeceive the Knight,
And in the very act restore his sight:
And set the strumpet here in open view,
A warning to the ladies, and to you,
And all the faithless sex, for ever to be true.”
  ‘And will you so,’ replied the Queen, ‘indeed?
Now, by my mother’s soul, it is decreed,
She shall not want an answer at her need.
For her, and for her daughters, I ’ll engage,
And all the sex in each succeeding age;
Art shall be theirs to varnish an offence,
And fortify their crimes with confidence.
Nay, were they taken in a strict embrace,
Seen with both eyes, and pinion’d on the place;
All they shall need is to protest and swear,
Breathe a soft sigh, and drop a tender tear;
Till their wise husbands, gull’d by arts like these,
Grow gentle, tractable, and tame as geese.
  ‘What tho’ this sland’rous Jew, this Solomon,
Call’d women fools, and knew full many a one?
The wiser Wits of later times declare
How constant, chaste, and virtuous women are:
Witness the Martyrs, who resign’d their breath,
Serene in torments, unconcern’d in death;
And witness next what Roman authors tell,
How Arria, Portia, and Lucretia fell.
  ‘But since the sacred leaves to all are free,
And men interpret texts, why should not we?
By this no more was meant than to have shown
That sov’reign goodness dwells in him alone,
Who only Is, and is but only One.
But grant the worst; shall women then be weigh’d
By every word that Solomon hath said?
What tho’ this king (as ancient story boasts)
Built a fair temple to the Lord of Hosts;
He ceas’d at last his Maker to adore,
And did as much for idol Gods, or more.
Beware what lavish praises you confer
On a rank lecher and idolater;
Whose reign indulgent God, says Holy Writ,
Did but for David’s righteous sake permit;
David, the monarch after Heav’n’s own mind,
Who lov’d our sex, and honour’d all our kind.
  ‘Well, I ’m a woman, and as such must speak;
Silence would swell me, and my heart would break.
Know, then, I scorn your dull authorities,
Your idle Wits, and all their learned lies:
By Heav’n, those authors are our sex’s foes,
Whom, in our right, I must and will oppose.’
  ‘Nay (quoth the King) dear madam, be not wroth:
I yield it up; but since I gave my oath,
That this much injur’d Knight again should see,
It must be done—I am a King,’ said he,
‘And one whose faith has ever sacred been—’
  ‘And so has mine (she said)—I am a Queen:
Her answer she shall have, I undertake;
And thus an end of all dispute I make.
Try when you list; and you shall find, my lord,
It is not in our sex to break our word.’
  We leave them here in this heroic strain,
And to the Knight our story turns again;
Who in the garden, with his lovely May,
Sung merrier than the cuckoo or the jay:
This was his song, ‘O kind and constant be,
Constant and kind I ’ll ever prove to thee.’
  Thus singing as he went, at last he drew
By easy steps to where the pear-tree grew:
The longing dame look’d up, and spied her love
Full fairly perch’d among the boughs above.
She stopp’d, and sighing, ‘O good Gods!’ she cried,
‘What pangs, what sudden shoots distend my side?
O for that tempting fruit, so fresh, so green!
Help, for the love of Heav’n’s immortal Queen!
Help, dearest lord, and save at once the life
Of thy poor infant, and thy longing wife!’
  Sore sigh’d the Knight to hear his lady’s cry,
But could not climb, and had no servant nigh:
Old as he was, and void of eyesight too,
What could, alas! a helpless husband do?
‘And must I languish then (she said), and die,
Yet view the lovely fruit before my eye?
At least, kind Sir, for charity’s sweet sake,
Vouchsafe the trunk between your arms to take,
Then from your back I might ascend the tree;
Do you but stoop, and leave the rest to me.’
  ‘With all my soul,’ he thus replied again,
‘I ’d spend my dearest blood to ease thy pain.’
With that his back against the trunk he bent;
She seiz’d a twig, and up the tree she went.
  Now prove your patience, gentle ladies all!
Nor let on me your heavy anger fall:
’T is truth I tell, tho’ not in phrase refin’d;
Tho’ blunt my tale, yet honest is my mind.
What feats the lady in the tree might do,
I pass, as gambols never known to you;
But sure it was a merrier fit, she swore,
Than in her life she ever felt before.
  In that nice moment, lo! the wond’ring Knight
Look’d out, and stood restor’d to sudden sight.
Straight on the tree his eager eyes he bent,
As one whose thoughts were on his spouse intent:
But when he saw his bosom-wife so dress’d,
His rage was such as cannot be express’d.
Not frantic mothers when their infants die
With louder clamours rend the vaulted sky:
He cried, he roar’d, he storm’d, he tore his hair;
‘Death! Hell! and Furies! what dost thou do there?’
  ‘What ails my lord?’ the trembling dame replied,
‘I thought your patience had been better tried:
Is this your love, ungrateful and unkind,
This my reward for having cured the blind?
Why was I taught to make my husband see,
By struggling with a man upon a tree?
Did I for this the power of magic prove?
Unhappy wife, whose crime was too much love!’
  ‘If this be struggling, by this holy light,
’T is struggling with a vengeance (quoth the Knight):
So Heav’n preserve the sight it has restored,
As with these eyes I plainly saw thee whored;
Whored by my slave—perfidious wretch! may Hell
As surely seize thee, as I saw too well.’
  ‘Guard me, good Angels!’ cried the gentle May,
‘Pray Heav’n this magic work the proper way!
Alas, my love! ’t is certain, could you see,
You ne’er had used these killing words to me:
So help me, Fates! as ’t is no perfect sight,
But some faint glimm’ring of a doubtful light.’
  ‘What I have said (quoth he) I must maintain,
For by th’ immortal Powers it seem’d too plain—’
  ‘By all those Powers, some frenzy seiz’d your mind
(Replied the dame): are these the thanks I find?
Wretch that I am, that e’er I was so kind!’
She said; a rising sigh express’d her woe,
The ready tears apace began to flow,
And as they fell she wiped from either eye
The drops (for women, when they list, can cry).
  The Knight was touch’d; and in his looks appear’d
Signs of remorse, while thus his spouse he cheer’d;
‘Madam, ’t is past, and my short anger o’er!
Come down, and vex your tender heart no more.
Excuse me, dear, if aught amiss was said,
For, on my soul, amends shall soon be made:
Let my repentance your forgiveness draw;
By Heav’n, I swore but what I thought I saw.’
‘Ah, my lov’d lord! ’t was much unkind (she cried)
On bare suspicion thus to treat your bride.
But till your sight’s establish’d, for a while
Imperfect objects may your sense beguile.
Thus, when from sleep we first our eyes display,
The balls are wounded with the piercing ray,
And dusky vapours rise, and intercept the day;
So just recov’ring from the shades of night
Your swimming eyes are drunk with sudden light,
Strange phantoms dance around, and skim before your sight.
Then, Sir, be cautious, nor too rashly deem;
Heav’n knows how seldom things are what they seem!
Consult your reason, and you soon shall find
’T was you were jealous, not your wife unkind:
Jove ne’er spoke oracle more true than this,
None judge so wrong as those who think amiss.’
  With that she leap’d into her lord’s embrace,
With well dissembled virtue in her face.
He hugg’d her close, and kiss’d her o’er and o’er,
Disturb’d with doubts and jealousies no more:
Both pleas’d and bless’d, renew’d their mutual vows:
A fruitful wife, and a believing spouse.
Thus ends our tale; whose moral next to make,
Let all wise husbands hence example take;
And pray, to crown the pleasure of their lives,
To be so well deluded by their wives.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2020052102">
<head>
    <suptitle>Paraphrases from Chaucer</suptitle>
    <title>The Wife of Bath</title>
    <subtitle>Her Prologue</subtitle>
    <firstline>Behold the woes of matrimonial life</firstline>
    <keywords>chaucer</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>Behold</sc> the woes of matrimonial life,
And hear with rev’rence an experienced wife;
To dear-bought wisdom give the credit due,
And think for once a woman tells you true.
In all these trials I have borne a part:
I was myself the scourge that caus’d the smart;
For since fifteen in triumph have I led
Five captive husbands from the church to bed.
Christ saw a wedding once, the Scripture says,
And saw but one, ’t was thought, in all his days;
Whence some infer, whose conscience is too nice,
No pious Christian ought to marry twice.
  But let them read, and solve me if they can,
The words address’d to the Samaritan:
Five times in lawful wedlock she was join’d,
And sure the certain stint was ne’er defin’d.
  ‘Increase and multiply’ was Heav’n’s command,
And that ’s a text I clearly understand:
This too, ‘Let men their sires and mothers leave,
And to their dearer wives for ever cleave.’
More wives than one by Solomon were tried,
Or else the wisest of mankind’s belied.
I ’ve had myself full many a merry fit,
And trust in Heav’n I may have many yet;
For when my transitory spouse, unkind,
Shall die and leave his woful wife behind,
I ’ll take the next good Christian I can find.
  Paul, knowing one could never serve our turn,
Declared ’t was better far to wed than burn.
There ’s danger in assembling fire and tow;
I grant ’em that; and what it means you know.
The same apostle, too, has elsewhere own’d
No precept for virginity he found:
’T is but a counsel—and we women still
Take which we like, the counsel or our will.
  I envy not their bliss, if he or she
Think fit to live in perfect chastity:
Pure let them be, and free from taint or vice;
I for a few slight spots am not so nice.
Heav’n calls us diff’rent ways; on these bestows
One proper gift, another grants to those;
Not every man’s obliged to sell his store,
And give up all his substance to the poor:
Such as are perfect may, I can’t deny;
But by your leaves, Divines! so am not I.
  Full many a saint, since first the world began,
Liv’d an unspotted maid in spite of man:
Let such (a God’s name) with fine wheat be fed,
And let us honest wives eat barley bread.
For me, I ’ll keep the post assign’d by Heav’n,
And use the copious talent it has giv’n:
Let my good spouse pay tribute, do me right,
And keep an equal reck’ning every night;
His proper body is not his, but mine;
For so said Paul, and Paul’s a sound divine.
Know then, of those five husbands I have had,
Three were just tolerable, two were bad.
The three were old, but rich and fond beside,
And toil’d most piteously to please their bride;
But since their wealth (the best they had) was mine,
The rest without much loss I could resign:
Sure to be lov’d, I took no pains to please,
Yet had more pleasure far than they had ease.
  Presents flow’d in apace: with showers of gold
They made their court, like Jupiter of old:
If I but smiled, a sudden youth they found,
And a new palsy seiz’d them when I frown’d.
  Ye sov’reign Wives! give ear, and understand:
Thus shall ye speak, and exercise command;
For never was it giv’n to mortal man
To lie so boldly as we women can:
Forswear the fact, tho’ seen with both his eyes,
And call your maids to witness how he lies.
  Hark, old Sir Paul! (’t was thus I used to say)
Whence is our neighbour’s wife so rich and gay?
Treated, caress’d, where’er she ’s pleas’d to roam—
I sit in tatters, and immured at home.
Why to her house dost thou so oft repair?
Art thou so am’rous? and is she so fair?
If I but see a cousin or a friend,
Lord! how you swell and rage like any fiend!
But you reel home, a drunken beastly bear,
Then preach till midnight in your easy chair;
Cry, wives are false, and every woman evil,
And give up all that ’s female to the devil.
  If poor (you say), she drains her husband’s purse;
If rich, she keeps her priest, or something worse;
If highly born, intolerably vain,
Vapours and pride by turns possess her brain;
Now gaily mad, now sourly splenetic,
Freakish when well, and fretful when she ’s sick.
If fair, then chaste she-cannot long abide,
By pressing youth attack’d on every side;
If foul, her wealth the lusty lover lures,
Or else her wit some fool-gallant procures,
Or else she dances with becoming grace,
Or shape excuses the defects of face.
There swims no goose so gray, but soon or late
She finds some honest gander for her mate.
  Horses (thou say’st) and asses men may try,
And ring suspected vessels ere they buy;
But wives, a random choice, untried they take,
They dream in courtship, but in wedlock wake;
Then, not till then, the veil’s remov’d away,
And all the woman glares in open day.
  You tell me, to preserve your wife’s good grace,
Your eyes must always languish on my face,
Your tongue with constant flatt’ries feed my ear,
And tag each sentence with ‘My life! my dear!’
If by strange chance a modest blush be rais’d,
Be sure my fine complexion must be prais’d.
My garments always must be new and gay,
And feasts still kept upon my wedding day.
Then must my nurse be pleas’d, and fav’rite maid;
And endless treats and endless visits paid
To a long train of kindred, friends, allies:
All this thou say’st, and all thou say’st are lies.
  On Jenkin, too, you cast a squinting eye:
What! can your ’prentice raise your jealousy?
Fresh are his ruddy cheeks, his forehead fair,
And like the burnish’d gold his curling hair.
But clear thy wrinkled brow, and quit thy sorrow;
I ’d scorn your ’prentice should you die to-morrow.
  Why are thy chests all lock’d? on what design?
Are not thy worldly goods and treasure mine?
Sir, I ’m no fool; nor shall you, by St. John,
Have goods and body to yourself alone.
One you shall quit, in spite of both your eyes—
I heed not, I, the bolts, the locks, the spies.
If you had wit, you ’d say, ‘Go where you will,
Dear spouse! I credit not the tales they tell:
Take all the freedoms of a married life;
I know thee for a virtuous, faithful wife.’
  Lord! when you have enough, what need you care
How merrily soever others fare?
Tho’ all the day I give and take delight,
Doubt not sufficient will be left at night.
’T is but a just and rational desire
To light a taper at a neighbour’s fire.
There ’s danger too, you think, in rich array,
And none can long be modest that are gay.
The cat, if you but singe her tabby skin,
The chimney keeps, and sits content within:
But once grown sleek, will from her corner run,
Sport with her tail, and wanton in the sun:
She licks her fair round face, and frisks abroad
To show her fur, and to be catterwaw’d.
  Lo thus, my friends, I wrought to my desires
These three right ancient venerable sires.
I told them, Thus you say, and thus you do;
And told them false, but Jenkin swore ’t was true.
I, like a dog, could bite as well as whine,
And first complain’d whene’er the guilt was mine.
I tax’d them oft with wenching and amours,
When their weak legs scarce dragg’d them out of doors;
And swore the rambles that I took by night
Were all to spy what damsels they bedight:
That colour brought me many hours of mirth;
For all this wit is giv’n us from our birth.
Heav’n gave to woman the peculiar grace
To spin, to weep, and cully human race.
By this nice conduct and this prudent course,
By murm’ring, wheedling, stratagem, and force,
I still prevail’d, and would be in the right;
Or curtain lectures made a restless night.
If once my husband’s arm was o’er my side,
‘What! so familiar with your spouse?’ I cried:
I levied first a tax upon his need;
Then let him—’t was a nicety indeed!
Let all mankind this certain maxim hold;
Marry who will, our sex is to be sold.
With empty hands no tassels you can lure,
But fulsome love for gain we can endure;
For gold we love the impotent and old,
And heave, and pant, and kiss, and cling, for gold.
Yet with embraces curses oft I mixt,
Then kiss’d again, and chid, and rail’d betwixt.
Well, I may make my will in peace, and die,
For not one word in man’s arrears am I.
To drop a dear dispute I was unable,
Ev’n though the Pope himself had sat at table;
But when my point was gain’d, then thus I spoke:
‘Billy, my dear, how sheepishly you look!
Approach, my spouse, and let me kiss thy cheek;
Thou shouldst be always thus resign’d and meek!
Of Job’s great patience since so oft you preach,
Well should you practise who so well can teach.
’T is difficult to do, I must allow,
But I, my dearest! will instruct you how.
Great is the blessing of a prudent wife,
Who puts a period to domestic strife.
One of us two must rule, and one obey;
And since in man right Reason bears the sway,
Let that frail thing, weak woman, have her way.
The wives of all my family have ruled
Their tender husbands, and their passions cool’d.
Fie! ’t is unmanly thus to sigh and groan:
What! would you have me to yourself alone?
Why, take me, love! take all and every part!
Here ’s your revenge! you love it at your heart.
Would I vouchsafe to sell what Nature gave,
You little think what custom I could have.
But see! I ’m all your own—nay hold—for shame!
What means my dear?—indeed—you are to blame.’
  Thus with my first three lords I pass’d my life,
A very woman and a very wife.
What sums from these old spouses I could raise
Procur’d young husbands in my riper days.
Tho’ past my bloom, not yet decay’d was I,
Wanton and wild, and chatter’d like a pie.
In country dances still I bore the bell,
And sung as sweet as ev’ning Philomel.
To clear my quail-pipe, and refresh my soul,
Full oft I drain’d the spicy nut-brown bowl;
Rich luscious wines, that youthful blood improve,
And warm the swelling veins to feats of love:
For ’t is as sure as cold engenders hail,
A liquorish mouth must have a lech’rous tail:
Wine lets no lover unrewarded go,
As all true gamesters by experience know.
  But oh, good Gods! whene’er a thought I cast
On all the joys of youth and beauty past,
To find in pleasures I have had my part
Still warms me to the bottom of my heart.
This wicked world was once my dear delight;
Now all my conquests, all my charms, good night!
The flour consumed, the best that now I can
Is ev’n to make my market of the bran.
  My fourth dear spouse was not exceeding true;
He kept, ’t was thought, a private miss or two;
But all that score I paid—As how? you ’ll say:
Not with my body, in a filthy way;
But I so dress’d, and danc’d, and drank, and din’d
And view’d a friend with eyes so very kind,
As stung his heart, and made his marrow fry,
With burning rage and frantic jealousy.
His soul, I hope, enjoys eternal glory,
For here on earth I was his purgatory.
Oft, when his shoe the most severely wrung,
He put on careless airs, and sat and sung.
How sore I gall’d him only Heav’n could know,
And he that felt, and I that caus’d the woe.
He died when last from pilgrimage I came,
With other gossips, from Jerusalem;
And now lies buried underneath a rood,
Fair to be seen, and rear’d of honest wood:
A tomb, indeed, with fewer sculptures graced
Than that Mausolus’ pious widow placed,
Or where enshrin’d the great Darius lay;
But cost on graves is merely thrown away.
The pit fill’d up, with turf we cover’d o’er;
So bless the good man’s soul! I say no more.
  Now for my fifth lov’d lord, the last and best;
(Kind Heav’n afford him everlasting rest!)
Full hearty was his love, and I can show
The tokens on my ribs in black and blue;
Yet with a knack my heart he could have won,
While yet the smart was shooting in the bone.
How quaint an appetite in women reigns!
Free gifts we scorn, and love what costs us pains.
Let men avoid us, and on them we leap;
A glutted market makes provision cheap.
  In pure good will I took this jovial spark,
Of Oxford he, a most egregious clerk.
He boarded with a widow in the town,
A trusty gossip, one dame Alison;
Full well the secrets of my soul she knew,
Better than e’er our parish priest could do.
To her I told whatever could befall:
Had but my husband piss’d against a wall,
Or done a thing that might have cost his life,
She—and my niece—and one more worthy wife,
Had known it all: what most he would conceal,
To these I made no scruple to reveal.
Oft has he blush’d from ear to ear for shame
That e’er he told a secret to his dame.
  It so befell, in holy time of Lent,
That oft a day I to this gossip went;
(My husband, thank my stars, was out of town)
From house to house we rambled up and down,
This clerk, myself, and my good neighbour Alse,
To see, be seen, to tell, and gather tales.
Visits to every church we daily paid,
And march’d in every holy masquerade;
The stations duly and the vigils kept;
Not much we fasted, but scarce ever slept.
At sermons, too, I shone in scarlet gay:
The wasting moth ne’er spoil’d my best array;
The cause was this, I wore it every day.
  ’T was when fresh May her early blossoms yields,
This clerk and I were walking in the fields.
We grew so intimate, I can’t tell how,
I pawn’d my honour, and engaged my vow,
If e’er I laid my husband in his urn,
That he, and only he, should serve my turn.
We straight struck hands, the bargain was agreed;
I still have shifts against a time of need.
The mouse that always trusts to one poor hole
Can never be a mouse of any soul.
  I vow’d I scarce could sleep since first I knew him,
And durst be sworn he had bewitch’d me to him;
If e’er I slept I dream’d of him alone,
And dreams foretell, as learned men have shown.
All this I said; but dreams, Sirs, I had none:
I follow’d but my crafty crony’s lore,
Who bid me tell this lie—and twenty more.
  Thus day by day, and month by month we past;
It pleas’d the Lord to take my spouse at last.
I tore my gown, I soil’d my locks with dust,
And beat my breasts, as wretched widows—must.
Before my face my handkerchief I spread,
To hide the flood of tears I—did not shed.
The good man’s coffin to the church was borne;
Around the neighbours and my clerk too mourn.
But as he march’d, good Gods! he show’d a pair
Of legs and feet so clean, so strong, so fair!
Of twenty winters’ age he seem’d to be;
I (to say truth) was twenty more than he;
But vig’rous still, a lively buxom dame,
And had a wondrous gift to quench a flame.
A conjurer once, that deeply could divine,
Assur’d me Mars in Taurus was my sign.
As the stars order’d, such my life has been:
Alas, alas! that ever love was sin!
Fair Venus gave me fire and sprightly grace,
And Mars assurance and a dauntless face.
By virtue of this powerful constellation,
I follow’d always my own inclination.
  But to my tale:—A month scarce pass’d away,
With dance and song we kept the nuptial day.
All I possess’d I gave to his command,
My goods and chattels, money, house, and land;
But oft repented, and repent it still;
He prov’d a rebel to my sov’reign will;
Nay, once, by Heav’n! he struck me on the face:
Hear but the fact, and judge yourselves the case.
  Stubborn as any lioness was I,
And knew full well to raise my voice on high;
As true a rambler as I was before,
And would be so in spite of all he swore.
He against this right sagely would advise,
And old examples set before my eyes;
Tell how the Roman matrons led their life,
Of Gracchus’ mother, and Duilius’ wife;
And close the sermon, as beseem’d his wit,
With some grave sentence out of Holy Writ.
Oft would he say, ‘Who builds his house on sands,
Pricks his blind horse across the fallow lands,
Or lets his wife abroad with pilgrims roam,
Deserves a fool’s-cap and long ears at home.’
All this avail’d not, for whoe’er he be
That tells my faults, I hate him mortally!
And so do numbers more, I ’ll boldly say,
Men, women, clergy, regular and lay.
  My spouse (who was, you know, to learning bred)
A certain treatise oft at evening read,
Where divers authors (whom the devil confound
For all their lies) were in one volume bound:
Valerius whole, and of St. Jerome part;
Chrysippus and Tertullian, Ovid’s Art,
Solomon’s Proverbs, Eloisa’s loves,
And many more than sure the church approves.
More legends were there here of wicked wives
Than good in all the Bible and saints’ lives.
Who drew the lion vanquish’d? ’T was a man:
But could we women write as scholars can,
Men should stand mark’d with far more wickedness
Than all the sons of Adam could redress.
Love seldom haunts the breast where learning lies,
And Venus sets ere Mercury can rise.
Those play the scholars who can’t play the men,
And use that weapon which they have, their pen;
When old, and past the relish of delight,
Then down they sit, and in their dotage write
That not one woman keeps her marriage-vow.
(This by the way, but to my purpose now.)
  It chanc’d my husband, on a winter’s night,
Read in this book aloud with strange delight,
How the first female (as the Scriptures show)
Brought her own spouse and all his race to woe;
How Samson fell; and he whom Dejanire
Wrapp’d in th’ envenom’d shirt, and set on fire;
How curs’d Eriphyle her lord betray’d,
And the dire ambush Clytemnestra laid;
But what most pleas’d him was the Cretan dame
And husband-bull—Oh, monstrous! fie, for shame!
  He had by heart the whole detail of woe
Xantippe made her good man undergo;
How oft she scolded in a day he knew,
How many pisspots on the sage she threw—
Who took it patiently, and wiped his head:
‘Rain follows thunder,’ that was all he said.
  He read how Arius to his friend complain’d
A fatal tree was growing in his land,
On which three wives successively had twin’d
A sliding noose, and waver’d in the wind.
‘Where grows this plant,’ replied the friend, ‘oh where?
For better fruit did never orchard bear:
Give me some slip of this most blissful tree,
And in my garden planted it shall be.’
  Then how two wives their lords’ destruction prove,
Thro’ hatred one, and one thro’ too much love;
That for her husband mix’d a pois’nous draught,
And this for lust an am’rous philtre bought;
The nimble juice soon seiz’d his giddy head,
Frantic at night, and in the morning dead.
  How some with swords their sleeping lords have slain,
And some have hammer’d nails into their brain,
And some have drench’d them with a deadly potion:
All this he read, and read with great devotion.
  Long time I heard, and swell’d, and blush’d, and frown’d;
But when no end of these vile tales I found,
When still he read, and laugh’d, and read again,
And half the night was thus consumed in vain,
Provoked to vengeance, three large leaves I tore,
And with one buffet fell’d him on the floor.
With that my husband in a fury rose,
And down he settled me with hearty blows.
I groan’d, and lay extended on my side;
‘Oh! thou hast slain me for my wealth,’ I cried!
‘Yet I forgive thee—take my last embrace’—
He wept, kind soul! and stoop’d to kiss my face:
I took him such a box as turn’d him blue,
Then sigh’d and cried, ‘Adieu, my dear, adieu!’
  But after many a hearty struggle past,
I condescended to be pleas’d at last.
Soon as he said, ‘My mistress and my wife!
Do what you list the term of all your life;’
I took to heart the merits of the cause,
And stood content to rule by wholesome laws;
Receiv’d the reins of absolute command,
With all the government of house and land,
And empire o’er his tongue and o’er his hand.
As for the volume that revil’d the dames,
’T was torn to fragments, and condemn’d to flames.
  Now Heav’n on all my husbands gone bestow
Pleasures above for tortures felt below:
That rest they wish’d for grant them in the grave,
And bless those souls my conduct help’d to save!
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2020052103">
<head>
    <suptitle>Paraphrases from Chaucer</suptitle>
    <title>The Temple of Fame</title>
    <firstline>In that soft season, when descending showers</firstline>
    <keywords>chaucer</keywords>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
<sc>In</sc> that soft season, when descending showers
Call forth the greens, and wake the rising flowers,
When opening buds salute the welcome day,
And earth relenting feels the genial ray;
As balmy sleep had charm’d my cares to rest,
And love itself was banish’d from my breast,
(What time the morn mysterious visions brings,
While purer slumbers spread their golden wings)
A train of phantoms in wild order rose,
And join’d, this intellectual scene compose.
  I stood, methought, betwixt earth, seas, and skies,
The whole Creation open to my eyes;
In air self-balanced hung the globe below,
Where mountains rise and circling oceans flow;
Here naked rocks and empty wastes were seen,
There towery cities, and the forests green;
Here sailing ships delight the wand’ring eyes,
There trees and intermingled temples rise:
Now a clear sun the shining scene displays,
The transient landscape now in clouds decays.
  O’er the wide prospect as I gazed around,
Sudden I heard a wild promiscuous sound,
Like broken thunders that at distance roar,
Or billows murm’ring on the hollow shore:
Then gazing up, a glorious Pile beheld,
Whose tow’ring summit ambient clouds conceal’d;
High on a rock of ice the structure lay,
Steep its ascent, and slipp’ry was the way;
The wondrous rock like Parian marble shone,
And seem’d, to distant sight, of solid stone.
Inscriptions here of various names I view’d,
The greater part by hostile time subdued;
Yet wide was spread their fame in ages past,
And poets once had promis’d they should last.
Some fresh engraved appear’d of wits renown’d;
I look’d again, nor could their trace be found.
Critics I saw, that other names deface,
And fix their own with labour, in their place:
Their own, like others, soon their place resign’d,
Or disappear’d and left the first behind.
Nor was the work impair’d by storms alone,
But felt th’ approaches of too warm a sun;
For Fame, impatient of extremes, decays
Not more by envy than excess of praise.
Yet part no injuries of Heav’n could feel,
Like crystal faithful to the graving steel:
The rock’s high summit, in the temple’s shade,
Nor heat could melt, nor beating storm invade.
Their names inscribed unnumber’d ages past
From Time’s first birth, with Time itself shall last:
These ever new, nor subject to decays,
Spread, and grow brighter with the length of days.
  So Zembla’s rocks (the beauteous work of frost)
Rise white in air, and glitter o’er the coast;
Pale suns, unfelt, at distance roll away,
And on th’ impassive ice the lightnings play;
Eternal snows the growing mass supply,
Till the bright mountains prop th’ incumbent sky:
As Atlas fix’d, each hoary pile appears,
The gather’d winter of a thousand years.
  On this foundation Fame’s high temple stands;
Stupendous pile! not rear’d by mortal hands.
Whate’er proud Rome or artful Greece beheld,
Or elder Babylon, its frame excell’d.
Four faces had the dome, and ev’ry face
Of various structure, but of equal grace:
Four brazen gates, on columns lifted high,
Salute the diff’rent quarters of the sky.
Here fabled Chiefs in darker ages born,
Or Worthies old whom Arms or Arts adorn,
Who cities raised or tamed a monstrous race,
The walls in venerable order grace:
Heroes in animated marble frown,
And Legislators seem to think in stone.
  Westward, a sumptuous frontispiece appear’d,
On Doric pillars of white marble rear’d,
Crown’d with an architrave of antique mould,
And sculpture rising on the roughen’d gold.
In shaggy spoils here Theseus was beheld,
And Perseus dreadful with Minerva’s shield:
There great Alcides, stooping with his toil,
Rests on his club, and holds th’ Hesperian spoil:
Here Orpheus sings; trees moving to the sound
Start from their roots, and form a shade around:
Amphion there the loud creating lyre
Strikes, and beholds a sudden Thebes aspire;
Cithæron’s echoes answer to his call,
And half the mountain rolls into a wall:
There might you see the length’ning spires ascend,
The domes swell up, and widening arches bend,
The growing towers, like exhalations, rise,
And the huge columns heave into the skies.
  The eastern front was glorious to behold,
With diamond flaming, and barbaric gold.
There Ninus shone, who spread th’ Assyrian fame,
And the great founder of the Persian name;
There in long robes the royal Magi stand,
Grave Zoroaster waves the circling wand;
The sage Chaldeans robed in white appear’d,
And Brahmans, deep in desert woods revered.
These stopp’d the moon, and call’ th’ unbodied shades
To midnight banquets in the glimm’ring glades;
Made visionary fabrics round them rise,
And airy spectres skim before their eyes;
Of talismans and sigils knew the power,
And careful watch’d the planetary hour.
Superior, and alone, Confucius stood,
Who taught that useful science,—to be good.
  But on the south, a long majestic race
Of Egypt’s priests the gilded niches grace,
Who measured earth, described the starry spheres,
And traced the long records of Lunar Years.
High on his car Sesostris struck my view,
Whom sceptred slaves in golden harness drew:
His hands a bow and pointed jav’lin hold;
His giant limbs are arm’d in scales of gold.
Between the statues obelisks were placed,
And the learn’d walls with hieroglyphics graced.
  Of Gothic structure was the northern side,
O’erwrought with ornaments of barb’rous pride.
There huge Colosses rose, with trophies crown’d,
And Runic characters were graved around;
There sat Zamolxis with erected eyes,
And Odin here in mimic trances dies.
There on rude iron columns, smear’d with blood,
The horrid forms of Scythian Heroes stood,
Druids and Bards (their once loud harps unstrung)
And youths that died to be by poets sung.
These and a thousand more of doubtful fame,
To whom old fables gave a lasting name,
In ranks adorn’d the temple’s outward face;
The wall in lustre and effect like glass,
Which o’er each object casting various dyes,
Enlarges some, and others multiplies;
Nor void of emblem was the mystic wall,
For thus romantic Fame increases all.
  The temple shakes, the sounding gates unfold,
Wide vaults appear, and roofs of fretted gold,
Rais’d on a thousand pillars, wreath’d around
With laurel foliage, and with eagles crown’d.
Of bright transparent beryl were the walls,
The friezes gold, and gold the capitals;
As Heav’n with stars, the roof with jewels glows,
And ever-living lamps depend in rows.
Full in the passage of each spacious gate
The sage Historians in white garments wait;
Graved o’er their seats the from of Time was found,
His scythe revers’d, and both his pinions bound.
Within stood Heroes, who thro’ loud alarms
In bloody fields pursued renown in arms.
High on a throne, with trophies charged, I view’d
The youth that all things but himself subdued;
His feet on sceptres and tiaras trod,
And his horn’d head belied the Libyan God,
There Cæsar, graced with both Minervas, shone;
Cæsar, the world’s great master, and his own;
Unmov’d, superior still in ev’ry state,
And scarce detested in his country’s fate.
But chief were those who not for empire fought,
But with their toils their people’s safety bought:
High o’er the rest Epaminondas stood;
Timoleon, glorious in his brother’s blood;
Bold Scipio, saviour of the Roman state,
Great in his triumphs, in retirement great;
And wise Aurelius, in whose well-taught mind
With boundless power unbounded virtue join’d,
His own strict judge, and patron of mankind.
  Much-suff’ring heroes next their honours claim.
Those of less noisy, and less guilty fame,
Fair Virtue’s silent train: supreme of these
Here ever shines the godlike Socrates:
He whom ungrateful Athens could expel,
At all times just, but when he sign’d the shell:
Here his abode the martyr’d Phocion claims,
With Agis, not the last of Spartan names:
Unconquer’d Cato shows the wound he tore,
And Brutus his ill genius meets no more.
  But in the centre of the hallow’d choir
Six pompous columns o’er the rest aspire:
Around the shrine itself of Fame they stand,
Hold the chief honours and the fane command.
High on the first the mighty Homer shone;
Eternal adamant composed his throne;
Father of verse! in holy fillets drest,
His silver beard waved gently o’er his breast;
Tho’ blind, a boldness in his looks appears;
In years he seem’d, but not impair’d by years.
The wars of Troy were round the pillar seen;
Here fierce Tydides wounds the Cyprian Queen;
Here Hector, glorious from Patroclus’ fall,
Here, dragg’d in triumph round the Trojan wall.
Motion and life did ev’ry part inspire,
Bold was the work, and prov’d the master’s fire:
A strong expression most he seem’d t’ affect,
And here and there disclosed a brave neglect.
  A golden column next in rank appear’d,
On which a shrine of purest gold was rear’d;
Finish’d the whole, and labour’d ev’ry part,
With patient touches of unwearied art.
The Mantuan there in sober triumph sate,
Composed his posture, and his look sedate;
On Homer still he fix’d a rev’rend eye,
Great without pride, in modest majesty.
In living sculpture on the sides were spread
The Latian wars, and haughty Turnus dead;
Eliza stretch’d upon the funeral pyre;
Æneas bending with his aged sire:
Troy flamed in burning gold, and o’er the throne
‘Arms and the man’ in golden ciphers shone.
  Four swans sustain a car of silver bright,
With heads advanced, and pinions stretch’d for flight:
Here, like some furious prophet, Pindar rode,
And seem’d to labour with th’ inspiring God.
Across the harp a careless hand he flings,
And boldly sinks into the sounding strings.
The figured games of Greece the column grace:
Neptune and Jove survey the rapid race;
The youths hang o’er the chariots as they run;
The fiery steeds seem starting from the stone;
The champions in distorted postures threat;
And all appear’d irregularly great.
  Here happy Horace tuned th’ Ausonian lyre
To sweeter sounds, and temper’d Pindar’s fire:
Pleas’d with Alcæus’ manly rage t’ infuse
The softer spirit of the Sapphic Muse.
The polish’d pillar diff’rent sculptures grace;
A work outlasting monumental brass.
Here smiling loves and bacchanals appear,
The Julian star, and great Augustus here;
The doves, that round the infant poet spread
Myrtles and bays, hung hov’ring o’er his head.
  Here, in a shrine that cast a dazzling light,
Sate fix’d in thought the mighty Stagyrite;
His sacred head a radiant Zodiac crown’d,
And various animals his sides surround:
His piercing eyes, erect, appear to view
Superior worlds, and look all Nature thro’.
  With equal rays immortal Tully shone;
The Roman rostra deck’d the consul’s throne;
Gath’ring his flowing robe, he seem’d to stand
In act to speak, and graceful stretch’d his hand;
Behind, Rome’s Genius waits with civic crowns,
And the great father of his country owns.
  These massy columns in a circle rise,
O’er which a pompous dome invades the skies;
Scarce to the top I stretch’d my aching sight,
So large it spread, and swell’d to such a height.
Full in the midst proud Fame’s imperial seat
With jewels blazed, magnificently great;
The vivid em’ralds there revive the eye,
The flaming rubies show their sanguine dye,
Bright azure rays from lively sapphires stream,
And lucid amber casts a golden gleam.
With various-colour’d light the pavement shone,
And all on fire appear’d the glowing throne;
The dome’s high arch reflects the mingled blaze,
And forms a rainbow of alternate rays.
When on the Goddess first I cast my sight,
Scarce seem’d her stature of a cubit’s height;
But swell’d to larger size, the more I gazed,
Till to the roof her tow’ring front she rais’d.
With her, the temple ev’ry moment grew,
And ampler vistas open’d to my view:
Upward the columns shoot, the roofs ascend,
And arches widen, and long aisles extend.
Such was her form, as ancient bards have told;
Wings raise her arms, and wings her feet infold;
A thousand busy tongues the Goddess bears,
A thousand open eyes, and thousand list’ning ears.
Beneath, in order ranged, the tuneful Nine
(Her virgin handmaids) still attend the shrine;
With eyes on Fame for ever fix’d, they sing;
For Fame they raise the voice, and tune the string;
With Time’s first birth began the heav’nly lays,
And last, eternal, thro’ the length of days.
  Around these wonders as I cast a look,
The trumpet sounded, and the temple shook,
And all the nations summon’d at the call,
From diff’rent quarters fill the crowded hall.
Of various tongues the mingled sounds were heard;
In various garbs promiscuous throngs appear’d:
Thick as the bees, that with the spring renew
Their flowery toils, and sip the fragrant dew,
When the wing’d colonies first tempt the sky,
O’er dusky fields and shaded waters fly,
Or, settling, seize the sweets the blossoms yield,
And a low murmur runs along the field.
Millions of suppliant crowds the shrine attend,
And all degrees before the Goddess bend;
The poor, the rich, the valiant, and the sage,
And boasting youth, and narrative old age.
Their pleas were diff’rent, their request the same;
For good and bad alike are fond of Fame.
Some she disgraced and some with honours crown’d;
Unlike successes equal merits found.
Thus her blind sister, fickle Fortune, reigns,
And, undiscerning, scatters crowns and chains.
  First at the shrine the learned world appear,
And to the Goddess thus prefer their prayer:
‘Long have we sought t’ instruct and please mankind,
With studies pale, with midnight-vigils blind;
But thank’d by few, rewarded yet by none,
We here appeal to thy superior throne:
On Wit and Learning the just prize bestow,
For Fame is all we must expect below.’
  The Goddess heard, and bade the Muses raise
The golden trumpet of eternal praise:
From pole to pole the winds diffuse the sound,
That fills the circuit of the world around;
Not all at once, as thunder breaks the cloud,
The notes at first were rather sweet than loud;
By just degrees they every moment rise,
Fill the wide earth, and gain upon the skies.
At every breath were balmy odours shed,
Which still grew sweeter as they wider spread;
Less fragrant scents th’ unfolding rose exhales,
Or spices breathing in Arabian gales.
  Next these the good and just, an awful train,
Thus on their knees address the sacred fane:
‘Since living virtue is with envy curs’d,
And the best men are treated like the worst,
Do thou, just Goddess, call our merits forth,
And give each deed th’ exact intrinsic worth.’
‘Not with bare justice shall your act be crown’d
(Said Fame), but high above desert renown’d:
Let fuller notes th’ applauding world amaze,
And the loud clarion labour in your praise.’
  This band dismiss’d, behold another crowd
Preferr’d the same request, and lowly bow’d;
The constant tenor of whose well-spent days
No less deserv’d a just return of praise.
But straight the direful trump of Slander sounds;
Thro’ the big dome the doubling thunder bounds;
Loud as the burst of cannon rends the skies,
The dire report thro’ every region flies,
In every ear incessant rumours rung,
And gath’ring scandals grew on every tongue.
From the black trumpet’s rusty concave broke
Sulphureous flames, and clouds of rolling smoke:
The pois’nous vapour blots the purple skies,
And withers all before it as it flies.
  A troop came next, who crowns and armour wore,
And proud defiance in their looks they bore:
‘For thee (they cried) amidst alarms and strife,
We sail’d in tempests down the stream of life;
For thee whole nations fill’d with flames and blood,
And swam to Empire thro’ the purple flood:
Those ills we dared, thy inspiration own;
What virtue seem’d, was done for thee alone.’
‘Ambitious fools!’ (the Queen replied, and frown’d)
‘Be all your acts in dark oblivion drown’d;
There sleep forgot, with mighty tyrants gone,
Your statues moulder’d, and your names unknown!’
A sudden cloud straight snatch’d them from my sight,
And each majestic phantom sunk in night.
  Then came the smallest tribe I yet had seen;
Plain was their dress, and modest was their mien:
‘Great Idol of mankind! we neither claim
The praise of Merit, nor aspire to Fame!
But safe in deserts from th’ applause of men,
Would die unheard of, as we liv’d unseen;
’T is all we beg thee, to conceal from sight
Those acts of goodness which themselves requite.
O let us still the secret joy partake,
To follow Virtue ev’n for Virtue’s sake.’
  ‘And live there men who slight immortal fame?
Who then with incense shall adore our name?
But, mortals! know, ’t is still our greatest pride
To blaze those virtues which the good would hide.
Rise! Muses, rise! add all your tuneful breath;
These must not sleep in darkness and in death.’
She said: in air the trembling music floats,
And on the winds triumphant swell the notes;
So soft, tho’ high, so loud, and yet so clear,
Ev’n list’ning angels lean’d from Heav’n to hear:
To farthest shores th’ ambrosial spirit flies,
Sweet to the world, and grateful to the skies.
  Next these a youthful train their vows express’d,
With feathers crown’d, with gay embroid’ry dress’d:
‘Hither’ they cried ‘direct your eyes, and see
The men of pleasure, dress, and gallantry.
Ours is the place at banquets, balls, and plays,
Sprightly our nights, polite are all our days;
Courts we frequent, where ’t is our pleasing care
To pay due visits, and address the Fair;
In fact, ’t is true, no nymph we could persuade,
But still in fancy vanquish’d ev’ry maid;
Of unknown Duchesses lewd tales we tell,
Yet, would the world believe us, all were well;
The joy let others have, and we the name,
And what we want in pleasure, grant in fame.’
  The Queen assents: the trumpet rends the skies,
And at each blast a lady’s honour dies.
  Pleas’d with the strange success, vast numbers prest
Around the shrine, and made the same request:
‘What you’ she cried, ‘unlearn’d in arts to please,
Slaves to yourselves, and ev’n fatigued with ease,
Who lose a length of undeserving days,
Would you usurp the lover’s dear-bought praise?
To just contempt, ye vain pretenders, fall,
The people’s fable, and the scorn of all.’
Straight the black clarion sends a horrid sound,
Loud laughs burst out, and bitter scoffs fly round;
Whispers are heard, with taunts reviling loud,
And scornful hisses run thro’ all the crowd.
  Last, those who boast of mighty mischiefs done,
Enslave their country, or usurp a throne;
Or who their glory’s dire foundation laid
On sov’reigns ruin’d, or on friends betray’d;
Calm, thinking villains, whom no faith could fix,
Of crooked counsels and dark politics;
Of these a gloomy tribe surround the throne,
And beg to make th’ immortal treasons known.
The trumpet roars, long flaky flames expire,
With sparks that seem’d to set the world on fire.
At the dread sound pale mortals stood aghast,
And startled Nature trembled with the blast.
  This having heard and seen, some Power unknown
Straight changed the scene, and snatch’d me from the throne.
Before my view appear’d a structure fair,
Its site uncertain, if in earth or air;
With rapid motion turn’d the mansion round;
With ceaseless noise the ringing walls resound:
Not less in number were the spacious doors
Than leaves on trees, or sands upon the shores;
Which still unfolded stand, by night, by day,
Pervious to winds, and open every way.
As flames by nature to the skies ascend,
As weighty bodies to the centre tend,
As to the sea returning rivers roll,
And the touch’d needle trembles to the pole,
Hither, as to their proper place, arise
All various sounds from earth, and seas, and skies,
Or spoke aloud, or whisper’d in the ear;
Nor ever silence, rest, or peace is here.
As on the smooth expanse of crystal lakes
The sinking stone at first a circle makes;
The trembling surface by the motion stirr’d,
Spreads in a second circle, then a third;
Wide, and more wide, the floating rings advance,
Fill all the wat’ry plain, and to the margin dance:
Thus every voice and sound, when first they break,
On neighb’ring air a soft impression make;
Another ambient circle then they move;
That in its turn, impels the next above;
Thro’ undulating air the sounds are sent,
And spread o’er all the fluid element.
  There various news I heard of love and strife,
Of peace and war, health, sickness, death, and life,
Of loss and gain, of famine, and of store,
Of storms at sea, and travels on the shore,
Of prodigies, and portents seen in air,
Of fires and plagues, and stars with blazing hair,
Of turns of fortune, changes in the state,
The fall of fav’rites, projects of the great,
Of old mismanagements, taxations new;
All neither wholly false, nor wholly true.
  Above, below, without, within, around,
Confused, unnumber’d multitudes are found,
Who pass, repass, advance, and glide away,
Hosts rais’d by fear, and phantoms of a day:
Astrologers, that future fates foreshew,
Projectors, quacks, and lawyers not a few;
And priests, and party zealots, numerous bands,
With home-born lies or tales from foreign lands;
Each talk’d aloud, or in some secret place,
And wild impatience stared in ev’ry face.
The flying rumours gather’d as they roll’d,
Scarce any tale was sooner heard than told;
And all who told it added something new,
And all who heard it made enlargements too;
In ev’ry ear it spread, on ev’ry tongue it grew.
Thus flying east and west, and north and south,
News travel’d with increase from mouth to mouth.
So from a spark that, kindled first by chance,
With gath’ring force the quick’ning flames advance;
Till to the clouds their curling heads aspire,
And towers and temples sink in floods of fire.
  When thus ripe lies are to perfection sprung,
Full grown, and fit to grace a mortal tongue,
Thro’ thousand vents, impatient, forth they flow,
And rush in millions on the world below.
Fame sits aloft, and points them out their course,
Their date determines, and prescribes their force;
Some to remain, and some to perish soon,
Or wane and wax alternate like the moon.
Around, a thousand winged wonders fly,
Borne by the trumpet’s blast, and scatter’d thro’ the sky.
  There, at one passage, oft you might survey
A lie and truth contending for the way;
And long ’t was doubtful, both so closely pent,
Which first should issue thro’ the narrow vent:
At last agreed, together out they fly,
Inseparable now the truth and lie;
The strict companions are for ever join’d,
And this or that unmix’d, no mortal e’er shall find,
  While thus I stood, intent to see and hear,
One came, methought, and whisper’d in my ear:
‘What could thus high thy rash ambition raise?
Art thou, fond youth, a candidate for praise?’
  ‘’T is true,’ said I, ‘not void of hopes I came,
For who so fond as youthful bards of Fame?
But few, alas! the casual blessing boast,
So hard to gain, so easy to be lost.
How vain that second life in others’ breath,
Th’ estate which wits inherit after death!
Ease, health, and life for this they must resign,
(Unsure the tenure, but how vast the fine!)
The great man’s curse, without the gains, endure,
Be envied, wretched; and be flatter’d, poor;
All luckless wits their enemies profest,
And all successful, jealous friends at best.
Nor Fame I slight, nor for her favours call;
She comes unlook’d for, if she comes at all.
But if the purchase costs so dear a price
As soothing Folly, or exalting Vice;
Oh! if the Muse must flatter lawless sway,
And follow still where Fortune leads the way;
Or if no basis bear my rising name,
But the fall’n ruins of another’s fame;
Then teach me, Heav’n! to scorn the guilty bays;
Drive from my breast that wretched lust of praise;
Unblemish’d let me live or die unknown;
Oh, grant an honest fame, or grant me none!’
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2020052104">
<head>
    <title>Eloisa to Abelard</title>
    <firstline>In these deep solitudes and awful cells</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<prose>
<center>Argument</center>
Abelard and Eloisa flourished in the twelfth century; they were two of the most distinguished persons of their age in Learning and Beauty, but for nothing more famous than for their unfortunate passion. After a long course of calamities, they retired each to a several convent, and consecrated the remainder of their days to Religion. It was many years after this separation that a letter of Abelard’s to a friend, which contained the history of his misfortune, fell into the hands of Eloisa. This, awakening all her tenderness, occasioned those celebrated letters (out of which the following is partly extracted), which give so lively a picture of the struggles of Grace and Nature, Virtue and Passion.
</prose>
<poetry>
<sc>In</sc> these deep solitudes and awful cells,
Where heav’nly-pensive Contemplation dwells,
And ever-musing Melancholy reigns,
What means this tumult in a vestal’s veins?
Why rove my thoughts beyond this last retreat?
Why feels my heart its long-forgotten heat?
Yet, yet I love!—From Abelard it came,
And Eloisa yet must kiss the name.
  Dear fatal name! rest ever unreveal’d,
Nor pass these lips, in holy silence seal’d:
Hide it, my heart, within that close disguise,
Where, mix’d with God’s, his lov’d idea lies:
O write it not, my hand—the name appears
Already written—wash it out, my tears!
In vain lost Eloisa weeps and prays,
Her heart still dictates, and her hand obeys.
  Relentless walls! whose darksome round contains
Repentant sighs, and voluntary pains:
Ye rugged rocks, which holy knees have worn;
Ye grots and caverns shagg’d with horrid thorn!
Shrines! where their vigils pale-eyed virgins keep,
And pitying saints, whose statues learn to weep!
Tho’ cold like you, unmov’d and silent grown,
I have not yet forgot myself to stone.
All is not Heav’n’s while Abelard has part,
Still rebel Nature holds out half my heart;
Nor prayers nor fasts its stubborn pulse restrain,
Nor tears, for ages taught to flow in vain.
  Soon as thy letters trembling I unclose,
That well-known name awakens all my woes.
Oh name for ever sad! for ever dear!
Still breathed in sighs, still usher’d with a tear.
I tremble too, where’er my own I find,
Some dire misfortune follows close behind.
Line after line my gushing eyes o’erflow,
Led thro’a safe variety of woe:
Now warm in love, now with’ring in my bloom,
Lost in a convent’s solitary gloom!
There stern religion quench’d th’ unwilling flame,
There died the best of passions, Love and Fame.
  Yet write, O write me all, that I may join
Griefs to thy griefs, and echo sighs to thine.
Nor foes nor fortune take this power away;
And is my Abelard less kind than they?
Tears still are mine, and those I need not spare;
Love but demands what else were shed in prayer.
No happier task these faded eyes pursue;
To read and weep is all they now can do.
  Then share thy pain, allow that sad relief;
Ah, more than share it, give me all thy grief.
Heav’n first taught letters for some wretch’s aid,
Some banish’d lover, or some captive maid;
They live, they speak, they breathe what love inspires,
Warm from the soul, and faithful to its fires;
The virgin’s wish without her fears impart,
Excuse the blush, and pour out all the heart,
Speed the soft intercourse from soul to soul,
And waft a sigh from Indus to the Pole.
  Thou know’st how guiltless first I met thy flame,
When Love approach’d me under Friendship’s name;
My fancy form’d thee of angelic kind,
Some emanation of th’ all-beauteous Mind.
Those smiling eyes, attemp’ring every ray,
Shone sweetly lambent with celestial day,
Guiltless I gazed; Heav’n listen’d while you sung;
And truths divine came mended from that tongue.
From lips like those what precept fail’d to move?
Too soon they taught me ’t was no sin to love:
Back thro’ the paths of pleasing sense I ran,
Nor wish’d an angel whom I loved a man.
Dim and remote the joys of saints I see;
Nor envy them that Heav’n I lose for thee.
  How oft, when press’d to marriage, have I said,
Curse on all laws but those which Love has made!
Love, free as air, at sight of human ties,
Spreads his light wings, and in a moment flies.
Let Wealth, let Honour, wait the wedded dame,
August her deed, and sacred be her fame;
Before true passion all those views remove;
Fame, Wealth, and Honour! what are you to Love?
The jealous God, when we profane his fires,
Those restless passions in revenge inspires,
And bids them make mistaken mortals groan,
Who seek in love for aught but love alone.
Should at my feet the world’s great master fall,
Himself, his throne, his world, I ’d scorn ’em all:
Not Cæsar’s empress would I deign to prove;
No, make me mistress to the man I love;
If there be yet another name more free,
More fond than mistress, make me that to thee!
O happy state! when souls each other draw,
When Love is liberty, and Nature law:
All then is full, possessing and possess’d,
No craving void left aching in the breast:
Ev’n thought meets thought, ere from the lips it part,
And each warm wish springs mutual from the heart.
This sure is bliss (if bliss on earth there be),
And once the lot of Abelard and me.
  Alas, how changed! what sudden horrors rise!
A naked lover bound and bleeding lies!
Where, where was Eloise? her voice, her hand,
Her poniard had opposed the dire command.
Barbarian, stay! that bloody stroke restrain;
The crime was common, common be the pain.
I can no more; by shame, by rage suppress’d,
Let tears and burning blushes speak the rest.
  Canst thou forget that sad, that solemn day,
When victims at yon altar’s foot we lay?
Canst thou forget what tears that moment fell,
When, warm in youth, I bade the world farewell?
As with cold lips I kiss’d the sacred veil,
The shrines all trembled, and the lamps grew pale:
Heav’n scarce believ’d the conquest it survey’d,
And saints with wonder heard the vows I made.
Yet then, to those dread altars as I drew,
Not on the cross my eyes were fix’d, but you:
Not grace, or zeal, love only was my call,
And if I lose thy love, I lose my all.
Come! with thy looks, thy words, relieve my woe;
Those still at least are left thee to bestow.
Still on that breast enamour’d let me lie,
Still drink delicious poison from thy eye,
Pant on thy lip, and to thy heart be press’d;
Give all thou canst—and let me dream the rest.
Ah, no! instruct me other joys to prize,
With other beauties charm my partial eyes!
Full in my view set all the bright abode,
And make my soul quit Abelard for God.
  Ah, think at least thy flock deserves thy care,
Plants of thy hand, and children of thy prayer.
From the false world in early youth they fled,
By thee to mountains, wilds, and deserts led.
You raised these hallow’d walls; the desert smil’d,
And Paradise was open’d in the wild.
No weeping orphan saw his father’s stores
Our shrines irradiate or emblaze the floors;
No silver saints, by dying misers giv’n,
Here bribed the rage of ill-requited Heav’n;
But such plain roofs as piety could raise,
And only vocal with the Maker’s praise.
In these lone walls (their day’s eternal bound),
These moss-grown domes with spiry turrets crown’d,
Where awful arches make a noonday night,
And the dim windows shed a solemn light,
Thy eyes diffused a reconciling ray,
And gleams of glory brighten’d all the day.
But now no face divine contentment wears,
’T is all blank sadness, or continual tears.
See how the force of others’ prayers I try,
(O pious fraud of am’rous charity!)
But why should I on others’ prayers depend?
Come thou, my father, brother, husband, friend!
Ah, let thy handmaid, sister, daughter, move,
And all those tender names in one, thy love!
The darksome pines, that o’er yon rocks reclin’d,
Wave high, and murmur to the hollow wind,
The wand’ring streams that shine between the hills,
The grots that echo to the tinkling rills,
The dying gales that pant upon the trees,
The lakes that quiver to the curling breeze—
No more these scenes my meditation aid,
Or lull to rest the visionary maid:
But o’er the twilight groves and dusky caves,
Long-sounding aisles and intermingled graves,
Black Melancholy sits, and round her throws
A death-like silence, and a dread repose:
Her gloomy presence saddens all the scene,
Shades every flower, and darkens every green,
Deepens the murmur of the falling floods,
And breathes a browner horror on the woods.
  Yet here for ever, ever must I stay;
Sad proof how well a lover can obey!
Death, only Death can break the lasting chain;
And here, ev’n then shall my cold dust remain;
Here all its frailties, all its flames resign,
And wait till ’t is no sin to mix with thine.
  Ah, wretch! believ’d the spouse of God in vain,
Confess’d within the slave of Love and man.
Assist me, Heav’n! but whence arose that prayer?
Sprung it from piety or from despair?
Ev’n here, where frozen Chastity retires,
Love finds an altar for forbidden fires.
I ought to grieve, but cannot what I ought;
I mourn the lover, not lament the fault;
I view my crime, but kindle at the view,
Repent old pleasures, and solicit new;
Now turn’d to Heav’n, I weep my past offence,
Now think of thee, and curse my innocence.
Of all affliction taught a lover yet,
’T is sure the hardest science to forget!
How shall I lose the sin, yet keep the sense,
And love th’ offender, yet detest th’ offence?
How the dear object from the crime remove,
Or how distinguish Penitence from Love?
Unequal task! a passion to resign,
For hearts so touch’d, so pierced, so lost as mine:
Ere such a soul regains its peaceful state,
How often must it love, how often hate!
How often hope, despair, resent, regret,
Conceal, disdain—do all things but forget!
But let Heav’n seize it, all at once ’t is fired;
Not touch’d, but rapt; not waken’d, but inspired!
O come! O teach me Nature to subdue,
Renounce my love, my life, myself—and You:
Fill my fond heart with God alone, for he
Alone can rival, can succeed to thee.
  How happy is the blameless vestal’s lot!
The world forgetting, by the world forgot;
Eternal sunshine of the spotless mind,
Each prayer accepted, and each wish resign’d;
Labour and rest, that equal periods keep;
Obedient slumbers that can wake and weep;
Desires composed, affections ever ev’n;
Tears that delight, and sighs that waft to Heav’n.
Grace shines around her with serenest beams,
And whisp’ring angels prompt her golden dreams.
For her th’ unfading rose of Eden blooms,
And wings of seraphs shed divine perfumes;
For her the spouse prepares the bridal ring;
For her white virgins hymeneals sing;
To sounds of heav’nly harps she dies away,
And melts in visions of eternal day.
  Far other dreams my erring soul employ,
Far other raptures of unholy joy.
When at the close of each sad, sorrowing day,
Fancy restores what vengeance snatch’d away,
Then conscience sleeps, and leaving Nature free,
All my loose soul unbounded springs to thee!
Oh curst, dear horrors of all-conscious night!
How glowing guilt exalts the keen delight!
Provoking demons all restraint remove,
And stir within me every source of love.
I hear thee, view thee, gaze o’er all thy charms,
And round thy phantom glue my clasping arms.
I wake:—no more I hear, no more I view,
The phantom flies me, as unkind as you.
I call aloud; it hears not what I say:
I stretch my empty arms; it glides away.
To dream once more I close my willing eyes;
Ye soft illusions, dear deceits, arise!
Alas, no more! methinks we wand’ring go
Thro’ dreary wastes, and weep each other’s woe,
Where round some mould’ring tower pale ivy creeps,
And low-brow’d rocks hang nodding o’er the deeps.
Sudden you mount, you beckon from the skies;
Clouds interpose, waves roar, and winds arise.
I shriek, start up, the same sad prospect find,
And wake to all the griefs I left behind.
  For thee the Fates, severely kind, ordain
A cool suspense from pleasure and from pain;
Thy life a long dead calm of fix’d repose;
No pulse that riots, and no blood that glows.
Still as the sea, ere winds were taught to blow,
Or moving spirit bade the waters flow;
Soft as the slumbers of a saint forgiv’n,
And mild as opening gleams of promised Heav’n.
  Come, Abelard! for what hast thou to dread?
The torch of Venus burns not for the dead.
Nature stands check’d; Religion disapproves;
Ev’n thou art cold—yet Eloisa loves.
Ah, hopeless, lasting flames; like those that burn
To light the dead, and warm th’ unfruitful urn!
  What scenes appear where’er I turn my view;
The dear ideas, where I fly, pursue;
Rise in the grove, before the altar rise,
Stain all my soul, and wanton in my eyes.
I waste the matin lamp in sighs for thee,
Thy image steals between my God and me:
Thy voice I seem in every hymn to hear,
With every bead I drop too soft a tear.
When from the censer clouds of fragrance roll,
And swelling organs lift the rising soul,
One thought of thee puts all the pomp to flight,
Priests, tapers, temples, swim before my sight:
In seas of flame my plunging soul is drown’d,
While altars blaze, and angels tremble round.
  While prostrate here in humble grief I lie,
Kind virtuous drops just gath’ring in my eye,
While praying, trembling, in the dust I roll,
And dawning grace is opening on my soul:
Come, if thou dar’st, all charming as thou art!
Oppose thyself to Heav’n; dispute my heart;
Come, with one glance of those deluding eyes
Blot out each bright idea of the skies;
Take back that grace, those sorrows and those tears,
Take back my fruitless penitence and prayers;
Snatch me, just mounting, from the blest abode:
Assist the fiends, and tear me from my God!
No, fly me, fly me, far as pole from pole;
Rise Alps between us! and whole oceans roll!
Ah, come not, write not, think not once of me,
Nor share one pang of all I felt for thee.
Thy oaths I quit, thy memory resign;
Forget, renounce me, hate whate’er was mine.
Fair eyes, and tempting looks (which yet I view),
Long lov’d, ador’d ideas, all adieu!
O Grace serene! O Virtue heav’nly fair!
Divine Oblivion of low-thoughted care!
Fresh blooming Hope, gay daughter of the sky!
And Faith, our early immortality!
Enter each mild, each amicable guest;
Receive, and wrap me in eternal rest!
  See in her cell sad Eloisa spread,
Propt on some tomb, a neighbour of the dead.
In each low wind methinks a spirit calls,
And more than echoes talk along the walls.
Here, as I watch’d the dying lamps around,
From yonder shrine I heard a hollow sound:
‘Come, sister, come! (it said, or seem’d to say)
Thy place is here, sad sister, come away;
Once, like thyself, I trembled, wept, and pray’d,
Love’s victim then, tho’ now a sainted maid:
But all is calm in this eternal sleep;
Here grief forgets to groan, and love to weep;
Ev’n superstition loses ev’ry fear:
For God, not man, absolves our frailties here.’
  I come, I come! prepare your roseate bowers,
Celestial palms, and ever-blooming flowers.
Thither, where sinners may have rest, I go,
Where flames refin’d in breasts seraphic glow;
Thou, Abelard! the last sad office pay,
And smooth my passage to the realms of day:
See my lips tremble, and my eyeballs roll,
Suck my last breath, and catch my flying soul!
Ah, no—in sacred vestments mayst thou stand,
The hallow’d taper trembling in thy hand,
Present the cross before my lifted eye,
Teach me at once, and learn of me, to die.
Ah then, thy once lov’d Eloisa see!
It will be then no crime to gaze on me.
See from my cheek the transient roses fly!
See the last sparkle languish in my eye!
Till ev’ry motion, pulse, and breath be o’er,
And ev’n my Abelard be lov’d no more.
O Death, all-eloquent! you only prove
What dust we doat on, when ’t is man we love.
  Then too, when Fate shall thy fair frame destroy
(That cause of all my guilt, and all my joy),
In trance ecstatic may thy pangs be drown’d,
Bright clouds descend, and angels watch thee round;
From opening skies may streaming glories shine,
And saints embrace thee with a love like mine.
  May one kind grave unite each hapless name,
And graft my love immortal on thy fame!
Then, ages hence, when all my woes are o’er,
When this rebellious heart shall beat no more;
If ever chance two wand’ring lovers brings,
To Paraclete’s white walls and silver springs,
O’er the pale marble shall they join their heads,
And drink the falling tears each other sheds;
Then sadly say, with mutual pity mov’d,
‘O may we never love as these have lov’d!’
From the full choir, when loud hosannas rise,
And swell the pomp of dreadful sacrifice,
Amid that scene if some relenting eye
Glance on the stone where our cold relics lie,
Devotion’s self shall steal a thought from Heav’n,
One human tear shall drop, and be forgiv’n.
And sure if Fate some future bard shall join
In sad similitude of griefs to mine,
Condemn’d whole years in absence to deplore,
And image charms he must behold no more,—
Such if there be, who loves so long, so well,
Let him our sad, our tender story tell;
The well-sung woes will soothe my pensive ghost;
He best can paint them who shall feel them most.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="pope2020052105">
<head>
    <title>Epistle to Dr. Arbuthnot</title>
    <subtitle>Being the Prologue to the Satires</subtitle>
    <firstline>Shut, shut the door, good John!’ fatigued, I said</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<prose>
<center><sc>Advertisement</sc></center>

This paper is a sort of bill of complaint, begun many years since, and drawn up by snatches, as the several occasions offered. I had no thoughts of publishing it, till it pleased some Persons of Rank and Fortune (the authors of ‘Verses to the Imitator of Horace,’ and of an ‘Epistle to a Doctor of Divinity from a Nobleman at Hampton Court’) to attack, in a very extraordinary manner, not only my Writings (of which, being public, the Public is judge), but my Person, Morals, and Family; whereof, to those who know me not, a truer information may be requisite. Being divided between the necessity to say something of myself, and my own laziness to undertake so awkward a task, I thought it the shortest way to put the last hand to this epistle. If it have any thing pleasing, it will be that by which I am most desirous to please, the Truth and the Sentiment; and if any thing offensive, it will be only to those I am least sorry to offend, the vicious or the ungenerous.
  Many will know their own pictures in it, there being not a circumstance but what is true; but I have, for the most part, spared their names, and they may escape being laughed at if they please.
  I would have some of them know it was owing to the request of the learned and candid Friend to whom it is inscribed, that I make not as free use of theirs as they have done of mine. However, I shall have this advantage and honour on my side, that whereas, by their proceeding, any abuse may be directed at any man, no injury can possibly be done by mine, since a nameless character can never be found out but by its truth and likeness.
</prose>
<poetry>
<i>P.</i>  <sc>‘Shut</sc>, shut the door, good John!’ fatigued, I said;
‘Tie up the knocker, say I ’m sick, I ’m dead.’
The Dog-star rages! nay, ’t is past a doubt
All Bedlam or Parnassus is let out:
Fire in each eye, and papers in each hand,
They rave, recite, and madden round the land.
  What walls can guard me, or what shades can hide?
They pierce my thickets, thro’ my grot they glide,
By land, by water, they renew the charge,
They stop the chariot, and they board the barge.
No place is sacred, not the church is free,
Ev’n Sunday shines no Sabbath-day to me:
Then from the Mint walks forth the man of rhyme,
Happy to catch me just at dinner time.
  Is there a Parson much bemused in beer,
A maudlin Poetess, a rhyming Peer,
A clerk foredoom’d his father’s soul to cross,
Who pens a stanza when he should engross?
Is there who, lock’d from ink and paper, scrawls
With desp’rate charcoal round his darken’d walls?
All fly to TWIT’NAM, and in humble strain
Apply to me to keep them mad or vain,
Arthur, whose giddy son neglects the laws,
Imputes to me and my damn’d works the cause:
Poor Cornus sees his frantic wife elope,
And curses Wit and Poetry, and Pope.
  Friend to my life (which did not you prolong,
The world had wanted many an idle song)!
What Drop or Nostrum can this plague remove?
Or which must end me, a fool’s wrath or love?
A dire dilemma! either way I ’m sped;
If foes, they write, if friends, they read me dead.
Seiz’d and tied down to judge, how wretched I!
Who can’t be silent, and who will not lie.
To laugh were want of goodness and of grace,
And to be grave exceeds all power of face.
I sit with sad civility, I read
With honest anguish and an aching head,
And drop at last, but in unwilling ears,
This saving counsel, ‘Keep your piece nine years.’
  ‘Nine years!’ cries he, who, high in Drury lane,
Lull’d by soft zephyrs thro’ the broken pane,
Rhymes ere he wakes, and prints before Term ends,
Obliged by hunger and request of friends:
‘The piece, you think, is incorrect? why, take it!
I ’m all submission: what you ’d have it—make it.’
  Three things another’s modest wishes bound,
‘My friendship, and a Prologue, and ten pound.’
  Pitholeon sends to me: “You know his Grace,
I want a patron; ask him for a place.’
Pitholeon libell’d me—‘But here ’s a letter
Informs you, Sir, ’t was when he knew no better.
Dare you refuse him? Curll invites to dine,
He ’ll write a Journal, or he ’ll turn Divine.’
Bless me! a packet.—’T is a stranger sues,
A Virgin Tragedy, an Orphan Muse.
If I dislike it, ‘Furies, death, and rage!’
If I approve, ‘Commend it to the stage.’
There (thank my stars) my whole commission ends,
The players and I are, luckily, no friends.
Fired that the house rejects him, ‘’Sdeath, I ’ll print it,
And shame the fools—your int’rest, Sir, with Lintot.’
Lintot, dull rogue, will think your price too much:
‘Not, Sir, if you revise it, and retouch.’
All my demurs but double his attacks;
At last he whispers, ‘Do, and we go snacks.’
Glad of a quarrel, straight I clap the door;
‘Sir, let me see your works and you no more.’
  ’T is sung, when Midas’ ears began to spring
(Midas, a sacred person and a king),
His very Minister who spied them first
(Some say his Queen) was fore’d to speak or burst.
And is not mine, my friend, a sorer case,
When ev’ry coxcomb perks them in my face?
  <i>A.</i>  Good friend, forbear! you deal in dangerous things;
I ’d never name Queens, Ministers, or Kings;
Keep close to ears, and those let asses prick,
’T is nothing—  <i>P.</i>  Nothing! if they bite and kick?
Out with it, DUNCIAD! let the secret pass,
That secret to each fool, that he ’s an ass:
The truth once told (and wherefore should we lie?)
The Queen of Midas slept, and so may I.
  You think this cruel? take it for a rule,
No creature smarts so little as a fool.
Let peals of laughter, Codrus! round thee break,
Thou unconcern’d canst hear the mighty crack:
Pit, Box, and Gall’ry in convulsions hurl’d,
Thou stand’st unshook amidst a bursting world.
Who shames a Scribbler? break one cobweb thro’,
He spins the slight self-pleasing thread anew:
Destroy his fib, or sophistry—in vain!
The creature’s at his dirty work again,
Throned in the centre of his thin designs,
Proud of a vast extent of flimsy lines.
Whom have I hurt? has Poet yet or Peer
Lost the arch’d eyebrow or Parnassian sneer?
And has not Colley still his lord and whore?
His butchers Henley? his freemasons Moore?
Does not one table Bavius still admit?
Still to one Bishop Philips seem a wit?
Still Sappho—  <i>A.</i>  Hold! for God’s sake—you ’ll offend.
No names—be calm—learn prudence of a friend.
I too could write, and I am twice as tall;
But foes like these—  <i>P.</i>  One flatt’rer’s worse than all.
Of all mad creatures, if the learn’d are right,
It is the slaver kills, and not the bite.
A fool quite angry is quite innocent:
Alas! ’t is ten times worse when they repent.
  One dedicates in high heroic prose,
And ridicules beyond a hundred foes;
One from all Grub-street will my fame defend,
And, more abusive, calls himself my friend:
This prints my Letters, that expects a bribe,
And others roar aloud, ‘Subscribe, subscribe!’
  There are who to my person pay their court:
I cough like Horace; and tho’ lean, am short;
Ammon’s great son one shoulder had too high,
Such Ovid’s nose, and ‘Sir! you have an eye—’
Go on, obliging creatures! make me see
All that disgraced my betters met in me.
Say, for my comfort, languishing in bed,
‘Just so immortal Maro held his head:’
And when I die, be sure you let me know
Great Homer died three thousand years ago.
  Why did I write? what sin to me unknown
Dipp’d me in ink, my parents’, or my own?
As yet a child, nor yet a fool to fame,
I lisp’d in numbers, for the numbers came:
I left no calling for this idle trade,
No duty broke, no father disobey’d:
The Muse but serv’d to ease some friend, not wife,
To help me thro’ this long disease my life,
To second, ARBUTHNOT! thy art and care,
And teach the being you preserv’d, to bear.
  <i>A.</i>  But why then publish?  <i>P.</i>  Granville the polite,
And knowing Walsh, would tell me I could write;
Well-natured Garth inflamed with early praise,
And Congreve lov’d, and Swift endured my lays;
The courtly Talbot, Somers, Sheffield, read;
Ev’n mitred Rochester would nod the head,
And St. John’s self (great Dryden’s friends before)
With open arms receiv’d one poet more.
Happy my studies, when by these approv’d!
Happier their author, when by these belov’d!
From these the world will judge of men and books,
Not from the Burnets, Oldmixons, and Cookes.
  Soft were my numbers; who could take offence
While pure description held the place of sense?
Like gentle Fanny’s was my flowery theme,
‘A painted mistress, or a purling stream.’
Yet then did Gildon draw his venal quill;
I wish’d the man a dinner, and sat still:
Yet then did Dennis rave in furious fret;
I never answer’d; I was not in debt.
If want provoked, or madness made them print,
I waged no war with Bedlam or the Mint.
  Did some more sober critic come abroad;
If wrong, I smiled, if right, I kiss’d the rod.
Pains, reading, study, are their just pretence,
And all they want is spirit, taste, and sense.
Commas and points they set exactly right,
And ’t were a sin to rob them of their mite.
Yet ne’er one sprig of laurel graced these ribalds,
From slashing Bentleys down to piddling Tibbalds.
Each wight who reads not, and but scans and spells,
Each word-catcher that lives on syllables,
Ev’n such small critics some regard may claim,
Preserv’d in Milton’s or in Shakspeare’s name.
Pretty! in amber to observe the forms
Of hairs, or straws, or dirt, or grubs, or worms!
The things, we know, are neither rich nor rare,
But wonder how the devil they got there.
  Were others angry: I excused them too;
Well might they rage, I gave them but their due.
A man’s true merit ’t is not hard to find;
But each man’s secret standard in his mind,
That casting-weight Pride adds to emptiness,
This, who can gratify? for who can guess?
The bard whom pilfer’d pastorals renown,
Who turns a Persian tale for half-a-crown,
Just writes to make his barrenness appear,
And strains from hard-bound brains eight lines a year;
He who still wanting, tho’ he lives on theft,
Steals much, spends little, yet has nothing left;
And he who now to sense, now nonsense, leaning,
Means not, but blunders round about a meaning:
And he whose fustian’s so sublimely bad,
It is not poetry, but prose run mad:
All these my modest satire bade translate,
And own’d that nine such poets made a Tate.
How did they fume, and stamp, and roar, and chafe!
And swear not ADDISON himself was safe.
  Peace to all such! but were there one whose fires
True Genius kindles, and fair Fame inspires,
Bless’d with each talent and each art to please,
And born to write, converse, and live with ease;
Should such a man, too fond to rule alone,
Bear, like the Turk, no brother near the throne;
View him with scornful, yet with jealous eyes,
And hate for arts that caus’d himself to rise;
Damn with faint praise, assent with civil leer,
And without sneering teach the rest to sneer;
Willing to wound, and yet afraid to strike,
Just hint a fault, and hesitate dislike;
Alike reserv’d to blame or to commend,
A tim’rous foe, and a suspicious friend;
Dreading ev’n fools; by flatterers besieged,
And so obliging that he ne’er obliged;
Like Cato, give his little Senate laws,
And sit attentive to his own applause:
While Wits and Templars ev’ry sentence raise,
And wonder with a foolish face of praise—
Who but must laugh if such a man there be?
Who would not weep, if Atticus were he?
  What tho’ my name stood rubric on the walls,
Or plaster’d posts, with claps, in capitals?
Or smoking forth, a hundred hawkers load,
On wings of winds came flying all abroad?
I sought no homage from the race that write;
I kept, like Asian Monarchs, from their sight:
Poems I heeded (now berhymed so long)
No more than thou, great George! a birthday song.
I ne’er with Wits or Witlings pass’d my days
To spread about the itch of verse and praise;
Nor like a puppy daggled thro’ the town
To fetch and carry sing-song up and down;
Nor at rehearsals sweat, and mouth’d, and cried,
With handkerchief and orange at my side;
But sick of fops, and poetry, and prate,
To Bufo left the whole Castalian state.
  Proud as Apollo on his forked hill
Sat full-blown Bufo, puff’d by ev’ry quill:
Fed with soft dedication all day long,
Horace and he went hand in hand in song.
His library (where busts of poets dead,
And a true Pindar stood without a head)
Receiv’d of Wits an undistinguish’d race,
Who first his judgment ask’d, and then a place:
Much they extoll’d his pictures, much his seat,
And flatter’d ev’ry day, and some days eat:
Till grown more frugal in his riper days,
He paid some bards with port, and some with praise;
To some a dry rehearsal was assign’d,
And others (harder still) he paid in kind.
Dryden alone (what wonder?) came not nigh;
Dryden alone escaped this judging eye:
But still the great have kindness in reserve;
He help’d to bury whom he help’d to starve.
May some choice patron bless each gray goose quill!
May every Bavius have his Bufo still!
So when a statesman wants a day’s defence,
Or Envy holds a whole week’s war with Sense,
Or simple Pride for flatt’ry makes demands,
May dunce by dunce be whistled off my hands!
Bless’d be the great! for those they take away,
And those they left me—for they left me Gay;
Left me to see neglected Genius bloom,
Neglected die, and tell it on his tomb:
Of all thy blameless life the sole return
My Verse, and Queensb’ry weeping o’er thy urn!
  Oh let me live my own, and die so too
(To live and die is all I have to do)!
Maintain a poet’s dignity and ease,
And see what friends, and read what books I please;
Above a Patron, tho’ I condescend
Sometimes to call a minister my Friend.
I was not born for courts or great affairs;
I pay my debts, believe, and say my prayers;
Can sleep without a poem in my head,
Nor know if Dennis be alive or dead.
  Why am I ask’d what next shall see the light?
Heav’ns! was I born for nothing but to write?
Has life no joys for me? or (to be grave)
Have I no friend to serve, no soul to save?
‘I found him close with Swift’—‘Indeed? no doubt
(Cries prating Balbus) something will come out.’
’T is all in vain, deny it as I will;
‘No, such a genius never can lie still:’
And then for mine obligingly mistakes
The first lampoon Sir Will or Bubo makes.
Poor guiltless I! and can I choose but smile,
When ev’ry coxcomb knows me by my style?
  Curst be the verse, how well soe’er it flow,
That tends to make one worthy man my foe,
Give Virtue scandal, Innocence a fear,
Or from the soft-eyed virgin steal a tear!
But he who hurts a harmless neighbour’s peace,
Insults fall’n Worth, or Beauty in distress,
Who loves a lie, lame Slander helps about,
Who writes a libel, or who copies out;
That fop whose pride affects a patron’s name,
Yet absent, wounds an author’s honest fame;
Who can your merit selfishly approve,
And show the sense of it without the love;
Who has the vanity to call you friend,
Yet wants the honour, injured, to defend;
Who tells whate’er you think, whate’er you say,
And, if he lie not, must at least betray;
Who to the Dean and Silver Bell can swear,
And sees at Canons what was never there;
Who reads but with a lust to misapply,
Make satire a lampoon, and fiction lie:
A lash like mine no honest man shall dread,
But all such babbling blockheads in his stead.
  Let Sporus tremble—  <i>A.</i>  What? that thing of silk,
Sporus, that mere white curd of Ass’s milk?
Satire or sense, alas! can Sporus feel?
Who breaks a butterfly upon a wheel?
  <i>P.</i>  Yet let me flap this bug with gilded wings,
This painted child of dirt, that stinks and stings;
Whose buzz the witty and the fair annoys,
Yet Wit ne’er tastes, and Beauty ne’er enjoys;
So well-bred spaniels civilly delight
In mumbling of the game they dare not bite.
Eternal smiles his emptiness betray,
As shallow streams run dimpling all the way,
Whether in florid impotence he speaks,
And, as the prompter breathes, the puppet squeaks,
Or at the ear of Eve, familiar toad,
Half froth, half venom, spits himself abroad,
In puns, or politics, or tales, or lies,
Or spite, or smut, or rhymes, or blasphemies;
His wit all see-saw between that and this,
Now high, now low, now master up, now miss,
And he himself one vile Antithesis.
Amphibious thing! that acting either part,
The trifling head, or the corrupted heart;
Fop at the toilet, flatt’rer at the board,
Now trips a lady, and now struts a lord.
Eve’s tempter thus the Rabbins have exprest,
A cherub’s face, a reptile all the rest;
Beauty that shocks you, Parts that none will trust,
Wit that can creep, and Pride that licks the dust.
  Not Fortune’s worshipper, nor Fashion’s fool,
Not Lucre’s madman, nor Ambition’s tool,
Not proud nor servile;—be one poet’s praise,
That if he pleas’d, he pleas’d by manly ways:
That flatt’ry ev’n to Kings, he held a shame,
And thought a lie in verse or prose the same;
That not in fancy’s maze he wander’d long,
But stoop’d to truth, and moralized his song;
That not for Fame, but Virtue’s better end,
He stood the furious foe, the timid friend,
The damning critic, half approving wit,
The coxcomb hit, or fearing to be hit;
Laugh’d at the loss of friends he never had,
The dull, the proud, the wicked, and the mad;
The distant threats of vengeance on his head,
The blow unfelt, the tear he never shed;
The tale revived, the lie so oft o’erthrown,
Th’ imputed trash and dulness not his own;
The morals blacken’d when the writings ’scape,
The libell’d person, and the pictured shape;
Abuse on all he lov’d, or lov’d him, spread,
A friend in exile, or a father dead;
The whisper, that, to greatness still too near,
Perhaps yet vibrates on his SOV’REIGN’S ear—
Welcome for thee, fair Virtue! all the past:
For thee, fair Virtue! welcome ev’n the last!
  <i>A.</i>  But why insult the poor? affront the great?
  <i>P.</i>  A knave ’s a knave to me in ev’ry state;
Alike my scorn, if he succeed or fail,
Sporus at court, or Japhet in a jail;
A hireling scribbler, or a hireling peer,
Knight of the post corrupt, or of the shire;
If on a Pillory, or near a Throne,
He gain his prince’s ear, or lose his own.
  Yet soft by nature, more a dupe than wit,
Sappho can tell you how this man was bit:
This dreaded Satirist Dennis will confess
Foe to his pride, but friend to his distress:
So humble, he has knock’d at Tibbald’s door,
Has drunk with Cibber, nay, has rhymed for Moore.
Full ten years slander’d, did he once reply?
Three thousand suns went down on Welsted’s lie.
To please a mistress one aspers’d his life;
He lash’d him not, but let her be his wife:
Let Budgell charge low Grub-street on his quill,
And write whate’er he pleased, except his will;
Let the two Curlls of town and court abuse
His father, mother, body, soul, and muse:
Yet why? that father held it for a rule,
It was a sin to call our neighbour fool;
That harmless mother thought no wife a whore:
Hear this, and spare his family, James Moore!
Unspotted names, and memorable long,
If there be force in Virtue, or in Song.
  Of gentle blood (part shed in honour’s cause,
While yet in Britain honour had applause)
Each parent sprung—  <i>A.</i>  What fortune, pray?—
  <i>P.</i>            Their own;
And better got than Bestia’s from the throne.
Born to no pride, inheriting no strife,
Nor marrying discord in a noble wife,
Stranger to civil and religious rage,
The good man walk’d innoxious thro’ his age.
No courts he saw, no suits would ever try,
Nor dared an oath, nor hazarded a lie.
Unlearn’d, he knew no schoolman’s subtle art,
No language but the language of the heart.
By Nature honest, by Experience wise,
Healthy by Temp’rance and by Exercise;
His life, tho’ long, to sickness pass’d unknown,
His death was instant and without a groan.
O grant me thus to live, and thus to die!
Who sprung from kings shall know less joy than I.
  O friend! may each domestic bliss be thine!
Be no unpleasing melancholy mine:
Me, let the tender office long engage
To rock the cradle of reposing Age,
With lenient arts extend a Mother’s breath,
Make Languor smile, and smooth the bed of Death;
Explore the thought, explain the asking eye,
And keep a while one parent from the sky!
On cares like these if length of days attend,
May Heav’n, to bless those days, preserve my friend!
Preserve him social, cheerful, and serene,
And just as rich as when he serv’d a Queen.
  <i>A.</i>  Whether that blessing be denied or giv’n,
Thus far was right;—the rest belongs to Heav’n.
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
