<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="longfellow" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="longfellow2001081801">
<head>
   <title>King Christian</title>
   <subtitle>A national song of Denmark</subtitle>
   <toctitle>King Christian</toctitle>
   <indextitle>King Christian</indextitle>
   <firstline>King Christian stood by the lofty mast</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Oversættelse af Ewalds <xref type="translation" poem="ewlad1999022205"/>.</note>
   </notes>
</head>
<body>
King Christian stood by the lofty mast
   In mist and smoke;
His sword was hammering so fast,
Through Gothic helm and brain it passed;
Then sank each hostile hulk and mast,
   In mist and smoke.
"Fly!" shouted they, "fly, he who can!
Who braves of Denmark's Christian
   The stroke?"

Nils Juel gave heed to the tempest's roar,
   Now is the hour!
He hoisted his blood-red flag once more,
And smote upon the foe full sore,
And shouted Loud, through the tempest's roar,
   "Now is the hour!"
"Fly!" shouted they, "for shelter fly!
Of Denmark's Juel who can defy
   The power?"

North Sea! a glimpse of Wessel rent
   Thy murky sky!
Then champions to thine arms were sent;
Terror and Death glared where he went;
From the waves was heard a wail, that
    rent
   Thy murky sky!
From Denmark, thunders Tordenskiol',
Let each to Heaven commend his soul,
    And fly!

Path of the Dane to fame and might!
   Dark-rolling wave!
Receive thy friend, who, scorning flight
Goes to meet danger with despite,
Proudly as thou the tempest's might
   Dark-rolling wave!
And amid pleasures and alarms;
And war and victory, be thine arms
   My grave!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="longfellow2018042301">
<head>
   <title>Childhood</title>
   <firstline>There was a time when I was very small</firstline>
   <notes>
      <note>Oversættelse af Baggesens <xref type="translation" poem="baggesen2001082701"/>.</note>
   </notes>
</head>
<body>
There was a time when I was very small,
  When my whole frame was but an ell in height;
Sweetly, as I recall it, tears do fall,
  And therefore I recall it with delight.

I sported in my tender mother's arms,
  And rode a-horseback on best father's knee;
Alike were sorrows, passions and alarms,
  And gold, and Greek, and love, unknown to me,

Then seemed to me this world far less in size,
  Likewise it seemed to me less wicked far;
Like points in heaven, I saw the stars arise,
  And longed for wings that I might catch a star.

I saw the moon behind the island fade,
  And thought, "Oh, were I on that island there,
I could find out of what the moon is made,
  Find out how large it is, how round, how fair!"

Wondering, I saw God's sun, through western skies,
  Sink in the ocean's golden lap at night,
And yet upon the morrow early rise,
  And paint the eastern heaven with crimson light;

And thought of God, the gracious Heavenly Father,
  Who made me, and that lovely sun on high,
And all those pearls of heaven thick-strung together,
  Dropped, clustering, from his hand o'er all the sky.

With childish reverence, my young lips did say
  The prayer my pious mother taught to me:
"O gentle God! oh, let me strive alway
  Still to be wise, and good, and follow Thee!"

So prayed I for my father and my mother,
  And for my sister, and for all the town;
The king I knew not, and the beggar-brother,
  Who, bent with age, went, sighing, up and down.

They perished, the blithe days of boyhood perished,
  And all the gladness, all the peace I knew!
Now have I but their memory, fondly cherished;--
  God! may I never lose that too!
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
