<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<kalliopework id="andre" author="campbell" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<text id="campbell2019090801">
<head>
   <title>The Soldier's Dream</title>
   <firstline>Our bugles sang truce—for the night-cloud had lowered</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Our bugles sang truce—for the night-cloud had lowered,
  And the sentinel stars set their watch in the sky;
And thousands had sunk on the ground overpowered,
  The weary to sleep, and the wounded to die.

When reposing that night on my pallet of straw,
  By the wolf-scaring faggot that guarded the slain,
At the dead of the night a sweet vision I saw,
  And thrice ere the morning I dreamt it again.

Methought from the battle-field’s dreadful array,
  Far, far I had roamed on a desolate track:
’Twas Autumn,—and sunshine arose on the way
  To the home of my fathers, that welcomed me back.

I flew to the pleasant fields traversed so oft
  In life’s morning march, when my bosom was young
I heard my own mountain-goats bleating aloft,
  And knew the sweet strain that the corn-reapers sung.

Then pledged we the wine-cup, and fondly I swore,
  From my home and my weeping friends never to part
My little ones kissed me a thousand times o’er,
  And my wife sobbed aloud in her fulness of heart,

Stay, stay with us,—rest, thou art weary and worn;
  And fain was their war-broken soldier to stay;—
But sorrow returned with the dawning of morn,
  And the voice in my dreaming ear melted away.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="campbell2019090802">
<head>
    <title>Gilderoy</title>
    <firstline>The last, the fatal hour is come</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
The last, the fatal hour is come,
  That bears my love from me;
I hear the dead note of the drum,
  I mark the gallows’ tree!

The bell has tolled; it shakes my heart;
  The trumpet speaks thy name;
And must my Gilderoy depart
  To bear a death of shame?

No bosom trembles for thy doom;
  No mourner wipes a tear;
The gallows’ foot is all thy tomb,
  The sledge is all thy bier.

Oh, Gilderoy! bethought we then
  So soon, so sad to part,
When first in Roslin’s lovely glen
  You triumphed o’er my heart?

Your locks they glittered to the sheen,
  Your hunter garb was trim;
And graceful was the ribbon green
  That bound your manly limb!

Ah! little thought I to deplore
  Those limbs in fetters bound;
Or hear, upon the scaffold floor,
  The midnight hammer sound.

Ye cruel, cruel, that combined
  The guiltless to pursue;
My Gilderoy was ever kind,
  He could not injure you!

A long adieu! but where shall fly
  Thy widow all forlorn,
When every mean and cruel eye
  Regards my woe with scorn?

Yes! they will mock thy widow’s tears,
  And hate thine orphan boy;
Alas! his infant beauty wears
  The form of Gilderoy.

Then will I seek the dreary mound
  That wraps thy mouldering clay,
And weep and linger on the ground,
  And sigh my heart away.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="campbell2019090803">
<head>
    <title>The Harper</title>
    <firstline>On the green banks of Shannon, when Sheelah was nigh</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
On the green banks of Shannon, when Sheelah was nigh,
No blithe Irish lad was so happy as I;
No harp like my own could so cheerily play,
And wherever I went was my poor dog Tray.

When at last I was forced from my Sheelah to part,
She said (while the sorrow was big at her heart),
“Oh! remember your Sheelah when far, far away;
And be kind, my dear Pat, to our poor dog Tray.”

Poor dog! he was faithful and kind, to be sure,
And he constantly loved me, although I was poor;
When the sour-looking folks sent me heartless away,
I had always a friend in my poor dog Tray.

When the road was so dark, and the night was so cold,
And Pat and his dog were grown weary and old,
How snugly we slept in my old coat of grey,
And he licked me for kindness—my poor dog Tray.

Though my wallet was scant, I remembered his case,
Nor refused my last crust to his pitiful face;
But he died at my feet on a cold winter day,
And I played a sad lament for my poor dog Tray.

Where now shall I go, poor, forsaken, and blind
Can I find one to guide me, so faithful, and kind;
To my sweet native village, so far, far away,
I can never more return with my poor dog Tray.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="campbell2019090804">
<head>
    <title>Lines Written on Visiting a Scene in Argyleshire</title>
    <firstline>At the silence of twilight’s contemplative hour</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
At the silence of twilight’s contemplative hour,
  I have mused in a sorrowful mood,
On the wind-shaken weeds that embosom the bower,
  Where the home of my forefathers stood.
All ruined and wild is their roofless abode,
  And lonely the dark raven’s sheltering tree:
And travelled by few is the grass-covered road,
Where the hunter of deer and the warrior trode
  To his hills that encircle the sea.

Yet wandering, I found on my ruinous walk,
  By the dial-stone agèd and green,
One rose of the wilderness left on its stalk,
  To mark where a garden had been
Like a brotherless hermit, the last of its race,
  All wild in the silence of nature, it drew,
From each wandering sun-beam, a lonely embrace,
For the night-weed and thorn overshadowed the place,
  Where the flower of my forefathers grew.

Sweet bud of the wilderness! emblem of all
  That remains in this desolate heart!
The fabric of bliss to its centre may fall,
  But patience shall never depart!
Though the wilds of enchantment, all vernal and bright,
  In the days of delusion by fancy combined
With the vanishing phantoms of love and delight,
Abandon my soul, like a dream of the night,
  And leave but a desert behind.

Be hushed, my dark spirit! for wisdom condemns
  When the faint and the feeble deplore;
Be strong as the rock of the ocean that stems
  A thousand wild waves on the shore!
Through the perils of chance, and the scowl of disdain,
  May thy front be unaltered, thy courage elate!
Yea! even the name I have worshipped in vain
Shall awake not the sigh of remembrance again:
  To bear is to conquer our fate.    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

<text id="campbell2019090805">
<head>
    <title>Song</title>
    <firstline>Oh, how hard it is to find</firstline>
</head>
<body>
<poetry>
Oh, how hard it is to find
The one just suited to our mind;
  And if that one should be
False, unkind, or found too late,
What can we do but sigh at fate,
  And sing, Woe’s me—Woe’s me!

Love’s a boundless burning waste,
Where Bliss’s stream we seldom taste,
  And still more seldom flee
Suspense’s thorns, Suspicion’s stings;
Yet somehow Love a something brings
  That’s sweet—e’en when we sigh, “Woe’s me!”    
</poetry>
</body>
</text>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
