<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="andre" author="moore" status="incomplete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Andre digte</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="moore2000010902">
<head>
   <title>The Light of Other Days</title>
   <toctitle>The Light of Other Days</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Light of Other Days</indextitle>
   <firstline>Oft, in the stilly night</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Oft, in the stilly night,
   Ere slumber's chain has bound me,
Fond Memory brings the light
   Of other days around me:
      The smiles, the tears
      Of boyhood's years,
   The words of love then spoken;
      The eyes that shone,
      Now dimm'd and gone,
   The cheerful hearts now broken!
Thus, in the stilly night,
   Ere slumber's chain has bound me,
Sad Memory brings the light
   Of other days around me.

When I remember all
   The friends, so link'd together,
I've seen around me fall
   Like leaves in wintry weather,
      I feel like one
      Who treads alone
   Some banquet-hall deserted,
      Whose lights are fled,
      Whose garlands dead,
   And all but he departed!
Thus, in the stilly night,
   Ere slumber's chain has bound me.
Sad Memory brings the light
   Of other days around me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111201">
<head>
   <title>To ...: Sweet Lady, Look Not Thus Again</title>
   <firstline>Sweet lady, look not thus again</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Sweet lady, look not thus again:
Those bright, deluding smiles recall
A maid remember'd now with pain,
Who was my love, my life, my all!

Oh! while this heart bewildered took
Sweet poison from her thrilling eye,
Thus would she smile and lisp and look,
And I would hear and gaze and sigh!

Yes, I did love her - wildly love -
She was her sex's best deceiver!
And oft she swore she'd never rove -
And I was destined to believe her!

Then, lady, do not wear the smile
Of one whose smile could thus betray;
Alas! I think the lovely wile
Again could steal my heart away.

For, when those spells that charmed my mind
On lips so pure as thine I see,
I fear the heart which she resigned
Will err again and fly to thee!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111202">
<head>
   <title>On a beautiful East-Indian</title>
   <firstline>If all the daughters of the sun</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If all the daughters of the sun
Have loving looks and eyes of flame.
Go, tell me not that she is one —
'Twas from the wintry moon she came

And yet, sweet eye ! thou ne'er wert given
To kindle what thou dost not feel;
And yet, thou flushing lip — by heaven!
Thou ne'er wert made for Dian's seal!

Oh! for a sunbeam, rich and warm
From thy own Ganges' fervid haunts.
To light thee up, thou lovely fonn!
To all my soul adores and wants:

To see thee burn — to faint and sigh
Upon that bosom as it blaz'd.
And be myself the first to die.
Amid the flame myself had rais'd!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111203">
<head>
   <title>To Julia Weeping</title>
   <firstline>Oh! if your tears are given to care</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Oh! if your tears are given to care,
    If real woe disturbs your peace,
Come to my bosom, weeping fair!
    And I will bid your weeping cease.

But if with Fancy's visioned fears,
    With dreams of woe your bosom thrill;
You look so lovely in your tears,
    That I must bid you drop them still.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111204">
<head>
   <title>To Cara, After An Interval Of Absence</title>
   <firstline>Concealed within the shady wood</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Concealed within the shady wood
    A mother left her sleeping child,
And flew, to cull her rustic food,
    The fruitage of the forest wild.

But storms upon her pathway rise,
    The mother roams, astray and weeping;
Far from the weak appealing cries
    Of him she left so sweetly sleeping.

She hopes, she fears; a light is seen,
    And gentler blows the night wind's breath;
Yet no - 'tis gone - the storms are keen,
    The infant may be chilled to death!

Perhaps, even now, in darkness shrouded,
    His little eyes lie cold and still; -
And yet, perhaps, they are not clouded,
    Life and love may light them still.

Thus, Cara, at our last farewell,
    When, fearful even thy hand to touch,
I mutely asked those eyes to tell
    If parting pained thee half so much:

I thought, - and, oh! forgive the thought,
    For none was e'er by love inspired
Whom fancy had not also taught
    To hope the bliss his soul desired.

Yes, I think, in Cara's mind,
    Though yet to that sweet mind unknown,
I left one infant wish behind,
    One feeling, which I called my own.

Oh blest! though but in fancy blest,
    How did I ask of Pity's care,
To shield and strengthen, in thy breast,
    The nursling I had cradled there.

And, many an hour, beguiled by pleasure,
    And many an hour of sorrow numbering,
I ne'er forgot the new-born treasure,
    I left within thy bosom slumbering.

Perhaps, indifference has not chilled it,
    Haply, it yet a throb may give -
Yet, no - perhaps, a doubt has killed it;
    Say, dearest - the feeling live?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111205">
<head>
   <title>A Study From The Antique</title>
   <firstline>Behold, my love, the curious gem</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Behold, my love, the curious gem
    Within this simple ring of gold;
'Tis hallow'd by the touch of them
    Who lived in classic hours of old.

Some fair Athenian girl, perhaps,
    Upon her hand this gem displayed,
Nor thought that time's succeeding lapse
    Should see it grace a lovelier maid.

Look, dearest, what a sweet design!
    The more we gaze, it charms the more;
Come - closer bring that cheek to mine,
    And trace with me its beauties o'er.

Thou seest, it is a simple youth
    By some enamored nymph embraced -
Look, as she leans, and say in sooth
    Is not that hand most fondly placed?

Upon his curled head behind
    It seems in careless play to lie,
Yet presses gently, half inclined
    To bring the truant's lip more nigh.

Oh happy maid! Too happy boy!
    The one so fond and little loath,
The other yielding slow to joy -
    Oh rare, indeed, but blissful both.

Imagine, love, that I am he,
    And just as warm as he is chilling;
Imagine, too, that thou art she,
    But quite as coy as she is willing:

So may we try the graceful way
    In which their gentle arms are twined,
And thus, like her, my hand I lay
    Upon thy wreathed locks behind:

And thus I feel thee breathing sweet,
    As slow to mine thy head I move;
And thus our lips together meet,
    And thus, - and thus, - I kiss thee, love.

<nonum><center>* * * * *</center></nonum>

There's not a look, a word of thine,
    My soul hath e'er forgot;
Thou ne'er hast bid a ringlet shine,
Nor given thy locks one graceful twine
    Which I remember not.

There never yet a murmur fell
    From that beguiling tongue,
Which did not, with a lingering spell,
Upon thy charmed senses dwell,
    Like songs from Eden sung.

Ah! that I could, at once, forget
    All, all that haunts me so—
And yet, thou witching girl,—and yet,
To die were sweeter than to let
    The loved remembrance go.

No; if this slighted heart must see
    Its faithful pulse decay,
Oh let it die, remembering thee,
And, like the burnt aroma, be
    Consumed in sweets away.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111206">
<head>
   <title>Give me, my love, that billing kiss</title>
   <firstline>Give me, my love, that billing kiss</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Give me, my love, that billing kiss
I taught you one delicious night,
When, turning epicures in bliss,
We tried inventions of delight.

Come, gently steal my lips along,
And let your lips in murmurs move, -
Ah, no! - again - that kiss was wrong -
How can you be so dull, my love?

'Cease, cease!' the blushing girl replies -
And in her milky arms she caught me -
'How can you thus your pupil chide;
You know' twas in the dark you taught me!'
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111207">
<head>
   <title>The Lake Of The Dismal Swamp</title>
   <subtitle>A Ballad</subtitle>
   <firstline>They made her a grave, too cold and damp</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
"They made her a grave, too cold and damp
    "For a soul so warm and true;
"And she's gone to the Lake of the Dismal Swamp,
    "Where, all night long, by a firefly lamp,
"She paddles her white canoe.

"And her fire-fly lamp I soon shall see,
    "And her paddle I soon shall hear;
"Long and loving our life shall be,
"And I'll hide the maid in a cypress tree,
    "When the footstep of death is near."

Away to the Dismal Swamp he speeds—
    His path was rugged and sore,
Through tangled juniper, beds of reeds,
Through many a fen, where the serpent feeds,
    And man never trod before.

And, when on the earth he sunk to sleep
    If slumber his eyelids knew,
He lay, where the deadly vine doth weep
Its venomous tear and nightly steep
    The flesh with blistering dew!

And near him the she-wolf stirred the brake,
    And the copper-snake breathed in his ear,
Till he starting cried, from his dream awake,
"Oh! when shall I see the dusky Lake,
    "And the white canoe of my dear?"

He saw the Lake, and a meteor bright
    Quick over its surface played—
"Welcome," he said, "my dear one's light!"
And the dim shore echoed, for many a night,
    The name of the death-cold maid.

Till he hollowed a boat of the birchen bark,
    Which carried him off from shore;
Far, far he followed the meteor spark,
The wind was high and the clouds were dark,
    And the boat returned no more.

But oft, from the Indian hunter's camp
    This lover and maid so true
Are seen at the hour of midnight damp
To cross the Lake by a fire-fly lamp,
    And paddle their white canoe!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111208">
<head>
   <title>Black And Blue Eyes</title>
   <firstline>The brilliant black eye</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The brilliant black eye
         May in triumph let fly
All its darts without Caring who feels 'em;
         But the soft eye of blue,
         Tho' it scatter wounds too,
Is much better pleased when it heals 'em—
         Dear Fanny!
Is much better pleased when it heals 'em.

         The black eye may say,
         "Come and worship my ray—
"By adoring, perhaps you may move me!"
         But the blue eye, half hid,
         Says from under its lid,
"I love and am yours, if you love me!"
         Yes, Fanny!
         The blue eye, half hid,
         Says, from under its lid,
"I love and am yours, if you love me!"

         Come tell me, then, why
         In that lovely blue eye
Not a charm of its tint I discover;
         Oh why should you wear
         The only blue pair
That ever said "No" to a lover?
        Dear Fanny!
        Oh, why should you wear
        The only blue pair
That ever said "No" to a lover?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111301">
<head>
   <title>The Catalogue</title>
   <firstline>Come, tell me, says Rosa, as kissing and kist</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
"Come, tell me," says Rosa, as kissing and kist,
    One day she reclined on my breast;
"Come, tell me the number, repeat me the list
    "Of the nymphs you have loved and carest."—
Oh Rosa! 'twas only my fancy that roved,
    My heart at the moment was free;
But I'll tell thee, my girl, how many I've loved,
    And the number shall finish with thee.

My tutor was Kitty; in infancy wild
    She taught me the way to be blest;
She taught me to love her, I loved like a child,
    But Kitty could fancy the rest.
This lesson of dear and enrapturing lore
    I have never forgot, I allow:
I have had it very often before,
    But never until now.

Pretty Martha was next, and my soul was all flame,
    But my head was so full of romance
That I fancied her into some chivalry dame,
    And I was her knight of the lance.
But Martha was not of this fanciful school,
    And she laughed at her poor little knight;
While I thought her a goddess, she thought me a fool,
    And I'll swear was most in the right.

My soul was now calm, till, by Cloris's looks,
    Again I was tempted to rove;
But Cloris, I found, was so learned in books
    That she gave me more logic than love.
So I left this young Sappho, and hastened to fly
    To those sweeter logicians in bliss,
Who argue the point with a soul-telling eye,
    And convince us at once with a kiss.

Oh! Susan was then all the world unto me,
    But Susan was piously given;
And the worst of it was, we could never agree
    On the road that was shortest to Heaven.
"Oh, Susan!" I've said, in the moments of mirth,
    "What's devotion to thee or to me?
"I devoutly believe there's a heaven on earth,
    "And believe that that heaven's in !"
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018111302">
<head>
   <title>To Phillis</title>
   <firstline>Phillis, you little rosy rake</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Phillis, you little rosy rake,
    That heart of yours I long to rifle;
Come, give it me, and do not make
    So much ado about a !
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121001">
<head>
   <title>Sic Juvat Perire</title>
   <firstline>When wearied wretches sink to sleep</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When wearied wretches sink to sleep,
How heavenly soft their slumbers lie!
How sweet is death to those who weep,
To those who weep and long to die!

Saw you the soft and grassy bed,
Where flowrets deck the green earth's breast?
'Tis there I wish to lay my head,
'Tis there I wish to sleep at rest.

Oh, let not tears embalm my tomb, —
None but the dews at twilight given!
Oh, let not sighs disturb the gloom, —
None but the whispering winds of heaven!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121002">
<head>
   <title>Take Back The Sigh</title>
   <firstline>Take back the sigh thy lips of art</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Take back the sigh thy lips of art
In passion's moment breathed to me;
Yet, no—it must not, will not part,
'Tis now the life-breath of my heart,
And has become too pure for thee!

Take back the kiss, that faithless sigh
With all the warmth of truth imprest:
Yet, no—the fatal kiss may lie,
Upon thy lip its sweets would die,
Or bloom to make a rival blest!

Take back the vows that, night and day
My heart received, I thought, from thine;
Yet, no—allow them still to stay,
They might some other heart betray,
As sweetly as they've ruin'd mine!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121003">
<head>
   <title>Dost Thou Remember</title>
   <subtitle>Portuguese Air</subtitle>
   <firstline>Dost thou remember that place so lonely</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Dost thou remember that place so lonely,
A place for lovers and lovers only,
    Where first I told thee all my secret sighs?
When, as the moonbeam that trembled o'er thee
Illumed thy blushes, I knelt before thee,
    And read my hope's sweet triumph in those eyes?
Then, then, while closely heart was drawn to heart,
Love bound us—never, never more to part!

And when I called thee by names the dearest
That love could fancy, the fondest, nearest,—
    "My life, my only life!" among the rest;
In those sweet accents that still enthral me,
Thou saidst, "Ah!" wherefore thy life thus call me?
    "Thy soul, thy soul's the name I love best;
"For life soon passes,—but how blest to be
"That Soul which never, never parts from thee!"
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121004">
<head>
   <title>Little Mary's Eye</title>
   <firstline>Is roguish, and all that, sir</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
    Is roguish, and all that, sir;
But her little tongue
    Is quite too full of chat, sir.
Since her eye can speak
    Enough to tell her blisses,
If she stir her tongue.
    Why—stop her mouth with kisses!
Oh! the little girls,
    Wily, warm, and winning;
When the angels tempt us to it.,
    Who can keep from sinning?

Nanny's beaming eye
    Looks as warm as any;
But her cheek was pale—
    Well-a-day, poor Nanny!
Nanny, in the field,
    She pluck'd a little posie,
And Nanny's pallid cheek
    Soon grew sleek and rosy.
        Oh! the little girls, etc

Sue, the pretty nun
    Prays with warm emotion;
Sweetly rolls her eye
    In love or in devotion.
If her pious heart
    Softens to relieve you,
She gently shares the crime,
    With «Oh! may God forgive you!»
Oh! the little girls,
    Wily, warm and winning
When angels tempt us to it,
    Who can keep from sinning?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121005">
<head>
   <title>Lying</title>
   <firstline>I do confess, in many a sigh</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I do confess, in many a sigh,
My lips have breath'd you many a lie,
And who, with such delights in view,
Would lose them for a lie or two?

Nay — look not thus, with brow reproving:
Lies are, my dear, the soul of loving!
If half we tell the girls were true,
If half we swear to think and do,
Were aught but lying's bright illusion,
The world would be in strange confusion!
If ladies' eyes were, every one,
As lovers swear, a radiant sun,
Astronomy should leave the skies,
To learn her lore in ladies' eyes!
Oh no! — believe me, lovely girl,
When nature turns your teeth to pearl,
Your neck to snow, your eyes to fire,
Your yellow locks to golden wire,
Then, only then, can heaven decree,
That you should live for only me,
Or I for you, as night and morn,
We've swearing kiss'd, and kissing sworn.

And now, my gentle hints to clear,
For once, I'll tell you truth, my dear!
Whenever you may chance to meet
A loving youth, whose love is sweet,
Long as you're false and he believes you,
Long as you trust and he deceives you,
So long the blissful bond endures;
And while he lies, his heart is yours:
But, oh! you've wholly lost the youth
The instant that he tells you truth!
</body>
</poem>


<poem id="moore2018121006">
<head>
   <title>Will you come to the bower?</title>
   <firstline>Will you come to the bower I have shaded for you?</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Will you come to the bower I have shaded for you?
Our bed shall be roses all spangled with dew.
     Will you, will you, will you, will you,
          Come to the bower?

There, under the bower on roses you’ll lie,
With a blush on your cheek, but a smile in your eye.
     Will you, will you, will you, will you,
          Smile my beloved?

But the roses we press shall not rival your lip,
Nor the dew be so sweet as the kisses we’ll sip.
     Will you, will you, will you, will you,
          Kiss me, my love!

And oh! for the joys that are sweeter than dew
From languishing roses, or kisses from you.
     Will you, will you, will you, will you,
          Won’t you, my love?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121006">
<head>
   <title>When 'midst the gay I meet </title>
   <firstline>When ’midst the gay I meet</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When ’midst the gay I meet 
      That gentle smile of thine, 
Though still on me it turns most sweet, 
      I scarce can call it mine: 
But when to me alone 
      Your secret tears you show, 
Oh, then I feel those tears my own, 
      And claim them while they flow. 
Then still with bright looks bless 
      The gay, the cold, the free; 
Give smiles to those who love you less, 
      But keep your tears for me. 

The snow on Jura’s steep 
      Can smile in many a beam, 
Yet still in chains of coldness sleep, 
      How bright soe’er it seem. 
But, when some deep-felt ray, 
      Whose touch is fire, appears, 
Oh, then the smile is warm’d away, 
      And, melting, turns to tears. 
Then still with bright looks bless 
      The gay, the cold, the free; 
Give smiles to those who love you less, 
      But keep your tears for me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121007">
<head>
   <title>Did Not</title>
   <firstline>Twas a new feeling - something more</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
'Twas a new feeling - something more
Than we had dared to own before,
Which then we hid not;
We saw it in each other's eye,
And wished, in every half-breathed sigh,
To speak, but did not.

She felt my lips' impassioned touch - 
'Twas the first time I dared so much,
And yet she chid not;
But whispered o'er my burning brow,
'Oh, do you doubt I love you now?'
Sweet soul! I did not.

Warmly I felt her bosom thrill,
I pressed it closer, closer still,
Though gently bid not;
Till - oh! the world hath seldom heard
Of lovers, who so nearly erred,
And yet, who did not. 
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121008">
<head>
   <title>Love Is a Hunter-boy</title>
   <firstline>Love is a hunter-boy</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Love is a hunter-boy,
Who makes young hearts his prey,
And in his nets of joy
Ensnares them night and day.
In vain concealed they lie—
Love tracks them every where;
In vain aloft they fly—
Love shoots them flying there.

But 't is his joy most sweet,
At early dawn to trace
The print of Beauty's feet,
And give the trembler chase.
And if, thro' virgin snow,
He tracks her footsteps fair,
How sweet for Love to know
None went before him there.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121009">
<head>
   <title>Bright Be Thy Dreams</title>
   <firstline>Bright be thy dreams—may all thy weeping</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Bright be thy dreams—may all thy weeping
Turn into smiles while thou art sleeping.
May those by death or seas removed,
The friends, who in thy springtime knew thee,
All thou hast ever prized or loved,
In dreams come smiling to thee!

There may the child, whose love lay deepest,
Dearest of all, come while thou sleepest;
Still as she was—no charm forgot—
No lustre lost that life had given;
Or, if changed, but changed to what
Thou'lt find her yet in Heaven!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121010">
<head>
   <title>Oh! see those cherries</title>
   <firstline>Oh! see those cherries—though once so glowing</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I.
Oh! see those cherries—though once so glowing, 
  They've lain too long on the sun-bright wall;
And mark! already their bloom is going; 
  Too soon they'll wither, too soon they'll fall. 
Once, caught by their blushes, the light bird flew round,
Oft on their ruby lips leaving love's wound;
  But now he passes them, ah! too knowing 
To taste wither'd cherries, when fresh may be found.

II.
Old Time thus fleetly his course is running;
  If bards were not moral, how maids would go wrong!
And thus thy beauties, now sunn'd and sunning,
  Would wither if left on the rose-tree too long. 
Then love while thou'rt lovely—e'en I should be glad 
So sweetly to save thee from ruin so sad;
  But, oh! delay not—we bards are too cunning 
To sigh for old beauties when young may be had. 
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121011">
<head>
   <title>Fanny, Dearest</title>
   <firstline>Oh! had I leisure to sigh and mourn</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Oh! had I leisure to sigh and mourn,
  Fanny, dearest, for thee I 'd sigh; 
And every smile on my cheek should turn 
  To tears when thou art nigh. 
But between love, and wine, and sleep, 
  So busy a life I live, 
That even the time it would take to weep 
  Is more than my heart can give. 
Then bid me not to despair and pine,
  Fanny, dearest of all the dears! 
The Love that's order'd to bathe in wine  
  Would be sure to take cold in tears.

Reflected bright in this heart of mine,
  Fanny, dearest, thy image lies; 
But oh, the mirror would cease to shine, 
   If dimm'd too often with sighs. 
They lose the half of beauty's light, 
  Who view it through sorrow's tear; 
And 'tis but to see thee truly bright 
  That I keep my eye-beam clear. 
Then wait no longer till tears shall flow, 
  Fanny, dearest—the hope is vain; 
If sunshine cannot dissolve thy snow, 
  I shall never attempt it with rain.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121012">
<head>
   <title>Row gently here</title>
   <subtitle>Venetian air</subtitle>
   <firstline>Row gently here</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
         Row gently here, 
         My gondolier, 
      So softly wake the tide, 
         That not an ear 
         On earth may hear, 
      But hers to whom we glide. 
Had Heaven but tongues to speak, as well 
      As starry eyes to see, 
Oh, think what tales 't would have to tell 
      Of wandering youths like me!

         Now rest thee here, 
         My gondolier; 
      Hush, hush, for up I go, 
         To climb yon light 
         Balcony's height, 
      While thou keep'st watch below. 
Ah! did we take for Heaven above 
      But half such pains as we 
Take, day and night, for woman's love, 
     What Angels we should be"     
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121101">
<head>
   <title>All that's bright must fade</title>
   <firstline>All that's bright must fade</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
All that's bright must fade,—
The brightest still the fleetest;
All that's sweet was made
But to be lost when sweetest.
Stars that shine and fall;—
The flower that drops in springing;—
These, alas! are types of all
To which our hearts are clinging.
All that's bright must fade,—
The brightest still the fleetest;
All that's sweet was made
But to be lost when sweetest?

Who would seek our prize
Delights that end in aching?
Who would trust to ties
That every hour are breaking?
Better far to be
In utter darkness lying,
Than to be blest with light and see
That light for ever flying.
All that's bright must fade,—
The brightest still the fleetest;
All that's sweet was made
But to be lost when sweetest!    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121102">
<head>
   <title>Reason and Folly and Beauty, they say</title>
   <subtitle>Italian Air</subtitle>
   <firstline>Reason and Folly and Beauty, they say</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Reason and Folly and Beauty, they say,
Went on a party of pleasure one day:
        Folly played
        Around the maid,
The bells of his cap rung merrily out;
        While Reason took
        To his sermon-book—
Oh! which was the pleasanter no one need doubt,
Which was the pleasanter no one need doubt.

Beauty, who likes to be thought very sage.
Turned for a moment to Reason's dull page,
        Till Folly said,
        «Look here, sweet maid!»—
The sight of his cap brought her back to herself;
        While Reason read
        His leaves of lead,
With no one to mind him, poor sensible elf!
No,—no one to mind him, poor sensible elf!

Then Reason grew jealous of Folly's gay cap;
Had he that on, he her heart might entrap—
        «There it is,»
        Quoth Folly, «old quiz!»
(Folly was always good-natured, 'tis said,)
        «Under the sun
        There's no such fun,
As Reason with my cap and bells on his head!»
«Reason with my cap and bells on his head!»

But Reason the head-dress so awkwardly wore,
That Beauty now liked him still less than before;
        While Folly took
        Old Reason's book,
And twisted the leaves in a cap of such <i>ton</i>,
        That Beauty vowed
        (Tho' not aloud),
She liked him still better in that than his own,
Yes,—liked him still better in that than his own.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121103">
<head>
   <title>There comes a time, a dreary time</title>
   <firstline>There comes a time, a dreary time</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
There comes a time, a dreary time,
To him whose heart hath flown
O'er all the fields of youth's sweet prime
And made each flower its own.
'Tis when his soul must first renounce
Those dreams so bright, so fond;
Oh! then's the time to die at once,
For Life has nought beyond.

When sets the sun on Afric's shore,
That instant all is night;
And so should life at once be o'er,
When Love withdraws his light -
Nor, like our northern day, gloom on
Through twilight's dim delay,
The cold remains of lustre gone,
Of fire long passed away.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121104">
<head>
   <title>Song</title>
   <firstline>Fly from the world, O Bessy! to me</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Fly from the world, O Bessy! to me, 
Thou wilt never find any sincerer; 
I'll give up the world, O Bessy! for thee, 
I can never meet any that's dearer. 
Then tell me no more, with a tear and a sigh, 
That our loves will be censured by many; 
All, all have their follies, and who will deny 
That ours is the sweetest of any? 
When your lip has met mine, in communion so sweet, 
Have we felt as if virtue forbid it? — 
Have we felt as if heaven denied them to meet? — 
No, rather 't was heaven that did it. 
So innocent, love, is the joy we then sip, 
So little of wrong is there in it, 
That I wish all my errors were lodged on your lip, 
And I'd kiss them away in a minute. 

Then come to your lover, oh! fly to his shed, 
From a world which I know thou despisest; 
And slumber will hover as light o'er our bed 
As e'er on the couch of the wisest. 
And when o'er our pillow the tempest is driven, 
And thou, pretty innocent, fearest, 
I'll tell thee, it is not the chiding of heaven, 
'T is only our lullaby, dearest. 

And, oh! while we lie on our deathbed, my love, 
Looking back on the scene of our errors. 
A sigh from my Bessy shall plead then above, 
And Death be disarmed of his terrors, 
And each to the other embracing will say, 
" Farewell! let us hope we 're forgiven. " 
Thy last fading glance will illumine the way, 
And a kiss be our passport to heaven!    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2018121105">
<head>
   <title>Elegiac Stanzas</title>
   <firstline>How sweetly could I lay my head</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
How sweetly could I lay my head 
  Within the cold grave's silent breast; 
Where Sorrow's tears no more are shed,
  No more the ills of life molest. 

For, ah! my heart, how very soon 
  The glitt'ring dreams of youth are past! 
And, long before it reach its noon,
  The sun of life is overcast.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2019013101">
<head>
   <title>To a sleeping maid</title>
   <firstline>Wake, my life! thy lover's arms</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Wake, my life! thy lover's arms
Are twined around thy sleeping charms:
Wake, my love! and let desire
Kindle those opening orbs of fire.

Yet, sweetest, though the bliss delight thee,
If the guilt, the shame affright thee,
Still those orbs in darkness keep;
Sleep, my girl, or <i>seem to sleep.</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore2019020101">
<head>
   <title>The probability</title>
   <firstline>My heart is united to Chloe's for ever</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My heart is united to Chloe's for ever, 
No time shall the link of their tenderness sever, 
And, if Love be the parent of joy and of pleasure, 
Chloe and I shall be blest beyond measure. 

Come, tell me, my girl, what's the sweetest of blisses? 
''I'll show you,'' she cries, and she gives me sweet kisses; 
Ah, Clo' if that languishing eye's not a traitor, 
It tells me you know of a bliss that is greater. 

''Indeed, and I do not,'' then softly she blushes, 
And her bosom the warm tint of modesty flushes; 
''I'm sure if I knew it, I'd certainly show it, 
''But Damon, dear, may be you know it."     
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908221">
<head>
    <title>Love and Time</title>
    <firstline>Tis said—but whether true or not</firstline>
</head>
<body>
't is said—but whether true or not
Let bards declare who 've seen 'em—
That Love and Time have only got
One pair of wings between 'em.
In courtship's first delicious hour,
The boy full oft can spare 'em;
So, loitering in his lady's bower,
He lets the gray-beard wear 'em.
Then is Time's hour of play;
Oh, how he flies, flies away!

But short the moments, short as bright,
When he the wings can borrow;
If Time to-day has had his flight,
Love takes his turn to-morrow.
Ah! Time and Love, your change is then
The saddest and most trying,
When one begins to limp again,
And t' other takes to flying.
Then is Love's hour to stray
Oh, how he flies, flies away!

But there's a nymph, whose chains I feel,
And bless the silken fetter,
Who knows, the dear one, how to deal
With Love and Time much better.
So well she checks their wanderings,
So peacefully she pairs 'em,
That Love with her ne'er thinks of wings,
And Time for ever wears 'em.
This is Time's holiday;
Oh, how he flies, flies away!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908222">
<head>
    <title>When Love was a Child</title>
    <subtitle>(Swedish Air.)</subtitle>
    <firstline>When Love was a child, and went idling round</firstline>
</head>
<body>
When Love was a child, and went idling round,
  'Mong flowers the whole summer's day,
One morn in the valley a bower he found,
  So sweet, it allured him to stay.

O'erhead, from the trees, hung a garland fair,
  A fountain ran darkly beneath;—
'Twas Pleasure had hung up the flowerets there;
  Love knew it, and jumped at the wreath.

But Love didn't know—and, at <i>his</i> weak years,
  What urchin was likely to know?—
That Sorrow had made of her own salt tears
  The fountain that murmured below.

He caught at the wreath—but with too much haste,
  As boys when impatient will do—
It fell in those waters of briny taste,
  And the flowers were all wet through.

This garland he now wears night and day;
  And, tho' it all sunny appears
With Pleasure's own light, each leaf, they say,
  Still tastes of the Fountain of Tears.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908223">
<head>
    <title>A Temple to Friendship</title>
    <subtitle>(Spanish Air.)</subtitle>
    <firstline>A Temple to Friendship; said Laura, enchanted</firstline>
</head>
<body>
"A Temple to Friendship;" said Laura, enchanted,
  "I'll build in this garden,—the thought is divine!"
Her temple was built and she now only wanted
  An image of Friendship to place on the shrine.
She flew to a sculptor, who set down before her
  A Friendship, the fairest his art could invent;
But so cold and so dull, that the youthful adorer
  Saw plainly this was not the idol she meant.

"Oh! never," she cried, "could I think of enshrining
  "An image whose looks are so joyless and dim;—
"But yon little god, upon roses reclining,
  "We'll make, if you please, Sir, a Friendship of him."
So the bargain was struck; with the little god laden
  She joyfully flew to her shrine in the grove:
"Farewell," said the sculptor, "you're not the first maiden
  "Who came but for Friendship and took away Love."    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908224">
<head>
    <title>When the wine-cup is smiling before us</title>
    <firstline>When the wine-cup is smiling</firstline>
</head>
<body>

When the wine-cup is smiling before us,
  And we pledge round to hearts that are true, boy, true,
Then the sky of this life opens o'er us,
  And Heaven gives a glimpse of its blue.
Talk of Adam in Eden reclining,
  We are better, far better off thus, boy, thus;
For <i>him</i> but <i>two</i> bright eyes were shining—
  See, what numbers are sparkling for us!

When on <i>one</i> side the grape-juice is dancing,
  While on t'other a blue eye beams, boy, beams,
'Tis enough, 'twixt the wine and the glancing,
  To disturb even a saint from his dreams.
Yet, tho' life like a river is flowing,
  I care not how fast it goes on, boy, on,
So the grape on its bank is still growing,
  And Love lights the waves as they run.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908225">
<head>
    <title>Love and Reason</title>
    <firstline>Twas in the summer time so sweet</firstline>
</head>
<body>
'Twas in the summer time so sweet,
  When hearts and flowers are both in season,
That—who, of all the world, should meet,
  One early dawn, but Love and Reason!

Love told his dream of yesternight,
  While Reason talked about the weather;
The morn, in sooth, was fair and bright,
  And on they took their way together.

The boy in many a gambol flew,
  While Reason, like a Juno, stalked,
And from her portly figure threw
  A lengthened shadow, as she walked.

No wonder Love, as on they past,
  Should find that sunny morning chill,
For still the shadow Reason cast
  Fell o'er the boy, and cooled him still.

In vain he tried his wings to warm.
  Or find a pathway not so dim
For still the maid's gigantic form
  Would stalk between the sun and him.

"This must not be," said little Love—
  "The sun was made for more than you."
So, turning through a myrtle grove,
  He bid the portly nymph adieu.

Now gayly roves the laughing boy
  O'er many a mead, by many a stream;
In every breeze inhaling joy,
  And drinking bliss in every beam.

From all the gardens, all the bowers,
  He culled the many sweets they shaded,
And ate the fruits and smelled the flowers,
  Till taste was gone and odor faded.

But now the sun, in pomp of noon,
  Looked blazing o'er the sultry plains;
Alas! the boy grew languid soon,
  And fever thrilled through all his veins.

The dew forsook his baby brow,
  No more with healthy bloom he smiled—
Oh! where was tranquil Reason now,
  To cast her shadow o'er the child?

Beneath a green and aged palm,
  His foot at length for shelter turning,
He saw the nymph reclining calm,
  With brow as cool as his was burning.

"Oh! take me to that bosom cold,"
  In murmurs at her feet he said;
And Reason oped her garment's fold,
  And flung it round his fevered head.

He felt her bosom's icy touch,
  And soon it lulled his pulse to rest;
For, ah! the chill was quite too much,
  And Love expired on Reason's breast!

<nonum><center>* * * * *</center></nonum>

Nay, do not weep, my Fanny dear;
  While in these arms you lie.
This world hath not a wish, a fear,
That ought to cost that eye a tear.
  That heart, one single sigh.

The world!—ah, Fanny, Love must shun
  The paths where many rove;
One bosom to recline upon,
One heart to be his only—one,
  Are quite enough for Love.

What can we wish, that is not here
  Between your arms and mine?
Is there, on earth, a space so dear
As that within the happy sphere
  Two loving arms entwine?

For me, there's not a lock of jet
  Adown your temples curled,
Within whose glossy, tangling net,
My soul doth not, at once, forget
  All, all this worthless world.

'Tis in those eyes, so full of love,
  My only worlds I see;
Let but _their_ orbs in sunshine move,
And earth below and skies above
  May frown or smile for me.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908232">
<head>
    <title>Go where glory waits thee</title>
    <firstline>Go where glory waits thee</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Go where glory waits thee,
But while fame elates thee,
  Oh! still remember me.
When the praise thou meetest
To thine ear is sweetest,
  Oh! then remember me.
Other arms may press thee,
Dearer friends caress thee,
All the joys that bless thee,
  Sweeter far may be;
But when friends are nearest,
And when joys are dearest,
  Oh! then remember me!

When, at eve, thou rovest
By the star thou lovest,
  Oh! then remember me.
Think, when home returning,
Bright we've seen it burning,
  Oh! thus remember me.
Oft as summer closes,
When thine eye reposes
On its lingering roses,
  Once so loved by thee,
Think of her who wove them,
Her who made thee love them,
  Oh! then, remember me.

When, around thee dying,
Autumn leaves are lying,
  Oh! then remember me.
And, at night, when gazing
On the gay hearth blazing,
  Oh! still remember me.
Then should music, stealing
All the soul of feeling,
To thy heart appealing,
  Draw one tear from thee;
Then let memory bring thee
Strains I used to sing thee,—
  Oh! then remember me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908233">
<head>
    <title>My Heart and Lute</title>
    <firstline>I give thee all—I can no more—</firstline>
</head>
<body>
I give thee all—I can no more—
  Tho' poor the offering be;
My heart and lute are all the store
  That I can bring to thee.
A lute whose gentle song reveals
  The soul of love full well;
And, better far, a heart that feels
  Much more than lute could tell.

Tho' love and song may fail, alas!
  To keep life's clouds away,
At least 'twill make them lighter pass,
  Or gild them if they stay.
And even if Care at moments flings
  A discord o'er life's happy strain,
Let Love but gently touch the strings,
  'Twill all be sweet again!    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908234" variant="moore2000082962">
<head>
    <title>Has Sorrow Thy Young Days shaded</title>
    <firstline>Has sorrow thy young days shaded</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Has sorrow thy young days shaded,
  As clouds o'er the morning fleet?
Too fast have those young days faded,
  That, even in sorrow, were sweet?
Does Time with his cold wing wither
  Each feeling that once was dear?—
Then, child of misfortune, come hither,
  I'll weep with thee, tear for tear.

Has love to that soul, so tender,
  Been like our Lagenian mine,<note>Our Wicklow Gold Mines, to which this verse alludes, deserve, I fear, but too well the character here given of them.</note>
Where sparkles of golden splendor
  All over the surface shine—
But, if in pursuit we go deeper,
  Allured by the gleam that shone,
Ah! false as the dream of the sleeper,
  Like Love, the bright ore is gone.

  Has Hope, like the bird in the story,<note> "The bird, having got its prize, settled not far off, with the talisman in his mouth. The prince drew near it, hoping it would drop it: but as he approached, the bird took wing, and settled again," etc. — "<i>Arabian Nights</i>."</note>
  That flitted from tree to tree
With the talisman's glittering glory—
  Has Hope been that bird to thee?
On branch after branch alighting,
  The gem did she still display,
And, when nearest and most inviting.
  Then waft the fair gem away?

If thus the young hours have fleeted,
  When sorrow itself looked bright;
If thus the fair hope hath cheated,
  That led thee along so light;
If thus the cold world now wither
  Each feeling that once was dear:—
Come, child of misfortune, come hither,
  I'll weep with thee, tear for tear.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908235">
<head>
    <title>Love and Hymen</title>
    <firstline>Love had a fever—ne'er could close</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Love had a fever—ne'er could close
  His little eyes till day was breaking;
And wild and strange enough, Heaven knows,
  The things he raved about while waking.

To let him pine so were a sin;—
  One to whom all the world's a debtor—
So Doctor Hymen was called in,
  And Love that night slept rather better.

Next day the case gave further hope yet,
  Tho' still some ugly fever latent;—
"Dose, as before"—a gentle opiate.
  For which old Hymen has a patent.

After a month of daily call,
  So fast the dose went on restoring,
That Love, who first ne'er slept at all,
  Now took, the rogue! to downright snoring.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908236">
<head>
    <title>The Sale of Loves</title>
    <firstline>I dreamt that, in the Paphian groves</firstline>
</head>
<body>
I dreamt that, in the Paphian groves,
  My nets by moonlight laying,
I caught a flight of wanton Loves,
  Among the rose-beds playing.
Some just had left their silvery shell,
  While some were full in feather;
So pretty a lot of Loves to sell,
  Were never yet strung together.
    Come buy my Loves,
    Come buy my Loves,
Ye dames and rose-lipped misses!—
  They're new and bright,
  The cost is light,
For the coin of this isle is kisses.

First Cloris came, with looks sedate.
  The coin on her lips was ready;
"I buy," quoth she, "my Love by weight,
  "Full grown, if you please, and steady."
"Let mine be light," said Fanny, "pray—
  "Such lasting toys undo one;
"A light little Love that will last to-day,—
  "To-morrow I'll sport a new one."
     Come buy my Loves,
     Come buy my Loves,
Ye dames and rose-lipped misses!—
  There's some will keep,
  Some light and cheap
At from ten to twenty kisses.

The learned Prue took a pert young thing,
  To divert her virgin Muse with,
And pluck sometimes a quill from his wing.
  To indite her billet-doux with,
Poor Cloe would give for a well-fledged pair
  Her only eye, if you'd ask it;
And Tabitha begged, old toothless fair.
  For the youngest Love in the basket.
    Come buy my Loves, etc.

But _one_ was left, when Susan came,
  One worth them all together;
At sight of her dear looks of shame,
  He smiled and pruned his feather.
She wished the boy—'twas more than whim—
  Her looks, her sighs betrayed it;
But kisses were not enough for him,
  I asked a heart and she paid it!
    Good-by, my Loves,
    Good-by, my Loves,
'Twould make you smile to've seen us
  First, trade for this
  Sweet child of bliss,
And then nurse the boy between us.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908251">
<head>
    <title>Love and Hope</title>
    <subtitle>(Swiss Air.)</subtitle>
    <firstline>At morn, beside yon summer sea</firstline>
</head>
<body>
At morn, beside yon summer sea,
  Young Hope and Love reclined;
But scarce had noon-tide come, when he
Into his bark leapt smilingly,
  And left poor Hope behind.

"I go," said Love, "to sail awhile
  "Across this sunny main;"
And then so sweet, his parting smile,
That Hope, who never dreamt of guile,
  Believed he'd come again.

She lingered there till evening's beam
  Along the waters lay;
And o'er the sands, in thoughtful dream,
Oft traced his name, which still the stream
  As often washed away.

At length a sail appears in sight,
  And toward the maiden moves!
'Tis Wealth that comes, and gay and bright,
His golden bark reflects the light,
  But ah! it is not Love's.

Another sail—'twas Friendship showed
  Her night-lamp o'er the sea;
And calm the light that lamp bestowed;
But Love had lights that warmer glowed,
  And where, alas! was he?

Now fast around the sea and shore
  Night threw her darkling chain;
The sunny sails were seen no more,
Hope's morning dreams of bliss were o'er—
  Love never came again!    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908252">
<head>
    <title>How shall I woo</title>
    <firstline>If I speak to thee in friendship's name</firstline>
</head>
<body>
If I speak to thee in friendship's name,
  Thou think'st I speak too coldly;
If I mention Love's devoted flame,
  Thou say'st I speak too boldly.
Between these two unequal fires,
  Why doom me thus to hover?
I'm a friend, if such thy heart requires,
  If more thou seek'st, a lover.
Which shall it be? How shall I woo?
  Fair one, choose between the two.

Tho' the wings of Love will brightly play,
  When first he comes to woo thee,
There's a chance that he may fly away,
  As fast as he flies _to_ thee.
While Friendship, tho' on foot she come,
  No flights of fancy trying,
Will, therefore, oft be found at home,
  When Love abroad is flying.
Which shall it be? How shall I woo?
  Dear one, choose between the two.

If neither feeling suits thy heart
  Let's see, to please thee, whether
We may not learn some precious art
  To mix their charms together;
One feeling, still more sweet, to form
  From two so sweet already—
A friendship that like love is warm,
  A love like friendship steady.
Thus let it be, thus let me woo,
  Dearest, thus we'll join the two.    
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908253">
<head>
    <title>Cloris and Fanny</title>
    <firstline>Cloris! if I were Persia's king</firstline>
</head>
<body>
Cloris! if I were Persia's king,
  I'd make my graceful queen of thee;
While FANNY, wild and artless thing,
  Should but thy humble handmaid be.

There is but _one_ objection in it—
  That, verily, I'm much afraid
I should, in some unlucky minute,
  Forsake the mistress for the maid.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908254">
<head>
    <title>Rondeau</title>
    <firstline>Good night! good night!—And is it so?</firstline>
</head>
<body>
"Good night! good night!"—And is it so?
And must I from my Rosa go?
Oh Rosa, say "Good night!" once more,
And I'll repeat it o'er and o'er,
Till the first glance of dawning light
Shall find us saying, still, "Good night."

And still "Good night," my Rosa, say—
But whisper still, "A minute stay;"
And I will stay, and every minute
Shall have an age of transport in it;
Till Time himself shall stay his flight,
To listen to our sweet "Good night."

"Good night!" you'll murmur with a sigh,
And tell me it is time to fly:
And I will vow, will swear to go,
While still that sweet voice murmurs "No!"
Till slumber seal our weary sight—
And then, my love, my soul, "Good night!"
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="moore201908291">
<head>
    <title></title>
    <firstline></firstline>
</head>
<body>
</body>
</poem>

</workbody>
</kalliopework>
