<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1929" author="lawrence" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Pansies</title>
   <year>1929</year>
   <notes>
      <note>Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="lawrence2001061105">
<head>
   <title>Our Day is Over</title>
   <toctitle>Our Day is Over</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Our Day is Over</indextitle>
   <firstline>Our day is over, night comes up</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Our day is over, night comes up
shadows steal out of the earth.
Shadows, shadows
wash over our knees and splash between our thighs,
our day is done;
we wade, we wade, we stagger, darkness rushes between our stones,
we shall drown.

Our day is over
night comes up.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061106">
<head>
   <title>Destiny</title>
   <toctitle>Destiny</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Destiny</indextitle>
   <firstline>O destiny, destiny</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
O destiny, destiny,
do you exist, and can a man touch your hand?

O destiny
if I could see your hand, and it were thumbs down,
I would be willing to give way, like the pterodactyl,
and accept obliteration.
I would not even ask to leave a fossil claw extant,
nor a thumb-mark like a clue,
I would be willing to vanish completely, completely.

But if it is thumbs up, and mankind must go on being mankind,
then I am willing to fight, I will roll my sleeves up
and start in.

Only, o destiny
I wish you'd show your hand.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061107">
<head>
   <title>How Beastly the Bourgeois Is</title>
   <toctitle>How Beastly the Bourgeois Is</toctitle>
   <indextitle>How Beastly the Bourgeois Is</indextitle>
   <firstline>How beastly the bourgeois is</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
How beastly the bourgeois is
especially the male of the species -

Presentable, eminently presentable -
shall I make you a present of him?

Isn't he handsome? Isn't he healthy? Isn't he a fine specimen?
Doesn't he look the fresh clean Englishman, outside?
Isn't it God's own image? tramping his thirty miles a day
after partridges, or a little rubber ball?
wouldn't you like to be like that, well off, and quite the thing?

Oh, but wait!
Let him meet a new emotion, let him be faced with another man's need,
let him come home to a bit of moral difficulty, let life face him with a new demand on his understanding
and then watch him go soggy, like a wet meringue.
Watch him turn into a mess, either a fool or a bully.
Just watch the display of him, confronted with a new demand on his intelligence,
a new life-demand.

How beastly the bourgeois is
especially the male of the species -

Nicely groomed, like a mushroom
standing there so sleek and erect and eyeable -
and like a fungus, living on the remains of a bygone life
sucking his life out of the dead leaves of greater life than his own.

And even so, he's stale, he's been there too long.
Touch him, and you'll find he's all gone inside
just like an old mushroom, all wormy inside, and hollow
under a smooth skin and an upright appearance.

Full of seething, wormy, hollow feelings
rather nasty -
How beastly the bourgeois is!

Standing in their thousands, these appearances, in damp England
what a pity they can't all be kicked over
like sickening toadstools, and left to melt back, swiftly
into the soil of England.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061764">
<head>
   <title>Worm Either Way</title>
   <toctitle>Worm Either Way</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Worm Either Way</indextitle>
   <firstline>If you live along with all the other people</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If you live along with all the other people
and are just like them, and conform, and are nice
you're just a worm -

and if you live with all the other people
and you don't like them and won't be like them and won't conform
then you're just the worm that has turned,
in either case, a worm.

The conforming worm stays just inside the skin
respectably unseen, and cheerfully gnaws away at the heart of life,
making it all rotten inside.

The unconforming worm - that is, the worm that has turned -
gnaws just the same, gnawing the substance out of life,
but he insists on gnawing a little hole in the social epidermis
and poking his head out and waving himself
and saying: Look at me, I am <i>not</i> respectable,
I do all the things the bourgeois daren't do,
I booze and fornicate and use foul language and despise your honest man. -

But why should the worm that has turned protest so much?
The bonnie, bonnie bourgeois goes a-whoring up back streets
just the same.
The busy, busy bourgeois imbibes his little share
just the same
if not more.
The pretty, pretty bourgeois pinks his language just as pink
if not pinker,
and in private boasts his exploits even louder, if you ask me,
than the other.
While as to honesty, Oh, look where the money lies!

So I can't see where the worm that has turned puts anything over
the worm that is too cunning to turn.
On the contrary, he merely gives himself away.
The turned worm shouts. I bravely booze!
the other says. What? Cat-piss?
The turned worm boasts: I copulate!
the unturned says: You look it.
You're a d--- b--- b--- p--- bb---, says the worm that's turned.
Quite! says the other. Cuckoo!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061765">
<head>
   <title>Swan</title>
   <toctitle>Swan</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Swan</indextitle>
   <firstline>Far-off</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Far-off
at the core of space
at the quick
of time
beats
and goes still
the great swan upon the waters of all endings
the swan within vast chaos, within the electron.

For us
no longer he swims calmly
nor clacks across the forces furrowing a great gay trail
of happy energy,
nor is he nesting passive upon the atoms,
nor flying north desolative icewards
to the sleep of ice,
nor feeding in the marshes,
nor honking horn-like into the twilight.

But he stoops, now
in the dark
upon us;
he is treading our women
and we men are put out
as the vast white bird
furrows our featherless women
with unknown shocks
and stamps his black marsh-feet on their white and marshy flesh.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061108">
<head>
   <title>Give us Gods</title>
   <toctitle>Give us Gods</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Give us Gods</indextitle>
   <firstline>Give us gods, Oh give them us!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Give us gods, Oh give them us!
Give us gods.
We are so tired of men
and motor-power. -

But not gods grey-bearded and dictatorial,
nor yet that pale young man afraid of fatherhood
shelving substance on to the woman, Madonna mia! shabby virgin!
nor gusty Jove, with his eye on immortal tarts,
nor even the musical, suave young fellow
wooing boys and beauty.

Give us gods
give us something else -

Beyond the great bull that bellowed through space, and got his throat cut.
Beyond even that eagle, that phoenix, hanging over the gold egg of all things,
further still, before the curled horns of the ram stepped forth
or the stout swart beetle rolled the globe of dung in which man should hatch,
or even the sly gold serpent fatherly lifted his head off the earth to think -

Give us gods before these -
Thou shalt have other gods before these.

Where the waters end in marshes
swims the wild swan
sweeps the high goose above the mists
honking in the gloom the honk of procreation from such throats.

Mists
where the electron behaves and misbehaves as it will,
where the forces tie themselves up into knots of atoms
and come untied;

Mists
of mistiness complicated into knots and clots that barge about
and bump on one another and explode into more mist, or don't,
mist of energy most scientific -
But give us gods!

Look then
where the father of all things swims in a mist of atoms
electrons and energies, quantums and relativities
mists, wreathing mists,
like a wild swan, or a goose, whose honk goes through my bladder.

And in the dark unscientific I feel the drum-winds of his wings
and the drip of his cold, webbed feet, mud-black
brush over my face as he goes
to seek the women in the dark, our women, our weird women whom he treads
with dreams and thrusts that make them cry in their sleep.

Gods, do you ask for gods?
Where there is woman there is swan.

Do you think, scientific man, you'll be father of your own babies?
Don't imagine it.
There'll be babies born that are cygnets, O my soul!
young wild swans!
And babies of women will come out young wild geese, O my heart!
the geese that saved Rome, and will lose London.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061109">
<head>
   <title>Let the Dead Bury their Dead</title>
   <toctitle>Let the Dead Bury their Dead</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Let the Dead Bury their Dead</indextitle>
   <firstline>Let the dead go bury their dead</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Let the dead go bury their dead
don't help them.
Let the dead look after the dead
leave them to one another,
don't serve them.

The dead in their nasty dead hands
have heaps of money,
don't take it.

The dead in their seething minds
have phosphorescent teeming white words
of putrescent wisdom and sapience that subtly stinks;
don't ever believe them.

The dead are in myriads, they seem mighty.
They make trains chuff, motor-cars titter, ships lurch,
mills grind on and on,
and keep you in millions at the mills, sightless pale slaves,
pretending these are the mills of God.

It is the great lie of the dead.
The mills of industry are not the mills of God.
And the mills of God grind otherwise, with the winds of life for the mill-stones.
Trust the mills of God, though they grind exceeding small.
But as for the mills of men
don't be harnessed to them.

The dead give ships and engines, cinema, radio and gramophone,
they send aeroplanes across the sky,
and they say: Now, behold, you are living the great life!
While you listen in, while you watch the film, while you drive the car,
while you read about the air-ship crossing the wild Atlantic
behold, you are living the great life, the stupendous life!

As you know, it is a complete lie.
You are all going dead and corpse-pale
listening in to the lie.
Spit it out.

O cease to listen to the living dead.
They are only greedy for your life!
O cease to labour for the gold-toothed dead,
they are so greedy, yet so helpless if not worked for.
Don't ever be kind to the smiling, tooth-mouthed dead
don't ever be kind to the dead
it is pandering to corpses,
the repulsive, living fat dead.

Bury a man gently if he has lain down and died.
But with the walking and talking and conventionally persuasive dead
with bank accounts and insurance policies
don't sympathise, or you taint the unborn babies.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061110">
<head>
   <title>We are Transmitters</title>
   <toctitle>We are Transmitters</toctitle>
   <indextitle>We are Transmitters</indextitle>
   <firstline>As we live, we are transmitters of life</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
As we live, we are transmitters of life.
And when we fail to transmit life, life fails to flow through us.

That is part of the mystery of sex, it is a flow onwards.
Sexless people transmit nothing.

And if, as we work, we can transmit life into our work,
life, still more life, rushes into us to compensate, to be ready
and we ripple with life through the days.

Even if it is a woman making an apple dumpling, or a man a stool,
if life goes into the pudding, good is the pudding
good is the stool,
content is the woman, with fresh life rippling in to her,
content is the man.

Give, and it shall be given unto you
is still the truth about life.
But giving life is not so easy.
It doesn't mean handing it out to some mean fool, or letting the living dead eat you up.
It means kindling the life-quality where it was not,
even if it's only in the whiteness of a washed pocket-handkerchief.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061111">
<head>
   <title>Let us be Men</title>
   <toctitle>Let us be Men</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Let us be Men</indextitle>
   <firstline>For God's sake, let us be men</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1,korrektur2</quality>
</head>
<body>
For God's sake, let us be men
not monkeys minding machines
or sitting with our tails curled
while the machine amuses us, the radio or film or gramophone.

Monkeys with a bland grin on our faces.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061760">
<head>
   <title>Good husbands Make Unhappy Wives</title>
   <toctitle>Good husbands Make Unhappy Wives</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Good husbands Make Unhappy Wives</indextitle>
   <firstline>Good husbands make unhappy wives</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Good husbands make unhappy wives
so do bad husbands, just as often;
but the unhappiness of a wife with a good husband
is much more devastating
than the unhappiness of a wife with a bad husband.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061112">
<head>
   <title>The Elephant is Slow to Mate</title>
   <toctitle>The Elephant is Slow to Mate</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Elephant is Slow to Mate</indextitle>
   <firstline>The elephant, the huge old beast</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The elephant, the huge old beast,
               is slow to mate;
he finds a female, they show no haste
               they wait

for the sympathy in their vast shy hearts
               slowly, slowly to rouse
as they loiter along the river-beds
               and drink and browse

and dash in panic through the brake
               of forest with the herd,
and sleep in massive silence, and wake
               together, without a word.

So slowly the great hot elephant hearts
               grow full of desire,
and the great beasts mate in secret at last,
               hiding their fire.

Oldest they are and the wisest of beasts
               so they know at last
how to wait for the loneliest of feasts
               for the full repast.

They do not snatch, they do not tear;
               their massive blood
moves as the moon-tides, near, more near,
               till they touch in flood.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061113">
<head>
   <title>Self-Pity</title>
   <toctitle>Self-Pity</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Self-Pity</indextitle>
   <firstline>I never saw a wild thing</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I never saw a wild thing
sorry for itself.
A small bird will drop frozen dead from a bough
without ever having felt sorry for itself.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061114">
<head>
   <title>Kill Money</title>
   <toctitle>Kill Money</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Kill Money</indextitle>
   <firstline>Kill money, put money out of existence</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Kill money, put money out of existence.
It is a perverted instinct, a hidden thought
which rots the brain, the blood, the bones, the stones, the soul.

Make up your mind about it:
that society must establish itself upon a different principle
from the one we've got now.

We must have the courage of mutual trust.
We must have the modesty of simple living.
And the individual must have his house, food and fire all free like a bird.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061115">
<head>
   <title>My Naughty Book</title>
   <toctitle>My Naughty Book</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My Naughty Book</indextitle>
   <firstline>They say I wrote a naughty book</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
They say I wrote a naughty book
With perfectly awful things in it,
putting in all the impossible words
like b--- and f--- and sh---.

Most of my friends were deeply hurt
and haven't forgiven me yet;
I'd loaded the camel's back before
with dirt they couldn't forget.

And now, no really, the final straw
was words like sh--- and f---!
I heard the camel's back to crack
beneath the weight of muck.

Then out of nowhere rushed John Bull,
that mildewed pup, good doggie!
squeakily bellowing for all he was worth,
and slavering wet and soggy.

He couldn't bite 'em he was much too old,
but he made a pool of dribblings;
so while the other one heaved her sides
with moans and hollow bibblings.

He did his best, the good old dog
to support her, the hysterical camel,
and everyone listened and loved it, the
ridiculous bimmel-bammel.

But still, one has no right to take
the old dog's greenest bones
that he's buried now for centuries
beneath England's garden stones.

And, of course, one has no right to lay
such words to the camel's charge,
when she prefers to have them left
in the W.C. writ large.

Poor homely words. I must give you back
to the camel and the dog,
for her to mumble and him to crack
in secret, great golliwog!

And hereby I apologise
to all my foes and friends
for using words they privately keep
for their own immortal ends.

And henceforth I will never use
more than the chaste, short dash;
so do forgive me! I sprinkle my hair
with grey, repentant ash.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061761">
<head>
   <title>When I Read Shakespeare</title>
   <toctitle>When I Read Shakespeare</toctitle>
   <indextitle>When I Read Shakespeare</indextitle>
   <firstline>When I read Shakespeare I am struck with wonder</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When I read Shakespeare I am struck with wonder
that such trivial people should muse and thunder
in such lovely language.

Lear, the old buffer, you wonder his daughters
didn't treat him rougher,
the old chough, the old chuffer!

And Hamlet, how boring, how boring to live with,
so mean and self-conscious, blowing and snoring
his wonderful speeches, full of other folks' whoring!

And Macbeth and his Lady, who should have been choring,
such suburban ambition, so messily goring
old Duncan with daggers!

How boring, how small Shakespeare's people are!
Yet the language so lovely! like the dyes from gas-tar.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061762">
<head>
   <title>The Grudge of the Old</title>
   <toctitle>The Grudge of the Old</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Grudge of the Old</indextitle>
   <firstline>The old ones want to be young, and they aren't young</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The old ones want to be young, and they aren't young,
and it rankles, they ache when they see the young,
and they can't help wanting to spite it on them
venomously.

The old ones say to themselves: We are not going to be old,
we are not going to make way, we are not going to die,
we are going to stay on and on and on and on and on
and make the young look after us
till they are old. We are stronger than the young.
We have more energy, and our grip on life is harder.
Let us triumph, and let the young be listless
with their puny youth.
We are younger even now than the young, we can put their youth in abeyance.

And it is true.
And they do it.
And so it goes on.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061116">
<head>
   <title>Beautiful Old Age</title>
   <toctitle>Beautiful Old Age</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Beautiful Old Age</indextitle>
   <firstline>It ought to be lovely to be old</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
It ought to be lovely to be old
to be full of the peace that comes of experience
and wrinkled ripe fulfilment.

The wrinkled smile of completeness that follows a life
lived undaunted and unsoured with accepted lies
If people lived without accepting lies
they would ripen like apples, and be scented like pippins
in their old age.

Soothing, old people should be, like apples
when one is tired of love.
Fragrant like yellowing leaves, and dim with the soft
stillness and satisfaction of autumn.

And a girl should say:
It must be wonderful to live and grow old.
Look at my mother, how rich and still she is!

And a young man should think: By Jove
my father has faced all weathers, but it's been a life!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061117">
<head>
   <title>Courage</title>
   <toctitle>Courage</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Courage</indextitle>
   <firstline>What makes people unsatisfied</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
What makes people unsatisfied
is that they accept lies.

If people had courage, and refused lies
and found out what they really felt and really meant
and acted on it,

They would distil the essential oil out of every experience
and like hazel-nuts in autumn, at last
be sweet and sound.

And the young among the old
would be as in the hazel-woods of September
nutting, gathering nuts of ripe experience.

As it is, all that the old can offer
is sour, bitter fruits, cankered by lies.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061201">
<head>
   <title>Desire is Dead</title>
   <toctitle>Desire is Dead</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Desire is Dead</indextitle>
   <firstline>Desire may be dead</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Desire may be dead
and still a man can be
a meeting place for sun and rain,
wonder outwaiting pain
as in a wintry tree.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061118">
<head>
   <title>Dies Irae</title>
   <toctitle>Dies Irae</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Dies Irae</indextitle>
   <firstline>Even the old emotions are finished</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Even the old emotions are finished,
we have worn them out.
And desire is dead.
And the end of all things is inside us.

Our epoch is over,
a cycle of evolution is finished,
our activity has lost its meaning,
we are ghosts, we are seed;
for our word is dead
and we know not how to live wordless.

We live in a vast house
full of inordinate activities,
and the noise, and the stench, and the dreariness and lack of meaning
madden us, but we don't know what to do.

All we can know at this moment
is the fulfilment of nothingness.
Lo, I am nothing!

It is a consummation devoutly to be wished
in this world of mechanical self-assertion.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061119">
<head>
   <title>The Death of our Era</title>
   <toctitle>The Death of our Era</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Death of our Era</indextitle>
   <firstline>Our era is dying</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Our era is dying
yet who has killed it?
Have we, who are it?

In the middle of voluted space
its knell has struck.
And in the middle of every atom, which is the same thing,
a tiny bell of conclusion has sounded.

The curfew of our great day
the passing-bell of our way of knowing
the knell of our bald-headed consciousness
the tocsin of this our civilisation.

Who has struck the bell?
Who rang the knell?
Not I, not you,
yet all of us.

At the core of space the final knell
of our era has struck, and it chimes
in terrible rippling circles between the stars
till it reaches us, and its vibrations shatter us
each time they touch us.

And they keep on coming, with greater force
striking us, the vibrations of our finish.

And all that we can do
is to die the amazing death
with every stroke, and go on
till we are blank.

And yet, as we die, why should not our vast mechanised day die with us,
so that when we are re-born, we can be born into a fresh world.

For the new word is Resurrection.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061120">
<head>
   <title>The Optimist</title>
   <toctitle>The Optimist</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Optimist</indextitle>
   <firstline>The optimist builds himself safe inside a cell</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The optimist builds himself safe inside a cell
and paints the inside walls sky-blue
and blocks up the door
and says he's in heaven.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061121">
<head>
   <title>A Sane Revolution</title>
   <toctitle>A Sane Revolution</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Sane Revolution</indextitle>
   <firstline>If you make a revolution, make it for fun</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If you make a revolution, make it for fun,
don't make it in ghastly seriousness,
don't do it in deadly earnest,
do it for fun.

Don't do it because you hate people,
do it just to spit in their eye.

Don't do it for the money,
do it and be damned to the money.

Don't do it for equality,
do it because we've got too much equality
and it would be fun to upset the apple-cart
and see which way the apples would go a-rolling.

Don't do it for the working classes.
Do it so that we can all of us be little aristocracies on our own
and kick our heels like jolly escaped asses.

Don't do it, anyhow, for international Labour.
Labour is the one thing a man has had too much of.
Let's abolish labour, let's have done with labouring!
Work can be fun, and men can enjoy it; then it's not labour.
Let's have it so! Let's make a revolution for fun!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061122">
<head>
   <title>Poor Young Things</title>
   <toctitle>Poor Young Things</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Poor Young Things</indextitle>
   <firstline>The young to-day are born prisoners</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The young to-day are born prisoners,
poor things, and they know it.
Born in a universal workhouse,
and they feel it.
Inheriting a sort of confinement,
work, and prisoners' routine
and prisoners' flat, ineffectual pastime.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061123">
<head>
   <title>Wages</title>
   <toctitle>Wages</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Wages</indextitle>
   <firstline>The wages of work is cash</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The wages of work is cash.
The wages of cash is want more cash.
The wages of want more cash is vicious competition.
The wages of vicious competition is - the world we live in.

The work-cash-want circle is the viciousest circle
that ever turned men into fiends.

Earning a wage is a prison occupation
and a wage-earner is a sort of gaol-bird.
Earning a salary is a prison overseer's job,
a gaoler instead of a gaol-bird.

Living on your income is strolling grandly outside the prison
in terror lest you have to go in. And since the work-prison covers
almost every scrap of the living earth, you stroll up and down
on a narrow beat, about the same as a prisoner taking his exercise.

This is called universal freedom.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061124">
<head>
   <title>A Tale Told By an Idiot</title>
   <toctitle>A Tale Told By an Idiot</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Tale Told By an Idiot</indextitle>
   <firstline>Modern life is a tale told by an idiot</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Modern life is a tale told by an idiot;
flat-chested, crop-headed, chemicalised women, of indeterminate sex,
and wimbly-wambly young men, of sex still more indeterminate,
and hygienic babies in huge hulks of coffin-like perambulators -
The great social idiot, it must be confessed,
tells dull, meaningless, disgusting tales,
and repeats himself like the flushing of a W.C.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061125">
<head>
   <title>Being Alive</title>
   <toctitle>Being Alive</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Being Alive</indextitle>
   <firstline>The only reason for living is being fully alive</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The only reason for living is being fully alive;
and you can't be fully alive if you are crushed by secret fear,
and bullied with the threat: Get money, or eat dirt! -
and forced to do a thousand mean things meaner than your nature,
and forced to clutch on to possessions in the hope they'll make you feel safe,
and forced to watch everyone that comes near you, lest they've come to do you down.

Without a bit of common trust in one another, we can't live.
In the end, we go insane.
It is the penalty of fear and meanness, being meaner than our natures are.

To be alive, you've got to feel a generous flow,
and under a competitive system that is impossible, really.
The world is waiting for a new great movement of generosity,
or for a great wave of death.
We must change the system, and make living free to all men,
or we must see men die, and the die ourselves.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061763">
<head>
   <title>Relativity</title>
   <toctitle>Relativity</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Relativity</indextitle>
   <firstline>I like relativity and quantum theories</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I like relativity and quantum theories
because I don't understand them
and they make me feel as if space shifted about like a swan that can't settle,
refusing to sit still and be measured;
and as if the atom were an impulsive thing
always changing its mind.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061202">
<head>
   <title>Now it's Happened</title>
   <toctitle>Now it's Happened</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Now it's Happened</indextitle>
   <firstline>One cannot now help thinking</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
One cannot now help thinking
how much better it would have been
if Vronsky and Anna Karenin
had stood up for themselves, and seen
Russia across her crisis,
instead of leaving it to Lenin.

The big, flamboyant Russia
might have been saved, if a pair
of rebels like Anna and Vronsky
had blasted the sickly air
of Dostoevsky and Tchekov,
and spy-government everywhere.

But Tolstoi was a traitor
to the Russia that needed him most,
the clumsy, bewildered Russia
so worried by the Holy Ghost.
He shifted his job on to the peasants
and landed them all on toast.

Dostoevsky, the Judas,
with his sham christianity
epileptically ruined
the last bit of sanity
left in the hefty bodies
of the Russian nobility.

So our goody-good men betray us
and our sainty-saints let us down,
and a sickly people will slay us
if we touch the sob-stuff crown
of such martyrs; while Marxian tenets
naturally take hold of the town.

Too much of the humble Willy wet-leg
and the holy can't-help-it touch,
till you've ruined a nation's fibre
and they loathe all feeling as such,
and want to be cold and devilish hard
like machines - and you can't wonder much.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061203">
<head>
   <title>Know Thyself, and That Thou Art Mortal</title>
   <toctitle>Know Thyself, and That Thou Art Mortal</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Know Thyself, and That Thou Art Mortal</indextitle>
   <firstline>If you want to know yourself</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If you want to know yourself
you've got to keep up with yourself.
Your self moves on, and is not to-day what it was yesterday;
and you've got to run, to keep up with it.

But sometimes we run ahead too fast
running after a figment of ourselves.
And that's what we've done to-day.

We think we're such clever little johnnies
with our sharp little eyes and our high-power machines
which get us ahead so much faster than our feet could ever carry us.

When alas, it's only part of our clever little self that gets ahead!
Something is left behind, lost and howling, and we know it.

Ah, clever Odysseus who outwitted the cyclop
and blinded him in his one big eye,
put out a light of consciousness and left a blinded brute.

Clever little ants in spectacles, we are,
performing our antics.

But what we also are, and we need to know it,
is blinded brutes of cyclops, with our cyclopean eye put out.

And we still bleed, and we grope and roar;
for spectacles and bulging clever ant-eyes are no good to the cyclop,
he wants his one great wondering eye, the eye of the cavern and the portent.

As little social ants perhaps we function all right.
But oh, our human lives, the lunging blind cyclops we are!
hitting ourselves against unseen rock, crashing our head against the roof
of the ancient cave, smashing into one another,
tearing each other's feelings, trampling each other's tenderest emotions to mud
and never knowing what we are doing, roaring blind with pain and dismay.

Ah, cyclops, the little ant-men can never enlighten you
with their bulging policeman's-lamp eyes.
You need your own great wondering eye that flashes with instinct in the cavern
and gleams on the world with the warm dark vision of intuition!

Even our brilliantest young intellectuals
are also poor blind cyclops, moaning
with all the hurt to their instinctive and emotional selves,
and grieving with puppy-like blind crying
over their mutilated cyclopean eye.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061204">
<head>
   <title>Stand Up!</title>
   <toctitle>Stand Up!</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Stand Up!</indextitle>
   <firstline>Stand up, but not for Jesus!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Stand up, but not for Jesus!
It's a little late for that.
Stand up for justice and a jolly life.
I'll hold your hat.

Stand up, stand up for justice,
ye swindled little blokes!
Stand up and do some punching,
give 'em a few hard pokes.

Stand up for jolly justice
you haven't got much to lose:
a job you don't like and a scanty chance
for a dreary little booze.

Stand up for something different,
and have a little fun
fighting for something worth fighting for
before you've done.

Stand up for a new arrangement
for a chance of life all round
for freedom, and the fun of living
bust in, and hold the ground!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061205">
<head>
   <title>Be a Demon!</title>
   <toctitle>Be a Demon!</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Be a Demon!</indextitle>
   <firstline>Oh be a demon</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Oh be a demon
outside all class!
If you're a woman
or even an ass
still be a demon
beyond the mass.

Somewhere inside you
lives your own little fiend,
and woe betide you
if he feels demeaned,
better do him justice,
keep his path well cleaned.

When you've been being
too human, too long,
and your demon starts lashing out
going it strong,
don't get too frightened
it's you who've been wrong.

You're not altogether
such a human bird,
you're as mixed as the weather,
not just a good turd,
so shut up pie-jaw blether,
let your demon be heard.

Don't look for a saviour,
you've had some, you know!
Drop your sloppy behaviour
and start in to show
your demon rump twinkling
with a hie! hop below!

If, poor little bleeder,
you still feel you must follow
some wonderful leader
now the old ones ring hollow,
then follow your demon
and hark to his <i>holloa</i>!
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
