<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="1930" author="lawrence" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Nettles</title>
   <year>1930</year>
   <notes>
      <note type="credits">Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="lawrence2001061405">
<head>
   <title>13,000 People</title>
   <toctitle>13,000 People</toctitle>
   <indextitle>13,000 People</indextitle>
   <firstline>Thirteen thousand people came to see</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Thirteen thousand people came to see
my pictures, eager as the honey bee

for the flowers; and I'll tell you what
all eyes sought the same old spot

in every picture, every time,
and gazed and gloated without rhyme

or reason, where the leaf should be
the fig-leaf that was not, woe is me!

And they blushed, they giggled, they sniggered, they leered,
or they boiled and they fumed, in fury they sneered

and said: Oh boy! I tell you what,
look at that one there, that's pretty hot! -

And they stared and they stared, the half-witted lot
at the spot where the fig-leaf just was not!

But why, I ask you? Oh tell me why?
Aren't they made quite the same, then, as you and I?

Can it be they've been trimmed, so they've never seen
the innocent member that a fig-leaf will screen?

What's the matter with them? aren't they women and men?
or is something missing? or what's wrong with them then?

that they stared and leered at the single spot
where a fig-leaf might have been, and was not.

I thought it was a commonplace
that a man or a woman in a state of grace

<i>in puris naturalibus</i>, don't you see,
had normal pudenda, like you and me.

But it can't be so, for they behaved
like lunatics looking, they bubbled and raved

or gloated or peeped at the simple spot
where a fig-leaf might have been, but was not.

I tell you, there must be something wrong
with my fellow-countrymen; or else I don't belong.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061206">
<head>
   <title>My Little Critics</title>
   <toctitle>My Little Critics</toctitle>
   <indextitle>My Little Critics</indextitle>
   <firstline>My little critics must all have been brought up by their Aunties</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My little critics must all have been brought up by their Aunties
who petted them, and had them fixed
to save them from undesirable associations.

It must be so. Otherwise
the sight of an ordinary Tom wouldn't send them into such silly hysterics,
my little critics, dear, safe little pets.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061401">
<head>
   <title>Question</title>
   <toctitle>Question</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Question</indextitle>
   <firstline>Was your's a daddy</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Was your's a daddy
or a Daddy-do-nothing?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061402">
<head>
   <title>Modern Prayer</title>
   <toctitle>Modern Prayer</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Modern Prayer</indextitle>
   <firstline>Almighty Mammon, make me rich!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Almighty Mammon, make me rich!
Make me rich quickly, with never a hitch
in my fine prosperity! Kick those in the ditch
who hinder me, Mammon, great son of a bitch!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061403">
<head>
   <title>What Have They Done to You -?</title>
   <toctitle>What Have They Done to You -?</toctitle>
   <indextitle>What Have They Done to You -?</indextitle>
   <firstline>What have they done to you, men of the masses</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
What have they done to you, men of the masses
creeping back and forth to work?

What have they done to you, the saviours of the people?
Oh what have they saved you from?

Alas, they have saved you from yourself,
from your own body, saved you from living your own life.

And given you this jig-jig-jig
tick-tick-ticking of machines,
this life which is no-man's-life.

Oh a no-man's-life in a no-man's-land
this is what they've given you
in place of your own life.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061404">
<head>
   <title>The People</title>
   <toctitle>The People</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The People</indextitle>
   <firstline>Ah the people, the people!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Ah the people, the people!
surely they are flesh of my flesh!

When, in the streets of the working quarters
they stream past, stream past, going to work;

then, when I see the iron hooked in their faces,
their poor, their fearful faces

then I scream in my soul, for I know I cannot
cut the iron hook out of their faces, that makes them so drawn,
nor cut the invisible wires of steel that pull them

back and forth to work,
back and forth, to work

like fearful and corpse-like fishes hooked and being played
by some malignant fisherman on an unseen, safe shore
where he does not choose to land them yet, hooked fishes of the factory world.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
