<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE kalliopework SYSTEM "../../data/kalliopework.dtd">
<kalliopework id="rhyming" author="lawrence" status="complete" type="poetry">
<workhead>
   <title>Rhyming Poems (1913-28)</title>
   <year>?</year>
   <notes>
      <note type="credits">Bidrag fra Brian Bentsen.</note>
   </notes>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
   <cvs-timestamp>$Id$</cvs-timestamp>
</workhead>
<workbody>

<poem id="lawrence2001061207">
<head>
   <title>The Wild Common</title>
   <toctitle>The Wild Common</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Wild Common</indextitle>
   <firstline>The quick sparks on the gorse-bushes are leaping</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The quick sparks on the gorse-bushes are leaping
Little jets of sunlight texture imitating flame;
Above them, exultant, the peewits are sweeping:
They have triumphed again o'er the ages, their screamings proclaim.

Rabbits, handfuls of brown earth, lie
Low-rounded on the mournful turf they have bitten down to the quick.
Are they asleep? - are they living? - Now see, when I
Lift my arms, the hill bursts and heaves under their spurting kick!

The common flaunts bravely; but below, from the rushes
Crowds of glittering king-cups surge to challenge the blossoming bushes;
There the lazy streamlet pushes
His bent course mildly; here wakes again, leaps, laughs, and gushes

Into a deep pond, an old sheep-dip,
Dark, overgrown with willows, cool, with the brook ebbing through so slow;
Naked on the steep, soft lip
Of the turf I stand watching my own white shadow quivering to and fro.

What if the gorse-flowers shrivelled, and I were gone?
What if the waters ceased, where were the marigolds then, and the gudgeon?
What is this thing that I look down upon?
White on the water wimples my shadow, strains like a dog on a string, to run on.

How it looks back, like a white dog to its master!
I on the bank all substance, my shadow all shadow looking up to me, looking back!
And the water runs, and runs faster, runs faster,
And the white dog dances and quivers, I am holding his cord quite slack.

But how splendid it is to be substance, here!
My shadow is neither here nor there; but I, I am royally here!
I am here! I am here! screams the peewit; the may-blobs burst out in a laugh as they hear!
Here! flick the rabbits. Here! pants the gorse. Here! say the insects far and near.

Over my skin in the sunshine, the warm, clinging air,
Flushed with the songs of seven larks singing at once, goes kissing me glad.
You are here! You are here! We have found you! Everywhere
We sought you substantial, you touchstone of caresses, you naked lad!

Oh but the water loves me and folds me,
Plays with me, sways me, lifts me and sinks me, murmurs: Oh marvellous stuff!
No longer shadow! - and it holds me
Close, and it rolls me, enfolds me, touches me, as if never it could touch me enough.

Sun, but in substance, yellow water-blobs!
Wings and feathers on the crying, mysterious ages, peewits wheeling!
All that is right, all that is good, all that is God takes substance! a rabbit lobs
In confirmation, I hear sevenfold lark-songs pealing.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061208">
<head>
   <title>From a College Window</title>
   <toctitle>From a College Window</toctitle>
   <indextitle>From a College Window</indextitle>
   <firstline>The glimmer of the limes, sun-heavy, sleeping</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The glimmer of the limes, sun-heavy, sleeping,
   Goes trembling past me up the College wall.
Below, the lawn, in soft blue shade is keeping
   The daisy-froth quiescent, softly in thrall.

Beyond the leaves that overhang the street,
   Along the flagged, clean pavement summer-white,
Passes the world with shadows at their feet
   Going left and right.

Remote, although I hear the beggar's cough,
   See the woman's twinkling fingers tend him a coin,
I sit absolved, assured I am better off
   Beyond a world I never want to join.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061217">
<head>
   <title>Discord in Childhood</title>
   <toctitle>Discord in Childhood</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Discord in Childhood</indextitle>
   <firstline>Outside the house an ash-tree hung its terrible whips</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Outside the house an ash-tree hung its terrible whips,
And at night when the wind rose, the lash of the tree
Shrieked and slashed the wind, as a ship's
Weird rigging in a storm shrieks hideously.

Within the house two voices arose, a slender lash
Whistling she-delirious rage, and the dreadful sound
Of a male thong booming and bruising, until it had drowned
The other voice in a silence of blood, 'neath the noise of the ash.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061209">
<head>
   <title>Virgin Youth</title>
   <toctitle>Virgin Youth</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Virgin Youth</indextitle>
   <firstline>Now and again</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Now and again
The life that looks through my eyes
And quivers in words through my mouth,
And behaves like the rest of men,
Slips away, so I gasp in surprise.

And then
My unknown breasts begin
To wake, and down the thin
Ripples below the breast an urgent
Rhythm starts, and my silent and slumberous belly
In one moment rouses insurgent.

My soft, slumbering belly
Quivering awake with one impulse and one will,
Then willy nilly
A lower gets up and greets me;
Homunculus stirs from his roots, and strives until,
Risen up, he beats me.

He stands, and I tremble before him.
- Who then art thou? -
He is wordless, but sultry and vast,
And I can't deplore him.
- Who art thou? What hast
Thou to do with me, thou lustrous one, iconoclast? -

How beautiful he is! without sound,
Without eyes, without hands;
Yet, flame of the living ground
He stands, the column of fire by night.
And he knows from the depths; he quite
Alone understands.

Quite alone, he alone
Understands and knows.
Lustrously sure, unknown
Out of nowhere he rose.

I tremble in his shadow, as he burns
For the dark goal.
He stands like a lighthouse, night churns
Round his base, his dark light rolls
Into darkness, and darkly returns.

Is he calling, the lone one? Is his deep
Silence full of summons?
Is he moving invisibly? Does his steep
Curve sweep towards a woman's?

Traveller, column of fire,
It is vain.
The glow of thy full desire
Becomes pain.

Dark, ruddy pillar, forgive me! I
Am helplessly bound
To the rock of virginity. Thy
Strange voice has no sound.

We cry in the wilderness. Forgive me, I
Would so gladly lie
In the womanly valley, and ply
Thy twofold dance.

Thou dark one, thou pride, curved beauty! I
Would worship thee, letting my buttocks prance.
But the hosts of men with one voice deny
Me the chance.

They have taken the gates from the hinges
And built up the way. I salute thee
But to deflower thee. Thy tower impinges
On nothingness. Pardon me!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061210">
<head>
   <title>Study</title>
   <toctitle>Study</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Study</indextitle>
   <firstline>Somewhere the long mellow note of the blackbird</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Somewhere the long mellow note of the blackbird
Quickens the unclasping hands of hazel.
Somewhere the wind-flowers fling their heads back
Stirred by an impetuous wind. Some ways'll
All be sweet with white and blue violet -
    (<i>Hush now, hush! Where am I? - Biuret -</i>)

On the green wood's edge a shy girl hovers
From out of the hazel-screen on to the grass,
Where wheeling and screaming the petulant plovers
Wave frighted. - Who comes? - A labourer, alas!
Oh the sunset swims in her eyes' swift pool.
    (<i>Work, work, you foo-</i>)

Somewhere the lamp hanging low from the ceiling
Lights the soft hair of a girl as she reads,
And the red firelight steadily reeling
Puts the hard hands of my friend in sleep.
And the white dog snuffs the warmth, appealing
For the man to heed lest the girl shall weep.

    Tears and dreams for them; for me
    Bitter science - the exams are near.
    I wish I bore it more willingly!
    I wish you did not wait, my dear,
    For me to come; since work I must.
    Though it's all the same when we are dead -
              I wish I was only a bust,
                        All head - !
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061211">
<head>
   <title>Love on the Farm</title>
   <toctitle>Love on the Farm</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Love on the Farm</indextitle>
   <firstline>What large, dark hands are those at the window</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
What large, dark hands are those at the window
Grasping in the golden light
Which weaves its way through the evening wind
       At my heart to-night?

Ah, only the leaves! But in the west
I see a redness suddenly come
Into the evening's anxious breast -
       'Tis the wound of love goes home!

The woodbine creeps abroad
 Calling low to her lover:
   The sun-lit flirt who all the day
   Has poised above her lips in play
   And stolen kisses, shallow and gay
   Of pollen, now has gone away -
      She woos the moth with her sweet, low word:
And when above her his moth-wings hover
 Then her bright breast she will uncover
 And yeild her honey-drop to her lover.

Into the yellow, evening glow
 Saunters a man from the farm below;
Leans, and looks in at the low-built shed
 Where the swallow has hung her marriage bed.
   The bird lies warm against the wall.
   She glances quick her startled eyes
   Towards him, then she turns away
   Her small head, making warm display
   Of red upon the throat. Her terrors sway
   Her out of the nest's warm, busy ball,
   Whose plaintive cry is heard as she flies
   In one blue stoop from out the sties
   Into the twilight's empty hall.

Oh, water-hen, beside the rushes
 Hide your quaintly scarlet blushes,
 Still your quick tail, lie still as dead,
 Till the distance folds over his ominous tread!

The rabbit presses back her ears,
Turns back her liquid, anguished eyes
And crouches low; then with wild spring
Spurts from the terror of <i>his</i> oncoming;
To be choked back, the wire ring
Her frantic effort throttling:
    Piteous brown ball of quivering fears!
Ah soon in his large, hard hands she dies,
And swings all loose to the swing of his walk!
Yet calm and kindly are his eyes
And ready to open in brown surprise
Should I not answer to his talk
Or should he my tears surmise.

I hear his hand on the latch, and rise from my chair
Watching the door open; he flashes bare
His strong teeth in a smile, and flashes his eyes
In a smile like triumph upon me; then careless-wise
He flings the rabbit soft on the table board
And comes towards me: ah! the uplifted sword
Of his hand against my bosom! and oh, the broad
Blade of his hand that asks me to applaud
His coming! With his hand he turns my face to him
And caresses me with his fingers that still smell grim
Of the rabbit's fur! God, I am caught in a snare!
I know not what fine wire is round my throat;
I only know I let him finger there
My pulse of life, letting him nose like a stoat
Who sniffs with joy before he drinks the blood.

And down his mouth comes to my mouth! and down
His bright dark eyes come over me, like a hood
Upon my mind! his lips meet mine, and a flood
Of sweet fire sweeps across me, so I drown
Against him, die, and find death good.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061212">
<head>
   <title>Gipsy</title>
   <toctitle>Gipsy</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Gipsy</indextitle>
   <firstline>I, the man with the red scarf</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I, the man with the red scarf,
       Will give thee what I have, this last week's earnings.
Take them, and buy thee a silver ring
       And wed me, to ease my yearnings.

For the rest, when thou art wedded
       I'll wet my brow for thee
With sweat, I'll enter a house for thy sake,
       Thou shalt shut doors on me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061213">
<head>
   <title>Flapper</title>
   <toctitle>Flapper</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Flapper</indextitle>
   <firstline>Love has crept out of her sealèd heart</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Love has crept out of her sealèd heart
       As a field-bee, black and amber,
       Breaks from the winter-cell, to clamber
Up the warm grass where the sunbeams start.

Mischief has come in her dawning eyes,
       And a glint of coloured iris brings
       Such as lies along the folded wings
Of the bee before he flies.

Who, with a ruffling, careful breath,
       Has opened the wings of the wild young sprite?
       Has fluttered her spirit to stumbling flight
In her eyes, as a young bee stumbleth?

Love makes the burden of her voice.
       The hum of his heavy, staggering wings
       Sets quivering with wisdom the common things
That she says, and her words rejoice.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061214">
<head>
   <title>Thief in the Night</title>
   <toctitle>Thief in the Night</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Thief in the Night</indextitle>
   <firstline>Last night a thief came to me</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Last night a thief came to me
       And struck at me with something dark.
I cried, but no one could hear me,
       I lay dumb and stark.

When I awoke this morning
       I could find no trace;
Perhaps 'twas a dream of warning,
       For I've lost my peace.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061215">
<head>
   <title>Monologue of a Mother</title>
   <toctitle>Monologue of a Mother</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Monologue of a Mother</indextitle>
   <firstline>This is the last of all, then, this is the last!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
This is the last of all, then, this is the last!
I must fold my hands, and turn my face to the fire,
And watch my dead days fusing together in dross,
Shape after shape, and scene after scene of my past
Clotting to one dead mass in the sinking fire
Where ash on the dying coals grows swiftly, like heavy moss.

Strange he is, my son, whom I have waited like a lover;
Strange to me, like a captive in a foreign country, haunting
The confines, gazing out beyond, where the winds go free;
White and gaunt, with wistful eyes that hover
Always on the distance, as if his soul were chaunting
The monotonous weird of departure away from me.

Like a thin white bird blown out of the northern seas,
Like a bird from the far north blown with a broken wing
Into our sooty garden, he drags and beats
Along the fence perpetually, seeking release
From me, from the hand of my love which creeps up, needing
His happiness, whilst he in displeasure retreats.

I must look away from him, for my faded eyes
Like a cringing dog at his heels offend him now,
Like a toothless hound pursuing him with my will;
Till he chafes at my crouching persistence, and a sharp spark flies
In my soul from under the sudden frown of his brow
As he blenches and turns away, and my heart stands still.

This is the last, it will not be any more.
All my life I have borne the burden of myself,
All the long years of sitting in my husband's house;
Never have I said to myself as he closed the door:
"Now I am caught! You are hopelessly lost, O Self!
You are frightened with joy, my heart, like a frightened mouse."

Three times have I offered myself, three times rejected.
It will not be any more. No more, my son, my son! -
Never to know the glad freedom of obedience, since long ago
The angel of childhood kissed me and went! I expected
This last one to claim me; - and now, my son, O my son,
I must sit alone and wait, and never know
The loss of myself, till death comes, who cannot fail.

Death, in whose service is nothing of gladness, takes me;
For the lips and the eyes of God are behind a veil.
And the thought of the lipless voice of the Father shakes me
With dread, and fills my heart with the tears of desire,
And my heart rebels with anguish as night draws nigher.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061216">
<head>
   <title>In a Boat</title>
   <toctitle>In a Boat</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In a Boat</indextitle>
   <firstline>See the stars, love</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
See the stars, love,
In the water much clearer and brighter
Than those above us, and whiter,
Like nenuphars!

Star-shadows shine, love:
How many stars in your bowl?
How many shadows in your soul?
Only mine, love, mine?

When I move the oars, see
How the stars are tossed,
Distorted, even lost!
Even yours, do you see?

The poor waters spill
The stars, waters troubled, forsaken! -
The heavens are not shaken, you say, love;
Its stars stand still.

There! did you see
That spark fly up at us? even
Stars are not safe in heaven!
What of me then, love, me?

What then, love, if soon
Your star be tossed over a wave?
Will the darkness look like a grave?
Would you swoon, love, swoon?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061501">
<head>
   <title>Flat Suburbs, S.W., in the Morning</title>
   <toctitle>Flat Suburbs, S.W., in the Morning</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Flat Suburbs, S.W., in the Morning</indextitle>
   <firstline>The new red houses spring like plants</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The new red houses spring like plants
      In level rows
Of reddish herbage that bristles and slants
      Its square shadows.

The pink young houses show one side bright
      Flatly assuming the sun,
And one side shadow, half in sight,
      Half-hiding the pavement-run;

Where hastening creatures pass intent
      On their level way,
Threading like ants that can never relent
      And have nothing to say.

Bare stems of street lamps stiffly stand
      At random, desolate twigs,
To testify to a blight on the land
      That has stripped their sprigs.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061502">
<head>
   <title>Suburbs on a Hazy Day</title>
   <toctitle>Suburbs on a Hazy Day</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Suburbs on a Hazy Day</indextitle>
   <firstline>O stiffly shapen houses that change not</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
O stiffly shapen houses that change not,
        What conjurer's cloth was thrown across you, and raised
To show you thus transfigured, changed,
        Your stuff all gone, your menace almost rased?

Such resolute shapes so harshly set
        In hollow blocks and cubes deformed, and heaped
In void and null profusion, how is this?
        In what strong aqua regia now are you steeped?

That you lose the brick-stuff out of you
        And hover like a presentment, fading faint
And vanquished, evaporate away
        To leave but only the merest possible taint!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061503">
<head>
   <title>Weeknight Service</title>
   <toctitle>Weeknight Service</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Weeknight Service</indextitle>
   <firstline>The five old bells</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The five old bells
Are hurrying and stridently calling,
Insisting, protesting
They are right, yet clamorously falling
Into gabbling confusion, without resting,
Like spattering shouts of an orator endlessly dropping
From the tower on the town, but endlessly, never stopping.

The silver moon
That somebody has spun so high
To settle the question, heads or tails? has caught
In the net of the night's balloon,
And sits with a smooth, bland smile up there in the sky
Serenely smiling at naught,
Unless the little star that keeps her company
Makes tittering jests at the bells' obscenity;
As if <i>he</i> knew aught!

While patient Night
Sits indifferent, hugged in her rags;
She neither knows nor cares
Why the old church bellows and brags;
The noise distresses her eyes, and tears
At her tattered silence, as she crouches and covers her face,
Bent, if we did but know it, on a weary and bitter grimace.

The wise old trees
Drop their leaves with a faint, sharp hiss of contempt;
A car at the end of the street goes by with a laugh.
As by degrees
The damned bells cease, and we are exempt,
And the stars can chaff
The cool high moon at their ease; while the droning church
Is peopled with shadows and wailing, and last ghosts lurch
Towards its cenotaph.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061504">
<head>
   <title>Letter from Town: On a Grey Morning in March</title>
   <toctitle>Letter from Town: On a Grey Morning in March</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Letter from Town: On a Grey Morning in March</indextitle>
   <firstline>The clouds are pushing in grey reluctance slowly northward to you</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The clouds are pushing in grey reluctance slowly northward to you,
   While north of them all, at the farthest ends, stands one bright-bosomed, aglance
With fire as it guards the wild north-coasts, red-fire seas running through
   The rocks where ravens flying to windward melt as a well-shot lance.

You should be out by the orchard, where violets secretly darken the earth,
   Or there in the woods of the twilight, with northern wind-flowers shaken astir.
Think of me here in the library, trying and trying a song that is worth
   Tears and swords to my heart, arrows no armour will turn or deter.

You tell me the lambs have come, they lie like daisies white in the grass
   Of the dark-green hills; new calves in shed; peewits turn after the plough -
It is well for you. For me the navvies work in the road where I pass
   And I want to smite in anger the barren rock of each waterless brow.

Like the sough of a wind that is caught up high in the mesh of the budding trees,
   A sudden car goes sweeping past, and I strain my soul to hear
The voice of the furtive triumphant engine as it rushes past like a breeze,
   To hear on its mocking triumphance unwitting the after-echo of fear.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061505">
<head>
   <title>Letter from Town: The Almond-Tree</title>
   <toctitle>Letter from Town: The Almond-Tree</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Letter from Town: The Almond-Tree</indextitle>
   <firstline>You promised to send me some violets. Did you forget?</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
You promised to send me some violets. Did you forget?
    White ones and blue ones from under the orchard hedge?
    Sweet dark purple, and white ones mixed for a pledge
Of our early love that hardly has opened yet.

Here there's an almond-tree - you have never seen
    Such a one in the north - it flowers on the street, and I stand
    Every day by the fence to look up for the flowers that expand
At rest in the blue, and wonder at what they mean.

Under the almond-tree, the happy lands
    Provence, Japan, and Italy repose;
    And passing feet are chatter and clapping of those
Who play around us, country girls clapping their hands.

You, my love, the foremost, in a flowered gown,
    All your unbearable tenderness, you with the laughter
    Startled upon your eyes now so wide with hereafter,
You with loose hands of abandonment hanging down.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061506">
<head>
   <title>Violets</title>
   <toctitle>Violets</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Violets</indextitle>
   <firstline>Sister, tha knows while we was on th' planks</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Sister, tha knows while we was on th' planks
        Aside o' t' grave, an' th' coffin set
On th' yaller clay, wi' th' white flowers top of it
        Waitin' ter be buried out o' th' wet?

An' t' parson makin' haste, an' a' t' black
        Huddlin' up i' t' rain,
Did t' 'appen ter notice a bit of a lass away back
        Hoverin', lookin' poor an' plain?

            - How should I be lookin' round!
                  An' me standin' there on th' plank,
              An' our Ted's coffin set on th' ground,
                  Waitin' to be sank!

              I'd as much as I could do, to think
                  Of 'im bein' gone
              That young, an' a' the fault of drink
                  An' carryin's on! -

Let that be; 'appen it worna th' drink, neither,
Nor th' carryin' on as killed 'im.
                                              - No, 'appen not,
My sirs! But I say 'twas! For a blither
Lad never stepped, till 'e got in with your lot. -

All right, all right, it's my fault! But let
 Me tell thee about that lass. When you'd all gone
Ah stopped behind on t' pad, i' t' pourin' wet
An' watched what 'er 'ad on.

Tha should ha' seed 'er slive up when yer'd gone!
 Tha should ha' seed 'er kneel an' look in
At th' sloppy grave! an' 'er little neck shone
 That white, an' 'er cried that much, I'd like to begin

Scraightin' mysen as well. 'Er undid 'er black
 Jacket at th' bosom, an' took out
Over a double 'andful o' violets, a' in a pack
An' white an' blue in a ravel, like a clout.

An' warm, for th' smell come waftin' to me. 'Er put 'er face
 Right in 'em, and scraighted a bit again,
Then after a bit 'er dropped 'em down that place,
 An' I come away, acause o' th' teemin' rain.

But I thowt ter mysen, as that wor th' only bit
O' warmth as 'e got down theer; th' rest wor stone cold.
From that bit of a wench's bosom; 'e'd be glad of it,
Gladder nor of thy lilies, if tha maun be told.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061507">
<head>
   <title>Baby Running Barefoot</title>
   <toctitle>Baby Running Barefoot</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Baby Running Barefoot</indextitle>
   <firstline>When the white feet of the baby beat across the grass</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When the white feet of the baby beat across the grass
The little white feet nod like white flowers in a wind,
They poise and run like puffs of wind that pass
Over water where the weeds are thinned.

And the sight of their white playing in the grass
Is winsome as a robin's song, so fluttering;
Or like two butterflies that settle on a glass
Cup for a moment, soft little wing-beats uttering.

And I wish that the baby would tack across here to me
Like a wind-shadow running on a pond, so she could stand
With two little bare white feet upon my knee
And I could feel her feet in either hand

Cool as syringa buds in morning hours,
Or firm and silken as young peony flowers.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061508">
<head>
   <title>Sigh No More</title>
   <toctitle>Sigh No More</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sigh No More</indextitle>
   <firstline>The cuckoo and the coo-dove's ceaseless calling</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The cuckoo and the coo-dove's ceaseless calling,
                    Calling,
Of a meaningless monotony is palling
All my morning's pleasure in the sun-fleck-scattered wood.

May-blossom and blue bird's-eye flowers falling,
                    Falling
In a litter through the elm-tree shade are scrawling
Messages of true-love down the dust of the highroad.

I do not like to hear the gentle grieving,
                     Grieving
Of the she-dove in the blossom, still believing
Love will yet again return to her and make all good.

When I know that there must ever be deceiving,
                     Deceiving
Of the mournful constant heart, that while she's weaving
Her woes, her lover woos and sings within another wood.

Oh, boisterous the cuckoo shouts, forestalling,
                     Stalling
A progress down the intricate enthralling
By-paths where the wanton-headed flowers doff their hood.

And like a laughter leads me onward, heaving,
                     Heaving
A sigh among the shadows, thus retrieving
A decent short regret for that which once was very good.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061509">
<head>
   <title>Hyde Park at Night, Before the War</title>
   <toctitle>Hyde Park at Night, Before the War</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Hyde Park at Night, Before the War</indextitle>
   <firstline>We have shut the doors behind us, and the velvet flowers of night</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>CLERKS</i>
We have shut the doors behind us, and the velvet flowers of night
Lean about us scattering their pollen grains of golden light.

Now at last we lift our faces, and our faces come aflower
To the night that takes us willing, liberates us to the hour.

Now at last the ink and dudgeon passes from our fervent eyes
And out of the chambered wilderness wanders a spirit abroad on its enterprise.

                 Not too near and not too far
                 Out of the stress of the crowd
                 Music screams as elephants scream
                 When they lift their trunks and scream aloud
                 For joy of the night when masters are
                        Asleep and adream.

                 So here I hide in the Shalimar
                 With a wanton princess slender and proud,
                 And we swoon with kisses, swoon till we seem
                 Two streaming peacocks gone in a cloud
                 Of golden dust, with star after star
                        On our stream.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061510">
<head>
   <title>Piccadilly Circus at Night</title>
   <toctitle>Piccadilly Circus at Night</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Piccadilly Circus at Night</indextitle>
   <firstline>When into the night the yellow light is roused like dust above the towns</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>STREET-WALKERS</i>
When into the night the yellow light is roused like dust above the towns,
Or like a mist the moon has kissed from off a pool in the midst of the downs,

Our faces flower for a little hour pale and uncertain along the street,
Daisies that waken all mistaken white-spread in expectancy to meet

The luminous mist which the poor things wist was dawn arriving across the sky,
When dawn is far behind the star the dust-lit town has driven so high.

All the birds are folded in a silent ball of sleep,
    All the flowers are faded from the asphalt isle in the sea,
Only we hard-faced creatures go round and round, and keep
    The shores of this innermost ocean alive and illusory.

Wanton sparrows that twittered when morning looked in at their eyes
    And the Cyprian's pavement-roses are gone, and now it is we
Flowers of illusion who shine in our gauds, make a Paradise
    On the shores of this ceaseless ocean, gay birds of the town-dark sea.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061511">
<head>
   <title>A Baby Asleep After Pain</title>
   <toctitle>A Baby Asleep After Pain</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Baby Asleep After Pain</indextitle>
   <firstline>As a drenched, drowned bee</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
       As a drenched, drowned bee
Hangs numb and heavy from a bending flower,
       So clings to me
My baby, her brown hair brushed with wet tears
       And laid against her cheek;
Her soft white legs hanging heavily over my arm
       Swing to my walking movement, weak
With after-pain. My sleeping baby hangs upon my life
       Like a burden she hangs on me;
She has always seemed so light,
       Now wet with tears and pain hangs heavily
       Even her floating hair sinks heavily
              Reaching downwards;
As the wings of a drenched, drowned bee
       Are a heaviness, and a weariness.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061512">
<head>
   <title>Last Lesson of the Afternoon</title>
   <toctitle>Last Lesson of the Afternoon</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Last Lesson of the Afternoon</indextitle>
   <firstline>When will the bell ring, and end this weariness?</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When will the bell ring, and end this weariness?
How long have they tugged the leash, and strained apart,
My pack of unruly hounds! I cannot start
Them again on a quarry of knowledge they hate to hunt,
I can haul them and urge them no more.

No longer now can I endure the brunt
Of the books that lie out on the desks; a full threescore
Of several insults of blotted pages, and scrawl
Of slovenly work that they have offered me.
I am sick, and what on earth is the good of it all?
What good to them or me, I cannot see!

                                                 So, shall I take
My last dear fuel of life to heap on my soul
And kindle my will to a flame that shall consume
Their dross of indifference; and take the toll
Of their insults in punishment? - I will not! -

I will not waste my soul and my strength for this.
What do I care for all that they do amiss!
What is the point of this teaching of mine, and of this
Learning of theirs? It all goes down the same abyss.

What does it matter to me, if they can write
A description of a dog, or if they can't?
What is the point? To us both, it is all my aunt!
And yet I'm supposed to care, with all my might.

I do not, and will not; they won't and they don't; and that's all!
I shall keep my strength for myself; they can keep theirs as well.
Why should we beat our heads against the wall
Of each other? I shall sit and wait for the bell.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061513">
<head>
   <title>School on the Outskirts</title>
   <toctitle>School on the Outskirts</toctitle>
   <indextitle>School on the Outskirts</indextitle>
   <firstline>How different, in the midst of snow, the great school rises red!</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
How different, in the midst of snow, the great school rises red!
   A red rock silent and shadowless, clung round with clusters of shouting lads,
Some few dark-cleaving the doorway, souls that cling as the souls of the dead
   In stupor persist at the gates of life, obstinate dark monads.

This new red rock in a waste of white rises against the day
   With shelter now, and with blandishment, since the winds have had their way
And laid the desert horrific of silence and snow on the world of mankind,
   School now is the rock in this weary land the winter burns and makes blind.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061514">
<head>
   <title>A Winter's Tale</title>
   <toctitle>A Winter's Tale</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Winter's Tale</indextitle>
   <firstline>Yesterday the fields were only grey with scattered snow</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Yesterday the fields were only grey with scattered snow,
And now the longest grass-leaves hardly emerge;
Yet her deep footsteps mark the snow, and go
On towards the pines at the hill's white verge.

I cannot see her, since the mist's pale scarf
Obscures the dark wood and the dull orange sky;
But she's waiting, I know, impatient and cold, half
Sobs struggling into her frosty sigh.

Why does she come so promptly, when she must know
She's only the nearer to the inevitable farewell?
The hill is steep, on the snow my steps are slow -
Why does she come, when she knows what I have to tell?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061515">
<head>
   <title>Scent of Irises</title>
   <toctitle>Scent of Irises</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Scent of Irises</indextitle>
   <firstline>A faint, sickening scent of irises</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
A faint, sickening scent of irises
Persists all morning. Here in a jar on the table
A fine proud spike of purple irises
Rising up in the class-room litter, makes me unable
To see the class's lifted and bended faces
Save in a broken pattern, amid purple and gold and sable.

I can smell the bog-end, gorgeous in its breathless
Dazzle of may-blobs, where the marigold glare overcast you
With fire on your cheeks and your brow and your chin as you dipped
Your face in the marigold bunch, to touch and contrast you,
Your own dark mouth with the bridal faint lady-smocks,
And the kingcups' glisten, that shall long outlast you.

You amid the bog-end's yellow incantation,
You sitting in the cowslips of the meadow above,
Me, your shadow on the bog-flame flowery may-blobs,
Me full length in the cowslips, muttering you love;
You, your soul like a lady-smock, lost, evanescent,
You with your face all rich, like the sheen on a dove!

You are always asking, do I remember, remember
The buttercup bog-end where the flowers rose up
And glazed you over with a sheen of gold?
You ask me, do the healing days close up
The gulf that came between us, and drew us in?
Do they wipe away the gloom the gulf throws up?

You upon the dry, dead beech-leaves, once more, only once
Taken like a sacrifice, in the night invisible;
Only the darkness, and the scent of you! -
And yes, thank God, it still is possible
The healing days shall close the dark gulf up
Wherein we fainted like a smoke or dew!

Like vapour, dew, or poison! Now, thank God,
The last year's fire is gone, and your face is ash;
And the gulf that came between you, woman, and me, man,
That day, is half grown over, it need not abash
Either of us any more; henceforth we can
Forget each other and the bruise of our bodies' clash.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061516">
<head>
   <title>Prophet</title>
   <toctitle>Prophet</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Prophet</indextitle>
   <firstline>Ah, my darling, when over the purple horizon shall loom</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Ah, my darling, when over the purple horizon shall loom
The shrouded mother of a new idea, men hide their faces,
Cry out and fend her off, as she seeks her procreant groom,
Wounding themselves against her, denying her fecund embraces.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061517">
<head>
   <title>Discipline</title>
   <toctitle>Discipline</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Discipline</indextitle>
   <firstline>It is stormy, and raindrops cling like silver bees to the panes</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
It is stormy, and raindrops cling like silver bees to the panes,
The thin sycamores in the playground is swinging with flattened leaves;
The heads of the boys move dimly through a yellow gloom that stains
The class; over them all the dark net of my discipline weaves.

It is no good, dear, gentleness and forbearance; I endured too long.
I have pushed my hands in the dark soil, under the flower of my soul
And the gentle leaves, and have felt where the roots are strong
Fixed in the darkness, grappling for the deep soil's crowded control.

And there in the dark, my darling, where the roots are entangled and fight
Each one for its hold on the concrete darkness, I know that there
In the night where we first have being, before we rise on the light,
We are not lovers, my darling, we fight and we do not spare.

And in the original dark the roots cannot keep, cannot know
Any communion whatever, but they bind themselves on to the dark,
And drawing the darkness together, crush from it a twilight, a slow
Dim self that rises slowly to leaves and the flower's gay spark.

I came to the boys with love, dear, and only they turned on me;
With gentleness came I, with my heart 'twixt my hands like a bowl,
Like a loving-cup, like a grail, but they spilt it triumphantly
And tried to break the vessel, and violate my soul.

And perhaps they were right, for the young are busy deep down at the roots,
And love would only weaken their under-earth grip, make shallow
Their hold on reality, enfeeble their rising shoots
With too much tincture of me, instead of the dark's deep fallow.

I thought that love would do all things, but now I know I am wrong.
There are depths below depths, my darling, where love does not belong.
Where the fight that is fight for being is fought throughout the long
Young years, and the old must not win, not even if they love and are strong.

I must not win their souls, no never, I only must win
The brief material control of the hour, leave them free of me.
Learn they must obey, for all harmony is discipline,
And only in harmony with others the single soul can be free.

Let them live, the boys, and learn not to trespass; I had to learn
Not to trespass on them with love, they must learn not to trespass in the young
Cruel self; the fight is not for existence, the fight is to burn
At last into blossom of being, each one his own flower outflung.

They are here to learn but one lesson, that they shall not thwart each other
Nor be thwarted, in life's slow struggle to unfold the flower of the self.
They draw their sap from the Godhead, not from me, but they must not smother
The sun from their neighbour either, nor be smothered in turn by pelf.

I will teach them the beginning of the lesson at the roots, and then no more.
I throw from out of the darkness myself like a flower into sight
Of the day, but it's nothing to do with the boys, so let them ignore
What's beyond them, and fight with me in discipline's little fight.

But whoever would pluck apart my flowering will burn their hands,
For flowers are tender folk, and roots can only hide.
But sometimes the opening petals are fire, and the scarlet brands
Of the blossom are roses to look at, but flames when they're tried.

But now I am trodden to earth, and my fires are low;
Now I am broken down like a plant in winter, and all
Myself but a knowledge of roots, of roots in the dark, that throw
A net on the undersoil, that lies passive, and quickened with gall.

Yet wait awhile, for henceforth I will love when a blossom calls
To my blossom in perfume and seed-dust, and only then; I will give
My love where it is wanted. Yet wait awhile! My fall
Is complete for the moment, yet wait, and you'll see that my flower will live.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061518">
<head>
   <title>The Punisher</title>
   <toctitle>The Punisher</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Punisher</indextitle>
   <firstline>I have fetched the tears up out of the little wells</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I have fetched the tears up out of the little wells,
Scooped them up with small, iron words,
            Dripping over the runnels.

The harsh, cold wind of my words drove on, and still
I watched the tears on the guilty cheek of the boys
            Glitter and spill.

Cringing Pity, and Love, white-handed, came
Hovering about the Judgment which stood in my eyes,
            Whirling a flame.
           .           .           .           .           .           .
The tears are dry, and the cheek's young fruits are fresh
With laughter, and clear the exonerated eyes, since pain
            Beat through the flesh.

The Angel of Judgment has departed again to the Nearness.
Desolate I am as a church whose lights are put out.
            And doubt enters in drearness.

The fire rose up in the bush and blazed apace,
The thorn-leaves crackled and twisted and sweated in anguish;
            Then God left the place.

Like a flower that the frost has hugged and let go, my head
Is heavy, and my heart beats slowly, laboriously,
            My strength is dead.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061519">
<head>
   <title>Tease</title>
   <toctitle>Tease</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Tease</indextitle>
   <firstline>I will give you all my keys</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I will give you all my keys,
   You shall be my châtelaine,
You shall enter as you please,
   As you please shall go again.

When I hear you jingling through
   All the chambers of my soul,
How I sit and laugh at you
   In your close housekeeping rôle!

Jealous of the smallest cover,
   Angry at the simplest door;
Well, you anxious, inquisitive lover,
   Are you pleased with what's in store?

You have fingered all my treasures,
   Have you not, most curiously,
Handled all my tools and measures
   And masculine machinery?

Over every single beauty
   You have had your little rapture;
You have slain, as was your duty,
   Every sin-mouse you could capture.

Still you are not satisfied!
   Still you tremble faint reproach!
Challenge me I keep aside
   Secrets that you may not broach.

Maybe yes, and maybe no;
   Maybe there <i>are</i> secret places,
Altars barbarous below,
   Elsewhere halls of high disgraces.

Maybe yes, and maybe no,
   You may have it as you please,
Since you are so keen to know
   Everything, Miss Ill-at-ease!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061520">
<head>
   <title>Mystery</title>
   <toctitle>Mystery</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Mystery</indextitle>
   <firstline>Now I am all</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Now I am all
One bowl of kisses,
Such as the tall
Slim votaresses
Of Egypt filled
For divine excesses.

I lift to you
My bowl of kisses,
And through the temple's
Blue recesses
Cry out to you
In wild caresses.

And to my lips'
Bright crimson rim
The passion slips;
And down my slim
White body drips
The moving hymn.

And still before
The altar, I
Exalt the bowl
Brimful, and cry
To you to stoop
And drink, Most High.

Ah, drink me up
That I may be
Within your cup
Like a mystery,
Like wine that is still
In ecstasy.

Glimmering still
In ecstasy,
Commingled wines
Of you and me
In one fulfil
The mystery.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061521">
<head>
   <title>The End</title>
   <toctitle>The End</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The End</indextitle>
   <firstline>If I could have put you in my heart</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
If I could have put you in my heart,
If but I could have wrapped you in myself
How glad I should have been!
And now the chart
Of memory unrolls again to me
The course of our journey here, here where we part.

And oh, that you had never, never been
Some of your selves, my love; that some
Of your several faces I had never seen!
And still they come before me, and they go;
And I cry aloud in the moments that intervene.

And oh, my love, as I rock for you to-night,
And have not any longer any hope
To heal the suffering, or make requite
For all your life of asking and despair,
I own that some of me is dead to-night.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061601">
<head>
   <title>The Bride</title>
   <toctitle>The Bride</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Bride</indextitle>
   <firstline>My love looks like a girl to-night</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My love looks like a girl to-night,
              But she is old.
The plaits that lie along her pillow
              Are not gold,
But threaded with filigree silver,
              And uncanny cold.

She looks like a young maiden, since her brow
              Is smooth and fair;
Her cheeks are very smooth, her eyes are closed,
              She sleeps a rare,
Still, winsome sleep, so still, and so composed.

Nay, but she sleeps like a bride, and dreams her dreams
              Of perfect things.
She lies at last, the darling, in the shape of her dream;
              And her dead mouth sings
By its shape, like the thrushes in clear evenings.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061602">
<head>
   <title>The Virgin Mother</title>
   <toctitle>The Virgin Mother</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Virgin Mother</indextitle>
   <firstline>My little love, my darling</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
My little love, my darling,
You were a doorway to me;
You let me out of the confines
Into this strange countrie
Where people are crowded like thistles,
Yet are shapely and comely to see.

My little love, my dearest,
Twice you have issued me,
Once from your womb, sweet mother,
Once from your soul, to be
Free of all hearts, my darling,
Of each heart's entrance free.

And so, my love, my mother,
I shall always be true to you.
Twice I am born, my dearest:
To life, and to death, in you;
And this is the life hereafter
Wherein I am true.

I kiss you good-bye, my darling,
Our ways are different now;
You are a seed in the night-time,
I am a man, to plough
The difficult glebe of the future
For seed to endow.

I kiss you good-bye, my dearest,
It is finished between us here.
Oh, if I were calm as you are,
Sweet and still on your bier!
Oh God, if I had not to leave you
Alone, my dear!

Is the last word now uttered?
Is the farewell said?
Spare me the strength to leave you
Now you are dead.
I must go, but my soul lies helpless
Beside your bed.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061603">
<head>
   <title>At the Window</title>
   <toctitle>At the Window</toctitle>
   <indextitle>At the Window</indextitle>
   <firstline>The pine-trees bend to listen to the autumn wind as it mutters</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The pine-trees bend to listen to the autumn wind as it mutters
Something which sets the black poplars ashake with hysterical laughter;
As slowly the house of day is closing its eastern shutters.

Farther down the valley the clustered tombstones recede,
Winding about their dimness the mist's grey cerements, after
The street-lamps in the twilight have suddenly started to bleed.

The leaves fly over the window, and utter a word as they pass
To the face that gazes outwards, watching for night to waft a
Meaning or a message over the window glass.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061604">
<head>
   <title>Drunk</title>
   <toctitle>Drunk</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Drunk</indextitle>
   <firstline>Too far away, O love, I know</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
       Too far away, O love, I know,
       To save me from this haunted road
       Whose lofty roses break and blow
       On a night-sky bent with a load

       Of lights; each solitary rose,
       Each arc-lamp golden does expose
       Ghost beyond ghost of a blossom, shows
       Night blenched with a thousand snows.

       Of hawthorn and of lilac trees,
       White lilac; shows discoloured night
       Dripping with all the golden lees
       Laburnum gives back to light.

       And shows the red of hawthorn set
       On high to the fuming sky of night,
       Like flags in pale blood newly wet,
       Blood shed in the silent fight.

       Of life with love and love with life,
       Of battling for a little food,
       Of kisses, long seeking for a wife
       Long ago, long ago wooed.

       Too far away you are, my love,
       To steady my brain in this phantom show
       That passes the nightly road above
       And returns again below.

        .          .          .          .          .          .

The enormous cliff of horse-chestnut trees
       Has poised on each of its ledges
An erect small girl looking down at me;
White-nightgowned little chits I see
       And they peep at me over the edges
Of the leaves as though they would leap, should I call
       Them down to my arms:
- But, child, you're too small for me; too small
       Your little charms! -

White little sheaves of nightgowned maids
       Some other will thresh you out! -
But I see leaning from the shades
A lilac there, like a lady who braids
       Her white mantilla about
Her face, and forward leans to catch the sight
       Of a lover's face;
Gracefully sighing through the white
       Flowery mantilla of lace.

And another lilac in purple veiled
       Discreetly, yet recklessly calls
In a low, shocking perfume, to know who has hailed
Her forth from the dark: my strength has failed
       In her voice, and a weak tear falls -
Oh, and see the laburnum shimmering
       Her draperies down
As if she would slip the gold, and glimmering
       White stand naked of gown.

        .          .          .          .          .          .

The pageant of flowery trees above
       The street pale-passionate goes.
And down below on the pavement, love
       In a meaner pageant flows.

Two and two are the folk that walk,
       They pass in a half embrace
Of linking elbows, and they talk
       With dull face leaning to face.

But I am alone, and wavering home
       Along this haunted road;
And never a blossoming woman will roam
       To my arms with her welcome load.

And never a girl like a chestnut flower
       Will tiptoe into my room.
I shall get no answer in any hour.
       To live alone is my doom.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061605">
<head>
   <title>Sorrow</title>
   <toctitle>Sorrow</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sorrow</indextitle>
   <firstline>Why does the thin grey strand</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Why does the thin grey strand
Floating up from the forgotten
Cigarette between my fingers,
Why does it trouble me?

Ah, you will understand;
When I carried my mother downstairs,
A few times only, at the beginning
Of her soft-foot malady,

I should find, for a reprimand
To my gaiety, a few long grey hairs
On the breast of my coat; and one by one
I watched them float up the dark chimney.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061606">
<head>
   <title>Dolour of Autumn</title>
   <toctitle>Dolour of Autumn</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Dolour of Autumn</indextitle>
   <firstline>The acrid scents of autumn</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The acrid scents of autumn,
Reminiscent of slinking beasts, make me fear
Everything, tear-trembling stars of autumn
And the snore of the night in my ear.

For suddenly, flush-fallen,
All my life, in a rush
Of shedding away, has left me
Naked exposed on the bush.

I on the bush of the globe
Like a newly-naked berry shrink
Disclosed; but 'tis I who am prowling
As well in the scents that slink

Abroad: I in this naked berry
Of flesh that stands dismayed on the bush!
And I in the stealthy, brindled odours
Prowling about the lush

And acrid night of autumn!
My soul, along with the rout,
Rank and treacherous, prowling,
Disseminated out.

For the night, with a great breath taken
Has drawn my spirit outside
Me, till I reel with disseminated consciousness
Like a man who has died.

At the same time stand exposed
Here on the bush of the globe,
A newly-naked berry of flesh
For the stars to probe.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061607">
<head>
   <title>The Inheritance</title>
   <toctitle>The Inheritance</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Inheritance</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since you did depart</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Since you did depart
Out of my reach, my darling,
Into the hidden,
I see each shadow start
With recognition, and I
Am wonder-ridden.

I am dazed with the farewell
But I scarcely feel your loss.
You left me a gift
Of tongues, so the shadows tell
Me things, and silences toss
Me their drift.

You sent me a cloven fire
Out of death, and it burns in the draught
Of the breathing hosts,
Kindles the darkening pyre
Of the mournful, till people waft
Like candid ghosts.

Form after form, in the streets
Waves like a ghost along
Kindled to me;
The star above the house-tops greets
Me every eve with a long
Song fierily.

And all day long, the town
Glimmers with subtle ghosts
Going up and down
In a common, prison-like dress,
Yet their daunted looking flickers
To me, and I answer Yes!

So I am not lonely nor sad
Although bereaved of you,
My love.
I move among a townfolk clad
With words, but the night shows through
Their words as they move.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061608">
<head>
   <title>Silence</title>
   <toctitle>Silence</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Silence</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since I lost you, I am silence-haunted</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Since I lost you, I am silence-haunted;
       Sounds wave their little wings
A moment, then in weariness settle
       On the flood that soundless swings.

Whether the people in the street
       Like pattering ripples go by,
Or whether the theatre sighs and sighs
       With a loud, hoarse sigh:

Or the wind shakes a ravel of light
       Over the dead-black river,
Or last night's echoings
       Make the daybreak shiver:

I feel the silence waiting
       To sip them all up again,
In its last completeness drinking
       Down the noise of men.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061609">
<head>
   <title>Listening</title>
   <toctitle>Listening</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Listening</indextitle>
   <firstline>I listen to the stillness of you</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I listen to the stillness of you,
      My dear, among it all;
I feel your silence touch my words as I talk
      And hold them in thrall.

My words fly off a forge
      The length of a spark;
I see the silence easily sip them
      Up in the dark.

The lark sings loud and glad,
      Yet I am not loth
That silence should take the song and the bird
      And lose them both.

A train goes roaring south,
      The steam-flag flowing;
I see the stealthy shadow of silence
      Alongside going.

And off the forge of the world
      Whirling in the draught of life
Go myriad sparks of people, filling
      The night with strife.

Yet they never change the darkness
      Nor blench it with noise;
Alone on the perfect silence
      The stars are buoys.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061610">
<head>
   <title>Brooding Grief</title>
   <toctitle>Brooding Grief</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Brooding Grief</indextitle>
   <firstline>A yellow leaf, from the darkness</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
A yellow leaf, from the darkness
Hops like a frog before me;
Why should I start and stand still?

I was watching the woman that bore me
Stretched in the brindled darkness
Of the sick-room, rigid with will
To die: and the quick leaf tore me
Back to this rainy swill
Of leaves and lamps and the city street mingled before me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061611">
<head>
   <title>Last Words to Miriam</title>
   <toctitle>Last Words to Miriam</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Last Words to Miriam</indextitle>
   <firstline>Yours is the sullen sorrow</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Yours is the sullen sorrow,
       The disgrace is also mine;
Your love was intense and thorough,
Mine was the love of a growing flower
       For the sunshine.

You had the power to explore me,
       Blossom me stalk by stalk;
You woke my spirit, you bore me
To consciousness, you gave me the dour
       Awareness - then I suffered a balk.

Body to body I could not
       Love you, although I would.
We kissed, we kissed though we should not.
You yielded, we threw the last cast,
       And it was no good.

You only endured, and it broke
       My craftsman's nerve.
No flesh responded to my stroke;
So I failed to give you the last
       Fine torture you did deserve.

You are shapely, you are adorned
       But opaque and null in the flesh;
Who, had I but pierced with the thorned
Full anguish, perhaps had been cast
       In a lovely illumined mesh

Like a painted window; the best
       Fire passed through your flesh,
Undrossed it, and left it blest
In clean new awareness. But now
       Who shall take you afresh?

Now who will burn you free
       From your body's deadness and dross?
Since the fire has failed in me,
What man will stoop in your flesh to plough
       The shrieking cross?

A mute, nearly beautiful thing
       Is your face, that fills me with shame
As I see it hardening;
I should have been cruel enough to bring
       You through the flame.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061612">
<head>
   <title>Malade</title>
   <toctitle>Malade</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Malade</indextitle>
   <firstline>The sick grapes on the chair by the bed lie prone; at the window</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The sick grapes on the chair by the bed lie prone; at the window
The tassel of the blind swings constantly, tapping the pane
As the air moves in.

The room is the hollow rind of a fruit, a gourd
Scooped out and bare, where a spider,
Folded in its legs as in a bed,
Lies on the dust, watching where is nothing to see but dusky walls.

And if the day outside were mine! What is the day
But a grey cave, with great grey spider-cloths hanging
Low from the roof, and the wet dust falling softly from them
Over the wet dark rocks, the houses, and over
The spiders with white faces, that scuttle on the floor of the cave!

Ah, but I am ill, and it is still raining, coldly raining!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061613">
<head>
   <title>Troth with the Dead</title>
   <toctitle>Troth with the Dead</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Troth with the Dead</indextitle>
   <firstline>The moon is broken in twain, and half a moon</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The moon is broken in twain, and half a moon
Beyond me lies on the low, still floor of the sky;
The other half of the broken coin of troth
Is buried away in the dark, where the dead all lie.

They buried her half in the grave when they laid her away;
Pushed gently away and hidden in the thick of her hair
Where it gathered towards the plait, on that very last day;
And like a moon unshowing it must still shine there.

So half lies on the sky, for a general sign
Of the troth with the dead that we are pledged to keep;
Turning its broken edge to the dark, it shine
Ends like a broken love, that turns to the dark of sleep.

And half lies there in the dark where the dead all lie
Lost and yet still connected; and between the two
Strange beams must travel still, for I feel that I
Am lit beneath my heart with a half-moon, weird and blue.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061614">
<head>
   <title>Submergence</title>
   <toctitle>Submergence</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Submergence</indextitle>
   <firstline>When along the pavement</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When along the pavement,
Palpitating flames of life,
People flicker round me,
I forget my bereavement,
The gap in my life's constellation,
The place where a star used to be.

Nay, though the pole-star
Is blown out like a candle,
And all the heavens are wandering in disarray,
Yet when pleiads of people are
Deployed around me, and I see
The street's long, outstretched milky-way!

When people flicker down the pavement
I forget my bereavement.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061615">
<head>
   <title>The Enkindled Spring</title>
   <toctitle>The Enkindled Spring</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Enkindled Spring</indextitle>
   <firstline>This spring as it comes bursts up in bonfires green</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
This spring as it comes bursts up in bonfires green,
Wild puffing of green-fire trees, and flame-green bushes,
Thorn-blossom lifting in wreaths of smoke between
Where the wood fumes up and the flickering, watery rushes.

I am amazed at this spring, this conflagration
Of green fires lit on the soil of the earth, this blaze
Of growing, these smoke-puffs that puff in wild gyration,
Faces of people blowing across my gaze!

And I, what sort of fire am I among
This conflagration of spring? the gap in it all -!
Not even the palish smoke like the rest of the throng.
Less than the wind that runs to the flamy call!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061616">
<head>
   <title>Ballad of Another Ophelia</title>
   <toctitle>Ballad of Another Ophelia</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Ballad of Another Ophelia</indextitle>
   <firstline>O the green glimmer of apples in the orchard</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
O the green glimmer of apples in the orchard,
Lamps in a wash of rain!
O the wet walk of my brown hen through the stackyard!
O tears on the window-pane!

Nothing now will ripen the bright green apples
Full of disappointment and of rain;
Brackish they will taste, of tears, when the yellow dapples
Of autumn tell the withered tale again.

All round the yard it is cluck! my brown hen.
Cluck! and the rain-wet wings;
Cluck! my marigold bird, and again
Cluck! for your yellow darlings.

For a grey rat found the gold thirteen
Huddled away in the dark.
Flutter for a moment, oh, the beast is quick and keen,
Extinct one yellow-fluffy spark!

Once I had a lover bright like running water,
Once his face was open like the sky,
Open like the sky looking down in all its laughter
On the buttercups, and the buttercups was I.

What then is there hidden in the skirts of all the blossom?
What is peeping from your skirts, O mother hen?
'Tis the sun that asks the question, in a lovely haste for wisdom;
What a lovely haste for wisdom is in men!

Yea, but it is cruel when undressed is all the blossom
And her shift is lying white upon the floor,
That a grey one, like a shadow, like a rat, a thief, a rain-storm,
Creeps upon her then and ravishes her store!

O the grey garner that is full of half-grown apples!
O the golden sparkles laid extinct!
And O, behind the cloud-leaves, like yellow autumn dapples,
Did you see the wicked sun that winked?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061617">
<head>
   <title>After Many Days</title>
   <toctitle>After Many Days</toctitle>
   <indextitle>After Many Days</indextitle>
   <firstline>I wonder if with you, as it is with me</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I wonder if with you, as it is with me,
If under your slipping words, that easily flow
About you as a garment, easily,
       Your violent heart beats to and fro!

Long have I waited, never once confessed,
Even to myself, how bitter the separation;
Now, being come again, how make the best
       Reparation?

If I could cast this clothing off from me,
If I could lift my naked self to you,
Of if only you would repulse me, a wound would be
       Good, it would let the ache come through.

But that you hold me still so kindly cold
Aloof, my flaming heart will not allow;
Yea, but I loathe you that you should withhold
       Your greeting now!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061618">
<head>
   <title>Snap-Dragon</title>
   <toctitle>Snap-Dragon</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Snap-Dragon</indextitle>
   <firstline>She bade me follow to her garden where</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
She bade me follow to her garden where
The mellow sunlight stood as in a cup
Between the old grey walls; I did not dare
To raise my face, I did not dare look up,
Lest her bright eyes like sparrows should fly in
My windows of discovery, and shrill "Sin!"

So with a downcast mien and laughing voice
I followed, followed the swing of her white dress
That rocked in a lilt along; I watched the poise
Of her feet as they flew for a space, then paused to press
The grass deep down with the royal burden of her;
And gladly I'd offered my breast to the tread of her.

"I like to see," she said, and she crouched her down,
She sunk into my sight like a settling bird;
And her bosom couched in the confines of her gown
Like heavy birds at rest there, softly stirred
By her measured breaths: "I like to see," said she,
"The snap-dragon put out his tongue at me."

She laughed, she reached her hand out to the flower,
Closing its crimson throat. My own throat in her power
Strangled, my heart swelled up so full
As if it would burst its wine-skin in my throat,
Choke me in my own crimson. I watched her pull
The gorge of the gaping flower, till the blood did float

           Over my eyes, and I was blind -
           Her large brown hand stretched over
           The windows of my mind;
           And there in the dark I did discover
           Things I was out to find:

My Grail, a brown bowl twined
With swollen veins that met in the wrist,
Under whose brown the amethyst
I longed to taste! I longed to turn
My heart's red measure in her cup;
I longed to feel my hot blood burn
With the amethyst in her cup.

Then suddenly she looked up,
And I was blind in a tawny-gold day,
Till she took her eyes away.

So she came down from above
And emptied my heart of love.
So I held my heart aloft
To the cuckoo that hung like a dove,
And she settled soft.

It seemed that I and the morning world
Were pressed cup-shape to take this reiver
Bird who was weary to have furled
Her wings in us,
As we were weary to receive her:

              <i>This bird, this rich,
              Sumptuous central grain;
              This mutable witch,
              This one refrain,
              This laugh in the fight,
              This clot of night,
              This field of delight.</i>

She spoke, and I closed my eyes
To shut hallucinations out.
I echoed with surprise
Hearing my mere lips shout
The answer they did devise.

              Again I saw a brown bird hover
              Over the flowers at my feet;
              I felt a brown bird hover
              Over my heart, and sweet
              Its shadow lay on my heart.
              I thought I saw on the clover
              A brown bee pulling apart
              The closed flesh of the clover
              And burrowing into its heart.

              She moved her hand, and again
              I felt the brown bird cover
              My heart; and then
              The bird came down on my heart,
              As on a nest the rover
              Cuckoo comes, and shoves over
              The brim each careful part
              Of love, takes possession, and settles down,
              With her wings and her feathers to drown
              The nest in a heat of love.

She turned her flushed face to me for the glint
Of a moment. - "See," she laughed, "if you also
Can make them yawn!" - I put my hand to the dint
In the flower's throat, and the flower gaped wide with woe.
She watched, she went of a sudden intensely still,
She watched my hand, to see what it would fulfil.

I pressed the wretched, throttled flower between
My fingers, till its head lay back, its fangs
Poised at her. Like a weapon my hand was white and keen,
And I held the choked flower-serpent in its pangs
Of mordant anguish, till she ceased to laugh,
Until her pride's flag, smitten, cleaved down to the staff.

She hid her face, she murmured between her lips
The low word "Don't!" - I let the flower fall,
But held my hand afloat still towards the slips
Of blossom she fingered, and my fingers all
Put forth to her: she did not move, nor I,
For my hand like a snake watched hers, that could not fly.

Then I laughed in the dark of my heart, I did exult
Like a sudden chuckling of music. I bade her eyes
Meet mine, I opened her helpless eyes to consult
Their fear, their shame, their joy that underlies
Defeat in such a battle. In the dark of her eyes
My heart was fierce to make her laughter rise.

Till her dark deeps shook with convulsive thrills, and the dark
Of her spirit wavered like water thrilled with light;
And my heart leaped up in longing to plunge its stark
Fervour within the pool of her twilight,
Within her spacious soul, to find delight.

And I do not care, though the large hands of revenge
Shall get my throat at last, shall get it soon,
If the joy that they are lifted to avenge
Have risen red on my night as a harvest moon,
Which even death can only put out for me;
And death, I know, is better than not-to-be.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061780">
<head>
   <title>The Hands of the Betrothed</title>
   <toctitle>The Hands of the Betrothed</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The Hands of the Betrothed</indextitle>
   <firstline>Her tawny eyes are onyx of thoughtlessness</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Her tawny eyes are onyx of thoughtlessness,
Hardened they are like gems in time-long prudery;
Yea, and her mouth's prudent and crude caress
Means even less than her many words to me.

Except her kiss betrays me this, this only
Consolation, that in her lips her blood at climax clips
Two hard, crude paws in hunger on the lonely
Fruit of my heart, ere down, rebuked, it slips.

I know from her hardened lips that still her heart is
Hungry for love, yet if I lay my hand in her breast
She puts me away, like a saleswoman whose mart is
Endangered by the pilferer on his quest.

Though her hands are still the woman, her large, strong hands
Heavier than mine, yet like leverets caught in steel
When I hold them; my spent soul understands
Their dumb confession of what her blood must feel.

For never her hands come nigh me but they lift
Like heavy birds from the morning stubble, to settle
Upon me like sleeping birds, like birds that shift
Uneasily in their sleep, disturbing my mettle.

How caressingly she lays her hand on my knee!
How strangely she tries to disown it, as it sinks
In my flesh and bone, and forages into me!
How it stirs like a subtle stoat, whatever she thinks!

And often I see her clench her fingers tight
And thrust her fists suppressed in the folds of her skirt;
And sometimes, how she grasps her arms with her bright
Big hands, as if surely her arms did hurt.

And I have seen her stand all unaware
Pressing her spread hands over her breasts, as she
Would crush their mounds on her heart, to kill in there
The pain that is her simple ache for me.

She makes her hands take my part, the part of a man
To her; she crushes them into her bosom deep
Where I should lie, and with her own strong span
Closes her arms, that should fold on me in sleep.

Ah, and she puts her hands upon the wall,
Presses them there, and kisses her big dark hands,
Then lets her black hair loose, the darkness fall
About her from her maiden-folded bands.

And sits in her own dark night of her bitter hair
Dreaming - God knows of what, for to me she's the same
Betrothed young lady who loves me, and takes good care
Of her maidenly virtue and of my good name.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061781">
<head>
   <title>A Love Song</title>
   <toctitle>A Love Song</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Love Song</indextitle>
   <firstline>Reject me not if I should say to you</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Reject me not if I should say to you
I do forget the sounding of your voice,
I do forget your eyes that searching through
The mists perceive our marriage, and rejoice.

But, when the apple-blossom opens wide
Under the pallid moonlight's fingering,
I see your blanched face at my breast, and hide
My eyes from duteous work, malingering.

Ah, then, upon my bedroom I do draw
The blind to hide the garden, where the moon
Enjoys the open blossoms as they straw
Their beauty for his taking, boon for boon.

And I do lift my aching arms to you,
And I do lift my anguished, avid breast,
And I do weep for very pain of you,
And fling myself at the doors of sleep, for rest.

And I do toss through the troubled night for you,
Dreaming your yielded mouth is given to mine,
Feeling your strong breast carry me on into
The sleep no dream nor doubt can undermine.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061782">
<head>
   <title>Twofold</title>
   <toctitle>Twofold</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Twofold</indextitle>
   <firstline>How gorgeous that shock of red lilies, and larkspur cleaving</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
How gorgeous that shock of red lilies, and larkspur cleaving
All with a flash of blue! - when will she be leaving
Her room, where the night still hangs like a half-folded bat,
And passion unbearable seethes in the darkness, like must in a vat.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061783">
<head>
   <title>Tarantella</title>
   <toctitle>Tarantella</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Tarantella</indextitle>
   <firstline>Sad as he sits on the white sea-stone</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Sad as he sits on the white sea-stone
And the suave sea chuckles, and turns to the moon,
And the moon significant smiles at the cliffs and the boulders.
He sits like a shade by the flood alone
While I dance a tarantella on the rocks, and the croon
Of my mockery mocks at him over the waves' bright shoulders.

What can I do but dance alone,
Dance to the sliding sea and the moon,
For the moon on my breast and the air on my limbs and the foam on my feet?
For surely this earnest man has none
Of the night in his soul, and none of the tune
Of the waters within him; only the world's old wisdom to bleat.

I wish a wild sea-fellow would come down the glittering shingle,
A soulless neckar, with winking seas in his eyes
And falling waves in his arms, and the lost soul's kiss
On his lips: I long to be soulless, I tingle
To touch the sea in the last surprise
Of fiery coldness, to be gone in a lost soul's bliss.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061784">
<head>
   <title>Under the Oak</title>
   <toctitle>Under the Oak</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Under the Oak</indextitle>
   <firstline>You, if you were sensible</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
You, if you were sensible,
When I tell you the stars flash signals, each one dreadful,
You would not turn and answer me
"The night is wonderful."

Even you, if you knew
How this darkness soaks me through and through, and infuses
Unholy fear in my essence, you would pause to distinguish
What hurts from what amuses.

For I tell you
Beneath this powerful tree, my whole soul's fluid
Oozes away from me as a sacrifice steam
At the knife of a Druid.

Again I tell you, I bleed, I am bound with withies,
My life runs out.
I tell you my blood runs out on the floor of this oak.
Gout upon gout.

Above me springs the blood-born mistletoe
In the shady smoke.
But who are you, twittering to and fro
Beneath the oak?

What thing better are you, what worse?
What have you to do with the mysteries
Of this ancient place, of my ancient curse?
What place have you in my histories?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061785">
<head>
   <title>Brother and Sister</title>
   <toctitle>Brother and Sister</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Brother and Sister</indextitle>
   <firstline>The shorn moon trembling indistinct on her path</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The shorn moon trembling indistinct on her path,
Frail as a scar upon the pale blue sky,
Draws towards the downward slope; some sorrow hath
Worn her down to the quick, so she faintly fares
Along her foot-searched way without knowing why
She creeps persistent down the sky's long stairs.

Some day they see, though I have never seen,
The dead moon heaped within the new moon's arms;
For surely the fragile, fine young thing had been
Too heavily burdened to mount the heavens so!
But my heart stands still, as a new, strong dread alarms
Me; might a young girl be heaped with such shadow of woe?

Since Death from the mother moon has pared us down to the quick,
And cast us forth like thin, shorn moons, to travel
An uncharted way among the myriad thick
Strewn stars of unknown people, and luminous litter
Of lives which sorrows like mischievous dark mice chavel
To nought, diminishing each star's glitter;

Since Death has delivered us utterly, stripped and white,
Since the month of childhood is over, and we stand alone,
Since the beloved, faded mother that set us alight
Is delivered out and pays no heed though we moan
In sorrow; since we stand in bewilderment, strange
And fearful to sally forth down the sky's long range;

Let us not cry to her still to sustain us here,
Let us not hold her shadow back from the dark!
Oh, let us here forget, let us take the sheer
Unknown that lies before us, bearing the ark
Of the covenant onwards where she cannot go!
Let us rise and leave her now, she will never know.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061786">
<head>
   <title>Birdcage Walk</title>
   <toctitle>Birdcage Walk</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Birdcage Walk</indextitle>
   <firstline>When the wind blows her veil</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When the wind blows her veil
       And uncovers her laughter
I cease, I turn pale.
When the wind blows her veil
From the woes I bewail
       Of love and hereafter:
When the wind blows her veil
I cease, I turn pale.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061787">
<head>
   <title>In Trouble and Shame</title>
   <toctitle>In Trouble and Shame</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In Trouble and Shame</indextitle>
   <firstline>I look at the swaling sunset</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
    I look at the swaling sunset
    And wish I could go also
Through the red doors beyond the black-purple bar.

       I wish that I could go
Through the red doors where I could put off
       My shame like shoes in the porch,
       My pain like garments,
And leave my flesh discarded lying
Like luggage of some departed traveller
       Gone one knows not whither.

       Then I would turn round,
And seeing my cast-off body lying like lumber,
       I would laugh with joy.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061788">
<head>
   <title>Grey Evening</title>
   <toctitle>Grey Evening</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Grey Evening</indextitle>
   <firstline>When you went, how was it you carried with you</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
When you went, how was it you carried with you
My missal book of fine, flamboyant Hours?
My book of turrets and of red-thorn bowers,
And skies of gold, and ladies in bright tissue?

Now underneath a blue-grey twilight, heaped
Beyond the withering snow of the shorn fields
Stands rubble of stunted houses; all is reaped
And trodden that the happy summer yields.

Now lamps like yellow echoes glimmer among
The shadowy stubble of the under-dusk;
As farther off the scythe of night is swung
Ripe little stars come rolling from their husk.

And all the earth is gone into a dust
Of greyness mingled with a fume of gold,
Timeless as branching lichens, pale as must,
Since all the sky has withered and gone cold.

And so I sit and scan the book of grey,
Feeling the shadows like a blind man reading,
All fearful lest I find the last words bleeding:
Nay, take this weary Book of Hours away.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061789">
<head>
   <title>Firelight and Nightfall</title>
   <toctitle>Firelight and Nightfall</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Firelight and Nightfall</indextitle>
   <firstline>The darkness steals the forms of all the queens</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The darkness steals the forms of all the queens,
But oh, the palms of his two black hands are red
Inflamed with binding up the sheaves of dead
Hours that were once all glory and all queens.

And I remember all the sunny hours
Of queens in hyacinth and skies of gold,
And morning singing where the woods are scrolled
And diapered above the chaunting flowers.

Here lamps are white like snowdrops in the grass;
The town is like a churchyard, all so still
And grey now night is here; nor will
Another torn red sunset come to pass.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061790">
<head>
   <title>A Passing-Bell</title>
   <toctitle>A Passing-Bell</toctitle>
   <indextitle>A Passing-Bell</indextitle>
   <firstline>Mournfully to and fro, to and fro the trees are waving</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Mournfully to and fro, to and fro the trees are waving,
           <i>What did you say, my dear?</i>
The rain-bruised leaves are suddenly shaken, as a child
Asleep still shakes in the clutch of a sob -
           <i>Yes, my love, I hear.</i>

One lonely bell, one only, the storm-tossed afternoon is braving,
           <i>Why not let it ring?</i>
The roses lean down when they hear it, the tender, mild
Flowers of the bleeding-heart fall to the throb -
           <i>'Tis a little thing!</i>

A wet bird walks on the lawn, call to the boy to come and look,
           <i>Yes, it is over now.</i>
Call to him out of the silence, call him to see
The starling shaking its head as it walks in the grass -
           <i>Ah, who knows how?</i>

He cannot see it, I can never show it him, how it shook
           <i>Don't disturb it, darling! -</i>
Its head as it walked: I can never call him to me,
Never, he <i>is</i> not, whatever shall come to pass.
           <i>No, look at the wet starling!</i>
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061791">
<head>
   <title>Next Morning</title>
   <toctitle>Next Morning</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Next Morning</indextitle>
   <firstline>How have I wandered here to this vaulted room</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
How have I wandered here to this vaulted room
In the house of life? - the floor was ruffled with gold
Last evening, and she who was softly in bloom,
Glimmered as flowers that in perfume at twilight unfold

For the flush of the night; whereas now the gloom
Of every dirty, must-besprinkled mould
And damp old web of misery's heirloom
Deadens this day's grey-dropping arras-fold.

And what is this that floats on the undermist
Of the mirror towards the dusty grate, as if feeling
Unsightly its way to the warmth? - this thing with a list
To the left? - this ghost like a candle swealing?

Pale-blurred, with two round black drops, as if it missed
Itself among everything else, here hungrily stealing
Upon me! - my own reflection! - explicit gist
Of my presence there in the mirror that leans from the ceiling!

Then will somebody square this shade with the being I know
I was last night, when my soul rang clear as a bell
And happy as rain in summer? Why should it be so?
What is there gone against me, why am I in hell?
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061792">
<head>
   <title>Winter in the Boulevard</title>
   <toctitle>Winter in the Boulevard</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Winter in the Boulevard</indextitle>
   <firstline>The frost has settled down upon the trees</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The frost has settled down upon the trees
And ruthlessly strangled off the fantasies
Of leaves that have gone unnoticed, swept like old
Romantic stories now no more to be told.

The trees down the boulevard stand naked in thought,
Their abundant summery wordage silenced, caught
In the grim undertow; naked the trees confront
Implacable winter's long, cross-questioning brunt.

Has some hand balanced more leaves in the depths of the twigs?
Some dim little efforts placed in the threads of the birch? -
It is only the sparrows, like dead black leaves on the sprigs,
Sitting huddled against the cerulean, one flesh with their perch.

The clear, cold sky coldly bethinks itself.
Like vivid thought the air spins bright, and all
Trees, birds, and earth, arrested in the after-thought,
Awaiting the sentence out from the welkin brought.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061793">
<head>
   <title>Parliament Hill in the Evening</title>
   <toctitle>Parliament Hill in the Evening</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Parliament Hill in the Evening</indextitle>
   <firstline>The houses fade in a melt of mist</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The houses fade in a melt of mist
   Blotching the thick, soiled air
With reddish places that still resist
   The Night's slow care.

The hopeless, wintry twilight fades,
   The city corrodes out of sight
As the body corrodes when death invades
   That citadel of delight.

Now verdigris smoulderings softly spread
   Through the shroud of the town, as slow
Night-lights hither and thither shed
   Their ghastly glow.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061794">
<head>
   <title>Embankment at Night, Before the War</title>
   <toctitle>Embankment at Night, Before the War</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Embankment at Night, Before the War</indextitle>
   <firstline>By the river</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>CHARITY</i>

By the river
In the black wet night as the furtive rain slinks down,
Dropping and starting from sleep
Alone on a seat
A woman crouches.

I must go back to her.

I want to give her
Some money. Her hand slips out of the breast of her gown
Asleep. My fingers creep
Carefully over the sweet
Thumb-mound, into the palm's deep pouches.

So the gift!

God, how she starts!
And looks at me, and looks in the palm of her hand
And again at me! -
I turn and run
Down the Embankment, run for my life.

But why? - why?

Because of my heart's
Beating like sobs, I come to myself, and stand
In the street spilled over splendidly
With wet, flat lights. What I've done
I know not, my soul is in strife.

The touch was on the quick. I want to forget.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061795">
<head>
   <title>Embankment at Night, Before the War</title>
   <toctitle>Embankment at Night, Before the War</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Embankment at Night, Before the War</indextitle>
   <firstline>The night rain, dripping unseen</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
<i>OUTCASTS</i>

The night rain, dripping unseen,
Comes endlessly kissing my face and my hands.

The river slipping between
Lamps, is rayed with golden bands
Half way down its heaving sides;
Revealed where it hides.

Under the bridge
Great electric cars
Sing through, and each with a floor-light racing along at its side.
Far off, oh, midge after midge
Drifts over the gulf that bars
The night with silence, crossing the lamp-touched tide.

At Charing Cross, here, beneath the bridge
Sleep in a row the outcasts,
Packed in a line with their heads against the wall.
Their feet in a broken ridge
Stretch out on the way, and a lout casts
A look as he stands on the edge of this naked stall.

Beasts that sleep will cover
Their face in their flank; so these
Have huddled rags or limbs on the naked sleep.
Save, as the tram-cars hover
Past with the noise of a breeze
And gleam as of sunshine crossing the low black heap,

Two naked faces are seen
Bare and asleep,
Two pale clots swept by the light of the cars.
Foam-clots showing between
The long, low tidal-heap,
The mud-weed opening two pale, shadowless stars.

Over the pallor of only two faces
Passes the gallivant beam of the trams;
Shows in only two sad places
The white bare bone of our shams.

A little, bearded man, pale, peaked in sleeping,
With a face like a chickweed flower.
And a heavy woman, sleeping still keeping
Callous and dour.

Over the pallor of only two places
Tossed on the low, black, ruffled heap
Passes the light of the tram as it races
Out of the deep.

Eloquent limbs
In disarray
Sleep-suave limbs of a youth with long, smooth thighs
Hutched up for warmth; the muddy rims
Of trousers fray
On the thin bare shins of a man who uneasily lies.

The balls of five red toes
As red and dirty, bare
Young birds forsaken and left in a nest of mud -
Newspaper sheets enclose
Some limbs like parcels, and tear
When the sleeper stirs or turns on the ebb of the flood -

One heaped mound
Of a woman's knees
As she thrusts them upward under the ruffled skirt -
And a curious dearth of sound
In the presence of these
Wastrels that sleep on the flagstones without any hurt.

Over two shadowless, shameless faces
Stark on the heap
Travels the light as it tilts in its paces
Gone in one leap.

At the feet of the sleepers, watching,
Stand those that wait
For a place to lie down; and still as they stand, they sleep;
Wearily catching
The flood's slow gait
Like men who are drowned, but float erect in the deep.

Oh, the singing mansions,
Golden-lighted tall
Trams that pass, blown ruddily down the night!
The bridge on its stanchions
Stoops like a pall
To this human blight.

On the outer pavement, slowly,
Theatre people pass,
Holding aloft their umbrellas that flash and are bright
Like flowers of infernal moly
Over nocturnal grass
Wetly bobbing and drifting away on our sight.

And still by the rotten row of shattered feet,
Outcasts keep guard.
Forgotten,
Forgetting, till fate shall delete
One from the ward.

The factories on the Surrey side
Are beautifully laid in black on a gold-grey sky.
The river's invisible tide
Threads and thrills like ore that is wealth to the eye.

And great gold midges
Cross the chasm
At the bridges
Above intertwined plasm.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061796">
<head>
   <title>Sickness</title>
   <toctitle>Sickness</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Sickness</indextitle>
   <firstline>Waving slowly before me, pushed into the dark</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Waving slowly before me, pushed into the dark,
Unseen my hands explore the silence, drawing the bark
Of my body slowly behind.

Nothing to meet my fingers but the fleece of night
Invisible blinding my face and my eyes! What if in their flight
My hands should touch the door!

What if I suddenly stumble, and push the door
Open, and a great grey dawn swirls over my feet, before
I can draw back!

What if unwitting I set the door of eternity wide
And am swept away in the horrible dawn, am gone down the tide
Of eternal hereafter!

Catch my hands, my darling, between your breasts.
Take them away from their venture, before fate wrests
The meaning out of them.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061797">
<head>
   <title>In Church</title>
   <toctitle>In Church</toctitle>
   <indextitle>In Church</indextitle>
   <firstline>In the choir the boys are singing the hymn</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
In the choir the boys are singing the hymn.
         The morning light on their lips
Moves in silver-moist flashes, in musical trim.

Sudden outside the high window, one crow
         Hangs in the air
And lights on a withered oak-tree's top of woe.

One bird, one blot, folded and still at the top
         Of the withered tree! - in the grail
Of crystal heaven falls one full black drop.

Like a soft full drop of darkness it seems to sway
         In the tender wine
Of our Sabbath, suffusing our sacred day.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061798">
<head>
   <title>Piano</title>
   <toctitle>Piano</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Piano</indextitle>
   <firstline>Softly, in the dusk, a woman is singing to me</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Softly, in the dusk, a woman is singing to me;
Taking me back down the vista of years, till I see
A child sitting under the piano, in the boom of the tingling strings
And pressing the small, poised feet of a mother who smiles as she sings.

In spite of myself, the insidious mastery of song
Betrays me back, till the heart of me weeps to belong
To the old Sunday evenings at home, with winter outside
And hymns in the cozy parlour, the tinkling piano our guide.

So now it is vain for the singer to burst into clamour
With the great black piano appassionato. The glamour
Of childish days is upon me, my manhood is cast
Down in the flood of remembrance, I weep like a child for the past.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence2001061799">
<head>
   <title>The North Country</title>
   <toctitle>The North Country</toctitle>
   <indextitle>The North Country</indextitle>
   <firstline>In another country, black poplars shake themselves over a pond</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
In another country, black poplars shake themselves over a pond,
And rooks and the rising smoke-waves scatter and wheel from the works beyond:
The air is dark with north and with sulphur, the grass is a darker green,
And people darkly invested with purple move palpable through the scene.

Soundlessly down across the counties, out of the resonant gloom
That wraps the north in stupor and purple travels the deep, slow boom
Of the man-life north imprisoned, shut in the hum of the purpled steel
As it spins to sleep on its motion, drugged dense in the sleep of the wheel.

Out of the sleep, from the gloom of motion, soundlessly, somnambule
Moans and booms the soul of a people imprisoned, asleep in the rule
Of the strong machine that runs mesmeric, booming the spell of its word
Upon them and moving them helpless, mechanic, their will to its will deferred.

Yet all the while comes the droning inaudible, out of the violet air,
The moaning of sleep-bound beings in travail that toil and are will-less there
In the spellbound north, convulsive now with a dream near morning, strong
With violent achings heaving to burst the sleep that is now not long.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617100">
<head>
   <title>Love Storm</title>
   <toctitle>Love Storm</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Love Storm</indextitle>
   <firstline>Many roses in the wind</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Many roses in the wind
Are tapping at the window-sash.
A hawk is in the sky; his wings
Slowly begin to plash.

The roses with the west wind rapping
Are torn away, and a splash
Of red goes down the billowing air.

Still hangs the hawk, with the whole sky moving
Past him - only a wing-beat proving
The will that holds him there.

The daisies in the grass are bending,
The hawk has dropped, the wind is spending
All the roses, and unending
Rustle of leaves washes out the rending
Cry of a bird.

A red rose goes on the wind. - Ascending
The hawk his windswept way is wending
Easily down the sky. The daisies, sending
Strange white signals, seem intending
To show the place whence the scream was heard.

But, oh, my heart, what birds are piping!
A silver wind is hastily wiping
The face of the youngest rose.

And oh, my heart, cease apprehending!
The hawk is gone, a rose is tapping
The window-sash as the west-wind blows.

Knock, knock, 'tis no more than a red rose rapping,
And fear is a plash of wings.
What, then, if a scarlet rose goes flapping
Down the bright-grey ruin of things!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617101">
<head>
   <title>Twenty Years Ago</title>
   <toctitle>Twenty Years Ago</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Twenty Years Ago</indextitle>
   <firstline>Round the house were lilacs and strawberries</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Round the house were lilacs and strawberries
       And foal-foots spangling the paths,
And far away on the sand-hills, dewberries
       Caught dust from the sea's long swaths.

Up the wolds the woods were walking,
       And nuts fell out of their hair.
At the gate the nets hung, balking
       The star-lit rush of a hare.

In the autumn fields, the stubble
       Tinkled the music of gleaning.
At a mother's knees, the trouble
       Lost all its meaning.

Yea, what good beginnings
       To this sad end!
Have we had our innings?
       God forfend!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617102">
<head>
   <title>Reading a Letter</title>
   <toctitle>Reading a Letter</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Reading a Letter</indextitle>
   <firstline>She sits on the recreation ground</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
She sits on the recreation ground
        Under an oak whose yellow buds dot the pale blue sky.
The young grass twinkles in the wind, and the sound
        Of the wind in the knotted buds makes a canopy.

So sitting under the knotted canopy
        Of the wind, she is lifted and carried away as in a balloon
Across the insensible void, till she stoops to see
        The sandy desert beneath her, the dreary platoon.

She knows the waste all dry beneath her, in one place
        Stirring with earth-coloured life, ever turning and stirring.
But never the motion has a human face
        Nor sound, only intermittent machinery whirring.

And so again, on the recreation ground
        She alights a stranger, wondering, unused to the scene;
Suffering at sight of the children playing around,
        Hurt at the chalk-coloured tulips, and the evening-green.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617103">
<head>
   <title>Seven Seals</title>
   <toctitle>Seven Seals</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Seven Seals</indextitle>
   <firstline>Since this is the last night I keep you home</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Since this is the last night I keep you home,
Come, I will consecrate you for the journey.

Rather I had you would not go. Nay come,
I will not again reproach you. Lie back
And let me love you a long time ere you go.
For you are sullen-hearted still, and lack
The will to love me. But even so
I will set a seal upon you from my lip,
Will set a guard of honour at each door,
Seal up each channel out of which might slip
Your love for me.

                                  I kiss your mouth. Ah, love,
Could I but seal its ruddy, shining spring
Of passion, parch it up, destroy, remove
Its softly-stirring crimson welling-up
Of kisses! Oh, help me, God! Here at the source
I'd lie for ever drinking and drawing in
Your fountains, as heaven drinks from out their course
The floods.

                   I close your ears with kisses
And seal your nostrils; and round your neck you'll wear -
Nay, let me work - a delicate chain of kisses.
Like beads they go around, and not one misses
To touch its fellow on either side.

                                                             And there
Full mid-between the champaign of your breast
I place a great and burning seal of love
Like a dark rose, a mystery of rest
On the slow bubbling of your rhythmic heart.
Nay, I persist, and very faith shall keep
You integral to me. Each door, each mystic port
Of egress from you I will seal and steep
In perfect chrism.
                        Now it is done. The mort
Will sound in heaven before it is undone.
But let me finish what I have begun
And shirt you now invulnerable in the mail
Of iron kisses, kisses linked like steel.
Put greaves upon your thighs and knees, and frail
Webbing of steel on your feet. So you shall feel
Ensheathed invulnerable with me, with seven
Great seals upon your outgoings, and woven
Chain of my mystic will wrapped perfectly
Upon you, wrapped in indomitable me.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617104">
<head>
   <title>Two Wives</title>
   <toctitle>Two Wives</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Two Wives</indextitle>
   <firstline>Into the shadow-white chamber silts the white</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
I

Into the shadow-white chamber silts the white
Flux of another dawn. The wind that all night
Long has waited restless, suddenly wafts
A whirl like snow from the plum-trees and the pear,
Till petals heaped between the window-shafts
             In a drift die there.

A nurse in white, at the dawning, flower-foamed pane
Draws down the blinds, whose shadows scarcely stain
The white rugs on the floor, nor the silent bed
That rides the room like a frozen berg, its crest
Finally ridged with the austere line of the dead
             Stretched out at rest.

Less than a year the fourfold feet had pressed
The peaceful floor, when fell the sword on their rest.
Yet soon, too soon, she had him home again
With wounds between them, and suffering like a guest
That will not go. Now suddenly going, the pain
             Leaves an empty breast.

II

A tall woman, with her long white gown aflow
As she strode her limbs amongst it, once more
She hastened towards the room. Did she know
As she listened in silence outside the silent door?
Entering, she saw him in outline, raised on a pyre
             Awaiting the fire.

Upraised on the bed, with feet erect as a bow,
Like the prow of a boat, his head laid back like the stern
Of a ship that stands in a shadowy sea of snow
With frozen rigging, she saw him; she drooped like a fern
Refolding, she slipped to the floor as a ghost-white peony slips
             When the thread clips.

Soft she lay as a shed flower fallen, nor heard
The ominous entry, nor saw the other love,
The dark, the grave-eyed mistress who thus dared
At such an hour to lay her claim, above
A stricken wife, so sunk in oblivion, bowed
             With misery, no more proud.

III

The stranger's hair was shorn like a lad's dark poll
And pale her ivory face: her eyes would fail
In silence when she looked: for all the whole
Darkness of failure was in them, without avail.
Dark in indomitable failure, she who had lost
             Now claimed the host.

She softly passed the sorrowful flower shed
In blonde and white on the floor, nor even turned
Her head aside, but straight towards the bed
Moved with slow feet, and her eyes' flame steadily burned.
She looked at him as he lay with banded cheek,
             And she started to speak

Softly: "I knew it would come to this," she said,
"I knew that some day, soon, I should find you thus.
So I did not fight you. You went your way instead
Of coming mine - and of the two of us
I died the first, I, in the after-life
             Am now your wife."

IV

"'Twas I whose fingers did draw up the young
Plant of your body: to me you looked ere sprung
The secret of the moon within your eyes!
My mouth you met before your fine red mouth
Was set to song - and never your song denies
             My love, till you went south."

"'Twas I who placed the bloom of manhood on
Your youthful smoothness: I fleeced where fleece was none
Your fervent limbs with flickers and tendrils of new
Knowledge; I set your heart to its stronger beat;
I put my strength upon you, and I threw
             My life at your feet."

"But I whom the years had reared to be your bride,
Who for years was sun for your shivering, shade for your sweat,
Who for one strange year was as a bride to you - you set me aside
With the old, sweet things of our youth; - and never yet
Have I ceased to grieve that I was not great enough
             To defeat your baser stuff."

V

"But you are given back again to me
Who have kept intact for you your virginity.
Who for the rest of life walk out of care,
Indifferent here of myself, since I am gone
Where you are gone, and you and I out there
             Walk now as one."

"Your widow am I, and only I. I dream
God bows His head and grants me this supreme
Pure look of your last dead face, whence now is gone
The mobility, the panther's gambolling,
And all your being is given to me, so none
             Can mock my struggling."

"And now at last I kiss your perfect face,
Perfecting now our unfinished, first embrace.
Your young hushed look that then saw God ablaze
In every bush, is given you back, and we
Are met at length to finish our rest of days
             In a unity."

VI

The other woman rose, and swiftly said:
"So! you have come to get him now he's dead!
Now you can triumph, now he is no more
Than a dream of yours! 'twas all you ever could
See in him, your self's dream in his sore
             Heart's blood."

"How did you love him, you who only roused
His mind until it burnt his heart away!
'Twas you who killed him, when you both caroused
In words and things well said. But the other way
He never loved you, never with desire
             Touched you to fire."

"Take what you've got, your memory of words
Between you, but his touch you never knew.
Caresses never flew to you like birds.
You never bore his children, never drew
His body down in weight to rest in you
             The night through."

VII

"Take then eternity, for what is that
But another word, conceit and vanity!
But do not touch this man who never yet
Took pleasure in touching you. Mortality
Is not for you, and he is mortal still
             Against his will."

"Even dead, he still is mortal, and his hair
Is soft though it is cold. Do not dare
To touch him while he still is lying there!
Stand a way off, and if you like commune
With his wan spirit somewhere in the air
             Like a lost tune."

"But do not touch him, for he hated you
To touch him, and he said so, and you knew.
Why are you here? What is his corpse to you?
Stand you far off and triumph like a Jew
That he is dead and you are not. But stand
             Back, you understand!"
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617105">
<head>
   <title>Narcissus</title>
   <toctitle>Narcissus</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Narcissus</indextitle>
   <firstline>Where the minnows trace</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
Where the minnows trace
A glinting web quick hid in the gloom of the brook,
When I think of the place
And remember the small lad lying intent to look
Through the shadowy face
At the little fish thread-threading the watery nook -

It seems to me
The woman you are should be nixie, there is a pool
Where we ought to be.
You undine-clear and pearly, soullessly cool
And waterly
The pool for my limbs to fathom, my soul's last school.

Narcissus
Ventured so long ago in the deeps of reflection.
Illyssus
Broke the bounds and beyond! - Dim recollection
Of fishes
Soundlessly moving in heaven's other direction!

Be
Undine towards the waters, moving back;
For me
A pool! Put off the soul you've got, oh lack
Your human self immortal; take the watery track!
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617106">
<head>
   <title>On That Day</title>
   <toctitle>On That Day</toctitle>
   <indextitle>On That Day</indextitle>
   <firstline>On that day</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
         On that day
I shall put roses on roses, and cover your grave
With multitude of white roses: and, since you were brave
         One bright red ray.

         So people, passing under
The ash-trees of the valley-road, will raise
Their eyes and look at the grave on the hill, in wonder,
         Wondering mount, and put the flowers asunder:

         To see whose praise
Is blazoned here so white and so bloodily red.
Then they will say: "'Tis long since she is dead,
         Who has remembered her after many days?"

         And standing there
They will consider how you went your ways
Unnoticed among them, a still queen lost in the maze
         Of this earthly affair.

         A queen, they'll say,
Has slept unnoticed on a forgotten hill.
Sleeps on unknown, unnoticed there, until
         Dawns my insurgent day.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617107">
<head>
   <title>Autumn Sunshine</title>
   <toctitle>Autumn Sunshine</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Autumn Sunshine</indextitle>
   <firstline>The sun sets out the autumn crocuses</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
The sun sets out the autumn crocuses
       And fills them up a pouring measure
       Of death-producing wine, till treasure
Runs waste down their chalices.

All, all Persephone's pale cups of mould
       Are on the board, are over-filled;
       The portion to the gods is spilled;
Now, mortals all, take hold!

The time is now, the wine-cup full and full
       Of lambent heaven, a pledging-cup;
       Let now all mortal men take up
The drink, and a long, strong pull!

Out of the hell-queen's cup, the heaven's pale wine!
       Drink then, invisible heroes, drink!
       Lips to the vessels, never shrink,
Throats to the heavens incline.

And take within the wine the god's great oath
       By heaven and earth and hellish stream,
       To break this sick and nauseous dream
We writhe and lust in, both.

Swear, in the pale wine poured from the cups of the queen
       Of hell, to wake and be free
       From this nightmare we writhe in,
Break out of this foul has-been.
</body>
</poem>

<poem id="lawrence20010617108">
<head>
   <title>Restlessness</title>
   <toctitle>Restlessness</toctitle>
   <indextitle>Restlessness</indextitle>
   <firstline>At the open door of the room I stand and look at the night</firstline>
   <quality>korrektur1</quality>
</head>
<body>
At the open door of the room I stand and look at the night,
Hold my hand to catch the raindrops, that slant into sight,
Arriving grey from the darkness above suddenly into the light of the room.
I will escape from the hollow room, the box of light,
And be out in the bewildering darkness, which is always fecund, which might
Mate my hungry soul with a germ of its womb.

I will go out to the night, as a man goes down to the shore
To draw his net through the surf's thin line, at the dawn before
The sun warms the sea, little, lonely and sad, sifting the sobbing tide.
I will sift the surf that edges the night, with my net, the four
Strands of my eyes and my lips and my hands and my feet, sifting the store
Of flotsam until my soul is tired or satisfied.

I will catch in my eyes' quick net
The faces of all the women as they go past,
Bend over them with my soul, to cherish the wet
Cheeks and wet hair a moment, saying: "Is it you?"
Looking earnestly under the dark umbrellas, held fast
Against the wind; and if, where the lamplight blew
Its rainy swill about us, she answered me
With a laugh and a merry wildness that it was she
Who was seeking me, and had found me at last to free
Me now from the stunting bonds of my chastity,
How glad I should be!

Moving along in the mysterious ebb of the night
Pass the men whose eyes are shut like anemones in a dark pool;
Why don't they open with vision and speak to me? what have they in sight?
Why do I wander aimless among them, desirous fool?

I can always linger over the huddled books on the stalls,
Always gladden my amorous fingers with the touch of their leaves,
Always kneel in courtship to the shelves in the doorways, where falls
The shadow, always offer myself to one mistress, who always receives.

But oh, it is not enough, it is all no good.
There is something I want to feel in my running blood,
Something I want to touch; I must hold my face to the rain,
I must hold my face to the wind, and let it explain
Me its life as it hurries in secret.
I will trail my hands again through the drenched, cold leaves
Till my hands are full of the chillness and touch of leaves,
Till at length they induce me to sleep, and to forget.
</body>
</poem>
</workbody>
</kalliopework>
